<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>sonos on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>/tags/sonos.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in sonos on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/sonos/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Sonos just got complicated</title>
      <link>/2020/06/09/sonos-just-got-complicated.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/09/sonos-just-got-complicated.html</guid>
      <description>So this morning the 08:10 alarm in the living room did not go off. It was set to remind the son that it is time to get going for school. We noticed in time, but when I looked into the &amp;ldquo;Why?&amp;rdquo; things got interesting. That alarm is a chime from the household Sonos system, and when I investigated, I got this:
Sonos did the split and upgraded/rebranded their controller operating system to S1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sonos recycled their recycle mode</title>
      <link>/2020/03/06/sonos-recycled-their-recycle-mode.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/06/sonos-recycled-their-recycle-mode.html</guid>
      <description>So I wrote about [the Sonos Recycle Program]({% link _posts/2019-12-30-sonos-recycle-mode.md %}) before Sonos announced their plans to actively discontinue support for their older Speakers. Back then, the program did make sense, because it was kind of voluntary and avoided sending stuff back to Sonos for a Trade-Up. Even then, people disliked it.
Then Sonos announced that they would discontinue support for these devices and it&amp;rsquo;s basically &amp;lsquo;you brick them now, or we are going to brick them for you in May and without a rebate for new equipment&amp;rsquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sonos Recycle Mode</title>
      <link>/2019/12/30/sonos-recycle-mode.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/30/sonos-recycle-mode.html</guid>
      <description>Sonos is a company that makes Wifi Connected speakers. They offer acceptable sound quality and an extremely good user experience. They also so far have never cancelled support for any of their speakers.
Hardware Lineup and Timeline   Some of their speakers are now qualified for a Trade-Up program, in particular their
 Play:5 (1st generation) speaker, the Connect:Amp and the Connect.  The latter two (the Connect products) are somewhat obsolete as they were necessary when normal Wifi was usually not able to carry sound data at the required reliability, so Sonos speakers built their own Wifi Mesh network separately from the usual home Wifi.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
