<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>lang_en on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>/tags/lang_en.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in lang_en on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/lang_en/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: Python and WHERE ... IN ()</title>
      <link>/2021/10/28/python-where-in.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/10/28/python-where-in.html</guid>
      <description>As a developer using Python, I want to be able to hand a list to an SQL statement with a WHERE id IN (…) clause, and it should do the right thing.
 Well, that is not how it started, because it was asked on the internal no-work-channel, so it kind of escalated more.
A question   The original question was:
 Dev&amp;gt; Why is it 2021, and SQL prepared statements still can&amp;rsquo;t deal with IN?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metaverse (en)</title>
      <link>/2021/10/27/metaverse-en.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/10/27/metaverse-en.html</guid>
      <description>I wrote on Twitter something about the term &amp;ldquo;Metaverse&amp;rdquo;. That led to a contact with Michael Carl , who wanted to make an episode for his Podcast with me. My german notes and talk prep are now also available here:
Metaverse   The term &amp;ldquo;Metaverse&amp;rdquo; was initially coined by Neal Stephenson in 1992, but in the context of the current discussion it was defined as in The Metaverse: What It Is, Where to Find it, Who Will Build It, and Fortnite by Matthew Ball.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding git</title>
      <link>/2021/10/12/understanding-git.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/10/12/understanding-git.html</guid>
      <description>It occurred to me that I do not know nearly enough how git works, internally. The contents of the .git directory seem to be accessible enough, so I am going on a Safari in the git repository of this blog. You can follow along if you check out the blog .
Refs   All things git live in .git. The thing we are working with seem to live in .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Empty commits and other wrong tools for the job</title>
      <link>/2021/10/06/empty-commits-and-other-wrong-tools-for-the-job.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/10/06/empty-commits-and-other-wrong-tools-for-the-job.html</guid>
      <description>This is how you can make an empty commit:
$ git commit --allow-empty -m &amp;#34;Kick it&amp;#34; This has the disadvantage of also generating a commit message. Another way to achieve this seems to be
$ git commit --amend --no-edit &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git push -f but that will make people hate you in other ways.
So lets stop and ask: Why would you want to make an empty commit?
Most people want this because they attached a server-side action to a commit, a CI/CD activity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: Our MySQL in 2010, a hiring interview question</title>
      <link>/2021/09/27/mysql-booking-2010-a-hiring-interview-question.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/27/mysql-booking-2010-a-hiring-interview-question.html</guid>
      <description>I ranted about hiring interviews, and the canned questions that people have to answer. One of the interviews we do is a systems design interview, where we want to see how (senior) people use components and patterns to design a system for reliability and scale-out.
A sample question (based on a Twitter thread in German):
 It is 2010, and the company has a database structure where a fixed number front end machines form a cell.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: Binding the ORM</title>
      <link>/2021/09/17/binding-the-orm.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/17/binding-the-orm.html</guid>
      <description>My task is to collect performance data about a single query, using PERFORMANCE_SCHEMA (P_S for short) in MySQL, to ship it elsewhere for integration with other data.
In a grander scheme of things, I will need to define what performance data from a query I am actually interested in. I will also need to find a way to attribute the query (as seen on the server) to a point in the codebase of the client, which is not always easy when an ORM or other SQL generator is being used.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: Tracing a single query with PERFORMANCE_SCHEMA</title>
      <link>/2021/09/15/mysql-tracing-a-single-query-with-performanceschema.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/15/mysql-tracing-a-single-query-with-performanceschema.html</guid>
      <description>My task is to collect performance data about a single query, using PERFORMANCE_SCHEMA (P_S for short) in MySQL, to ship it elsewhere for integration with other data.
In a grander scheme of things, I will need to define what performance data from a query I am actually interested in. I will also need to find a way to attribute the query (as seen on the server) to a point in the codebase of the client, which is not always easy when an ORM or other SQL generator is being used.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: Page compression revisited</title>
      <link>/2021/09/14/mysql-page-compression-revisited.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/14/mysql-page-compression-revisited.html</guid>
      <description>Like I said, I never had much reason to use table compression, and only recently looked into the topic. MySQL Page Compression looks a lot easier at the database end of things, but relies on hole punching support in the file system. Let&amp;rsquo;s have a look at what that means.
Files, Inodes and Arrays of Blocks   The original Unix filesystem saw the disk as a sea of blocks, which were represented in a free map as an array of bits.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: CREATE IF NOT EXISTS TABLE, but CREATE OR REPLACE VIEW</title>
      <link>/2021/09/10/create-if-not-exists.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/10/create-if-not-exists.html</guid>
      <description>For the MySQL Million Challenge, I was going through the server syntax in order to understand what things can be created in the server. And now my OCD triggered. DDL is a mess.
Creation    As a database developer, I want to be able to create server objects using the CREATE thing syntax.
 The server gives you that for the following things:
 DATABASE EVENT FUNCTION (and FUNCTION SONAME) INDEX LOGFILE GROUP (NDB only, not going to look at this) PROCEDURE RESOURCE GROUP ROLE SERVER SPATIAL REFERENCE SYSTEM TABLE TABLESPACE TRIGGER USER VIEW  Safe creation    As a database developer I want to be able to script things safely, so I need IF NOT EXISTS clauses in my CREATE syntax.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: The Million Challenge</title>
      <link>/2021/09/10/mysql-million-challenge.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/10/mysql-million-challenge.html</guid>
      <description>A long-standing idea that I have is to test the servers limits: How does it fail and break if there are very many of a thing? Previously that was too easy, because many structures were constructed in a way that it was obvious they would not scale. But with MySQL 8 many things were overhauled, so let&amp;rsquo;s see what we can make many of and see how the server fares.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: The table &#39;../tmp/#sql…&#39; is full</title>
      <link>/2021/09/09/tmp-file-full.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/09/tmp-file-full.html</guid>
      <description>We observe a large number of messages of the kind
The table &amp;#39;../tmp/#sql…&amp;#39; is full Before MySQL 8   In older Versions of MySQL, implied temporary tables are being created, whenever your EXPLAIN contained the phrase using temporary.
In this case, MySQL would create an in-memory temporary table to materialize an intermediate query result, and then continue to process the data from there. If that temporary table was larger than some configurable limit, the temporary table would instead be converted to a MyISAM table on disk, streamed out, and then work would continue with this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: Two kinds of compression</title>
      <link>/2021/09/09/mysql-two-kinds-of-compression.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/09/mysql-two-kinds-of-compression.html</guid>
      <description>I never had much reason to use table compression, so I largely ignored the topic in MySQL. I knew that MySQL had table compression since 5.1, but I also knew the implementation was horribly complicated and double stored all data. There is also page compression, a feature introduced with 5.7, which replaces table compression and works much better.
Table Compression   Table Compression is available in MySQL 5.1 and newer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computer science</title>
      <link>/2021/09/07/computer-science.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/07/computer-science.html</guid>
      <description>Lilith Wittmann asked on Twitter:
 Why do we have so much dangerous software in Germany?
Because we don&amp;rsquo;t have the competency anywhere (administration, enterprise or science) to understand the complexity of software.
 My take was :
 Computer science is easy. It is the science of Zeroes and Ones, and it does not get any more complicated anywhere.
Computer science piles abstractions on top of each other, though, 30 layers deep and with non-linear interactions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: AI Superpowers</title>
      <link>/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-ai-superpowers.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-ai-superpowers.html</guid>
      <description>This 2018 book in some aspects is already outdated: Silicon Valley Techbro Kai-Fu Lee describes what AI is and what he thinks it will do to our future, the nature of work and the job market. But since then, the worlds view on what AI can and cannot do, what the problems to solve really are and a lot of other things have changed.
 AI Superpowers:China, Silicon Valley, and the New World Order , Kai-Fu Lee</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Old Man&#39;s War</title>
      <link>/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-old-mans-war.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-old-mans-war.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Old Man&amp;rsquo;s War &amp;rdquo; is the first &amp;ldquo;large&amp;rdquo; works by John Scalzi,
 Old Man&amp;rsquo;s War , John Scalzi
The plot premise is weird, but simple: Humanity has taken to the stars, but with private enterprise. Basically all advanced space technology is controlled by the Colonial Union. Life on earth on the other hand goes on almost as before.
John Perry enlists to serve in the Colonial Defense Force at the age of 75, to protect humanity, but mostly to have the CU fight the effects of him aging with some unspecified Scifi tech.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: These Savage Shores</title>
      <link>/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-these-savage-shores.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-these-savage-shores.html</guid>
      <description>Ram V is a writer, sometimes for comics. Together with artist Sumit Kumar he wrote a simple story: English Vampires vs. Indian Rakshasa.
 These Savage Shores , Ram V &amp;amp; Sumit Kumar
The 1760&amp;rsquo;ies. An english vampire puts his peers at risk by not having his desires unter control, and is exiled to Calicut, India. He soon finds out that even older and fiercer beings rule the night: Rakshasa, the Vampire equivalent of Indian Myth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: This Is How You Lose The Time War</title>
      <link>/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war.html</guid>
      <description>Max Gladstone and Amal El-Mohtar co-authored This Is How You Lose The Time-War , not exactly a Science Fiction novel.
 This Is How You Lose The Time War , Amal El-Mohtar and Max Gladstone
Red and Blue are representatives, spies and saboteurs of two nearly all-powerful, warring factions. They travel through time to manipulate events at critical points in history in favor of their respective factions. They are leaving each other messages, they taunt each other, and gradually earn mutual respect.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Typeset in the Future</title>
      <link>/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-typeset-in-the-future.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-typeset-in-the-future.html</guid>
      <description>Dave Addey ran a Tumblr once, titled &amp;ldquo;Typeset in the Future&amp;rdquo;, in which he dissected the typography of Science Fiction films. This has been turned into the eponymous book.
 Typeset in the Future , Dave Addey
In 2013, Addey nerded out over the fonts in a Science Fiction movie and discovered it was an Eurostile variant (&amp;ldquo;Eurostile Extended Bold&amp;rdquo;). He started a Tumblr about this, and in great detail went through a number of movies, and about every sign, letter and font used in there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: UNIX: A History and a Memoir</title>
      <link>/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-unix-a-history-and-a-memoir.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-unix-a-history-and-a-memoir.html</guid>
      <description>The memoir of Brian Kernighan, and the story of how UNIX came to be and what working at Bell Labs was like at that time: UNIX: A History and a Memoir is required reading for anyone who wants to know where Unix concepts came from and what ideas were behind its inception.
 &amp;quot;UNIX: A History and a Memoir &amp;quot;, Brian Kernighan
Kernighan takes us through the history and the setting of Bell Labs, why it existed and what it did.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epochalypse</title>
      <link>/2021/08/18/epochalypse.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/08/18/epochalypse.html</guid>
      <description>I had reason to look into the UNIX Eschaton, the time when the signed 32 bit counter of seconds since Midnight, 1970-01-01 UTC overflows. Going to Wikipedia , I learned we will die two years earlier, because in 2036-02-07, 06:28:16 UTC NTP will kill us all:
 At 06:28:16 UTC on Thursday, 7 February 2036, Network Time Protocol will loop over to the next epoch, as the 32-bit time stamp value used in NTP (unsigned, but based on 1 January 1900) will overflow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: 88 Names</title>
      <link>/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-88-names.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-88-names.html</guid>
      <description>It began with a tweet by Sebastian Bergmann , which made me buy &amp;ldquo;88 names &amp;rdquo; by Matt Ruff. The book is a tour of massive multiplayer online role playing games for people who do not play, and also a discussion of identity on the Internet.
John Chu has a small sherpa company, an outfit that helps causal players who have the coin to experience hard content in MMORPGs in an easy and successful way without investing too much time into the game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: A Kim Jong-Il Production</title>
      <link>/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-a-kim-jong-il-production.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-a-kim-jong-il-production.html</guid>
      <description>Paul Fischer writes &amp;ldquo;A Kim Jong-Il Production &amp;rdquo;, a documentary the 1978 abduction of the famous South Korean actress Madam Choi, and her ex-husband, the filmmaker Shin Sang-Ok.
Before becoming the leader of North Korea, Kim Jong-Il headed the Ministry for Propaganda. Dissatisfied with the talent available, he had the famous actress Choi Eun-Hee kidnammed. When her ex-husband started to investigate, he had him kidnapped in Hong Kong and transported to North Korea by ship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Merchant Princes Omnibus</title>
      <link>/2021/07/28/fertig-gelesen-the-merchant-princes-omnibus.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/07/28/fertig-gelesen-the-merchant-princes-omnibus.html</guid>
      <description>Charles Stross &amp;ldquo;The Merchant Princes &amp;rdquo; series of six books is another &amp;ldquo;Sliders &amp;rdquo; type of story, with the usual Stross-like twist. The story follows Miriam Beckstein, a woman who thinks she is a tech journalist. Miriam falls off a chair while looking at a strange pattern, and finds herself in a medival parallel earth.
 &amp;quot;The Merchant Princes Omnibus &amp;quot;, Charles Stross
In the course of the story, Miriam learns that she is actually from this parallel earth, and really is the Countess Helge Thorold-Hjorth in the kingdom of Gruinmarkt, which sits in the place of her world lines Boston.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Outland</title>
      <link>/2021/07/23/fertig-gelesen-outland.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/07/23/fertig-gelesen-outland.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Outland &amp;rdquo; is the first book by Dennis E. Taylor, preceding the Bobiverse and also &amp;ldquo;The Singularity Trap&amp;rdquo;. It is a &amp;ldquo;Sliders &amp;rdquo; storyline, much like Pratchett&amp;rsquo;s and Baxter&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Long Earth&amp;rdquo; , in which our heroes discover a parallel dimension with a seemingly uninhabited earth, and then need to colonize it.
 Outland , Dennis E. Taylor
Dennis E. Taylor is a computer programmer writing Scifi, and had problems finding a publishher for his debut novel, &amp;ldquo;Outland&amp;rdquo;, in 2015, so he self-published.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: A job queue in Python</title>
      <link>/2021/07/13/mysql-a-job-queue-in-python.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/07/13/mysql-a-job-queue-in-python.html</guid>
      <description>Somebody needed a job queue in Python: Multiple writers insert into it in random order, and the jobs are written into the MySQL table jobs. From the jobs table, multiple consumers claim jobs in batches of n or smaller (n=100), and process them. After processing, the consumers delete the jobs. We need concurrent job generation and consumption, with proper and efficient locking.
The full source for this example can be seen in mysql-dev-examples in mysql-claim-jobs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Black Count</title>
      <link>/2021/06/05/fertig-gelesen-the-black-count.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/06/05/fertig-gelesen-the-black-count.html</guid>
      <description>Another Monte-Cristo-themed book, Tom Reiss&#39; The Black Count nicely complements the german sci-fi novel Montecrypto by Tom Hillenbrand. It is a biography of the father of the French write Alexandere Dumas, Thomas-Alexandre Dumas Davy de la Pailleterie.
 &amp;quot;The Black Count &amp;quot;, by Tom Reiss.
Alexandre Dumas, the author of &amp;ldquo;The Three Musketeers&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;The Count of Monte Cristo&amp;rdquo; and many other books, is one of the most read French authors. He had it easy coming up with stories, because his father had one of the most unusual and wildest lives imaginable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NVME is not a hard disk</title>
      <link>/2021/05/25/nvme-is-not-a-hard-disk.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/05/25/nvme-is-not-a-hard-disk.html</guid>
      <description>So somebody tweeted about the Seagate Mach.2 , a harddisk with two independent heads &amp;ldquo;combs&amp;rdquo;, and I commented in german : &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s two drives in one chassis, even shown as two drives. And it still is rotating rust, so slow with seeks. Linear IO will be fine.&amp;rdquo;
That quickly devolved in a discussion of RAID-0 on a single disk drive : &amp;ldquo;RAID-0 on a single physical drive. Yeah, you can do that if you do not need your data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Windows 10 and Umlauts with an english keyboard</title>
      <link>/2021/05/15/windows-10-and-umlauts-with-an-english-keyboard.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/05/15/windows-10-and-umlauts-with-an-english-keyboard.html</guid>
      <description>I never wrote this up, and the information online is all referring to older versions of Windows, so let&amp;rsquo;s fix this.
 The MS-DOS version of getting Umlauts on a US keyboard is to type the ASCII codes. As I can&amp;rsquo;t and won&amp;rsquo;t remember these codes, this won&amp;rsquo;t work for me. There is a deadkey way to get a &amp;ldquo;US (International Keyboard)&amp;rdquo;. On these, you type Double Quotes &amp;quot;, and then the letter that should form the Umlaut, for example o, for an ö.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Linkers</title>
      <link>/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-linkers.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-linkers.html</guid>
      <description>Ian Lance Taylor is the author of a UUCP program that I have been using for a long time to connect to other USENET systems, long before I had access to the actual Internet.
UUCP queues up jobs for remote execution, dials other computers with a moden, exchanges the contents of the queued up work, and after disconnect executes the jobs. The jobs are mostly invocation of &amp;ldquo;rmail&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;rnews&amp;rdquo; programs for the exchange of mail and USENET news.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Needle</title>
      <link>/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-needle.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-needle.html</guid>
      <description>Needle and Through the Eye of a Needle are books by Hal Clement. Hal Clement was a Hard Sci-Fi author born in 1922, and &amp;ldquo;Needle&amp;rdquo; was written in 1950 as his first book, for Campbell, no less, and sold to Doubleday. The followup was produced almost 30 years later, in 1978.
 Needle 
The story begins with two spaceships crashing into planet earth, some time in the 1950&amp;rsquo;s idea of a future, close to an island in the Pacific ocean.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Antivirus Hackers Handbook</title>
      <link>/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-the-antivirus-hackers-handbook.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-the-antivirus-hackers-handbook.html</guid>
      <description>The Antivirus Hackers Handbook by Jaxeon Koret and Elias Bachaalany is part book, part a research report, detailing the findings of Jaxeon Koret and Elias Bachaalany in how Antivirus programs work, try to protect themselves and can be attacked and exploited.
 The Antivirus Hackers Handbook 
The book assumes that you have some basic knowledge how compilers produce programs, what assembler looks like and how to map that on program statements in the code you write, and have access to IDA Pro free edition, Ghidra, Hopper or some other reverse engineering and analysis tool.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Witcher</title>
      <link>/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-the-witcher.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-the-witcher.html</guid>
      <description>So, Netflix&#39; &amp;ldquo;The Witcher &amp;rdquo; was weird, and could not decide what it wanted to be: A &amp;ldquo;Hercules Legenday Journey&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo;-like half-comedy, half-camp series, or something else, darker and denser, with more story and background. It hinted at a better story, better told, that did not make it into the final product, and died somewhere between the scriptwriting and the cutting table.
Investigating, I got myself the equivalent of the Witcher Boxed Set on the Kindle and started reading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Titan</title>
      <link>/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-titan.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-titan.html</guid>
      <description>The story of Heaven&amp;rsquo;s River , stranding in and then exploring an alien megastructure, is one that has been written before: In Niven&amp;rsquo;s Ringworld , Clarke&amp;rsquo;s Rama , and Farmer&amp;rsquo;s Riverworld . John Varley&amp;rsquo;s take on this, very seventies, is Titan , Wizard , and Demon , the Gaia Trilogy.
 Titan , Wizard and Daemon
Cirocco Jones is the Commander of the Earth science ship Ringmaster, and is right now approaching the orbit of Saturn, where she and her crew discover a new moon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A MySQL flight recorder</title>
      <link>/2021/04/22/a-mysql-flight-recorder.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/04/22/a-mysql-flight-recorder.html</guid>
      <description>Sometimes things go wrong, and it surely would be nice if you at least knew afterwards what happened. Where I work, we are running a shell script older than time itself, once a minute. The script writes files to /var/log/mysql_pl, into a directory named after the current weekday and named after the current hour and minute.
So when a box crashes on Thursday at 22:09, as long as I can login to it, I still can try to look at /var/log/mysql_pl/Thu/22_0?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Children of Ruin</title>
      <link>/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-children-of-ruin.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-children-of-ruin.html</guid>
      <description>Children of Ruin is the second part of Children of Time by english Sci-Fi author Adrian Tchaikovsky.
 In &amp;ldquo;Children of Time&amp;rdquo;, mankind reached for the stars, almost suceeded and also almost died out. They did manage to create a digital lifeform, though, and also to seed and uplift life from earth on another world - just not the intended one. And so we ended up with a race of intelligent giant jumping spiders that manage to befriend the broken artificial intelligence orbiting their world and to rescue the remnants of humankind from themselves.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Conan, The Barbarian</title>
      <link>/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-conan-the-barbarian.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-conan-the-barbarian.html</guid>
      <description>Conan, The Barbarian by Robert E. Howard is a collection of all Conan stories.
 Imaginary Worlds Ep 114: The Man Behind the Sword (Episode Transcript PDF ) discussed Robert E. Howard, his 1930&amp;rsquo;s character Conan, The Barbarian and how Howard&amp;rsquo;s Conan is different from the Schwarzenegger character, and a much deeper and more complicated story. Go, and listen to the episode, it is well worth the time.
Having seen the Schwarzenegger film, but never actually having read the book I went out and got this complete collection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Heaven&#39;s River</title>
      <link>/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-heavens-river.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-heavens-river.html</guid>
      <description>Heaven&amp;rsquo;s River is the fourth part of the Bobiverse Trilogy, in which the original Bob finds a decaying alien megastructure, and investigates.
 Previously in the Bobiverse:
 We are Legion (We are Bob)  For We Are Many  All These Worlds   Bob Johannson is a successful software developer, and cashes out. Then he dies, becomes a sentient spaceship and von Neumann probe, and then earth is almost destroyed in a war.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Masters of Doom and The Game Engine Black Book: Doom</title>
      <link>/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-masters-of-doom.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-masters-of-doom.html</guid>
      <description>Masters of Doom: How Two Guys Created an Empire and Transformed Pop Culture by David Kushner is the story of the two Johns: Carmack and Romero, and the early video game culture and the genre of the 3D first person shooter.
 A lot of todays &amp;ldquo;hard core&amp;rdquo; and somewhat toxic video game culture was defined by the two Johns and the company they built, as well as the culture that followed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Other Minds</title>
      <link>/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-other-minds.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-other-minds.html</guid>
      <description>Peter Godfrey-Smith writes Other Minds: The Octopus and the Evolution of Intelligent Life , a book about the body, the mind and the life of Octopi.
Octopi are creatures that are across the tree of life about as different as can be from humans. How different are they? Their blood is not based on iron, as ours, but uses copper to transport Oxygen, and consequently is not red from hemoglobin, but blueish from hemocyanin.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Terry Jones&#39; Barbarians</title>
      <link>/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-terry-jones-barbarians.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-terry-jones-barbarians.html</guid>
      <description>Terry Jones&#39; Barbarians: An Alternative Roman History by Alan Ereira is the writeup to the BBC series &amp;ldquo;Terry Jones&#39; Barbarians &amp;rdquo;.
 Terry Jones, who sadly died in early 2020, was not only a member of Monty Pythons Flying Circus, but among many other things a TV author and presenter for a number of BBC series on medieval and ancient history. In many cases, he takes the controversial position and presents a view of history that challenges the popular view.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Vanishing Middle Class</title>
      <link>/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-the-vanishing-middle-class.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-the-vanishing-middle-class.html</guid>
      <description>The Vanishing Middle Class: Prejudice and Power in a Dual Economy by Peter Temin analyzes the economical and political structure of the USA. Temin does this through the lens of the &amp;ldquo;Dual Economy &amp;rdquo; Model.
 Dual Economies are normally prevalent in colonial societies of &amp;ldquo;less developed&amp;rdquo; countries. These countries usually have local production and production for a global export market, and besides economical and income structures around this separation, there are also social segration and a certain degree of isolation of the social groups from each other - in politics as well as attempts to prevent social migration into the higher ranked group.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL and UUIDs</title>
      <link>/2021/04/06/mysql-and-uuids.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/04/06/mysql-and-uuids.html</guid>
      <description>In ALTER TABLE for UUID we discuss currently proper way to store and handle UUID in MySQL. Currently it works, even in a performant way, but it still hurts. It should not.
Definition of UUID   The RFC 4122 defines various types of UUID, and how they are being formatted for presentation and as a bit field on the wire. As this document was written bei Leach and Salz, among others, RFC 4122 UUIDs are also called &amp;ldquo;Leach-Salz UUIDs&amp;rdquo; (for example in the Java Documentation ).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making an unexpected leap with interval syntax</title>
      <link>/2021/04/02/making-an-unexpected-leap-with-interval-syntax.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/04/02/making-an-unexpected-leap-with-interval-syntax.html</guid>
      <description>(based on a find by Ruud van Tol, and several Twitter contributions)
Ruud commented on our DST discussion with
mysql&amp;gt;SELECT&amp;#39;2019-02-28 12:34:56&amp;#39;+INTERVAL1YEAR+INTERVAL1DAYasa,&amp;#39;2019-02-28 12:34:56&amp;#39;+INTERVAL1DAY+INTERVAL1YEARasb\Ga:2020-02-2912:34:56b:2020-03-0112:34:562019 is a year before a leap year. Adding (left to right) a year brings us to 2020-02-28, and then adding a day makes this 2020-02-29, because it&amp;rsquo;s a leap year.
On the other hand, adding a day first makes it 2019-03-01, and then adding a year makes it 2020-03-01, a different result.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Things you didn&#39;t know about MySQL and Date and Time and DST</title>
      <link>/2021/03/29/mysql-date-time-dst.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/03/29/mysql-date-time-dst.html</guid>
      <description>(based on a conversation with a colleague, and a bit of Twitter )
A Conundrum   A developer colleague paged me with this:
mysql&amp;gt;selectUNIX_TIMESTAMP(&amp;#34;2021-03-26 03:07:00&amp;#34;+INTERVAL2YEAR)-UNIX_TIMESTAMP(&amp;#34;2021-03-26 02:07:00&amp;#34;+INTERVAL2YEAR)asdelta\Gdelta:420It is obviously wrong, and weirdly so. It only works for &amp;ldquo;2 year&amp;rdquo;, not with other values:
mysql&amp;gt;selectUNIX_TIMESTAMP(&amp;#34;2021-03-26 03:07:00&amp;#34;+INTERVAL1-11year_month)-UNIX_TIMESTAMP(&amp;#34;2021-03-26 02:07:00&amp;#34;+INTERVAL1-11year_month)asdelta\Gdelta:3600mysql&amp;gt;selectUNIX_TIMESTAMP(&amp;#34;2021-03-26 03:07:00&amp;#34;+INTERVAL1-12year_month)-UNIX_TIMESTAMP(&amp;#34;2021-03-26 02:07:00&amp;#34;+INTERVAL1-12year_month)asdelta\Gdelta:3600mysql&amp;gt;selectUNIX_TIMESTAMP(&amp;#34;2021-03-26 03:07:00&amp;#34;+INTERVAL1-13year_month)-UNIX_TIMESTAMP(&amp;#34;2021-03-26 02:07:00&amp;#34;+INTERVAL1-13year_month)asdelta\Gdelta:3600It has to be exactly 730 days (2 * 365 days, 2 years):
mysql&amp;gt;selectUNIX_TIMESTAMP(&amp;#34;2021-03-26 03:07:00&amp;#34;+INTERVAL729day)-UNIX_TIMESTAMP(&amp;#34;2021-03-26 02:07:00&amp;#34;+interval729day)asdelta\Gdelta:3600mysql&amp;gt;selectUNIX_TIMESTAMP(&amp;#34;2021-03-26 03:07:00&amp;#34;+INTERVAL730day)-UNIX_TIMESTAMP(&amp;#34;2021-03-26 02:07:00&amp;#34;+interval730day)asdelta\Gdelta:420mysql&amp;gt;selectUNIX_TIMESTAMP(&amp;#34;2021-03-26 03:07:00&amp;#34;+INTERVAL731day)-UNIX_TIMESTAMP(&amp;#34;2021-03-26 02:07:00&amp;#34;+interval731day)asdelta\Gdelta:3600The Reason   In our math, we have two expressions mixing MySQL Timestamp data types with UNIX Timestamp Integers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>That&#39;s a lot of databases</title>
      <link>/2021/03/24/a-lot-of-mysql.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/03/24/a-lot-of-mysql.html</guid>
      <description>Where I work, we are using MySQL a lot. The databases are being organized in replication hierarchies, and each hierarchy is a tree topology with a single primary and a number of intermediate replicas.
Replication is a tree managed by Orchestrator   We are using MySQL orchestrator to manage the replication topology.
MySQL Orchestrator shows a typical replication hierarchy. Each color indicates a different data center/availability zone. Replication is a tree, from the primary to per-AZ intermediate replicas for fan-out to leaf replicas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Memory saturated MySQL</title>
      <link>/2021/03/12/memory-saturated-mysql.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/03/12/memory-saturated-mysql.html</guid>
      <description>»If at all possible, we build databases so that the working set of the database fits into memory.« What does that even mean?
Working Set   In computer science, the “Working Set” of a program is the set of things it will be accessing in the near future. Because computer science has not yet solved looking into the future, we are looking at the set of things we accessed most recently and hope for The Best™.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL from Below</title>
      <link>/2021/02/25/mysql-from-below.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/02/25/mysql-from-below.html</guid>
      <description>When you insert data into a database and run COMMIT you expect things to be there: Atomically, Consistent, Isolated and Durable , like Codd commanded us 40 years ago, but also quickly. There is a surprising amount of sophistication being poured into this, but since I do not want to shame MongoDB and Redis developers in this post, I am not going to talk about that much in this place.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Validating storage</title>
      <link>/2021/02/24/validating-storage.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/02/24/validating-storage.html</guid>
      <description>Where I work, we try to run databases in a memory saturated way. That is, we try to provide so much memory that the working set of the database is memory resident, or in other words, the number of disk reads after an initial warmup is no longer dependent on the database load.
Workload Intelligence Analytics showing &amp;ldquo;IOPS over time&amp;rdquo; for a mixed read/write benchmark on Datera iSCSI.
We can validate and prove that with automated load testing: For each replication chain we single out a production host, and increase the hosts weight in the load balancer until the system load1 becomes critical.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Database as a Queue</title>
      <link>/2021/01/28/database-as-a-queue.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/28/database-as-a-queue.html</guid>
      <description>The DBA experience at work suggests that every single schema at some point in its lifecycle holds a queue table. These are tables in which some processes (the “producers”) put rows, which a swarm of other processes (the “consumers”) lock and consume.
A variation on that theme is the state machine, in which jobs are placed by producers. Consumers do not immediately delete them, but update them a few times to indicate processing progress, before the rows are ultimately being deleted.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unlimited Mail Addresses</title>
      <link>/2021/01/20/unlimited-mail-adresses.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/20/unlimited-mail-adresses.html</guid>
      <description>When people ask for my mail address, they usually get a personalized address from me. That is particularly true for all commercial email. So you don&amp;rsquo;t get to send mail to my main account, but to kris-yourbusiness@koehntopp.de , and that will end up going into INBOX.special.yourbusiness. At least until it leaks, receives spam or is otherwise burned. In which case I will short it out and route all incoming mail on that address to /dev/null.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Labyrinths (in Python)</title>
      <link>/2021/01/10/labyrinths-in-python.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/10/labyrinths-in-python.html</guid>
      <description>My son wants labyrinths. Ok, let&amp;rsquo;s make them like it&amp;rsquo;s the first semester.
We need a class Labyrinth that holds the dimensions of our maze, and the actual maze, in grid - a List of Lists of integers. That&amp;rsquo;s not exactly a two-dimensional array (it can have a ragged right edge), but it will do for us.
A basic container for labyrinths   class Labyrinth: &amp;#34;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;Store a labyrinth as a List of Lists of Integers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Python to bash</title>
      <link>/2021/01/05/using-python-to-bash.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/05/using-python-to-bash.html</guid>
      <description>Heise writes an introduction to bash programming (in german) :
 Bash ist eine vollwertige Programmiersprache, mit der Sie alltägliche Aufgaben leicht automatisieren.
Bash is a fully featured programming language that you can use to automate everyday tasks.
 Bash is not a fully featured programming language at all, and nothing in bash is ever easy. You are advised to use a proper programming language early on in development, and if possible never put bash commands into a file.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>fork, exec, wait and exit</title>
      <link>/2020/12/28/fork-exec-wait-and-exit.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/12/28/fork-exec-wait-and-exit.html</guid>
      <description>This is the english version of a 2007 article .
In de.comp.os.unix.linux.misc somebody asked:
  Are commands in a script executed strictly sequentially, that is, will the next command only be executed when the previous command has completed, or will the shell automatically start the next command if the system has spare capacity? Can I change the default behavior - whatever it may be - in any way?   If you are looking into the fine manual, it may explain at some point that the shell starts each command in a separate process.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SQL Clause is coming to town</title>
      <link>/2020/12/26/sql-clause-is-coming-to-town.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/12/26/sql-clause-is-coming-to-town.html</guid>
      <description>Olya Kudriavtseva has an ugly christmas sweater :
 &amp;ldquo;He&amp;rsquo;s making a table. He&amp;rsquo;s sorting it twice. SELECT * FROM contacts WHERE behavior = &amp;ldquo;nice&amp;rdquo;; SQL Clause is coming town! (buy here )
Katie Bauer observes :
 I mean, except for the fact that sorting something twice is TERRIBLY optimized
 So how bad is this? Let&amp;rsquo;s find out.
Some test data   We are defining a table santa, where we store peoples names (GDPR, EU Regulation 2016/679 applies!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Embracing the Stream</title>
      <link>/2020/12/09/embracing-the-stream.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/12/09/embracing-the-stream.html</guid>
      <description>So this happened: CentOS Project shifts focus to CentOS Stream  The future of the CentOS Project is CentOS Stream, and over the next year we’ll be shifting focus from CentOS Linux, the rebuild of Red Hat Enterprise Linux (RHEL), to CentOS Stream, which tracks just ahead of a current RHEL release. CentOS Linux 8, as a rebuild of RHEL 8, will end at the end of 2021. CentOS Stream continues after that date, serving as the upstream (development) branch of Red Hat Enterprise Linux.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not JOINing on PERFORMANCE_SCHEMA</title>
      <link>/2020/12/01/not-joining-on-performance-schema.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/12/01/not-joining-on-performance-schema.html</guid>
      <description>The tables in PERFORMANCE_SCHEMA (P_S) are not actually tables. You should not think of them as tables, even if your SQL works on them. You should not JOIN them, and you should not GROUP or ORDER BY them.
Unlocked memory buffers without indexes   The stuff in P_S has been created with &amp;ldquo;keep the impact on production small&amp;rdquo; in mind. That is, from a users point of view, you can think of them as unlocked memory buffers - the values in there change as you look at them, and there are precisely zero stability guarantees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Backups and Replication</title>
      <link>/2020/11/27/backups-and-replication.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/11/27/backups-and-replication.html</guid>
      <description>There was a question at work about MySQL backups and restore. I needed to explain more.
We use databases to make state persistent. That is: As a developer you can think of your database as a single giant, structured global variable with a weird access method, and to make things worse, concurrent access.
 A database is just a global variable to your code
 We can log statements that change the state of our database in a log.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gitlab in Docker</title>
      <link>/2020/11/22/gitlab-in-docker.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/11/22/gitlab-in-docker.html</guid>
      <description>These installation notes are mostly a note to myself, documenting the installation process of a Gitlab Omnibus Container in Docker, plus Gitlab Runners.
OS Setup   We are installing into /export/gitlab, a 10G xfs slice from the local flash pool:
# lvcreate -n gitlab -L 10G data # mkfs -t xfs /dev/data/gitlab # mkdir /export/gitlab # mount /dev/data/gitlab /export/gitlab # echo &amp;#34;/dev/data/gitlab\t/export/gitlab\txfs\tbsdgroups,usrquota,grpquota,attr2,nofail,noatime 1 2&amp;#34; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; /etc/fstab # mkdir /export/gitlab/{gitlab,gitlab-runner} # mkdir /export/gitlab/gitlab/{config,data,logs} Docker   We are using docker-compose to run this, with a .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the Observability of Outliers</title>
      <link>/2020/11/19/on-the-observability-of-outliers.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/11/19/on-the-observability-of-outliers.html</guid>
      <description>At work, I am in an ongoing discussion with a number of people on the Observability of Outliers. It started with the age-old question “How do I find slow queries in my application?” aka “What would I want from tooling to get that data and where should that tooling sit?”
 As a developer, I just want to automatically identify and isolate slow queries!
 Where I work, we do have SolarWinds Database Performance Monitor aka Vividcortex to find slow queries, so that helps.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My home sensor network</title>
      <link>/2020/11/15/my-home-sensor-network.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/11/15/my-home-sensor-network.html</guid>
      <description>I have been asked to document my home sensor network. Being married to a person with a background in web security sets boundary conditions:
 No cloud. We are running all services locally. No control, only metrics.  I am collecting data from a number of plugs with power meters over Wi-Fi, using the MQTT protocol. I am also collecting data from a number of temperature sensors over Zigbee, and convert to MQTT.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: Ecosystem fragmentation</title>
      <link>/2020/10/28/mysql-ecosystem-fragmentation.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/28/mysql-ecosystem-fragmentation.html</guid>
      <description>Sometimes things change in a way that is hard to put a finger on, but I am doing this MySQL thing since 3.23, and commercially since 2005, and the environment is changing. These days, when you talk to people in need of MySQL, the first thing you have to ask them is &amp;ldquo;Which MySQL&amp;rdquo;. And by that I do not mean a version number in the first place.
The answer may be:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Safe Biking: It&#39;s not the right of way that&#39;s wrong</title>
      <link>/2020/10/22/safe-biking-its-not-the-right-of-way-thats-wrong.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/22/safe-biking-its-not-the-right-of-way-thats-wrong.html</guid>
      <description>Sven Geggus trolled me . A bunch of nerds were speaking about what&amp;rsquo;s wrong with biking in Germany, and he wrote:
 Tweet : Der @isotopp wohnt doch in Holland. Wo sind denn bei euch die Vorfahrtsregeln anders und könnte man da was sinnvoll für .de übernehmen? &amp;ndash; @isotopp is living in the Netherlands. So how is the right of way different and how could .de learn from this?
Biking in the Netherlands does not suck, and that is not because of any specific traffic rules being any different, but because traffic is fundamentally different, and that somehow escalated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gespielt: Assassins Creed: Odyssey</title>
      <link>/2020/10/19/fertig-gespielt-assassins-creed-odyssey.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/19/fertig-gespielt-assassins-creed-odyssey.html</guid>
      <description>Ok, so the title is a bit of an exaggeration, I am about 80% done with the main games quests. Still, the shape and feel of the story is firmly established and it is fascinating. I have some 110 hours in &amp;ldquo;Assassins Creed: Origin&amp;rdquo;, and some 65 hours or so in &amp;ldquo;Assassins Creed: Odyssey&amp;rdquo;.
You can play &amp;ldquo;Assassins Creed: Odyssey&amp;rdquo; as Alexios or Kassandra, and the change is permanent for the playthrough for storytelling reasons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vijzelbuurt is changing</title>
      <link>/2020/10/08/vijzelbuurt-is-changing.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/08/vijzelbuurt-is-changing.html</guid>
      <description>Back when I was still commuting to work in an office, in the far past, I used to be in the Spaces building in Vijzelgracht in Amsterdam, every day. Mark Wagenbuur of BicycleDutch has been there today, and tweeted :
 Amsterdam is changing dramatically. I was in Vijzelstraat for the first time in about 2 years and I was pleasantly surprised! Looked up the old situation in Google StreetView for some before and afters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An unexpected pool size increase</title>
      <link>/2020/10/07/an-unexpeced-pool-size-increase.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/07/an-unexpeced-pool-size-increase.html</guid>
      <description>At work, replication chains have a single primary database node, to which you write, and then multiple replicas, in multiple AZs.
Here is what the one sample chain looks like in Orchestrator:
instance-918d is the current primary, in the blue AZ. Replicas in orange and green are in other AZs. Blue badges indicate multiple replicas, eg (38) means 38 machines.
When you talk to a database, you get two database handles:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What are the problems with POSIX?</title>
      <link>/2020/10/05/what-are-the-problems-with-posix.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/05/what-are-the-problems-with-posix.html</guid>
      <description>Every once in a while there is the IT news article that kind of triggers me. This time it was &amp;ldquo;Object-Storage-Protokoll könnte Posix ablösen&amp;rdquo; in german computer news site Golem . The article speaks about mmap(), NVMEoF and object storage and how it could revolutionize or complete object storages, but does not link to an original article, names no persons and no paper. Also, what do these things - mmap, NVMEoF, object storage and Posix, even have in common?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: Import CSV, not using LOAD DATA</title>
      <link>/2020/09/28/mysql-import-csv-not-using-load-data.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/28/mysql-import-csv-not-using-load-data.html</guid>
      <description>All over the Internet people are having trouble getting LOAD DATA and LOAD DATA LOCAL to work. Frankly, do not use them, and especially not the LOCAL variant. They are insecure, and even if you get them to work, they are limited and unlikely to do what you want. Write a small data load program as shown below.
Not using LOAD DATA LOCAL   The fine manual says :</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Importing account statements and building a data warehouse</title>
      <link>/2020/09/26/my-private-data-warehouse.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/26/my-private-data-warehouse.html</guid>
      <description>This is an update and translation of a much older article , which I wrote in German Language back then. I was experimenting with importing the account statements from my German Sparkasse, which at that time were being made available as a CSV.
The initial data load   The data looked like this:
$ head -2 /home/kris/Documents/banking/umsatz-22758031-29122004.csv &amp;#34;Local Account&amp;#34;;&amp;#34;Book Date&amp;#34;;&amp;#34;Valuta Date&amp;#34;;&amp;#34;Transaction Type&amp;#34;; &amp;#34;Purpose&amp;#34;; &amp;#34;Remote Party&amp;#34;;&amp;#34;Remote Account&amp;#34;;&amp;#34;Bank Code&amp;#34;; &amp;#34;Amount&amp;#34;;&amp;#34;Currency&amp;#34;;&amp;#34;Info&amp;#34; &amp;#34;08154711&amp;#34;;&amp;#34;30.12&amp;#34;;&amp;#34;30.12.05&amp;#34;;&amp;#34;Direct Debit&amp;#34;; &amp;#34;DRP 08154711 040441777 INKL.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: automatic partitions surely would be nice</title>
      <link>/2020/09/25/mysql-dynamic-partitions-suck.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/25/mysql-dynamic-partitions-suck.html</guid>
      <description>In Deleting data we have been looking at a process that loads data into MySQL, leveraging partitions to make it easier and faster to later get rid of the data again. For this, we created three processes, a data loader process, and two observers - one for creating partitions, and one for deleting them.
The observer processes have been running ANALYZE TABLES and then polling INFORMATION_SCHEMA.PARTITIONS every 1/10th of a second to check if intervention is needed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: Deleting data</title>
      <link>/2020/09/24/mysql-deleting-data.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/24/mysql-deleting-data.html</guid>
      <description>Completing the data lifecycle is often harder than originally expected: Deleting data can cost sometimes way more than inserting it in the first place. MySQL Partitions can offer a way out. We have an earlier post on the subject.
A sample table, and a problem statement   Let&amp;rsquo;s define a kind of log table, to which data is added with an auto_increment id value and some data.
#! /usr/bin/env python3 from time import sleep from random import randint from multiprocessing import Process import click import MySQLdb import MySQLdb.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: Provisioning .mylogin.cnf</title>
      <link>/2020/09/23/mylogin-cnf.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/23/mylogin-cnf.html</guid>
      <description>MySQL uses connection and config parameters from a number of possible sources. The easiest way to find out where it is looking for config files is to run
$ mysql --help | grep cnf order of preference, my.cnf, $MYSQL_TCP_PORT, /etc/my.cnf /etc/mysql/my.cnf /Users/kkoehntopp/homebrew/etc/my.cnf ~/.my.cnf As can be seen, my version of the MySQL client checks in this order
 /etc/my.cnf /etc/mysql/my.cnf /Users/kkoehntopp/homebrew/etc/my/cnf ~/.my.cnf  The cnf file is a file in dot-ini syntax, so you have [groups] and each group contains lines with key = value pairs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: ALTER TABLE for UUID</title>
      <link>/2020/09/22/alter-table-for-uuid.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/22/alter-table-for-uuid.html</guid>
      <description>A question to the internal #DBA channel at work: »Is it possible to change a column type from BIGINT to VARCHAR ? Will the numbers be converted into a string version of the number or will be it a byte-wise transition that will screw the values?«
Further asking yielded more information: »The use-case is to have strings, to have UUIDs.«
So we have two questions to answer:
 Is ALTER TABLE t CHANGE COLUMN c lossy?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: Encoding fields for great profit.</title>
      <link>/2020/09/18/mysql-encoding-fields-for-great-profit.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/18/mysql-encoding-fields-for-great-profit.html</guid>
      <description>Iterating schemas over time is not an uncommon thing. Often requirements emerge only after you have data, and then directed action is possible. Consequently, working on existing data, and structuring and cleaning it up is a common task.
In todays example we work with a log table that logged state transitions of things in freeform VARCHAR fields. After some time the log table grew quite sizeable, and the log strings are repeated rather often, contributing to the overall size of the table considerably.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feeds tagged, and a MySQL feed</title>
      <link>/2020/09/09/feeds-tagged-and-a-mysql-feed.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/09/feeds-tagged-and-a-mysql-feed.html</guid>
      <description>I have made changes to the RSS Feed of this blog:
 Each &amp;lt;item/&amp;gt; does now contain a container &amp;lt;tags/&amp;gt;, inside a sequence of &amp;lt;tag/&amp;gt; containers, with each posts tags. There is now a second RSS feed for posts tagged #mysql, because of demand. You can find it at https://blog.koehntopp.info/feed_mysql.xml .  Example for the tags:
&amp;lt;channel&amp;gt; &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt; ... &amp;lt;item&amp;gt; &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;A post title&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt; &amp;lt;link&amp;gt;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/09/...&amp;lt;/link&amp;gt; &amp;lt;guid isPermalink=&amp;#34;false&amp;#34;&amp;gt;/2020/09/...&amp;lt;/guid&amp;gt; &amp;lt;tags&amp;gt;&amp;lt;tag&amp;gt;lang_en&amp;lt;/tag&amp;gt;&amp;lt;tag&amp;gt;mysql&amp;lt;/tag&amp;gt;&amp;lt;tag&amp;gt;database&amp;lt;/tag&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/tags&amp;gt; &amp;lt;description&amp;gt;blah blah blah&amp;lt;/description&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/item&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/channel&amp;gt; So if you want only the MySQL content, subscribe to this feed , if you want all the content, subscribe to the original feed .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL from a Developers Perspective</title>
      <link>/2020/09/07/mysql-from-a-developers-perspective.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/07/mysql-from-a-developers-perspective.html</guid>
      <description>So this has turned into a small series, explaining how to work with MYSQL from a developers perspective. This post is intended as a directory for the individual articles. It will be amended and re-dated as necessary.
The code for the series is also available in isotopp/mysql-dev-examples on GitHub.
The Tag #mysqldev will reference all articles from this series.
  MySQL Transactions - the physical side . Looking at how MySQL InnoDB handles transactions on the physical media, enabling rollback and commit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: Generated Columns and virtual indexes</title>
      <link>/2020/09/07/mysql-generated-columns-and-virtual-indexes.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/07/mysql-generated-columns-and-virtual-indexes.html</guid>
      <description>We have had a look at how MySQL 8 handles JSON recently, but with all those JSON functions and expressions it is clear that many JSON accesses cannot be fast. To grab data from a JSON column, you will use a lot of $-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;field expressions and similar, and without indexes nothing of this will be fast.
JSON cannot be indexed.
But MySQL 8 offers another feature that comes in handy: Generated columns and indexes on those.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: Basic usage of the JSON data type</title>
      <link>/2020/09/04/mysql-json-data-type.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/04/mysql-json-data-type.html</guid>
      <description>MySQL 8 provides solid support for the JSON data type. The manual has an overview of the data type , a JSON function reference , an an overview on generated column indexes , and explains multi-values indexes .
Creating JSON columns   Creating JSON columns is easy: Make the column of the JSON data type, fill in valid JSON data.
mysql&amp;gt;createtablet(idintegernotnullprimarykeyauto_increment,jjson);QueryOK,0rowsaffected(0.11sec)mysql&amp;gt;insertintot(j)values-&amp;gt;(&amp;#39;null&amp;#39;),-&amp;gt;(&amp;#39;true&amp;#39;),-&amp;gt;(&amp;#39;false&amp;#39;),-&amp;gt;(&amp;#39;1&amp;#39;),-&amp;gt;(&amp;#39;&amp;#34;keks&amp;#34;&amp;#39;),-&amp;gt;(&amp;#39;[&amp;#34;eins&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;zwei&amp;#34;]&amp;#39;),-&amp;gt;(&amp;#39;{&amp;#34;eins&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;one&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;zwei&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;two&amp;#34;}&amp;#39;);QueryOK,5rowsaffected(0.02sec)mysql&amp;gt;selectjson_type(j)astype,json_valid(j)asvalid,isnull(j)assqlnull,j,idfromt;+---------+-------+---------+--------------------------------+----+ |type|valid|sqlnull|j|id|+---------+-------+---------+--------------------------------+----+ |NULL|NULL|1|NULL|1||NULL|1|0|null|2||BOOLEAN|1|0|true|3||BOOLEAN|1|0|false|4||INTEGER|1|0|1|5||STRING|1|0|&amp;#34;keks&amp;#34;|6||ARRAY|1|0|[&amp;#34;eins&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;zwei&amp;#34;]|7||OBJECT|1|0|{&amp;#34;eins&amp;#34;:&amp;#34;one&amp;#34;,&amp;#34;zwei&amp;#34;:&amp;#34;two&amp;#34;}|8|+---------+-------+---------+--------------------------------+----+ 8rowsinset(0.00sec)mysql&amp;gt;insertintot(j)values(&amp;#39;[&amp;#34;incomplete&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;array&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;closing bracket&amp;#34;&amp;#39;);ERROR3140(22032):InvalidJSONtext:&amp;#34;Missing a comma or &amp;#39;]&amp;#39; after an array element.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MacOS: Deleting Relocated Items</title>
      <link>/2020/09/02/macos-relocated-items.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/02/macos-relocated-items.html</guid>
      <description>I had to upgrade my company issued MacBook pro to Catalina for fleet unity reasons. The upgrade left me with a folder Relocated Items in /Users/Shared/Desktop and a link to that prominently on my Desktop.
Deleting that folder moved it to trash. Trying to empty trash then failed. That is because in that folder was several levels deep a folder or link to X11R6.
Apple considers that file outdated, which is why it ended up in Relocated Items.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Touching Candles, And Error Budgets</title>
      <link>/2020/08/31/on-touching-candles.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/31/on-touching-candles.html</guid>
      <description>Ok, it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Dad Stories&amp;rdquo; Time (from Twitter ). When my son was somewhat older than a year, he was learning to speak. He could already say &amp;ldquo;Mama&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Papa&amp;rdquo;.
It was around Christmas, and there was a candle on the table, glowing interestingly, so he wanted to touch it. &amp;ldquo;Nein, heiß&amp;rdquo; is what you would say in German.
Of course, a toddler does not understand the meaning of &amp;ldquo;heiß&amp;rdquo;. I mean, he&amp;rsquo;s trying to imitate the sound of it, but the meaning of &amp;ldquo;heiß&amp;rdquo; is something specific.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: NULL is NULL</title>
      <link>/2020/08/25/null-is-null.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/25/null-is-null.html</guid>
      <description>Question: Hey, I got a UNIQUE INDEX, but I can store multiple rows with the same value, NULL. That is surprising. Is that a bug?
 This is a rewrite of the same in German from 9 years ago .
 root@localhost[kris]&amp;gt;createtablet(ainteger,binteger,unique(a,b));QueryOK,0rowsaffected(0.09sec)root@localhost[kris]&amp;gt;insertintotvalues(1,2);QueryOK,1rowaffected(0.01sec)root@localhost[kris]&amp;gt;insertintotvalues(1,2);ERROR1062(23000):Duplicateentry&amp;#39;1-2&amp;#39;forkey&amp;#39;t.a&amp;#39;This does not work, as expected. But this does:
root@localhost[kris]&amp;gt;truncatetablet;QueryOK,0rowsaffected(0.16sec)root@localhost[kris]&amp;gt;insertintotvalues(1,NULL);QueryOK,1rowaffected(0.02sec)root@localhost[kris]&amp;gt;insertintotvalues(1,NULL);QueryOK,1rowaffected(0.03sec)root@localhost[kris]&amp;gt;select*fromt;+------+------+ |a|b|+------+------+ |1|NULL||1|NULL|+------+------+ 2rowsinset(0.00sec)Why is that?
This is usually where I point people at SQL for Smarties: Advanced SQL Programming .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why do Ops and Sec people wear black</title>
      <link>/2020/08/19/why-do-ops-and-sec-people-wear-black.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/19/why-do-ops-and-sec-people-wear-black.html</guid>
      <description>For reasons that don&amp;rsquo;t need exploring at this juncture I tweeted  Once upon a time there were shared boxes, on which the local Unix easily had 200-300 users, Junior Developers at a University.
A /tmp/ls found easily 3-4 people per day that had . (dot) in their path.
No particular reason. Why?
 and followed up with
 Hope is not a strategy.
Neither is curl stackoverflow | sudo bash.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: Some Character Set Basics</title>
      <link>/2020/08/18/mysql-character-sets.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/18/mysql-character-sets.html</guid>
      <description>This is the updated and english version of some older posts of mine in German. It is likely still incomplete, and will need information added to match current MySQL, but hopefully it is already useful.
Old source articles in German: 1 , 2 and 3 .
Some vocabulary   Symbol, Font, Encoding and Collation - what do they even mean?
A character set is a collection of symbols that belong together.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Building the Cycling City</title>
      <link>/2020/08/17/building-the-cycling-city.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/17/building-the-cycling-city.html</guid>
      <description>Melissa and Chris Bruntlett have been living in Vancouver close to the station, and decided to do as many daily runs as possible without a car, using public transport or bikes. In late 2015, early 2016 they did an extended visit to the Netherlands which resulted in a changed world view about what proper Urban Infrastructure can look like. Meanwhile they are living with two kids near Delft, in the Netherlands.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: A Wizard&#39;s Guide To Defensive Baking</title>
      <link>/2020/08/16/fertig-gelesen-defensive-baking.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/16/fertig-gelesen-defensive-baking.html</guid>
      <description>A Wizard&amp;rsquo;s Guide To Defensive Baking is a Yound Adult Coming-of-Age story about Mona. Mona works in her aunt&amp;rsquo;s bakery, and also is a hedge wizard. Her talent is mostly limited to influencing dough and baked goods, her familiar is a sourdough starter named Bob.
 A Wizards Guide To Defensive Baking, T. Kingfisher, Amazon Mona is a 14-year-old girl living in Riverbraid, a random city-state near a river in the floodplain of an otherwise unnamed country that vaguely feels like northern Italy during renaissance times.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ELI5: Epic vs Apple and Google</title>
      <link>/2020/08/14/eli5-epic-vs-apple-and-google.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/14/eli5-epic-vs-apple-and-google.html</guid>
      <description>@jpmens asked on Twitter:
 What is Fortnite? #outingmyself
Assuming XKCD 1053 .
Fortnite   Fortnite is a game made by Epic Games. They also make the Unreal Engine, which powers many modern computer games. Fortnite together with Roblox and Minecraft it is the set of games played most by people under 20.
You want to follow Matthew Ball .
Fortnite is a Battle Royal game, a 1st person shooter, in which a matchmaker puts you together with a set of other people of similar skill, drops you into an arena of ever shrinking size.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Foreign Key Constraints and Locking</title>
      <link>/2020/08/04/mysql-foreign-key-constraints-and-locking.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/04/mysql-foreign-key-constraints-and-locking.html</guid>
      <description>Since we now know how to look at the state of locking in a live database, let&amp;rsquo;s look at what happens when we run a normal insert or update and an insert or update with foreign key relationships defined, and compare.
We will be using the tables and structures from our previous examples, a simple 1:n relationship between a and b:
CREATETABLEa(a_idintNOTNULLAUTO_INCREMENT,PRIMARYKEY(a_id));INSERTINTOaVALUES(10),(20),(30),(40);CREATETABLEb(b_idintNOTNULLAUTO_INCREMENT,a_idintNOTNULL,PRIMARYKEY(b_id),KEY`a_id`(a_id),CONSTRAINTa_id_existsFOREIGNKEY(a_id)REFERENCESa(a_id)ONDELETERESTRICTONUPDATERESTRICT);INSERTINTObVALUES(10,10),(40,40);or the same definition for b without the constraint.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Foreign Keys and Foreign Key Constraints</title>
      <link>/2020/08/03/mysql-foreign-keys-and-foreign-key-constraints.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/03/mysql-foreign-keys-and-foreign-key-constraints.html</guid>
      <description>Foreign Keys are what links tables together and turns a set of tables into a model. Foreign Key Constraints are conditions that must be true for the content of the tables to be an internally consistent model. Foreign Key Constraints can be defined and enforced in InnoDB, but this comes at a considerable price, and for some it may hurt more than it is worth.
A very simple shop as a ER-model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Deadlocks with INSERT</title>
      <link>/2020/08/02/mysql-deadlocks-with-insert.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/02/mysql-deadlocks-with-insert.html</guid>
      <description>Support Channel. &amp;ldquo;Hi, I am getting deadlocks in the database and they occur when I have to rollback the transactions but if we don&amp;rsquo;t have to roll back all transactions get executed.&amp;rdquo; Wait, what? After some back and forth it becomes clear that the Dev experiences deadlocks and has data:
mysql&amp;gt;pagerlessmysql&amp;gt;showengineinnodbstatus\G...MySQLthreadid142531,OSthreadhandle139990258222848,queryid4799571somehost.somedomainsomeuserupdateINSERTintosometable(identifier_id,currency,balance)VALUES(&amp;#39;d4e84cb1-4d56-4d67-9d16-1d548fd26b55&amp;#39;,&amp;#39;EUR&amp;#39;,&amp;#39;0&amp;#39;)***(2)HOLDSTHELOCK(S):RECORDLOCKSspaceid3523pageno1106463nbits224indexPRIMARYoftable`somedb`.`sometable`trxid9843342279lockmodeSlocksgapbeforerecand that is weird because of the lock mode S locks gap in the last line. We get the exact same statement with the exact same value on the second thread, but with lock mode X locks gap.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL: Locks and Deadlocks</title>
      <link>/2020/08/01/mysql-locks-and-deadlocks.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/01/mysql-locks-and-deadlocks.html</guid>
      <description>In a previous article we wrote data to the database using atomic update statements, and then using transactions with SELECT ... FOR UPDATE. In this article we will look at what happens when we continue doing this, in a more complicated way. Source code for this article is also available on github.com .
A simple row lock   But first let&amp;rsquo;s do things manually: We create a table kris with an integer primary key column and a secondary unindexed data column.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Transactions - writing data</title>
      <link>/2020/07/30/mysql-transactions-writing-data.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/30/mysql-transactions-writing-data.html</guid>
      <description>Using the framework for testing we created in earlier articles, let&amp;rsquo;s try to modify some data. We are writing a small program that increments a counter. Our table looks like this, and contains 10 counters:
CREATETABLE`demo`(`id`bigintunsignedNOTNULLAUTO_INCREMENT,`counter`intNOTNULLDEFAULT&amp;#39;0&amp;#39;,UNIQUEKEY`id`(`id`))INSERTINTO`demo`VALUES(1,0);INSERTINTO`demo`VALUES(2,0);...INSERTINTO`demo`VALUES(10,0);We are using some very simple programming to increment a counter:
@sql.command() @click.option(&amp;#34;--name&amp;#34;, default=&amp;#34;demo&amp;#34;, help=&amp;#34;Table name to count in&amp;#34;) @click.option(&amp;#34;--id&amp;#34;, default=0, help=&amp;#34;Counter to use&amp;#34;) @click.option(&amp;#34;--count&amp;#34;, default=1000, help=&amp;#34;Number of increments&amp;#34;) def count(name, id, count): &amp;#34;&amp;#34;&amp;#34; Increment counter --id by --count many steps in table --name &amp;#34;&amp;#34;&amp;#34; for i in range(0, count): cmd = f&amp;#34;update {name}set counter=counter+1 where id = {id}&amp;#34; c = db.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Transactions - the logical side</title>
      <link>/2020/07/29/mysql-transactions-the-logical-view.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/29/mysql-transactions-the-logical-view.html</guid>
      <description>After having a look how MySQL handles transactions physically , let&amp;rsquo;s have a look at what is going on from a logical point of view.
We are using a test table called demo with an id and a counter field, both integer. In it we have 10 counters, all set to 0.
CREATETABLE`demo`(`id`bigintunsignedNOTNULLAUTO_INCREMENT,`counter`intNOTNULLDEFAULT&amp;#39;0&amp;#39;,UNIQUEKEY`id`(`id`))INSERTINTO`demo`VALUES(1,0);INSERTINTO`demo`VALUES(2,0);...INSERTINTO`demo`VALUES(10,0);In one session, we start a transaction and modify a counter value. We do not commit anything.
Session1&amp;gt;starttransactionreadwrite;Session1&amp;gt;updatedemosetcounter=10whereid=3;Isolation   In a second session, we check the data and notice a few things:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Connection Scoped State</title>
      <link>/2020/07/28/mysql-connection-scoped-state.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/28/mysql-connection-scoped-state.html</guid>
      <description>MySQL speaks its own proprietary protocol. It cannot be routed by a HTTP proxy, and a MySQL connection is entire unlike a HTTP connection. Specifically, a lot of state and configuration is tied to a MySQL connection, and it cannot be recovered on disconnect.
What state is tied to a connection?   Transactions   A disconnect implies a ROLLBACK. So if you are in a transaction, all changes to the database that you attempted are lost, rolled back, as if they never happened.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Commit Size and Speed</title>
      <link>/2020/07/27/mysql-commit-size-and-speed.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/27/mysql-commit-size-and-speed.html</guid>
      <description>When writing data to disk, for small transactions the cost of writing the commit out do disk dominates the execution time of the script. In order to show that, I wrote a little bit of Python.
The script creates a test table in a database and writes 10.000 rows of test data into it, in commit sizes of 1, 2, 4, &amp;hellip;, 1024 rows.
$ ./mysql.py --help Usage: mysql.py [OPTIONS] COMMAND [ARGS].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Transactions - the physical side</title>
      <link>/2020/07/27/mysql-transactions.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/27/mysql-transactions.html</guid>
      <description>So you talk to a database, doing transactions. What happens actually, behind the scenes? Let’s have a look.
There is a test table and we write data into it inside a transaction:
CREATETABLEt(idserial,datavarbinary(255))STARTTRANSACTIONREADWRITEINSERTINTOt(id,data)VALUES(NULL,RANDOM_BYTES(255))COMMITThe MySQL test instance we are talking to is running on a Linux machine, and otherwise idle to make observation easier. Also, we configured it with innodb_use_native_aio = false because observing actual physical asynchronous I/O and attributing it to the statement that caused it is really hard.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So I am a Windows User now</title>
      <link>/2020/07/07/so-i-am-a-windows-user-now.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/07/so-i-am-a-windows-user-now.html</guid>
      <description>So I am a Windows User now. I have an old MacBook pro, Late-2013 13&amp;quot; Retina, i7, 16 GB, 1 TB SSD, and the battery is done now, after 7 years. Also, the hardware is aging, and I want it refurbished and upgrade the son&amp;rsquo;s equipment (which is the previous 2010 MBP I had at that time).
Modern Apple is not my thing. I have a company MBP, 2018 Retina 13&amp;quot; Four-Port, i7, 16 GB, and everything about this device is wrong.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I set up my Python</title>
      <link>/2020/06/29/how-i-set-up-my-python.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/29/how-i-set-up-my-python.html</guid>
      <description>Because Martin wanted some starting point, here is how I set up my Python. There are a lot of other things one can do, but this is supposed to be just a starting point.
For a new project, make a project directory, usually not with a local git repository.
kk:Python kris$ mkdir project kk:Python kris$ cd project kk:project kris$ git init Initialized empty Git repository in /Users/kris/Python/project/.git/ We need a virtual environment to keep our modules apart from the system python.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Window Functions</title>
      <link>/2020/06/21/mysql-window-functions.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/21/mysql-window-functions.html</guid>
      <description>Two questions from Reddit&amp;rsquo;s /r/mysql related to Window Functions: How do I make row.numbers happen and Get the difference between two values in different recordings .
One of the new things in MySQL is the implementation of Window Functions. They are related to aggregates, but do not actually lump values together.
To better understand what goes on, let&amp;rsquo;s create some fake data to work with:
#! /usr/bin/env python3 # -*- coding: utf-8 -*- import MySQLdb as mdb import MySQLdb.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Export the entire database to CSV</title>
      <link>/2020/06/20/export-the-entire-database-to-csv.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/20/export-the-entire-database-to-csv.html</guid>
      <description>A question from Reddit&amp;rsquo;s /r/mysql:
 Really new to MySQL and had a request to export an entire database to csv for review. I can manually export each table using workbench but there are 10+ tables and 10+ databases so I was looking to export the entire database to csv.
 It is likely that you have additional requirements on top of this, so it would be best to script this in a way that would allow for customization.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pizza, People, Projects and Processes</title>
      <link>/2020/06/15/pizza-people-projects-and-processes.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/15/pizza-people-projects-and-processes.html</guid>
      <description>An older talk from 2 years ago, which for some reason I was not able to find in the blog.
For reasons that do not need exploration at this junction I had to explain Processes and Process Maturity some time ago, and a colleague asked me to put my thinking into a talk. So this is going to be boring, because you are likely to know most of this already, but on the other hand, it is good to be on the same page when it comes to models and vocabulary.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where do the JOINs go?</title>
      <link>/2020/06/10/where-do-the-joins-go.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/10/where-do-the-joins-go.html</guid>
      <description>I was asking on Twitter:
 Are you a Developer and understand (Micro-) Services? I am a database person and a bit simple, and I have a genuine Question:
When moving to a services architecture, where do the JOINs go?
I gave the following context:
 A simple shop
So you sell stuff, that is, you have an orders table o with an oid, which stores a customer id cid from a customers c table, and an article id aid, from an articles table a and a count cnt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sonos just got complicated</title>
      <link>/2020/06/09/sonos-just-got-complicated.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/09/sonos-just-got-complicated.html</guid>
      <description>So this morning the 08:10 alarm in the living room did not go off. It was set to remind the son that it is time to get going for school. We noticed in time, but when I looked into the &amp;ldquo;Why?&amp;rdquo; things got interesting. That alarm is a chime from the household Sonos system, and when I investigated, I got this:
Sonos did the split and upgraded/rebranded their controller operating system to S1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cloud and Energy</title>
      <link>/2020/06/08/cloud-and-energy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/08/cloud-and-energy.html</guid>
      <description>In Data Centers and Energy I wrote about Hyperscaler Data Centers and Open Compute, and how they bring down the PUE of data centers, making them more efficient, and in Streaming and Energy I followed up on this, explaining how Netflix energy usage fits into this. Now the Uptime Institute has released a study that claims &amp;ldquo;Data center energy efficiency gains have flattened out&amp;rdquo;.
It is summarized as:
 The average power usage effectiveness (PUE) ratio for a data center in 2020 is 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waffle House Index of Tooling</title>
      <link>/2020/06/08/waffle-house-index-of-tooling.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/08/waffle-house-index-of-tooling.html</guid>
      <description>Charity Majors was on fire and on target, again :
 What is a Waffle House Index ?
 The Waffle House Index is an informal metric named after the Waffle House restaurant chain and is used by the Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA) to determine the effect of a storm and the likely scale of assistance required for disaster recovery.
 A &amp;ldquo;Waffle House Index for Tooling&amp;rdquo; would be an indicator how bad the situation on the ground in an IT department is.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fixing &#34;ip netns&#34; for docker</title>
      <link>/2020/06/07/fixing-ip-netns-for-docker.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/07/fixing-ip-netns-for-docker.html</guid>
      <description>So I want to monitor my Jitsi Videobridge to get some useful statistics. The instructions say to enable Videobridge statistics and then grab stuff from port 8080.
Ok, I think I did that, but it did not work. Time to dig into the container network config.
And while I have a lot of network namespaces, they are unknown to ip netns, as can be seen when asking for a list. When we define a network namespace with ip netns, it will symlink the assigned name from /var/run/netns/&amp;lt;name&amp;gt; to /proc/&amp;lt;pid&amp;gt;/ns/net of the process that leads that namespace.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimistic locking</title>
      <link>/2020/06/04/optimistic-locking.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/04/optimistic-locking.html</guid>
      <description>A question from Reddit&amp;rsquo;s /r/mysql:
 Hey, I was planning to make a dashboard, where Users are subjected to make edits on their profiles every now and then, and I expect a high volume of requests to the database.
Having worked previously with MySQL for another Dashboard, I encountered errors for:
  Maximum user connections - when I connected to the database only while query was to be executed</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL store_result and use_result</title>
      <link>/2020/06/01/mysql-storeresult-and-useresult.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/01/mysql-storeresult-and-useresult.html</guid>
      <description>A question from Reddit’s /r/mysql led to a longer discussion of cursors and how they are implemented in MySQL, and what the advantages and drawbacks are.
The OP probably had a slow query, but was misphrasing the question:
 I am having performance problems where my cursor is taking 6-8 seconds to go through a hundred rows. I think this is because I am also using while loops to loop through JSON objects to pull information.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time Machine Editor</title>
      <link>/2020/05/26/time-machine-editor.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/26/time-machine-editor.html</guid>
      <description>I have an embedded Mac mini, it drives the local TV screen by doing OpenVPN to Germany, Netflix, Amazon and the local Subsonic . It does not really do much with the local disk, and it does not need to wake up every hour to make a Time Machine backup over the network.
To change the backup interval, install Time Machine Editor .
 Time Machine Editor can change the Time Machine Backup interval.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Air Quality Sensors</title>
      <link>/2020/05/25/air-quality-sensors.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/25/air-quality-sensors.html</guid>
      <description>In an earlier episode I asked for Plugs with Wi-Fi and ended up with Gosund and Tasmota . Considering this to be a success, I asked the Twitters for Temperature and Humidity Sensors. Of course, this got complicated.
 Now that I have Powermeter Plugs everywhere: What are good sensors for temperature, humidity and CO2 that can be tasmotified? Wi-Fi, http or mqtt?
I was pointed to Xiaomi Aqara , but these do not do Wi-Fi, but Zigbee - whatever that is, it is spoken by Zigbee USB Gateway Sticks and works with Raspi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gosund and Tasmota</title>
      <link>/2020/05/20/gosund-and-tasmota.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/20/gosund-and-tasmota.html</guid>
      <description>(continued from Plugs with Wi-Fi ) So the Gosund plugs came, as did the Raspi 4. I did cancel the Shelly plug and decomissioned the TP-Link Kaka, because Tasmota on Gosund is awesome and the Gosund hardware is dirt cheap.
Power consumption of the local data grave, with too old a mainboard and CPU and way too much storage
But lets start at the beginning:
4 Pack of Gosund SP111 V1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Note to self: Archiving Discord Chats</title>
      <link>/2020/05/18/note-to-self-archiving-discord-chats.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/18/note-to-self-archiving-discord-chats.html</guid>
      <description>When the Coronacrisis began, a good friend of mine started a Discord server and brought the band back together. As with any of the Coronavirus Quarantine Chats, the initial discussion revolved around baking proper bread. I wanted to archive this, so I needed a way to download Discord chat histories for archive.
The DiscordChatExporter can do that, and doing this was actually easy.
I needed
 Docker my Discord User Token No Discord Bot Token The Discord Channel ID  and then did a small starter script:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deleting data from MySQL</title>
      <link>/2020/05/13/deleting-data-from-mysql.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/13/deleting-data-from-mysql.html</guid>
      <description>I have been pointed at the following question: »Has anyone ever used mySQL events to auto-delete rows from a table after set period? Wondering your experience of doing this.«
 There are two ends to this question:
 expiring data from a MySQL table doing this with the event scheduler  Mass-deleting data from InnoDB   You can of course delete data from a table using the SQL DELETE statement with an arbitrary WHERE-clause at any time:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plugs with Wi-Fi</title>
      <link>/2020/05/12/plugs-with-wifi.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/12/plugs-with-wifi.html</guid>
      <description>So we are baking bread, and for that we have a Wiesheu minimat oven that comes in at a full 16A - supposedly it is using 3kW or more peak plus the condenser hood that comes in at another 500W top power draw. On the other hand, when running the thing is hardly lukewarm, it is running much cooler than the Neff household oven/microwave combo we have.
Wiesheu minimat with condenser hood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Access Programs and Pre-SQL systems</title>
      <link>/2020/05/01/data-access-programs.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/01/data-access-programs.html</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s have a look at very old database systems. Things like dBase or compatible systems (&amp;ldquo;xBases&amp;rdquo;) allowed to manipulate record based files (with indexes) in a procedural way. What does that mean?
xBase   The system allows developers to create files that contain a well defined (fixed size) record structure, basically an array of struct on disk, often together with the definition of on-screen masks designed to show a single record and a (searchable) list of records.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Deathworlders</title>
      <link>/2020/05/01/fertig-gelesen-deathworlders.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/01/fertig-gelesen-deathworlders.html</guid>
      <description>In the foreword to his short story &amp;ldquo;With Friends Like These&amp;quot; , Alan Dean Foster writes
HFY?    My favorite writer of science fiction was, and still is, the inimitable Eric Frank Russell. When I was turning in short stories to the magazines instead of papers to my college professors and collecting rejection slips instead of credits and grades, I often wondered why Russell had stopped writing. I miss him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Delta-V and Space Barons</title>
      <link>/2020/05/01/fertig-gelesen-delta-v-and-space-barons.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/01/fertig-gelesen-delta-v-and-space-barons.html</guid>
      <description>A lot of super rich people are currently busy blowing their money into space. Who are these people, and what drives them?
 Space Barons , Christian Davenport, 10.99 Eur (Kindle)
In Space Barons, Christian Davenport goes through the rather short list of super rich men who are trying to get private spacecraft flying, tells their history, successes and failures, and their motivations - or, in some cases, the story of the death of their dreams and how they drop out of the second, private space race.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Die Krone der Sterne: Hexenmacht/Maschinengötter</title>
      <link>/2020/05/01/fertig-gelesen-die-krone-der-sterne.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/01/fertig-gelesen-die-krone-der-sterne.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Hexenmacht&amp;rdquo; (German Edition) and &amp;ldquo;Maschinengötter&amp;rdquo; (German Edition) are part 2 and 3 in the series &amp;ldquo;Die Krone der Sterne&amp;rdquo; (The Crown of Stars) by Kai Meyer. See Die Krone der Sterne for a review of part 1.
 Hexenmacht , Kai Meyer, 12.99 Eur (Kindle)
Where part 1 spent a lot of time with world building and tourism, showing of the wonder and the atmosphere of the universe, part 2 is approaching from a different angle - we get a lot more action, and a lot less background.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Netflix does not bring down the Internet</title>
      <link>/2020/03/19/netflix-does-not-bring-down-the-internet.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/19/netflix-does-not-bring-down-the-internet.html</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s Coronavirus Crisis and Netflix is killing us all, again. This time it&amp;rsquo;s not their excessive energy use , but their dreaded HD videos that are overloading the Internet. Or is it?
It&amp;rsquo;s only Swisscom   Supposedly Switzerland is considering Netflix shutdown to prevent Home Office workers from being disconnected.
 According to its own statements, on the first day of the quasi curfew in our neighboring country, Swisscom recorded an enormous increase in the load on the infrastructure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The lack of developer centric MySQL monitoring - a rant</title>
      <link>/2020/03/18/the-lack-of-developer-centric-mysql-monitoring.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/18/the-lack-of-developer-centric-mysql-monitoring.html</guid>
      <description>So where I work we have a large number of MySQL instances. They are organized in a slightly smaller number of replication hierarchies, which tend to cross region boundaries.
Structure of a large database setup   A rough sketch of the setup we have. Variants of this exist in various sizes - from 6 replicas in 3 regions to hundreds of replicas per region, with Group Replication at the top and per Region Intermedia Master.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sonos recycled their recycle mode</title>
      <link>/2020/03/06/sonos-recycled-their-recycle-mode.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/06/sonos-recycled-their-recycle-mode.html</guid>
      <description>So I wrote about the Sonos Recycle Program before Sonos announced their plans to actively discontinue support for their older Speakers. Back then, the program did make sense, because it was kind of voluntary and avoided sending stuff back to Sonos for a Trade-Up. Even then, people disliked it.
Then Sonos announced that they would discontinue support for these devices and it&amp;rsquo;s basically &amp;lsquo;you brick them now, or we are going to brick them for you in May and without a rebate for new equipment&amp;rsquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some latency numbers illustrated</title>
      <link>/2020/02/28/some-latency-numbers-illustrated.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/28/some-latency-numbers-illustrated.html</guid>
      <description>These images are older than time itself. I picked them up while working as a consultant for MySQL AB, but I do not know the source.
Here are some important latency numbers. A pixel is a nanosecond (nano = 10^-9, a billionth of a second, 1 billion events/s = 1 GHz):
And below is the HDD disk seek latency in full at the same scale. An uncached index access can result in up to 5 disk seeks, worst case.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In which we cycle shopping...</title>
      <link>/2020/02/22/in-which-we-cycle-shopping.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/22/in-which-we-cycle-shopping.html</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the Netherlands. Please excuse me, I need to fetch a few things before I have time for you. I need a few things from Lidl in Hoofddorp, do you want to come with me?
It&amp;rsquo;s not far, we are taking the bike for some six kilometres. Also, I&amp;rsquo;m going to show you a trick: Look, Mom! Not riding with the cars, and no lights.
 Let&amp;rsquo;s follow path and go down Liniepad.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Under the sea...</title>
      <link>/2020/02/21/under-the-sea.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/21/under-the-sea.html</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the Netherlands. I am living at the bottom of a lake, 3.50 meters below the sea level, and there are sea shells in my garden.
When I dig in my garden, it looks like this.
The Netherlands (low lands) or Holland (hollow lands) are formed in large part by the Rhine Delta . This is an estuary delta (tidal delta), which means it is formed as much by erosion as it is formed by sedimentation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to build a cycling environment</title>
      <link>/2020/02/19/how-to-build-a-cycling-environment.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/19/how-to-build-a-cycling-environment.html</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the Netherlands. We&amp;rsquo;re building roads differently. They are better, safer and less stressful for cyclists, and that also makes them better, safer and less stressful for motorists. Here is how it works:
(based on a Twitter Thread )
What does it look like?   I am living in a village. That means a speed limit of 30 km/h inside the city limits, and that is being enforced by the design of the road.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some rules for primary keys</title>
      <link>/2020/01/28/some-rules-for-primary-keys.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/28/some-rules-for-primary-keys.html</guid>
      <description>On Twitter, @CaptainEyesight asked a question:
 »Database architecture question: For deleting records, instead of a DELETE, UPDATE the id to the negative (i.e. 1 becomes -1) and then add AND id &amp;gt; 0 to every query. Great idea? or Greatest idea?«
I was honestly a bit confused, because this idea is so weird that I took this question for a joke. But then I decided that this is a case for XKCD 1053 : »You are one of today&amp;rsquo;s lucky 10.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rolling back a rollout</title>
      <link>/2020/01/17/rolling-back-a-rollout.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/17/rolling-back-a-rollout.html</guid>
      <description>Florian Haas asks on Twitter :
&amp;ldquo;How do you solve reliable rollback. The definition of a reliable rollback being: &amp;lsquo;get reset &amp;ndash;hard &amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;git push -f&amp;rsquo; and then magic happening that returns your infra to the exact state it was at .&amp;rdquo;
The problem is relatively easy to solve with modern infrastructure-as-code for anything that is stateless. It becomes a bit more involved when you are dealing with things with state, such as database instances or Zookeepers or similar things.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disable Saitek X.52 pro Clutch Mode</title>
      <link>/2020/01/15/disable-saitek-x52-clutch-mode.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/15/disable-saitek-x52-clutch-mode.html</guid>
      <description>This post is a memo to self, and describes how to disable the X.52 clutch mode. I am flying with a Saitek/Logitech X.52 pro HOTAS , and this stick has a &amp;lsquo;clutch button&amp;rsquo; (labelled &amp;ldquo;i&amp;rdquo;) in the thumb position of the throttle (image: clutch highlighed in red)
&amp;ldquo;Clutch mode&amp;rdquo; for this button means that it is usable as a modfier for the other buttons, when pressed together with a second button.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sonos Recycle Mode</title>
      <link>/2019/12/30/sonos-recycle-mode.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/30/sonos-recycle-mode.html</guid>
      <description>Sonos is a company that makes Wi-Fi Connected speakers. They offer acceptable sound quality and an extremely good user experience. They also so far have never cancelled support for any of their speakers.
Hardware Lineup and Timeline   Some of their speakers are now qualified for a Trade-Up program, in particular their
 Play:5 (1st generation) speaker, the Connect:Amp and the Connect.  The latter two (the Connect products) are somewhat obsolete as they were necessary when normal Wi-Fi was usually not able to carry sound data at the required reliability, so Sonos speakers built their own Wi-Fi Mesh network separately from the usual home Wi-Fi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Streaming and Energy</title>
      <link>/2019/12/28/streaming-and-energy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/28/streaming-and-energy.html</guid>
      <description>A bunch of boomers in Germany is running a distraction campaign on the energy use of data centers and streaming. Example articles in german language can be found in Zeit and Bento , but there is a larger series of articles acrooss multiple newspapers.
A better structured reasoning can be found in SRF (German), and it highlights how arbitrary and wrong the energy numbers in the former articles are. But even this article ignores the facts that the energy consumption in a typical cloud data center is most likely carbon neutral, because the power used is likely to be completely green.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trying lvmraid for real</title>
      <link>/2019/12/03/trying-lvmraid-for-real.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/03/trying-lvmraid-for-real.html</guid>
      <description>So after testing LVM Raid in princple, I have been trying it on some real hardware to see what happens. The idea was to estimate if it scales and if not, how it doesn&amp;rsquo;t. I was expecting to run into all kinds of obscure problems in my testing, but in fact, it was a quick and short death.
Here is my box: QuantaGrid D42A-2U with an AMD EPYC 7551P CPU (32C, HT off), 1024 GB of memory, a boot disk and 12x Micron_9200_MTFDHAL11TATCW (PDF ) for 120TB of disk storage.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cloning and splitting logical volumes</title>
      <link>/2019/12/02/cloning-and-splitting-logical-volumes.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/02/cloning-and-splitting-logical-volumes.html</guid>
      <description>Where I work, we routinely run our databases on XFS on LVM2.
The setup   Each database has their database on /mysql/schemaname, with the subdirectories /mysql/schemaname/{data,log,tmp}. The entire /mysql/schemname tree is a LVM2 Logical Volume mysqlVol on the Volume Group vg00, which is then formatted as an XFS filesystem.
# pvcreate /dev/nvme*n1 # vgcreate vg00 /dev/nvme*n1 # lvcreate -n mysqlVol -L...G vg00 # mkfs -t xfs /dev/vg00/mysqlVol # mount -t xfs /dev/vg00/mysqlVol /mysql/schemaname Basic Ops   You can grow an existing LVM Logical Volume with lvextend -L+50G /dev/vg00/mysqlVol or similar, and then xfs_grow /dev/vg00/myqlVol.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Exit Strategy</title>
      <link>/2019/11/22/fertig-gelesen-exit-strategy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/11/22/fertig-gelesen-exit-strategy.html</guid>
      <description>Exit Strategy by Martha Wells is the fourth book in the the Murderbot Diaries (All Systems Red , Artificial Condition, Rogue Protocol, Exit Strategy, Network Effect).
This novella is the culmination of the Murderbot Novellas, in which our nameless murderbot cyborg tries to nail the evil GrayCris corporation for the series of crimes against settlers and researchers, has to rescue it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;owner&amp;rdquo;, sponsor and friend Dr. Mensah from the claws of GrayCris, and make friends on the way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Fashion and Its Social Agendas: Class, Gender, and Identity in Clothing</title>
      <link>/2019/11/21/fertig-gelesen-fashion-and-its-social-agendas-class-gender-and-identity-in-clothing.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/11/21/fertig-gelesen-fashion-and-its-social-agendas-class-gender-and-identity-in-clothing.html</guid>
      <description>Fashion and Its Social Agendas: Class, Gender, and Identity in Clothing by Diane Crane is an analysis of the changes in society during the various phases of the industrial revolution through the lens of clothing in various societal strata.
The book studies fashion and clothing choices in three countries - France, the United States, and England - over a period of 150 years. France and England are examples of class societies in the nineteenth century.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Wiz Biz</title>
      <link>/2019/11/20/fertig-gelesen-the-wiz-biz.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/11/20/fertig-gelesen-the-wiz-biz.html</guid>
      <description>The Wiz Biz by Rick Cook is a book in the genre of &amp;lsquo;magical realism&amp;rsquo;. Some real-world person is being transported into a universe with predictable magic in a classical fantasy setting and is applying scientic method and industrial production methods to the setting.
In this book, the real-world person is Walter Zumwalt, a stereotypical hacker, which as part of a hail-mary summoning rital is being transported into a magical war between the good guys and the bad guys.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When a file changes, do a thing</title>
      <link>/2019/11/19/when-a-file-changes-do-a-thing.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/11/19/when-a-file-changes-do-a-thing.html</guid>
      <description>When developing there is often an edit-compile-test cycle, or an edit-distribute-changes cycle or a similar repetetive task. You could poll changes, for example with cron every minute or similarly, but that is wasteful and slow.
All modern operating systems have mechanisms for processes to subscribe to file or directory changes. In MacOS, we do have the File System Events API since 10.5, in Linux we got three different implementations (as described in LWN ): The original dnotify, its replacement inotify and the even more recent fanotify (which got its own LWN article ).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A blast from the past</title>
      <link>/2019/11/18/a-blast-from-the-past.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/11/18/a-blast-from-the-past.html</guid>
      <description>TL:DR: If you have long running transactions, MySQL does not deal well with this, and it will slow down the box. That&amp;rsquo;s okay as long as you are basically alone on your box, but if you aren&amp;rsquo;t, the others will hate you.
The database machine &amp;lsquo;somehierarchy-02&amp;rsquo; in a general purpose load balancer pool for somehierarchy had replication delay.
It&amp;rsquo;s a MySQL replica and is receiving the same write workload than all the other boxen in that pool.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Change Agent</title>
      <link>/2019/11/18/fertig-gelesen-change-agent.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/11/18/fertig-gelesen-change-agent.html</guid>
      <description>Change Agent is Daniel Suarez fifth book.
 As usual, he builds his stories around one technology or technological change and constructs an action-rich storyline around it. For &amp;ldquo;Change Agent&amp;rdquo;, this is CRISPR genetic modification of living beings. He basically imagines a programmable genetic agent that rewrites living beings including humans on the go - the eponymous change agent.
It&amp;rsquo;s 2045, and an Interpol Agent Kenneth Durand is trying to pursue the Huli Jing cartel, a criminal black market corporation that produces enhanced designer babies for rich prospectice parents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Infinity Engine</title>
      <link>/2019/11/18/fertig-gelesen-infinity-engine.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/11/18/fertig-gelesen-infinity-engine.html</guid>
      <description>Infinity Engine is the third and final book in Neal Asher&amp;rsquo;s Transformation Sequence , a trilogy set in the Polity Universe .
 This is the conclusion of the three book arc about the redemption of the mis-manufactured and temporarily mad AI Penny Royal. Asher takes us through a set of encounters he prepared two other books for, contrasting the reconstruction and the redemption of Penny Royal with the descend into madness of the forensic AI Brockle, and weaving together all the other story-strands that he set up earlier into a literally star-shattering finale.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Everything was a file, but we got better</title>
      <link>/2019/11/14/everything-was-a-file-but-we-got-better.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/11/14/everything-was-a-file-but-we-got-better.html</guid>
      <description>I fell into the Twitters again. @CarrickDB joked about Unix, Files and Directories:
 And that is a case of &amp;ldquo;Haha, only serious&amp;rdquo;. Because directories used to be files, and that was a bad time. Check out the V7 Unix mkdir command. At this point in history we do not have a mkdir(2) syscall, yet, so we need to construct the entire directory in multiple steps.
 mknod(2) an inode that has the S_IFDIR flag set , even if that macro does not even exist yet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Filling disk space fast</title>
      <link>/2019/11/11/filling-disk-space-fast.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/11/11/filling-disk-space-fast.html</guid>
      <description>Some of the databases at work are a tad on the large side, in the high 2-digit terabytes of size. Copying these to new machines at the moment takes a rather long time, multiple days, up to a week. Speeding it up pays twice, because with shorter copy times there is also less binlog to catch up.
I have been looking into disk copy speeds in order to better understand the limits.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate change happened 30 years ago</title>
      <link>/2019/10/15/climate-change-happened-30-years-ago.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/10/15/climate-change-happened-30-years-ago.html</guid>
      <description>Water is a very weird substance. Melting ice at 0C to water at 0C takes a fantastic amount of energy: Water has a latent heat of 384J/gram. Compared to other materials that is pretty much at the upper end of the spectrum.
Warming up 1g of liquid water by 1C is the original definition of 1 Calorie, or 4.184 Joules in todays units.
The water on our planet is a buffer that can store energy if there is more energy incoming that the earth can dissipate, or release energy if the bilancing is negative.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ignoring Catalina nags</title>
      <link>/2019/10/15/ignoring-catalina-nags.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/10/15/ignoring-catalina-nags.html</guid>
      <description>Note to self: Ignoring the Catalina Nagscreens is done like this:
$ sudo softwareupdate --ignore &amp;#34;macOS Catalina&amp;#34; $ defaults write com.apple.systempreferences AttentionPrefBundleIDs 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; killall Dock And that should make MacOS ignore Catalina until further notice. Further notice does look like this:
$ /usr/sbin/softwareupdate --reset-ignored </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Catalina: Upgrade carefully.</title>
      <link>/2019/10/08/catalina-upgrade-carefully.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/10/08/catalina-upgrade-carefully.html</guid>
      <description>Catalina is here. It fixes many things, among them iTunes. On the other hand, it drops support for 32-Bit MacOS applications.
Consider the upgrade carefully.
$ system_profiler SPApplicationsDataType … Steam: Version: 1.5 Obtained from: Identified Developer Last Modified: 23.08.16, 20:32 Kind: Intel 64-Bit (Intel): No Signed by: Developer ID Application: Valve Corporation, Developer ID Certification Authority, Apple Root CA Location: /Applications/Steam.app … Anything listed with 64-Bit (Intel): No will stop working after the upgrade.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Centers and Energy</title>
      <link>/2019/10/05/data-centers-and-energy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/10/05/data-centers-and-energy.html</guid>
      <description>Deutsche Welle is shocked: Generation Greta is watching Netflix (Article in German Language), Netflix runs on computers, and apparently computers are using power.
Let&amp;rsquo;s have a look.
EDIT: Second part Streaming and Energy now available.
End-User Device.   It&amp;rsquo;s 2019. End user devices are using Wi-Fi, and are running on Batteries. They are Cellphones, Tablets or Laptops.
Devices that are not connected to grid are more usable if they are trying to save energy, and so all modern devices are full of special purpose hardware that allows them to fulfill their main functions more energy efficient.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Does Disk I/O</title>
      <link>/2019/09/27/mysql-does-disk-io.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/27/mysql-does-disk-io.html</guid>
      <description>We had a discussion at work about MySQL doing Disk I/O to a NVME disk, and if it is valid to turn off the doublewrite buffer when using XFS.
TL;DR: It&amp;rsquo;s not, you can turn off the doublewrite buffer only on filesystems that never do in-place updates (ZFS, btrfs), or that have their own doublewrite buffer (ext4 with journal=data). A flash layer underneath the actual filesystem is likely not going to help you without additional measures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Rockforth Fertilizer Incident</title>
      <link>/2019/09/26/how-not-to-handle-an-ingame-incident.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/26/how-not-to-handle-an-ingame-incident.html</guid>
      <description>So I have been playing this Internet Spaceships Game. No, the other one . It also has NPC Backstory, and on 13-Sep-3305 , a multiplanetary food crisis was predicted, as a prep for the introduction of a new tradeable good on 18-Sep-3005 .
 Distribution of the fertiliser has started at Marshall Dock in the Riedquat system. We encourage traders to take advantage of our introductory prices.”
 That went wrong.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Performance Limits</title>
      <link>/2019/09/06/mysql-performance-limits.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/06/mysql-performance-limits.html</guid>
      <description>The last time I saw a MySQL server operating at a performance limit was in 2012. Back them we had a production master on (then) current hardware, running stable at about 21000 QPS. At 24000 QPS it tended to become unstable and fall over, dying in global locks on the InnoDB Adaptive Hash Index or other global locks.
I need to better understand how MySQL works today, and what the limits are on a box that is considered large in 2019.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ceph and NVME - not a good combination?</title>
      <link>/2019/07/16/ceph-and-nvme-not-a-good-combination.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/07/16/ceph-and-nvme-not-a-good-combination.html</guid>
      <description>Saving an older twitter thread on Ceph .
 I just have finished reading Part 4: RHCS 3.2 Bluestore Advanced Performance Investigation and now I do not know what to say.
Ceph set out with the idea to make storage a commodity by using regular PCs + a lot of local hard disks + software to make inexpensive storage. For that, you ran a number of control processes and an OSD process per disk (&amp;ldquo;object storage demon&amp;rdquo;).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not quite storage any more</title>
      <link>/2019/06/14/not-quite-storage-any-more.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/06/14/not-quite-storage-any-more.html</guid>
      <description>While I was testing away on all the SSD and NVME toys, I got my hand on a test box with even stranger that usual equipment. It was a Dual Platinum-8280 box with a really weird amount of memory: 7.5 TB.
“8280 ”. This is a machine with a “2” in the second digit, indicating Cascade Lake , CLX.
And one thing that is new with CLX is “Intel Optane Persistent Memory Technology”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adventures in Storageland</title>
      <link>/2019/06/13/adventures-in-storageland.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/06/13/adventures-in-storageland.html</guid>
      <description>Adventures in Storageland   Devices   In the last few weeks, I have been benchmarking server storage in order to get a better idea what the state of the hardware is these days. There is a summary with recommendations at the end of this article. Storage technology
In the past, we had stored data on rotating disks.
An open hard disk chassis. You can see the topmost of a stack of disks, and the arm with the r/w heads.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>But is it atomic?</title>
      <link>/2018/11/29/but-is-it-atomic.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/11/29/but-is-it-atomic.html</guid>
      <description>From Pluspora But is it atomic?   So a few days ago, a colleague asked “Why do we love files on disk?” and in the course of that discussion, I made a comment that, among other things, used the assumption that somebody is updating some file on some Linux system atomically. I wrote:
Let&amp;rsquo;s assume we are using local files, and we do so in a managed, sane way:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Murderbot Diaries</title>
      <link>/2018/09/25/fertig-gelesen-murderbot-diaries.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/25/fertig-gelesen-murderbot-diaries.html</guid>
      <description>Murderbot is a corporate owned killing machine, a secbot, a half-organic artificially intelligent android. Its purpose is to protect corporate assets - settlers and science teams - in hostile environments for as long as it makes economic sense.
 All Systems Red Due to an incident of an unclear nature, Murderbot manages to hack its governor module, which chains it to its owning corporation and prevents it from going rogue. So finally unleashed, there is nothing at all which can hold Murderbot back from…</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Reflex, Impulse, Exo &#43; Griffin</title>
      <link>/2018/09/25/fertig-gelesen-reflex-impulse-exo-griffin.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/25/fertig-gelesen-reflex-impulse-exo-griffin.html</guid>
      <description>Reflex, Impulse and Exo are the continuation of Jumper . Jumper was dealing with a young man, living with an alcohol dependent father and dealing with abuse. The young man leaves, builds a new existence and in this conflicts with secret services and terrorists. In the course of the story he makes peace with his father and his past, manages to build a meaningful relationship and build a stable life and income.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Sled Driver</title>
      <link>/2018/09/25/fertig-gelesen-sled-driver.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/25/fertig-gelesen-sled-driver.html</guid>
      <description>The SR-71 was the fastest, highest, stealthiest airplane, built from exotic materials, and it looked really mean - but was unarmed. Its engines were its only defense and the only thing it ever shot were pictures. How did it come to be, how did it fly, what did it do and what was it like to fly it.
 Sled Driver Brian Shul describes the SR-71 from a pilots perspective, without bothering too much about the physics and the engineering, concentrating on the operations from a pilots POV and the doing of things.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Throne of Glass</title>
      <link>/2018/09/25/fertig-gelesen-throne-of-glass.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/25/fertig-gelesen-throne-of-glass.html</guid>
      <description>The young and incredibly pretty (except for the scars that document her suffering in the salt mines) Mary Sue was about eight when she was found half frozen at the shore of a winterly river by the King of Assassins, who took her in and forged her into the deadliest of his assassins through harsh and cruel training. Too bad that, eighteen years old, she was caught, punished and was sent to the salt mines of Endovier, by the king who conquered her homeland and slaughtered her parents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Good Taste</title>
      <link>/2018/07/15/fertig-gelesen-good-taste-isaac-asimov-1976.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/07/15/fertig-gelesen-good-taste-isaac-asimov-1976.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Good Taste&amp;rdquo;, Isaac Asimov (1976)
In which the spacer Chawker Minor, leaves his home, the Orbital Habitat Gammer, and tours other places, including the deadly depths of the Gravity well created by the mass of planet Earth. The literal dirt.
And he brings back with him spectacular new flavors.
That does not go over well.
 ‘The idea for the dish occurred to me, actually, on the Other-World Kapper, which is why I called it Mountain Cap, in tribute.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Websense DLP gives instant root</title>
      <link>/2018/06/18/websense-dlp-gives-instant-root.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/06/18/websense-dlp-gives-instant-root.html</guid>
      <description>Enterprise security software is interesting, because in order to do what it does it often uses privilege, but it is also very often written extremely badly.
In ASLR we have had a look on the Trend Micro binary on MacOS and found that it is running as root, and with ASLR off. That means we have a privileged process that is being loaded at a fixed address, and that process is parsing random user generated data in order to scan it for viruses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Harebrained Battletech</title>
      <link>/2018/04/26/harbebrained-battletech.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/26/harbebrained-battletech.html</guid>
      <description>So two days ago Harebrained Schemes&#39; Battletech came out.
Harebrained Schemes is an Indie Game Dev Studio from Seattle, previously known for the very successful Shadowrun Games . I found time to play the intro and the first few chapters in the campaign, and the game is exceptionally nice. It feels like one of those over designed simulation games, where you can minmax the player characters and their gear to the limit, but the computer is taking over the task of all the bookkeeping, so the bookkeeping is not going to pull you down.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>beep, patch and ed</title>
      <link>/2018/04/06/beep-patch-and-ed.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/06/beep-patch-and-ed.html</guid>
      <description>So a few days ago, somebody found an exploit in beep - now CVE-2018-0492 .
beep is a program that is part of Debian (and Ubuntu) to have the PC speaker multiple times, at different frequencies, with different pauses and beep lengths. That works just fine. It&amp;rsquo;s also SUID root. There is zero code in it that deals with the fact that it may run privileged.
The author confidently writes:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spectre #2 Mitigation - Retpolines</title>
      <link>/2018/02/26/spectre-2-mitigation-retpolines.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/02/26/spectre-2-mitigation-retpolines.html</guid>
      <description>Intel finally published a whitepaper about Spectre #2 Mitigation. The PDF is also featured on Hacker News . It&amp;rsquo;s a technical whitepaper, but you can see the footprints of lawyers all over the language. For me, it basically says that, yes, Retpolines are indeed incompatible with Controlflow Enforcement Technology (CET) that Intel was planning for later CPUs (PDF , El Reg article ).
CET introduces a shadow stack for return addresses only, and will fail your code into an exception if the normal stack return address and the shadow stack address disagree.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Journey to Open Compute</title>
      <link>/2018/02/21/a-journey-to-open-compute.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/02/21/a-journey-to-open-compute.html</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, Booking.com hosted the Open Compute Meetup in Amsterdam. My talk is on Slideshare and a recording is on Youtube.
 Slideshare: A journey to OCP  Youtube: A journey to OCP   A cleaned up and more coherent transcript of the talk is here: Booking.com started out as a small online travel agency in Amsterdam, but is now financially about 15% of Google. We have about 200 offices in 70 countries, support 46 languages and reach about any touristically interesting spot on this planet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swap and Memory Pressure: How Developers think to how Operations people think</title>
      <link>/2018/01/22/swap-and-memory-pressure-how-developers-think-to-how-operations-people-think.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/22/swap-and-memory-pressure-how-developers-think-to-how-operations-people-think.html</guid>
      <description>There is a very useful and interesting article by Chris Down: &amp;ldquo;In defence of swap: common misconceptions &amp;rdquo;.
Chris explains what Swap is, and how it provides a backing store of anonymous pages as opposed to the actual code files, which provide backing store for file based pages. I have no problem with the information and background knowledge he provides. This is correct and useful stuff, and I even learned a thing about what cgroups can do for me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Knock, Knock</title>
      <link>/2018/01/15/knock-knock.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/15/knock-knock.html</guid>
      <description>What does your Mac do on Startup? Knockknock knows .
It&amp;rsquo;s not properly updated for current versions of MacOS, but it is still useful. &amp;ldquo;git clone https://github.com/synack/knockknock&#34; and &amp;ldquo;/usr/bin/python knockknock.py&amp;rdquo; is sufficient to test.
TOTAL ITEMS FOUND: 44 That&amp;rsquo;s quite a bit. Apparently, I am starting
 Google Music Manager, AirServer, Karabiner, Alfred 3, a Chrome app_mode_loader, the Android File Transfer Agent, Dropbox, Divvy, Expandrive, Chrome itself, Soundflower, an AX88179 USB GBit Ethernet adapter driver, Steam Drivers, /Library/PrivilegedHelperTools/org.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conway&#39;s Law</title>
      <link>/2018/01/12/conways-law.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/12/conways-law.html</guid>
      <description>Melvin Conway is a compiler developer and systems designer, who is well known for the eponymous Conway&amp;rsquo;s Law . Various phrasings exist of that, and one popular is
 Organizations which design systems are constrained to produce designs which are copies of the communication structures of these organizations.
 The original paper and an introductory paragraph can be found on his website . It&amp;rsquo;s worth reading, because there are more useful insights to be found in the original writeup.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Apollo Guidance Computer: Architecture and Operation</title>
      <link>/2017/12/08/fertig-gelesen-the-apollo-guidance-computer-architecture-and-operation.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/12/08/fertig-gelesen-the-apollo-guidance-computer-architecture-and-operation.html</guid>
      <description>Frank O&amp;rsquo;Brien explains an outstanding piece of engineering: The Apollo Guidance Computer (AGC) was the computer that controlled the thrusters and navigation on the Apollo Command Module, and a second instance, on the Lunar Module. It&amp;rsquo;s a 32kg box with core memory and core rope ROM, a 16 bit discrete CPU (15 data bits and parity) running at 1 MHz effective, and some very special hardware behind its I/O ports.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>d = a*b&#43;c at scale</title>
      <link>/2017/11/25/d-abc-at-scale.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/25/d-abc-at-scale.html</guid>
      <description>Introduction to GPUs (PDF)
So you already know how your CPU works, basically, and want to understand what your GPU does differently. Ofer Rosenberg has you covered: Introduction to GPUs does what it says on the tin.
The NVIDIA take on this can be found in An Introduction to Modern GPU Architecture by Ashu Rege, but because this is from 2008, it&amp;rsquo;s showing it&amp;rsquo;s age. The first 15 slides or so focus more on the gaming aspect and less on the technology, but are full of matching screenshots.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: How to Make a Zombie</title>
      <link>/2017/11/09/fertig-gelesen-how-to-make-a-zombie.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/09/fertig-gelesen-how-to-make-a-zombie.html</guid>
      <description>Frank Swain takes us on a tour of the myths, stories and historic reports of the undead corpse throughout the history of humanity. Referencing sources and quoting people, he shows us the various aspects of the mindless physical body shuffling around after the soul departed, and how that as a theme has been following us around throughout our history.
The first chapter deals with the &amp;ldquo;original&amp;rdquo; haitian zombies, later chapters take us to victorian experimentation with corpses of the executed, soviet experiments and many other encounters between humans and the living undead.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Zombie Survival Guide</title>
      <link>/2017/11/09/fertig-gelesen-the-zombie-survival-guide.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/09/fertig-gelesen-the-zombie-survival-guide.html</guid>
      <description>Max Brooks, author of World War Z, delivers a straight on, zero tongue in cheek, nitty-gritty survival guide for the coming Zombie Apocalypse. The book delivers exactly what is promised in the table of contents: The Solanum Virus and how it works and does not work, Weapons and Combat Techniques that work, defending your home, public spaces or other places, how to organise a breakout or run, useful equipment to have or to loot, and then fighting back and finally containing the outbreak.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: All Systems Red</title>
      <link>/2017/11/08/fertig-gelesen-all-systems-red.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/08/fertig-gelesen-all-systems-red.html</guid>
      <description>»I COULD HAVE BECOME a mass murderer after I hacked my governor module, but then I realized I could access the combined feed of entertainment channels carried on the company satellites.«
 This is how »All Systems Red« begins.
The protagonist in this book is a robot mercenary android, or Murderbot, as it refers to itself. In a universe of corporations and contracts, Expeditions and Exploration teams are taking these company supplied machines with the for their own safety, and for compliance reasons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Collapsing Empire</title>
      <link>/2017/11/08/fertig-gelesen-the-collapsing-empire.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/08/fertig-gelesen-the-collapsing-empire.html</guid>
      <description>»The mutineers would have gotten away with it, too, if it weren’t for the collapse of the Flow.
There is, of course, a legal, standard way within the guilds for a crew to mutiny, a protocol that has lasted for centuries. A senior crew member, preferably the executive officer/first mate, but possibly the chief engineer, chief technician, chief physician or, in genuinely bizarre circumstances, the owner’s representative, would offer the ship’s imperial adjunct a formal Bill of Grievances Pursuant to a Mutiny, consistent with guild protocol.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Children of Time</title>
      <link>/2017/11/07/fertig-gelesen-children-of-time.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/07/fertig-gelesen-children-of-time.html</guid>
      <description>The people of Earth are on the verge of transcendence: They almost managed to create mind uploads, they are on the verge of creating true synthetic AI, they have been traveling to remote stars and are beginning to terraform worlds, on which they will seed Earth lifeforms and uplift them. All this progress, though, draws the ire of militant terrorists from the &amp;ldquo;Non Ultra Nature&amp;rdquo; radicals, which culminates into the sabotage of Brin 2 lab while seeding a terraformed world, and at the same time the complete destruction of humanity and its in-system colonies back home.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: River of Teeth</title>
      <link>/2017/11/07/fertig-gelesen-river-of-teeth.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/07/fertig-gelesen-river-of-teeth.html</guid>
      <description>»In the early twentieth century, the Congress of our great nation debated a glorious plan to resolve the meat shortage in America. The idea was this: import hippos and raise them in Louisiana&amp;rsquo;s bayous. The hippos would eat the ruinously invasive water hyacinth; the American people would eat the hippos; everyone would go home happy. Well, except the hippo&amp;rsquo;s. They&amp;rsquo;d go home eaten.«
This plan, on which Congress did not follow through in our timeline, is the premise and the setting for Sarah Gailey&amp;rsquo;s alternate universe story &amp;ldquo;River of Teeth&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Power budgets for computing resources - portable and stationary</title>
      <link>/2017/11/07/power-budgets-for-computing-resources-portable-and-stationary.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/07/power-budgets-for-computing-resources-portable-and-stationary.html</guid>
      <description>Fanless devices   A cellphone or tablet is a fanless device. So is the 12&amp;quot; Macbook. That means you can do whatever is possible at any point in time within a TDP of approximately 5W.
Here is the power consumption of my cellphone over a 12h period. The scale on the left is mW, down is discharge, up is recharge (plugged in). It&amp;rsquo;s basically limited to 5W, and that only for short periods of time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: All these worlds</title>
      <link>/2017/11/06/fertig-gelesen-all-these-worlds.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/06/fertig-gelesen-all-these-worlds.html</guid>
      <description>All these worlds is the third and final part of the adventures of Bob, conqueror of the universe and saviour of humanity.
Bob started out as a dead computer programmer, uploaded as a control AI into the core of a von Neumann probe and spaceship. He then went forth and multiplied, mostly because he needed more of himself to cover up first his own fuckups and then to clean up the mess all of humanity made of his homeworld during his departure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Sourdough</title>
      <link>/2017/11/06/fertig-gelesen-sourdough.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/06/fertig-gelesen-sourdough.html</guid>
      <description>Lori Clary is a software engineer and silicon valley geek, programming embedded systems and robot arms at General Dexterity for a living. She&amp;rsquo;s living the silicon valley lifestyle - basically coding all day, collapsing in her hole of a non-appartment, and not having contact with real people at all. With one exception: She&amp;rsquo;s ordering dinner from a delivery service that is run by two mysterious brothers, who make a mean spicy soup and crusty bread.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unicode is over and it dies over Emoji</title>
      <link>/2017/11/05/unicode-is-over-and-it-dies-over-emoji.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/05/unicode-is-over-and-it-dies-over-emoji.html</guid>
      <description>In 1982, Scott Fahlmann invented the use of :-) and :-( for marking up emotions or semantic context in written online communication. That was a great idea.
The :-) is just a symbol for an emotion.
It is specifically not a human face, it does not have a hair color, eye color, skin color or other human attributes. It is universal. Then some cellphone maker turned that into , anthropomorphising it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ASLR</title>
      <link>/2017/10/20/aslr.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/20/aslr.html</guid>
      <description>#define MH_PIE 0x200000 /* When this bit is set, the OS will load the main executable at a random address. Only used in MH_EXECUTE filetypes. */If that flag is on, MacOS will enable ASLR and the binary will have different load addresses for code, data, heap and stack every time it is running.
$ sudo otool -h &amp;#39;/Library/Application Support/TrendMicro/TmccMac/iCoreService_tmsm&amp;#39; Mach header magic cputype cpusubtype caps filetype ncmds sizeofcmds flags 0xfeedfacf 16777223 3 0x80 2 20 2656 0x00018085 Check the &amp;lsquo;flags&amp;rsquo; for this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Edgedancer</title>
      <link>/2017/10/19/fertig-gelesen-edgedancer.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/19/fertig-gelesen-edgedancer.html</guid>
      <description>Edgedancer Right now, one month before we get Oathbringer, the third part of The Stormlight Archive , we get Edgedancer. This is a Novella that previously was part of Arcanum Unbounded , a collection of short stories playing in the Cosmere . As a standalone Novella is has been expanded and is now 40k words long.
Edgedancer picks up the story of Lift , a scrappy Reshi thief that happens to bond with a Spren to follow the path of the Edgedancer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Asperger&#39;s on the Job</title>
      <link>/2017/10/16/fertig-gelesen-aspergers-on-the-job.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/16/fertig-gelesen-aspergers-on-the-job.html</guid>
      <description>[](Asperger&amp;rsquo;s on the Job)
Asperger&amp;rsquo;s on the Job These weird people with headphones on, working strange hours, not wanting to stand in front of the group in Standups and for talks - what are they, where to they come from and how do you handle them at work?
The book is structured as a self-help book, assessing various aspects of Asperger Syndrome , how they manifest and what that might mean in the workplace.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So what is the state of the Ads mess?</title>
      <link>/2017/10/13/so-what-is-the-state-of-the-ads-mess.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/13/so-what-is-the-state-of-the-ads-mess.html</guid>
      <description>Ads on the web have many problems:
 Ad selection criteria have been abused for dissemination of propaganda, for targeted malware attacks. Content sites have basically lost the control over what kind of stuff they deliver through the ad-space on their site. Tracking is increasingly a concern for users. Ads bloat sites, slow down page display times and mess with peoples mobile data plans. Ads use power and create heat in devices with a tight power budgets (basically, anything that runs on a battery and has no fans, phones, tablets, laptops).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Latency Numbers, visualised and memorised</title>
      <link>/2017/10/12/latency-numbers-visualised-and-memorised.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/12/latency-numbers-visualised-and-memorised.html</guid>
      <description>There is a well known Github Gist &amp;ldquo;Latency Numbers Every Programmer Should Know &amp;rdquo;, which explains which things take how long.
 Scaled Latency Numbers If you scale these things down 3 billion times, a clock cycle (0.3ns) becomes a second. And suddenly things are relateable. (Tweet )
 Another attempt to visualize this , not entirely unlike this XKCD .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The inherent Asymmetry of online attacks</title>
      <link>/2017/10/12/the-inherent-asymmetry-of-online-attacks.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/12/the-inherent-asymmetry-of-online-attacks.html</guid>
      <description>Katie Moussouris explains teh Cyber and how it is asymmetric:
»&amp;quot;#Cassandra moment: Explaining that determining &amp;ldquo;cyber norms&amp;rdquo; in today&amp;rsquo;s world order misses emerging capabilities &amp;amp; motivations of new actors.
Forget &amp;ldquo;attribution&amp;rdquo;. Not what I mean.
Deterrence, state responsibility, etc in existing state context assumes most want to keep stability. Plenty of non-terrorist smaller states &amp;amp; non-state-non-criminal actors have or can acquire capabilities &amp;amp; would not be sanctionable, for example when we think through deterrence strategies, consider not just world order we have that prefers stability, but those who prefer destability.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What GPUs can do…</title>
      <link>/2017/10/12/what-gpus-can-do.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/12/what-gpus-can-do.html</guid>
      <description>Pcgamer reports &amp;ldquo;Nvidia CEO says Moore’s Law is dead and GPUs wi replace CPUs &amp;rdquo;.
Now, Jensen Huang might be a bit biased here, but he reminded us that &amp;ldquo;GPUs are advancing at a much faster pace than CPUs&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;that GPUs will replace CPUs soon, adding that at this point, designers can hardly work out advanced parallel instruction architectures for CPUs.&amp;rdquo; So what can a modern GPU do? Well, apparently Font Rendering is still a hard problem for GPUs, and a bottleneck in modern browsers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When Video Games are not quite playing things straight…</title>
      <link>/2017/10/12/when-video-games-are-not-quite-playing-things-straight.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/12/when-video-games-are-not-quite-playing-things-straight.html</guid>
      <description>]
Computer Games are cheating A lot of computer games are cheating, so that you can actually have fun with the game. Read the thread.
»Hey #gamedev, tell me about some brilliant mechanics in games that are hidden from the player to get across a certain feeling.«
»This is probably somewhere way down the list, but third person game thumbstick correction is a favourite. Pretty standard in AAA. (know you know but extrapolation for readers) game detects collision blocks and steers player around them, ignoring direction of input.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A (sad) security user story</title>
      <link>/2017/10/10/a-sad-security-user-story.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/10/a-sad-security-user-story.html</guid>
      <description>Here is a user story for implementors of security systems and platform hardening initiatives:
 As any user , I never want to get a &amp;ldquo;denied&amp;rdquo; message, but a &amp;quot; in order to do what you want you are missing the X permission&amp;quot; message in order to be able to track down the root cause and request the appropriate permissions more easily.
 It&amp;rsquo;s not that hard, really.
 GitLab: You are not allowed to push code to this project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shared Space Experiment at Alexanderplein</title>
      <link>/2017/09/27/shared-space-experiment-at-alexanderplein.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/09/27/shared-space-experiment-at-alexanderplein.html</guid>
      <description>Shared Space Experiment The Guardian has an article about a Shared Space Experiment at Amsterdam Alexanderplein.
A Shared Space is an approach to urban traffic design in which segregation of traffic modes is minimized and signage or other regulation is taken away, leaving traffic participants to make up rules and agreements on the spot through interaction. Several preconditions need to be there in order for Shared Spaces to have a chance of working:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where do you see yourself in five years?</title>
      <link>/2017/09/11/where-do-you-see-yourself-in-five-years.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/09/11/where-do-you-see-yourself-in-five-years.html</guid>
      <description>Seriously, HR people ask the weirdest questions.    &amp;ldquo;Where do you see yourself in five years?&amp;rdquo;
 For a Twentysomething with no owned property and no family the truthful answer is of course &amp;ldquo;In a different company, twice removed. Not because you suck more than anywhere else, but, like, statistically.&amp;rdquo;
 &amp;ldquo;Where do you see yourself in five years?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Week 27 or 28?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; LionKingLee That time when you finish school and university and before you settle down with dependencies that make you immobile - it is an important time in your life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Separate Infrastructure</title>
      <link>/2017/09/08/separate-infrastructure.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/09/08/separate-infrastructure.html</guid>
      <description>Cargobike mum with child cycling independently on Upper Thames Street. Unimaginable before cycling infrastructure. &amp;ndash; Mark Treasure A lot of people in Germany, especially Bike Activists, are stuck in the 80ies, victims of the Kampfradler mentality. Let&amp;rsquo;s have a look at that:
The german word Kampfradler literally is made up from &amp;ldquo;Kampf&amp;rdquo; (fight) and &amp;ldquo;Radler&amp;rdquo; (cyclist) . A Kampfradler is a fighting cyclist, or confrontational cyclist. Wikipedia dates the Kampfradler to 2011, but it&amp;rsquo;s much older.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Secret History of Wonder Woman</title>
      <link>/2017/09/04/fertig-gelesen-the-secret-history-of-wonder-woman.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/09/04/fertig-gelesen-the-secret-history-of-wonder-woman.html</guid>
      <description>One of the weirdest and most interesting characters in the DC Universe is Wonder Woman, because she is full of seemingly irreconcilable contradictions. Created by a man, William Moulton Marston , in 1941, her history is actually deeply rooted in the Suffragette movement of the early 20th century. Marston owes much of the ideas and the origin myth to earlier stories from that era and cosmos, through his wifes Elizabeth Holloway Marston and Olive Byrne, and through Olives Byrne&amp;rsquo;s connection with Ethel Byrne and Margaret Sanger .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I can&#39;t transfer money with my Monitor upright</title>
      <link>/2017/08/28/why-i-cant-transfer-money-with-my-monitor-upright.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/28/why-i-cant-transfer-money-with-my-monitor-upright.html</guid>
      <description>Berliner Sparkasse Onlinebanking FAQ :
 Why do I get the message &amp;lsquo;mobile device, can&amp;rsquo;t perform smsTAN money transfer&amp;rsquo; when using my Desktop computer.
  A possible cause is the display resolution. Your computer is being detected as a mobile device by our online banking system. smsTAN is not working from a mobile device.
Solution: Change the display resolution
 So 1920x1080 does work, but 1080x1920 doesn&amp;rsquo;t.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Community Management?</title>
      <link>/2017/08/23/community-management.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/23/community-management.html</guid>
      <description>Today is a weird day. First thing is a friend asking about help with community management. And next thing is Fefe reiterating his longstanding fallacy (Rant in German ) that programmers are able to do anything just because they are able to do one thing (here: Community Management). The TL;DR is that he rants against non-programmers showing interest into programming projects because they like the software, thereby ruining everything by not being programmers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why you can&#39;t have nice things…</title>
      <link>/2017/08/13/why-you-cant-have-nice-things.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/13/why-you-cant-have-nice-things.html</guid>
      <description>»Yay for discounts, aber die Einstellung vom Köhntopp finde ich ja eigentlich ziemlich vermessen und ekelhaft.« Back in the day at university, there used to be a group of people who went to the Cinema every week on Thursday. We were sometimes six, sometimes more like ten people, but at the core it was a pretty stable group. Ticket sales started one week before and we are pretty consistently getting our tickets pretty much the hour ticket sales started.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monitoring - the data you have and the data you want</title>
      <link>/2017/08/09/monitoring-the-data-you-have-and-the-data-you-want.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/09/monitoring-the-data-you-have-and-the-data-you-want.html</guid>
      <description>So you are running systems in production and you want to collect data from your systems. You need to build a monitoring system. That won&amp;rsquo;t work and it won&amp;rsquo;t scale. So please stop for a moment, and think. What kind of monitoring do you want do build? I know at least three different types of monitoring system, and they have very different objectives, and consequently designs.
Three types of Monitoring Systems   The first and most important system you want to have is checking for incidents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating the Changing Causes of Photovoltaics Cost Reduction</title>
      <link>/2017/08/08/evaluating-the-changing-causes-of-photovoltaics-cost-reduction.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/08/evaluating-the-changing-causes-of-photovoltaics-cost-reduction.html</guid>
      <description>Evaluating the Changing Causes of Photovoltaics Cost Reduction Why is PV Solar Energy getting cheaper and cheaper?
 We find that increased module efficiency was the leading low-level cause of cost reduction in 1980-2001, contributing almost 30% of the cost decline. The most important high-level mechanism was R&amp;amp;D in these earlier stages of the technology. After 2001, scale economies became a more significant cause of cost reduction, approaching R&amp;amp;D in importance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Story of CO2 (and other Greenhouse Gas Emissions)</title>
      <link>/2017/08/08/the-story-of-co2-and-other-greenhouse-gas-emissions.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/08/the-story-of-co2-and-other-greenhouse-gas-emissions.html</guid>
      <description>Our World in Data has a very nice long read with many interactive visualisations giving context to CO2.
We begin with exploring CO2 cumulative (how much CO2 did each nation produce over its industrial history), scaling it to annual emission and then scaling it by population, too. We also learn about CO2 produced vs. CO2 in the atmosphere, which is a delayed system.
The second part then deals with CO2 and industrialisation: Emission vs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So you want to write a Shell script</title>
      <link>/2017/08/07/so-you-want-to-write-a-shell-script.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/07/so-you-want-to-write-a-shell-script.html</guid>
      <description>So some people, companies even, have guidelines that describe how to write shell scripts , or even unit tests for shell scripts , as if &amp;ldquo;UNIX Shell&amp;rdquo; was a programming language.
That&amp;rsquo;s wrong.
&amp;ldquo;Modern Shells&amp;rdquo; are based on a language that has been written without a formal language specification. The source looked like this , because somebody didn&amp;rsquo;t like C and wanted Algol, abusing the preprocessor . The original functionality and language rules had to be reverse engineered from that source, and original shell has a lot of weird rules and quirks :</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The company as a social engine</title>
      <link>/2017/08/07/the-company-as-a-social-engine.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/07/the-company-as-a-social-engine.html</guid>
      <description>So why is everything so complicated? At work, I mean.
Think of a small company. A single person, a founder, is building her business. She knows her way around, it&amp;rsquo;s all in her head: The plan, the things that are important and why, and how they are to be executed. Also, tradeoffs to be corrected later, potential opportunities for later and a lot of other meta: Stuff that does not get executed right now, but that informs decisions, priorities and preferences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Attack of the 50 foot Blockchain</title>
      <link>/2017/08/01/fertig-gelesen-attack-of-the-50-foot-blockchain.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/01/fertig-gelesen-attack-of-the-50-foot-blockchain.html</guid>
      <description>The Blockchain is the solution to everything, and especially the problem of the state. So or similar goes the hype. This book attacks that hype, and it&amp;rsquo;s fun to read.
It very briefly (one chapter of many) and rather easily understandable explains what Merkle trees and eternal logfiles are, how they are different from the blockchain, what &amp;lsquo;proof of work&amp;rsquo; actually means.
It then goes on and actually takes apart the libertarian politics bullshit on top of that, by going through all the history of people and &amp;ldquo;businesses&amp;rdquo; connected to Bitcoin, Ethereum and the likes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twitter so: Testing in Production</title>
      <link>/2017/08/01/twitter-so-testing-in-production.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/01/twitter-so-testing-in-production.html</guid>
      <description>Matthew Dutton: »@mipsytipsy I thought &amp;ldquo;You have to test in production&amp;rdquo; was a bold statement and would love to hear more of your thoughts on the topic.«
Charity Majors: »Hmmm, you&amp;rsquo;re not the only one to call this out. I&amp;rsquo;ll add it to my list of &amp;ldquo;articles to write someday&amp;rdquo; ? but here&amp;rsquo;s the gist: We have always tested in production, just not well. And obviously, I&amp;rsquo;m not advising anyone to do less of the usual pre-production testing methods, but at some point, esp with distributed systems, you just can&amp;rsquo;t usefully mimic the qualities of size and chaos that tease out the long thin tail of bugs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: How to Kill a City, Gentrification, Inequality and the Fight for the Neighborhood</title>
      <link>/2017/07/31/fertig-gelesen-how-to-kill-a-city-gentrification-inequality-and-the-fight-for-the-neighborhood.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/31/fertig-gelesen-how-to-kill-a-city-gentrification-inequality-and-the-fight-for-the-neighborhood.html</guid>
      <description>In How to Kill a City Peter Moskowitz takes severals US example cities to show the general process of Gentriciation and the individual differences. We get to know the development stories of New Orleans, Detroit, San Francisco and New York, in order to better understand the mechanism and root causes of Gentrification, which is not about Hipsters and Latte at all, but about rent seeking, backroom dealing to change the law, and - specifically in the US - also about the history and perpetuation of racism.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Kill Process</title>
      <link>/2017/07/30/fertig-gelesen-kill-process.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/30/fertig-gelesen-kill-process.html</guid>
      <description>Kill Process is set in the same universe as &amp;ldquo;Avogadro Corp:, but is a freestanding story and not part of the Avogadro Series.
We meet Angelina Benenati. She&amp;rsquo;s a self taught hacker and database architect for Tomo, which is as much not Facebook as Avogadro Corporation is not Google and Braeburn is not Apple in Hertlings stories. She has a shady past, in which she hacked systems under the name of &amp;ldquo;Angel of Mercy&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Steerswoman Series</title>
      <link>/2017/07/29/fertig-gelesen-the-steerswoman-series.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/29/fertig-gelesen-the-steerswoman-series.html</guid>
      <description>The story begins as a Fantasy novel in a magical universe: We have two warring factions of magicians, a dragon attack, Gnomes and other entities from the fables and fairy tales.
We also have Rowan, the Steerswoman. She is more than a navigator and map maker, she&amp;rsquo;s part of a group of people that believes in science, in documentation and in open sources - the steerswomen. When a Steerswoman asks, you must answer, and truthfully.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: For We Are Many</title>
      <link>/2017/07/28/fertig-gelesen-for-we-are-many.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/28/fertig-gelesen-for-we-are-many.html</guid>
      <description>Bob is making what he was built for: more Bobs. Bob is in fact a dead computer programmer back from the destroyed and near inhabitable Planet Earth, who has been turned into an upload inhabiting a Von Neumann probe. His mission is to explore strange new worlds, going where nothing has gone before and make more of himself.
You can read more of his Genesis in We Are Legion Part 1 of the Bobiverse series .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Illegal and undocumented instructions</title>
      <link>/2017/07/28/illegal-and-undocumented-instructions.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/28/illegal-and-undocumented-instructions.html</guid>
      <description>Illegal and undocumented instructions are not a new thing. The Commodore 64 CPU, a 6502 with a few additional I/O lines, was known to have them. Since on current CPUs we can completely VLSI simulate a 6502 in Javascript we also understand where they come from.
Pagetable.com has a wonderful article on this . So how about current CPUs? Modern CPUs are vastly bigger and more complicated than a 6502, and they are also set up very differently.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: War Factory</title>
      <link>/2017/07/27/fertig-gelesen-war-factory.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/27/fertig-gelesen-war-factory.html</guid>
      <description>War Factory is the second of three Books in Neal Ashers Transformation Sequence , a trilogy set in his Polity Universe The storyline continues with the characters and themes of the first book - it&amp;rsquo;s about atonement and redemption. And as we learn, not just about the redemption of the mad AI Penny Royal, but also about the aftermath of the Human-Prador war and the redemption of the various persons (Human, Haiman, Prador and AI) that have been damaged by the war.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zero Factor Authentication</title>
      <link>/2017/07/27/zero-factor-authentication.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/27/zero-factor-authentication.html</guid>
      <description>Dear Internet, Today I Learned that oath-toolkit exists in Homebrew. So, this is a thing:
$ brew install oath-toolkit $ alias totp=&amp;#39;oathtool --totp -b YOURSECRET32BLA | pbcopy&amp;#39; And so is this:
#! /usr/bin/env expect -f # exp_internal 1 set seed [ exec security find-generic-password -w -a $USER -s seed ] set totp [ exec oathtool --totp -b $seed ] set pass [ exec security find-generic-password -w -a $USER -s pass ] spawn ssh verysecure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An abundance of IOPS and Zero Jitter</title>
      <link>/2017/07/26/an-abundance-of-iops-and-zero-jitter.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/26/an-abundance-of-iops-and-zero-jitter.html</guid>
      <description>Two weeks ago, I wrote about The Data Center in the Age of Abundance and claimed that IOPS are - among other things - a solved problem.
What does a solved problem look like?
Here is a benchmark running 100k random writes of 4K per second, with zero Jitter, at 350µs end-to-end write latency across six switches. Databases really like reliably timed writes like these. Maximum queue depth would be 48, the system is not touching that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Financial dynamics of a shift to BEV transport</title>
      <link>/2017/07/26/financial-dynamics-of-a-shift-to-bev-transport.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/26/financial-dynamics-of-a-shift-to-bev-transport.html</guid>
      <description>The German Language podcast Lage der Nation has published an interview with Axel Friedrich on Dieselgate. Axel Friedrich has been a department lead in the German Umweltbundesamt until 2008, now working with BUND and other environmental NGOs in Germany and instrumental in uncovering Dieselgate on the German side.
The interview contains some very interesting remarks on rental car companies and car maker owned car leasing companies, and how the shape the car market.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Renewables: Energy is free, guarantees cost money</title>
      <link>/2017/07/26/renewables-energy-is-free-guarantees-cost-money.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/26/renewables-energy-is-free-guarantees-cost-money.html</guid>
      <description>Digging through my bookmarks and open tabs was interesting. The picture of the future that emerges: With costs for energy approaching the 1 cent range per kWh, electrical energy is going to be close to free. Money can and will be charged for guarantees, because batteries or other forms of storage still cost money.
 Guardian: &amp;lsquo;Spectacular&amp;rsquo; drop in renewable energy costs leads to record global boost »The new renewable energy capacity installed worldwide in 2016 was 161GW, a 10% rise on 2015 […] The new record capacity cost $242bn, a 23% reduction in investment compared to 2015, and renewables investment remained larger than for all fossil fuels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Threads vs. Watts</title>
      <link>/2017/07/19/threads-vs-watts.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/19/threads-vs-watts.html</guid>
      <description>So I have been testing, again. My hapless test subject this time is a Dell Box, an R630. It has a comfortable 384GB of memory, one of two 25 GBit/s ports active, and it comes with two E5-2690v4 CPUs. That gives it 14 cores per die, 28 cores in total, or with hyperthreading, 56 threads.
$ cat /proc/cpuinfo | grep &amp;#39;model name&amp;#39; | uniq -c 56 model name : Intel(R) Xeon(R) CPU E5-2690 v4 @ 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mandatory solar panels for new homes</title>
      <link>/2017/07/18/mandatory-solar-panels-for-new-homes.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/18/mandatory-solar-panels-for-new-homes.html</guid>
      <description>Short link to NBC Miami :
 South Miami Set to Become First City in Florida to Require Solar Panels on New Homes The new law would require owners of new homes &amp;ndash; including single-family homes, townhouses and multi-story residential buildings &amp;ndash; to install solar panels. It also applies to owners who expand their homes by 75% or greater. Once the measure is passed, South Miami would become the fourth U.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using MySQL Partitions (a Python example)</title>
      <link>/2017/07/09/using-mysql-partitions-a-python-example.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/09/using-mysql-partitions-a-python-example.html</guid>
      <description>Today somebody had a problem with expiring a large table (a Serendipity Blog table).
In MySQL InnoDB, tables are physically ordered by primary key (InnoDB data is a B+ tree, a balanced tree where the data pages are the leaves of the tree). If you are expiring old data from such a log table, you are deleting from the left hand side of the tree, and since it is a balanced tree, that triggers a lot of rebalancing - hence it is very slow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Technology vs Planned Obsolescence</title>
      <link>/2017/07/07/new-technology-vs-planned-obsolescence.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/07/new-technology-vs-planned-obsolescence.html</guid>
      <description>based on an old Google plus article from 2015: What you observe as Planned Obsolescence is often the natural outcome of fast product cycles that are necessary for any new technology. When a new thing arrives in the market, it is often barely viable, a minimum viable product .
We are remembering the iPhone 1 as revolutionary, but we chose to forget about is slowness, its clunkyness and the very limited feature set it had.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday Deploys, and other harmful BOFH memes</title>
      <link>/2017/07/03/friday-deploys-and-other-harmful-bofh-memes.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/03/friday-deploys-and-other-harmful-bofh-memes.html</guid>
      <description>Glorifying toil, glorifying organisational ossification
So somebody posted this on G+, and it&amp;rsquo;s a classic example for a thing that I classify as BOFH memes. That&amp;rsquo;s a group of memes and stories from operations people from a time past glorifying the toil and nastiness of operations.
This is going away now, for some time, and people identifying with BOFH thinking or finding it funny need to change, or go out of job.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project Zero</title>
      <link>/2017/06/29/project-zero.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/06/29/project-zero.html</guid>
      <description>Fortune has a kind of home story on Project Zero , explaining what it is, how it came to be and who the people in there are.
If you do not know what Project Zero is and why it is important, it&amp;rsquo;s a good starting point. If you know about Project Zero, it&amp;rsquo;s still a fun read because of all the parentheses that read »x declined to be interviewed for this story.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On cache problems, and what they mean for the future</title>
      <link>/2017/06/23/on-cache-problems-and-what-they-mean-for-the-future.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/06/23/on-cache-problems-and-what-they-mean-for-the-future.html</guid>
      <description>This is a disk utilization graph on a heavily loaded Graphite box. In this case, a Dell with a MegaRAID, but that actually does not matter too much.
Go-carbon was lagging and buffering on the box, because the SSD was running at its IOPS limit. At 18:10, the write-back cache and the &amp;ldquo;intelligent read-ahead&amp;rdquo; are being disabled, that is, the MegaRAID is being force-dumbed down to a regular non-smart controller. The effect is stunning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>25 years &#34;Individual Network e.V.&#34;</title>
      <link>/2017/06/20/25-years-individual-network-e-v.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/06/20/25-years-individual-network-e-v.html</guid>
      <description>Heiko Schlichting reminds us that 25 years ago, on the 20./21. of June 1992, the Individual Network e.V. was created (Text in German). Individual Network e.V. was a NGO of NGOs, a construct where local citizen network NGOs could be members. Individual Network would then make contracts with the German Science Network DFN and other providers and buy traffic rights in bulk, in order to allow its members to use this traffic for non-commercial, private use.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Google took over the classroom</title>
      <link>/2017/06/13/how-google-took-over-the-classroom.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/06/13/how-google-took-over-the-classroom.html</guid>
      <description>Using electronic devices in the classroom seems to be a topic older than time, and the implementation often involved a lot of tedium. The problems and possible solutions are well understood in Germany (report about LTSP among other things), but the (purposefully) fragmented market for education in Germany is getting in the way here. Biggest problem usually is keeping the machines clean and orderly, and keeping the data available across device loss.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shit found on github: bork</title>
      <link>/2017/06/12/shit-found-on-github-bork.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/06/12/shit-found-on-github-bork.html</guid>
      <description>I&amp;gt; Good Morning!
M&amp;gt; And to you, too!
I&amp;gt; I hope you have a nice and technically reliable start into a new week full of hope!
I&amp;gt; Here, catch. https://github.com/mattly/bork M&amp;gt; »A bash DSL for config management« And it&amp;rsquo;s not even chistmas, ye
I&amp;gt; &amp;ldquo;the Swedish Chef Puppet of Config Management. [&amp;hellip;] Bork is written against Bash 3.2 and common unix utilities such as sed, awk and grep. It is designed to work on any UNIX-based system and maintain awareness of platform differences between BSD and GPL versions of unix utilities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Google Chrome integrates Adblocker</title>
      <link>/2017/06/02/google-chrome-integrates-adblocker.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/06/02/google-chrome-integrates-adblocker.html</guid>
      <description>The Ad and Adblock situations both are now so bad that even Google considers integrating an Adblocker by default into the Chrome browser.
This is a twofold action.
It&amp;rsquo;s purpose is of course to filter out ads, the worst of the worst in annoyance and the obvious malvertising. It&amp;rsquo;s purpose is also to take back control on adblocking, because it will let through acceptable ads according to the Coalition for Better Ads standards.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good Riddance to the Query Cache</title>
      <link>/2017/05/31/good-riddance-to-the-query-cache.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/31/good-riddance-to-the-query-cache.html</guid>
      <description>MySQL 8.0 will be retiring support for the Query Cache . The MySQL Query cache is a result cache: The MySQL server will record all result sets that are small enough to keep in the cache, and a hash of the query that produced it.
If a query meets certain requirements, and the hash of the same query string is ever seen again, the query will not be actually parsed and executed, but the same result set will be replayed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zero Tests and Testing in Production</title>
      <link>/2017/05/29/zero-tests-and-testing-in-production.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/29/zero-tests-and-testing-in-production.html</guid>
      <description>There is a pretty cool Twitter thread by Sarah Mei, starting at
Thread I spammed into this at /14 .
@samphippen :
 Big secret: there exist vast tranches of business contexts in which having literally zero tests is fine.
 @sarahmei :
 Been thinking about this. Conventional wisdom says you need a comprehensive set of regression tests to go green before you release code. /1
You want to know that your changes didn&amp;rsquo;t break something elsewhere in the app.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Measles vs your immune system</title>
      <link>/2017/05/26/the-measles-vs-your-immune-system.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/26/the-measles-vs-your-immune-system.html</guid>
      <description>NPR has an article about the measles. It is already known that after a measles infection the immune system goes down for a few weeks and followup infections are common. It seems that what the infection does is worse than that. With the introduction of measles vaccination it has been observed that other infections went down within 2-3 years after measles immunization took place. Researchers wanted to know why and found evidence that</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking Transportation</title>
      <link>/2017/05/23/rethinking-transportation.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/23/rethinking-transportation.html</guid>
      <description>Tony Seba (Stanford University) came up with a kind of best-case scenario for electrification and decarbonization. &amp;ldquo;Rethinking Transportation 2020-2030 &amp;rdquo; sees a self-amplifiying change in how we travel and transport things:
 By 2030, within 10 years of regulatory approval of autonomous vehicles (AVs), 95% of U.S. passenger miles traveled will be served by on-demand autonomous electric vehicles owned by fleets, not individuals, in a new business model we call “transportas-a-service” (TaaS).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Handling Wannacrypt - a few words about technical debt</title>
      <link>/2017/05/15/handling-wannacrypt-a-few-words-about-technical-debt.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/15/handling-wannacrypt-a-few-words-about-technical-debt.html</guid>
      <description>So Microsoft had a bug in their systems. Many of their sytems. For many years. That happens. People write code. These people write bugs. Microsoft over the years has become decently good with fixing bugs and rolling out upgrades, quickly. That&amp;rsquo;s apparently important, because we all are not good enough at not writing bugs. So if we cannot prevent them, we need to be able to fix them and then bring these fixes to the people.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Canary Skill Endorsements</title>
      <link>/2017/05/09/canary-skill-endorsements.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/09/canary-skill-endorsements.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Canary Skill Endorsements &amp;quot;: If you see them being used in a letter sent to you by a recruiter, you go all Van Halen when they spot a brown M&amp;amp;M .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RTT-based vs. drop based congestion management</title>
      <link>/2017/05/09/rtt-based-vs-drop-based-congestion-management.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/09/rtt-based-vs-drop-based-congestion-management.html</guid>
      <description>APNIC discusses different TCP congestion control algorithms , coming from Reno, going through CUBIC and Vegas, then introducing BBR (seems to be a variation on CoDel) and what they observed when running BBR in a network with other implementations.
TCP congestion control algorithms try to estimate the bandwidth limit of a multi-segment network path, where a stream crosses many routers. Each segment may have a different available capacity. Overloading the total path (that is, the thinnest subsegment of the path) will force packet drops by overloading the buffers of the router just in front of that thin segment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kris, where are the posts?</title>
      <link>/2017/05/08/kris-where-are-the-posts.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/08/kris-where-are-the-posts.html</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s not my fault, really. It&amp;rsquo;s Schenker , and Urban Games . They sent me my Nvidia 1070 (with a side of CPU and Memory), and now there is a Windows Shoebox (well, Clown Shoe sized showbox) somewhere in our home, and Steam Streaming is busy. I&amp;rsquo;m off laying tracks with the family, now the screen updates are not jumpy any more.
 XMG Prime </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The bike as a feeder system to the train system</title>
      <link>/2017/04/29/the-bike-as-a-feeder-system-to-the-train-system.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/29/the-bike-as-a-feeder-system-to-the-train-system.html</guid>
      <description>A talk by Marco te Brömmelstroet and others about how neither the Bike nor the train themselves are a viable transport alternative, but how they together are much more than the sum of their parts:
 Nine Arguments for seeing bicycle-train as one mobility system Biking increases the catchment area of train stations, allowing an increase of the distance between stops for stop-trains, and consequently also for all higher-order trains. This speeds up the train system, making it a lot more attractive and a lot more viable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>jq</title>
      <link>/2017/04/26/jq.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/26/jq.html</guid>
      <description>When dealing with Kubernetes, you will inevitably have to deal with config and data that is in JSON format. jq is a cool tool to handle this, but while the man page is complete, it is also very dry. A nice tutorial can be found at The Programming Historian, which uses some real world use cases. My personal use case is Converting JSON to CSV , and the inverse of that .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Militant capitalist attacked german soccer bus</title>
      <link>/2017/04/21/militant-capitalist-attacked-german-soccer-bus.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/21/militant-capitalist-attacked-german-soccer-bus.html</guid>
      <description>The bomb attack on the bus of the german soccer club BVB has been solved. The attacker was not an islamist extremist, as the fake letters found on site suggested. They also weren&amp;rsquo;t Neo-Nazis, as the fake letters to two german newspapers claimed. The perpetrator was instead a militant capitalist who tried to influence BVB stock in order, after he purchased 15k put options on BVB stock. An english language article with background can be found at the BBC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding sysdig</title>
      <link>/2017/04/20/understanding-sysdig.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/20/understanding-sysdig.html</guid>
      <description>The open source sysdig is a piece of software that does not quite, but almost, what strace or oprofile do: It instrument the kernel, and traces system calls as well as a few other kernel activities.
Youtube: Sysdig Open Source - Getting Started With Csysdig It does not utilize the ptrace(2) kernel facility, though, but its own interface. This interface picks up data in the kernel and writes it into a ring buffer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>node.js idea of an inode is approximately broken</title>
      <link>/2017/04/19/node-js-idea-of-an-inode-is-approximately-broken.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/19/node-js-idea-of-an-inode-is-approximately-broken.html</guid>
      <description>The Tweet points to the bug report . After the facepalming there is still a lot to say about that.
About the bug:   There is a system call stat(2) in Posix, which returns a struct stat as a result. Part of that data structure is a field st_ino, which contains the inode number of that file. That number is a unique file identifier, a 64 bit bit pattern.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Curlbash, and Desktop Containers</title>
      <link>/2017/04/13/curlbash-and-desktop-containers.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/13/curlbash-and-desktop-containers.html</guid>
      <description>I was having two independent discussions recently, which started with some traditional Unix person condemning software installing with curlbash (curl https://... | bash), or even curl | sudo bash.
I do not really think this to be much more dangerous than the installation of random rpm or dpkg packages any more. Especially if those packages are unsigned or the signing key gets installed just before the package.
The threat model really became a different one in the last few years, and the security mechanism have had to change as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Apostrophiser</title>
      <link>/2017/04/05/apostrophiser.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/05/apostrophiser.html</guid>
      <description>The Telegraph had a article on a self-styled &amp;lsquo;grammar vigilante&amp;rsquo;, who corrects badly punctuated shop signs in the dead of the night, and the article has not been dated April, 1st.
 […] the man has corrected tens of missing and misplaced apostrophes on shop banners across Bristol over the past 13 years. The pedant, who is yet to reveal his identity, claims his efforts are needed to bring an end to the improper use of English.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strong weak ties</title>
      <link>/2017/04/05/strong-weak-ties.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/05/strong-weak-ties.html</guid>
      <description>A long time ago, I wrote a text on the German Blog and on Carta: Wieso wir uns veröffentlichen (Why we publish ourselves).
In the middle of a discussion about privacy I was explaining why people publish themselves, why they publicly reveal (sometimes intimate) facts about themselves. They are doing this, I wrote, to find other like-minded people, to become searchable and to become approachable, to build trust. Trust is a wonderful thing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Interview in the Enterprise</title>
      <link>/2017/03/27/the-interview-in-the-enterprise.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/27/the-interview-in-the-enterprise.html</guid>
      <description>See also an earlier article in the blog, and Why I Don&amp;rsquo;t Talk to Google Recruiters mentioned in the comments. Where I work we have regular round tables, in which you can talk and ask questions to middle management from other departments than your own. I had the opportunity to talk to a person who manages development priorities and staffs teams, and who of course has some insight into hiring and the interview process.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Electric car confusion</title>
      <link>/2017/03/23/electric-car-confusion.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/23/electric-car-confusion.html</guid>
      <description>Autoblog titles: The race for autonomous cars is over. Silicon Valley lost . The point they want to make is:
 To paraphrase Elon Musk, Silicon Valley is learning that &amp;ldquo;Making rockets is hard, but making cars is really hard.&amp;rdquo; People outside of the auto industry tend to have a shallow understanding of how complex the business really is. They think all you have to do is design a car and start making it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 reasons not to do HTTPS interception</title>
      <link>/2017/03/22/10-reasons-not-to-do-https-interception.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/22/10-reasons-not-to-do-https-interception.html</guid>
      <description>Marnix Dekker has an article on HTTPS interception as it is being done in some workplaces. He lists:
 Are you serious? We worked so hard to make the web more secure and you are fucking it up. HSTS, you are breaking it. Blinds the browser and the user, because you re-encrypt with wildcard certs. Disrupts personal use. Breaks pinning and CT. Breaks with consumerization. Disrupts BYOD. Discourages good user practices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Malvertising - we have only seen the beginning</title>
      <link>/2017/03/21/malvertising-we-have-only-seen-the-beginning.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/21/malvertising-we-have-only-seen-the-beginning.html</guid>
      <description>Netzpolitik.org has an article (in German) in which they are interviewing IT-Security Consultant Thorsten Schröder on Adblockers, wasted capped mobile bandwidth and Malvertising.
 netzpolitik.org : Neben dem Schutz vor Malware, welche weiteren Gründe für die Nutzung von Adblockern findest Du wichtig?
Thorsten Schröder : Wenn wir als Malware all das klassifizieren, was Nutzer ausspioniert, täuscht, kompromittiert oder finanziell schädigt, haben wir im Grunde schon mal eine ganze Reihe an Gründen abgehakt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No such thing as a wilderness, part II</title>
      <link>/2017/03/21/no-such-thing-as-a-wilderness-part-ii.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/21/no-such-thing-as-a-wilderness-part-ii.html</guid>
      <description>Science Daily writes :
 New research investigating the transition of the Sahara from a lush, green landscape 10,000 years ago to the arid conditions found today, suggests that humans may have played an active role in its desertification. [&amp;hellip;] As more vegetation was removed by the introduction of livestock, it increased the albedo (the amount of sunlight that reflects off the earth&amp;rsquo;s surface) of the land, which in turn influenced atmospheric conditions sufficiently to reduce monsoon rainfall.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No such thing as a wilderness?</title>
      <link>/2017/03/21/no-such-thing-as-a-wilderness.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/21/no-such-thing-as-a-wilderness.html</guid>
      <description>Some 40 authors are listed in the title of Persistent effects of pre-Columbian plant domestication on Amazonian forest composition in Science.
The TL;DR is: The Amazonas Rain Forest is a 10.000 year old garden, which has been left untended for the last 500 years after the Amerindian genocide of European conquistadors.
 The extent to which pre-Columbian societies altered Amazonian landscapes is hotly debated. We performed a basin-wide analysis of pre-Columbian impacts on Amazonian forests by overlaying known archaeological sites in Amazonia with the distributions and abundances of 85 woody species domesticated by pre-Columbian peoples.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Salted Doorknobs kill MRSA</title>
      <link>/2017/03/21/salted-doorknobs-kill-mrsa.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/21/salted-doorknobs-kill-mrsa.html</guid>
      <description>Salted Doorknobs kill MRSA Says this article at The Atlantic :
 Superbugs like Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus, or MRSA, have wreaked havoc on the health-care system in recent years. [&amp;hellip;] How do you stop them? Frequent hand washing is one option, but that requires a behavior change, which can be difficult, even for hospital staff. Another option is to coat those frequently fondled objects most likely to carry the bugs—doorknobs, bed rails, toilet handles—with a special anti-microbial surface, like copper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When you commit to git, how long does it matter?</title>
      <link>/2017/03/20/when-you-commit-to-git-how-long-does-it-matter.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/20/when-you-commit-to-git-how-long-does-it-matter.html</guid>
      <description>Commit to git Erik Bernhardsson has been running Big Data on Git repositories of various kinds. He was trying to find out what the half-life of code is. That is, when you commit to a repository, your code becomes part of a project, but eventually other code will replace it and it will no longer be part of the current version. How stable is the codebase, what is the half-life of code?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>That&#39;s no moon!</title>
      <link>/2017/03/13/thats-no-moon.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/13/thats-no-moon.html</guid>
      <description>So Saturn has a &amp;lsquo;moon&amp;rsquo;. At least that&amp;rsquo;s what They want us to believe. But we know better.
 Supposedly Pan , a Saturn Moon, as seen by Cassini.
BASIS , as we know it from Rhodan </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We learned a few things about Cycle Path design in the last 25 years</title>
      <link>/2017/03/13/we-learned-a-few-things-about-cycle-path-design-in-the-last-25-years.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/13/we-learned-a-few-things-about-cycle-path-design-in-the-last-25-years.html</guid>
      <description>In any discussion about cycling in Germany, sooner or later some geek who has been exposed to USENET shows up and then the ADFC #173 (http://bernd.sluka.de/Radfahren/fdf173.pdf ) is being quoted. That&amp;rsquo;s a thing from 1992.
The usual thing happened here on Facebook - a discussion about the SolaRoad Krommenie diverged into &amp;ldquo;Cycle Paths are stupid&amp;rdquo; and then linked over to the ADFC #173.
Here is a bunch of more recent material and links.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IRC so: 110 Freedom Volts</title>
      <link>/2017/03/10/irc-so-110-freedom-volts.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/10/irc-so-110-freedom-volts.html</guid>
      <description>Work Chat said: [On boiling water with Gas instead of an electric cooker]
L&amp;gt; Yeah, they have 110 freedom volts. Or whatever weird unit they use for that.
I&amp;gt; So what is the imperial unit for Volt?
 Let&amp;rsquo;s see. Volt in SI units :
 That gives us $$ 1V = 1 kg * m^2 * s^{-3} * A^{-1}. $$
We can turn the kg into pounds and the square meters into square feet, but we can&amp;rsquo;t easily imperialize the seconds and Amperes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The cost of winning…</title>
      <link>/2017/03/10/the-cost-of-winning.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/10/the-cost-of-winning.html</guid>
      <description>Tech.co has an article titled Artificial Intelligence Startups Are Winning the Cybersecurity Race . The claim is basically first that old, pattern and signature based malware recognition is useless, and second, that new, behavior based malware recognition employing mystery AI technologies fixes things. The article closes with
 In the near future, we predict that AI will be able to effectively fight against hackers by easily detecting repacked viruses. It’s just a matter of time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>github updates its TOS, and they are not trying to cheat</title>
      <link>/2017/03/09/github-updates-its-tos-and-they-are-not-trying-to-cheat.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/09/github-updates-its-tos-and-they-are-not-trying-to-cheat.html</guid>
      <description>Every single time a big Silicon Valley company updates their Terms of Service, there is somebody who mis-interprets the change as an attempt to landgrab, or take ownership of the things being uploaded to the service.
This time it affects github.
Their new TOS has a section on User-Generated Content , which in github&amp;rsquo;s case is all the repositories, snippets and other stuff they are hosting. In order to do the stuff they are doing on their users behalf, they need a lot of legal permissions on the stuff you are sending to them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Engineer Wizard</title>
      <link>/2017/03/04/fertig-gelesen-the-engineer-wizard.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/04/fertig-gelesen-the-engineer-wizard.html</guid>
      <description>The Engineer Wizard Paul Armstead is a fat, old man with no life. Helping a stranger in a snow storm, he gets a mystery box, which contains a Genie. Helping the Genie, he&amp;rsquo;s being transformed into a wizard, a being which can affect reality in an acausal way. For the last 400 years, no new wizards have been created on earth, and the remaining 300 or so wizards and witches are ossified.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: We are Legion (We are Bob)</title>
      <link>/2017/03/02/fertig-gelesen-we-are-legion-we-are-bob.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/02/fertig-gelesen-we-are-legion-we-are-bob.html</guid>
      <description>We are Legion Somebody pointed me to We are Legion (We are Bob) , but somehow I can&amp;rsquo;t find that post any more. Anyway, following that hint, I picked up the book and read it. It&amp;rsquo;s awesome.
Bob Johannson made it big: Sold his software company to his greatest competitor, took the money, got a cryopreservation contract on his head and went to a SciFi convention, partying. Where he is run over crossing the street and dies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Explorations - First Contact</title>
      <link>/2017/02/28/fertig-gelesen-explorations-first-contact.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/28/fertig-gelesen-explorations-first-contact.html</guid>
      <description>Explorations: First Contact Explorations: First Contact is a great concept well executed: This is a writing prompt anthology. So there is a base story - in this case, humanity sends a probe to the back side of the moon, finds an anomaly which turns out to be a dying alien spaceship that manages to upload the secrets of it&amp;rsquo;s drive and a partial database of other alien civilisations it once visited into the minds of the astronauts that make the contact.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Galactic Exploration</title>
      <link>/2017/02/28/fertig-gelesen-galactic-exploration.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/28/fertig-gelesen-galactic-exploration.html</guid>
      <description>Galactic Exploration One of the very first things I read on Kindle has been Anomaly by Peter Cawdron - his first publication. My review in German Language is here . Turns out, Cawdron is a quite productive author, and active and responsive on Goodreads . Seeing my review there, he pointed me to his other works, and to his mailing list . Through that I found Galactic Exploration and other works by him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Culture Map</title>
      <link>/2017/02/28/fertig-gelesen-the-culture-map.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/28/fertig-gelesen-the-culture-map.html</guid>
      <description>The Culture Map Erin Meyer is a professor at INSEAD, an international business school based in Paris. She&amp;rsquo;s specialized in cross-cultural communication and facilitation, and in her book explains the dimensions and differences between different cultures in the world, and how they can shape or interfere with exchanges in a multi-cultural environment.
The book introduces eight different cultural scales or spectra, and where the various national cultures position themselves on these scales.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solar plus Storage in Australia</title>
      <link>/2017/02/24/solar-plus-storage-in-australia.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/24/solar-plus-storage-in-australia.html</guid>
      <description>In the 2016 South Australia Blackout , a storm lead to a cascading failure, with in turn left 1/6 of the continent without electricity. Fortunately, this is not a densely populated area even for australian circumstances, so it affected some 1.5 mio people (out of 20 mio total for all of Australia) - still quite a lot of people. The news of a 73-year-old Tesla Powerwall owner powering through this outage without even noticing made the headlines in the aftermath, and in consequence demand for PV + Battery combination surged.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OMG, our cybervaccines are failing</title>
      <link>/2017/02/17/omg-our-cybervaccines-are-failing.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/17/omg-our-cybervaccines-are-failing.html</guid>
      <description>Dark Reading is scared: All new malware is &amp;ldquo;zero-day&amp;rdquo;, for an interesting and wrong definition of zero-day, because then the article reads much more impressive.
The actual definition of a Zero Day is a previously unknown exploit that is being used by some party to compromise a machine. In the article, the term is used differently, meaning a file that is a known malware, but has changed itself so that it has a checksum that is not in currently distributed signature catalogs of known malware.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Load, Load Testing and Benchmarking</title>
      <link>/2017/02/16/load-load-testing-and-benchmarking.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/16/load-load-testing-and-benchmarking.html</guid>
      <description>(This article also available in german language .)
So you have a new system and want to know what the load limits are. For that you want to run a benchmark.
Basic Benchmarking   The main plan looks like this:
The basic idea: Find a box, offer load, see what happens, learn.
You grab a box and find a method to generate load. Eventually the box will be fully loaded and you will notice this somehow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Die Krone der Sterne</title>
      <link>/2017/02/13/fertig-gelesen-die-krone-der-sterne.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/13/fertig-gelesen-die-krone-der-sterne.html</guid>
      <description>Die Krone der Sterne (German Edition), Kai Meyer, 12.99 EUR (Kindle)
&amp;ldquo;Die Krone der Sterne&amp;rdquo; (The Crown of the Stars) is the first book in a series by Kai Meyer, establishing a setting, the players and the mood.
We are thrown into a decaying, galaxy spanning empire with a distinct Dune like flair. Tech is always huge, somewhat clunky and unreliable, covered in rust, dirt, runes and unnecessary decoaration, and it operates on principles that are never explained and also not really understood by it&amp;rsquo;s users - it has been inherited by previous, more advanced generations and today&amp;rsquo;s people can barely operate it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hipsterdoom with Mongobingo</title>
      <link>/2017/02/10/hipsterdoom-at-mongobingo.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/10/hipsterdoom-at-mongobingo.html</guid>
      <description>Felix Gessert does a postmortem of the failed Parse startup and product: &amp;ldquo;The AWS and MongoDB Infrastructure of Parse: Lessons Learned &amp;rdquo;.
 Technical problem II: the real problem and bottleneck was not the API servers but almost always the shared MongoDB database cluster.
 And that was with MongoRocks (Mongo on RocksDB) and replacing the initial app in Ruby with a Go implementation of said thing, with WriteConcern = 1, and other horrible presets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Normalcy: The rest times of truck drivers in Europe</title>
      <link>/2017/02/09/on-normalcy-the-rest-times-of-truck-drivers-in-europe.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/09/on-normalcy-the-rest-times-of-truck-drivers-in-europe.html</guid>
      <description>DVZ Landverkehr reports (article in German):
 LKW-Fahrer dürfen ihre wöchentliche Ruhezeit nicht im Fahrzeug verbringen. Zu diesem Ergebnis kommt Generalanwalt Evgeni Tanchev in seinen Schlussanträgen vom 2. Februar vor dem Europäischen Gerichtshof (EuGH). Hintergrund ist die Klage des Transportunternehmens Vaditrans gegen den Belgischen Staat.
(&amp;ldquo;Truck drivers must not spend their weekly downtime within the vehicle. That&amp;rsquo;s the conclusion drawn by general attorney Evgeni Tanchev in his final plea of Feb, 2nd before the ECJ.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Video: 20 Years of continuous improvement in crash safety</title>
      <link>/2017/02/09/video-20-years-of-continuous-improvement-in-crash-safety.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/09/video-20-years-of-continuous-improvement-in-crash-safety.html</guid>
      <description>Continual improvement is sometimes hard to see, because each iteration, each incremental step itself is tiny so that the actual change escapes our attention. Also, just living our lives, our time sense is sometimes distorted. Me for example, I was almost 30 already in the late Nineties, and while that is already 20 years ago, it feels like yesterday to me. So car safety in the Nineties, compared to now? It was crap.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FOSDEM Talk: cgroups-v2</title>
      <link>/2017/02/07/fosdem-talk-cgroups-v2.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/07/fosdem-talk-cgroups-v2.html</guid>
      <description>The talk The cgroups-v2 API is incompatible with cgroups-v1. This is a good thing, because the initial use cases for cgroups have not been fleshed out properly, and the API is kind of overly complicated from the POV of the consumers. v2 is being built with use cases and experience in mind, and is much easier to use. Control groups allow Linux users to limit the kind and amount of resources being used, which is employed by systemd, container drivers and many other things.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The History of Moore&#39;s Law</title>
      <link>/2017/02/07/the-history-of-moores-law.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/07/the-history-of-moores-law.html</guid>
      <description>Commodore 64, Evan-Amos @ Wikipedia As Moore&amp;rsquo;s Law shows signs of coming to an end, the Guardian has an article about the history of computing from the Intel 4004 to current tech, and how with the Internet of Shit and Chips and Networking in everything, all of our computers are becoming just one computer.
 Everyone knows that modern computers are better than old ones. But it is hard to convey just how much better, for no other consumer technology has improved at anything approaching a similar pace.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maya empire remains</title>
      <link>/2017/02/06/maya-empire-remains.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/06/maya-empire-remains.html</guid>
      <description>Lidar Image
Two articles about the Maya civilization: Seeker article about LiDAR being used to reveal ancient structures on the Jungle ground: A network of 150km of prehistoric Autobahn ran through the Jungle, binding the Mayan Empire together.
 &amp;ldquo;These causeways are 130 feet wide, up to 20 feet high and in some cases they extend as far as 25 miles,&amp;rdquo; Hansen said.
 A causeway is a raised road across difficult, often wet or unstable ground.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stockholm&#39;s congestion charge vs. Asthma</title>
      <link>/2017/02/06/stockholms-congestion-charge-vs-asthma.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/06/stockholms-congestion-charge-vs-asthma.html</guid>
      <description>Inside Science reports on the congestion charge in Stockholm (Link to actual paper ). Stockholm always has been a city with relatively clean air and PM10 and NOx levels well below limits. The introduction of a congestion charge in 2007 reduced air pollution in Stockholm by approximately 10 percent. Yet, after several years, Asthma in children 0-5 years old is reduced of 45 percent.
 &amp;ldquo;It appears that what they&amp;rsquo;ve found is these cumulative effects of pollution,&amp;rdquo; he said.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parser Bug Hell</title>
      <link>/2017/02/03/parser-bug-hell.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/03/parser-bug-hell.html</guid>
      <description>Wireshark Bug Stats
So Debian just posted an advisory for over 40 bugs in tcpdump . tcpdump is a tool that collects traffic on the network, and then parses its way down the stack from the Ethernet or other physical frames all the way through the IP and TCP stacks to the application layers and the data formats in there.
Parsing data is hard. Even the actual full blown applications normally reading that data often have problems parsing their own data format, and they are crashing if you throw malformed data at them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Racing our galaxy</title>
      <link>/2017/02/02/racing-our-galaxy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/02/racing-our-galaxy.html</guid>
      <description>Why is our galaxy moving through space, and into which directions is everything else moving?
Scientists at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem have been mapping these forces, and found a very empty region in space that seems to push a lot of galaxies away from it, as well as a (previously known) region thats attracting them.
The result looks like a billion light year magnet:
 The dipole repeller What causes these forces is as of now not well understood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Europol discovers CGN</title>
      <link>/2017/02/01/europol-discovers-cgn.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/01/europol-discovers-cgn.html</guid>
      <description>The Council of the European Union discusses the &amp;ldquo;problem&amp;rdquo; of Carrier Grader NAT, and would like to see all Ip address logging and storage extended to port numbers, as well as all NAT state tables to be stored and preserved, in order to be able to resolve Internet accesses to subscriber identities, says Statewatch .
The paper in question has been submitted by EUROPOL and claims that clients are &amp;ldquo;going dark&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exponential Fuck-Off</title>
      <link>/2017/02/01/exponential-fuck-off.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/01/exponential-fuck-off.html</guid>
      <description>»Damian: The solution is to send emails with increasing frequency
@markzabaro: It&amp;rsquo;s called exponential fuck-off.«
&amp;ndash; https://mobile.twitter.com/dgryski/status/826385338104954881 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nobody wants backup. Everybody wants restore.</title>
      <link>/2017/02/01/nobody-wants-backup-everybody-wants-restore.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/01/nobody-wants-backup-everybody-wants-restore.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;/uploads/2017/02/mysql-backup-and-recovery-15-638.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Operations matter. I know the Hipster crowd does not like to
hear that, cloud or not. But reality has a way of making itself
heard, whether you like it or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1GCK53YDcBWQveod9kfzW-VCxIABGiryG7_z_6jHdVik/pub&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gitlab.com just discovered that.&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So some sysadmin deleted the wrong folder, which in itself
should not be a problem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bielefeld Conspiracy hits Facebook</title>
      <link>/2017/01/26/bielefeld-conspiracy-hits-facebook.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/26/bielefeld-conspiracy-hits-facebook.html</guid>
      <description>Westfalenblatt knows:
 Yesterday all references to the place name &amp;ldquo;Bielefeld&amp;rdquo; have been replaced with &amp;ldquo;Bielefeldverschwörung &amp;rdquo; (Bielefeld Conspiracy):
 Facebook showing &amp;ldquo;Bielefeldverschwörung&amp;rdquo; (Bielefeld Conspiracy) instead of the proper city name.
Bielefeld is a typical while label city in Germany. In fact, it is conspiciously inconspicious, and that is, so the conspiracy theory fabricated by Achim Held in 1993, because the city does not actually exist. It&amp;rsquo;s a fake location that protects something else on the map, probably an entrance to the Hollow Earth or something else, but we don&amp;rsquo;t actually know.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chinese New Year, and birthrate anomalies</title>
      <link>/2017/01/26/chinese-new-year-and-birthrate-anomalies.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/26/chinese-new-year-and-birthrate-anomalies.html</guid>
      <description>Coming up: Chinese New Year on 28. January. The coming year is a year of the Fire Rooster , and apparently these things mean a lot to a lot of people. So what influence does the Chinese Zodiac have? Well, one sign that is supposed to be very unlucky is the Fire Horse. An article from 2012 explains:
 People born during the year of the Fire Horse are notorious for being bad luck.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EU described own policy as &#39;complete failure&#39;</title>
      <link>/2017/01/26/eu-described-own-policy-as-complete-failure.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/26/eu-described-own-policy-as-complete-failure.html</guid>
      <description>EU Observer reports on a five page internal note from the EU director-general at the commission&amp;rsquo;s internal market and industry department:
 &amp;ldquo;Absolute NOx emissions of diesel vehicles under real driving conditions have hardly changed” despite “various” EU “steps”. “On the road, a Euro 5 vehicle emits almost the same amount of NOx per km as a Euro 3 vehicle.&amp;rdquo;
 The testing method, which is nothing like real road conditions, is mentioned as a contributing factor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finished Reading: Maddrax 443 &#34;Die Erleuchteten&#34;</title>
      <link>/2017/01/26/finished-reading-maddrax-443-die-erleuchteten.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/26/finished-reading-maddrax-443-die-erleuchteten.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Maddrax 443: Die Erleuchteten &amp;rdquo;, Jo Zybell (german language, EUR 1.49)
So Maddrax is one of those pulp series that are sold in booklet format in train stations, right next to romance novels. The setting echoes Planet of the Apes or other post-apocalyptic scenarios with Sci-Fantasy elements.
During a failed space mission involving firing nukes at an asteroid/alien terraformship on a collision course with earth, Matthew ‘Matt’ Drax is transported five centuries into the future, where he finds a barbarian wilderness sparsely populated by mutant survivors of the impact and barbarians.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finished Reading: Pre-Suasion: A Revolutionary Way to Influence and Persuade</title>
      <link>/2017/01/26/finished-reading-pre-suasion-a-revolutionary-way-to-influence-and-persuade.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/26/finished-reading-pre-suasion-a-revolutionary-way-to-influence-and-persuade.html</guid>
      <description>]
&amp;ldquo;Pre-Suasion: A Revolutionary Way to Influence and Persuade &amp;rdquo;, Robert Cialdini, (english language, EUR 12.99)
Robert Cialdini is a professor emeritus of Psychology and Marketing at the Arizona State University, a visiting professor of marketing, business and psychology at Stanford University, and is the author of several books on the psychology of Influencing and Persuasion. This book is about getting someones attention, and using it.
Cialdini speaks about privileged moments, points in time where we have someones attention, and that person is also primed to actually follow our reasoning along with our message.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Grumpy</title>
      <link>/2017/01/25/grumpy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/25/grumpy.html</guid>
      <description>So Python is a beautiful language, which is also kind of slow. And the more cores you have, the worse it gets, because of the GIL in the most popular implementations. Other languages are much better at concurrency, one of them supposedly being Go. So Geeks at Google have been pondering the problem, and came up with a Python-to-Go compiler called Grumpy.
Read more about it in their blog . In rigged benchmarks it looks awesome, and under real world load it supposedly performs quite well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sending letters the CIA way</title>
      <link>/2017/01/25/sending-letters-the-cia-way.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/25/sending-letters-the-cia-way.html</guid>
      <description>Palaeofuture has an interesting article on sending letters, the CIA way.
 When you file a Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) request with a federal agency, they’ll often send you physical letters in the mail. When I got my first response letter from the CIA, I was a little surprised to see some old-fashioned, anti-spy tech on the back of the envelope. As you can see from the photos above and below, there’s no way to open the envelope without making it clear you’ve been messing with it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Topography of the Death Star</title>
      <link>/2017/01/25/the-topography-of-the-death-star.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/25/the-topography-of-the-death-star.html</guid>
      <description>The trench ain&amp;rsquo;t here:
It is elsewhere .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Be simple. Be boring. Be obvious.</title>
      <link>/2016/09/01/be-simple-be-boring-be-obvious.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/09/01/be-simple-be-boring-be-obvious.html</guid>
      <description>On Core.Infra day, I was invited to speak. This is my talk. There were many like it, but this was mine.
In operations, code is not your friend.   This is about what I did the two years I have not been around here. I first worked for Booking in 2006 as a MySQL consultant doing databasey things. I joined Booking as an employee later, in 2008. By then, I was working in Amsterdam, but living in Berlin, so I was flying around quite a bit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Dracula: The Modern Prometheus</title>
      <link>/2015/11/30/fertig-gelesen-dracula-the-modern-prometheus.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/11/30/fertig-gelesen-dracula-the-modern-prometheus.html</guid>
      <description>Ok. So I read earlier works from Rafael Chandler and while they have been grim und bloody they also have been light and funny. This one is different.
 Dracula Chandler does a weird and impossible thing - he takes Frankenstein and Dracula and mixes and genderbends the two tales to create something else, which is unique - strangely depressing and entertaining at the same time. Reading this was no fun at all, and yet I was entertained.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Go away, or I will replace you with a very small shell script</title>
      <link>/2015/03/27/go-away-or-i-will-replace-you.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/03/27/go-away-or-i-will-replace-you.html</guid>
      <description>This is the writeup for the english variant of the talk &amp;ldquo;Go away or I will replace you with a very small Shell script&amp;rdquo;. The original version of the talk was given in German at GUUG FFG 2015 in Stuttgart. A recorded version in german language has been made at Froscon in August 2015.
Go Away Or I Will Replace You With A Very Small Shell Script or There Is No Such Thing As A Devops Team</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Hexcommunicated</title>
      <link>/2015/02/14/fertig-gelesen-hexcommunicated.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/02/14/fertig-gelesen-hexcommunicated.html</guid>
      <description>Turns out people go insane by the way of identity loss if you provide remove too much of their own body in the process of giving them milspec cyber enhancements. Turns out that&amp;rsquo;s fixable by giving them a good backstory and themed identity. At least that is the premise that Chandler uses to excuse his merciless verbal sadism that brings us Nosferodents, Vampoules, Fearwolves, Frankenstitches and other Force Amplified Entities (FAE) of the Hermetic Extroy Division (Hex Divison).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Kady Cross &#34;The Girl with the ...&#34;</title>
      <link>/2014/08/11/fertig-gelesen-kady-cross-the-girl-with-the.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/08/11/fertig-gelesen-kady-cross-the-girl-with-the.html</guid>
      <description>League of Extraordinary Gentle(wo)men done right, meets X-Men, meets Wild-Wild West. Larger-than-life steampunk universe with cheesy supervillain opponents forces a Mary-Sueish rich and overly able brooding enlisch Peer to form a team of mutants fighting the cunning &amp;ldquo;Machinst&amp;rdquo;, saving the Empire.
&amp;ldquo;The Girl in the Steel Corset &amp;rdquo;, #1
Team formation, introduction of the mysterious supervillain, Storytelling Focus on Finley Jayne, the daugher of Dr. Jekyll/Mr. Hyde. Girl with Superpowers has to choose between the brooding rich guy with a dark secret and the smart and witty underworld boss.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL 5.6.7-RC: GTID vs. MyISAM</title>
      <link>/2012/10/02/mysql-5-6-7-rc-gtid-vs-myisam.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/02/mysql-5-6-7-rc-gtid-vs-myisam.html</guid>
      <description>So we tested the 5.6.7-RC. And ran into a strange problem:
Because of a test, a preexisting configuration with GTID enabled existed, and suddenly we did not have properly initialized grants in mysql.* created for a new installation. Turns out: GTID and non-transactional tables are no friends, and that is even documented .
 When using GTIDs, updates to tables using nontransactional storage engines such as MyISAM are not supported. This is because updates to such tables mixed with updates to tables that use a transactional storage engine such as InnoDB can result in multiple GTIDs being assigned to the same transaction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inhaltliche und kulturelle Steuerung von Foren</title>
      <link>/2008/07/23/inhaltliche-und-kulturelle-steuerung-von-foren.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2008/07/23/inhaltliche-und-kulturelle-steuerung-von-foren.html</guid>
      <description>(Update: 2020-06-19 Russian version contributed by Vladimir Htr)
Many years ago, late in 1999, I was involved in the creation of de.comp.lang.php, a USENET newsgroup. Since the group was new I began a personal experiment to influence the communication culture of an open USENET group .
That went on for four to five year, out of which I have been actively involved for two years, earning good Karma . But unfortunately http://www.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
