<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>elite dangerous on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/elite-dangerous.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in elite dangerous on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 May 2023 19:06:09 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/elite-dangerous/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Disable Saitek X.52 pro Clutch Mode</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/01/15/disable-saitek-x52-clutch-mode.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 18:21:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/01/15/disable-saitek-x52-clutch-mode.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is a memo to self, and describes how to disable the
X.52 clutch mode. I am flying with a Saitek/Logitech X.52 pro
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HOTAS&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;HOTAS&lt;/a&gt;

, and this stick has
a &amp;lsquo;clutch button&amp;rsquo; (labelled &amp;ldquo;i&amp;rdquo;) in the thumb position of the
throttle (image: clutch highlighed in red)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/01/x.52-clutch-0.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Clutch mode&amp;rdquo; for this button means that it is usable as a
modfier for the other buttons, when pressed together with a
second button. Alone, it does nothing. For me, that is useless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to disable function, go into Windows Settings, click
Devices, and search for &amp;ldquo;Set up USB Game Controllers&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/01/x.52-clutch-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, useful things in Windows can only be accessed via
search and not via menu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/01/x.52-clutch-2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Select the device, and then hit the device properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/01/x.52-clutch-3.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the MFD (Multi Function Display) of all places you can also
disable the clutch function (which, of course, has nothing to do
with the MFD at all).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because Windows is stupid and saves this configuration per
USB-port, you will have to redo it every time you plug the stick
into a different USB port.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Rockforth Fertilizer Incident</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/09/26/how-not-to-handle-an-ingame-incident.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 10:16:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/09/26/how-not-to-handle-an-ingame-incident.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So I have been playing this Internet Spaceships Game.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.frontierstore.net/games/elite-dangerous-cat.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;No, the other one&lt;/a&gt;

.
It also has NPC Backstory, and on
&lt;a href=&#34;https://community.elitedangerous.com/galnet/uid/5d7b5ecf830d4740111e16ba&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;13-Sep-3305&lt;/a&gt;

,
a multiplanetary food crisis was predicted, as a prep for the introduction
of a new tradeable good on
&lt;a href=&#34;https://community.elitedangerous.com/galnet/uid/5d81fa48ffcb4306ea212c82&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;18-Sep-3005&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distribution of the fertiliser has started at Marshall Dock in the
Riedquat system. We encourage traders to take advantage of our
introductory prices.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;that-went-wrong&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#that-went-wrong&#34;&gt;
	That went wrong.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So some people flew to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://eddb.io/station/market/999&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Marshall Dock&lt;/a&gt;


and looked at the prices for
&lt;a href=&#34;https://eddb.io/commodity/359&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Rockforth Fertilizer&lt;/a&gt;

. What they found was a
single station buying and selling the good at the same time, and buying it
at about 9000 CR higher than they sold it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here is what we have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fdev introduces a new tradeable good by the way of the backstory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They announce that, and introductory prices in Galnet in order to alert
players to this fact and to lure them to Riedquat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They misconfigure a station in Riedquat so that it sells and buys
the new good to Fdev&amp;rsquo;s disadvantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Players follow the trail and … trade. A lot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, that news made the rounds rather quickly, and soon a lot of
people were docking large freighters at Marshall and bought and sold
fertilizer as quickly as the game GUI would fill and empty their cargo bays.
That is easily several million CR every five seconds, and I know of some
people who ran this for 11 billion CR (11e09 CR).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;that-is-what-frontier-did-to-fix&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#that-is-what-frontier-did-to-fix&#34;&gt;
	That is what Frontier did to &amp;ldquo;fix&amp;rdquo;.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frontier Developments became aware of the misconfigured station only after
several hours, and the sale was available for the larger part of a day, from
around shortly before noon CEST to shortly before 7pm in the evening of the
same day, when they fixed the trade tables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not know if Fdev have in-game trade dashboards that alert them to
abnormally fast or high volume transaction volumes or cash flows. Or to
abnormally quickly growing player budgets. But the slowness of detection
lets me suspect that their in-game monitoring maybe has potential for
improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result of the situation, Fdev decided to correct CR volumes on a number
of accounts on the grounds of players &amp;lsquo;abusing game mechanics&amp;rsquo;. Well,
playing the game is literally this, so that&amp;rsquo;s weird, but they what they
decided to do is to book back the CR earned, and/or also delete any goods
purchased with the CR earned (mostly, ships).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/elite-0cr.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Alternative Account of a player, after the deduction. Went from 51m CR to
1.3b CR, then purchased an Anaconda. After the correction 0CR, in an
Anaconda, and with Elite Trade Rank plus Arx earned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;now-thats-not-how-any-of-this-works&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#now-thats-not-how-any-of-this-works&#34;&gt;
	Now, that&amp;rsquo;s not how any of this works.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of game mechanics, what happened is a trade. A trade does much more
than earn you money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trade does&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;earn you money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are in a wing, your wingmates also
&lt;a href=&#34;https://elite-dangerous.fandom.com/wiki/Trade_Dividend&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;earn a share of&lt;/a&gt;


the trade. Some people winged with their Alt, or friends.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trading in the game is also an activity that earns you
&lt;a href=&#34;https://elite-dangerous.fandom.com/wiki/Trader#Ranks&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;trade rank&lt;/a&gt;


(some people went from &amp;ldquo;Pennyless&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;Elite&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trading in the game is also an activity that earn you
&lt;a href=&#34;https://elite-dangerous.fandom.com/wiki/ARX&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Arx&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have a crew member, they will receive a variable share of
all money you earn in trade, so you will receive less CR in your
account than the trade is worth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fdev deciced to &amp;ldquo;fix&amp;rdquo; the situation by taking away money earned in the
Trade, but due to whatever reasons mis-calculated the values of the
earnings, in some cases by several hundred million CR. They also took away
goods purchased with this money (deleted ships, mostly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They did not revise any wing trade dividends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They did not revise any rank gained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They did not revise any Arx earned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They did not take crew member mechanics into account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT:&lt;/strong&gt; The miscalculation is probably because FDev based the money
deducted on trade value, not taking into account Crew Member mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;evaluation&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#evaluation&#34;&gt;
	Evaluation.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this entire thing reeks of unprofessional execution, &amp;ldquo;as if an intern ran
the entire thing from setting up the tradeable to misconfiguring the station
to mishandling the aftermath&amp;rdquo;. It hints at badly executed ad-hoc
non-process, and generally bad policy at handling in-game incidents -
whoever did this did not just set it up wrongly, but also did not understand
the consequences of the proceedings when trying to mop up the aftermath. And
the math was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elite (1984) was one of the first games that had savegames, and progression,
and since then the game has always been about &amp;lsquo;state&amp;rsquo; and moving forward.
The incident handling here basically mishandled game state at a large scale,
at every stage of the entire proceedings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Other Internet Spaceships Game has the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://eve.fandom.com/wiki/Council_of_Stellar_Management&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Council of Stellar Management&lt;/a&gt;

.
The story of its inception is
&lt;a href=&#34;https://v1.escapistmagazine.com/articles/view/video-games/editorials/op-ed/847-Jumpgate-EVE-s-Devs-and-the-Friends-They-Keep&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;rather famous&lt;/a&gt;


and a much larger incident than here, but the logic behind it is similar:
The company has been handling an in-game incident badly, and a structure
needed to be put into place that can evaluate, judge and define process
properly to handle situations like these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E:D has no such structure, and it seems that this might need to be addressed
somehow, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT:&lt;/strong&gt; Chris_W noted that there is also crew member mechanics. This post
has been amended to reflect this.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Elite: Dangerous Braindumping</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/02/21/some-elite-dangerous-braindumping.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2019 09:10:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/02/21/some-elite-dangerous-braindumping.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;some-elite-dangerous-braindumping&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#some-elite-dangerous-braindumping&#34;&gt;
	Some Elite: Dangerous Braindumping
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of my previous posts, some people have been talking to me about the game, and I have been spamming a lot of in- and out-of game content on them.
Then I realized: &amp;ldquo;Why should you have it better?&amp;rdquo; and decided to spam things here as well, for balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;install-a-eddn-client&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#install-a-eddn-client&#34;&gt;
	Install a EDDN client
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E:D is a sandbox game, which over time acquired a lot of content and backstory, and with them in-game activities that are better planned out of the game.
For this, data collection happened originally through on-screen OCR, until Frontier embraced this play-style and provided an API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This API is being harvested by a number of clients, with all upload it into the Elite: Dangerous Data Network &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/EDSM-NET/EDDN&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;EDDN&lt;/a&gt;

 and then feed it to a number of backend sites for planning, optimizing and minmaxing.
I am using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Marginal/EDMarketConnector/wiki&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;EDMC&lt;/a&gt;

 client and fed it with all necessary API keys and accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure the EDDN client is on before you launch the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;making-use-of-the-eddn-client-data&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#making-use-of-the-eddn-client-data&#34;&gt;
	Making use of the EDDN client data
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Backends are the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.edsm.net&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Elite: Dangerous Star Map&lt;/a&gt;

 which also hands out a number of Achievements, if you are into this kind of thing.
The two most important backends using EDSM data are &lt;a href=&#34;https://eddb.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;EDDB&lt;/a&gt;

 for finding stations, suppliers and planets, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://inara.cz/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;INARA&lt;/a&gt;

, which does the same things and also helps you with engineering planning and unlocking Guardian technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guardian tech is necessary if you want a guardian frame shift drive extender, which adds range on top of engineering, so many explorer ship builds have it.
It also has a lot of scanner and weapon tech, which is essential for Thargoid combat.
You actually hardly have a chance against Thargoids without Guardian tech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;making-money-fast&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#making-money-fast&#34;&gt;
	Making Money Fast
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously, you could make a lot of money with passenger transport.
Basically, after your grind your way to a Cobra MK III, add a number of passenger cabins and do one of two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fly to Robigo: &amp;ldquo;Robigo Mines&amp;rdquo; or Ceos: &amp;ldquo;Babbage&amp;rdquo; and take on passengers for Sothis: &amp;ldquo;Sirius Atmospherics&amp;rdquo;, fly them to the target, come to a full stop &amp;lt;2km from the target and scan the target until you get a confirmation.
Then dump the passengers back at the port of origin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this you would need Biz, First and Luxury cabins (for the Cobra: Biz), and grind your way up to Reputation with all factions.
At Robigo Mines you have a chance to pick up wanted persons, too, and these usually pay more.
Robigo is an Outpost, so Landing Pads are Small and Medium, and it never scans, so transporting outlaws is safe in Solo and Private.
Griefers with Manifest Scanners and Kill Warrant Scanners wait in open at Robigo, so don&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ceos is much closer to Sothis, and is HighSec, so do not go there with anything illegal.
Babbage will scan you at least once for every approach.
You can reach Sothis with a single jump, tho, so you need to do the math if faster RTT or higher CR/trip work for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to make CR/h with passenger cabins is to fit lots of cheap economy cabins, and then search for stations in trouble (on fire, Thargoid attack or otherwise troubled), fly there and take on bulk passengers for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cNw2QXX4gYA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;rescue trips&lt;/a&gt;

 out of the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet another way to make high CR/h is Core Mining, but this requires a higher up front invest.
Check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nIfZu1clbRg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ObsidianAnt on Youtube&lt;/a&gt;

 for a Core Mining build and tutorial, and aim for Void Opals or Blood Diamonds.
Also prepared for NPC Pirate combat, because they will come after you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;build-with-coriolisio&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#build-with-coriolisio&#34;&gt;
	Build with Coriolis.io
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For every ship, plan the base price in CR again for purchase and upgrades, so the actual ship you want to fly is usually base price times two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://coriolis.io&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Coriolis&lt;/a&gt;

 planner for the build you want and get a more precise cost estimate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then use &lt;a href=&#34;https://eddb.io/stations&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;EDDB&lt;/a&gt;

 to find the stations that sell you the parts you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being on good terms reputation wise with the Federation is nice (but you will need to pledge yourself to the Fed and have rank with them for a Sol permit, which gives you access to Jameson Memorial, which has all buyable stuff in the game).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being on good terms with Sirius is also useful, because you get the Sirius permit and then gives you access to other interesting stations. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hrMaBiMgP94&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this tutorial&lt;/a&gt;

 for details&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;controls&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#controls&#34;&gt;
	Controls
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a Hotas or want to manage your controls better, search for .binds file in your game install or the application data in your User Home in Windows.
The Binds-File can be uploaded to &lt;a href=&#34;https://edrefcard.info/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;EDRefcard&lt;/a&gt;

, which will print you one or two pages of nice reference cards.
Twice as nice for Hotas users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, &lt;a href=&#34;http://arkku.com/elite/hud_editor/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;HUD Editor&lt;/a&gt;

 for non-amber ship HUDs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;engineering&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#engineering&#34;&gt;
	Engineering
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You get more Jump Range with Engineering, and one of the first engineers to unlock is Felicity Farseer, so Frontier understands that need very well.
For &lt;a href=&#34;https://elite-dangerous.fandom.com/wiki/Felicity_Farseer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Felicity&lt;/a&gt;

, you need Meta Alloy, which you can buy at the Maia system in the Pleiades, at Darnielle&amp;rsquo;s Progress or find elsewhere in the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://eddb.io/commodity/114&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Meta Alloy&lt;/a&gt;

, &lt;a href=&#34;https://elite-dangerous.fandom.com/wiki/Meta-Alloys&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Meta Alloy&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have unlocked Felicity, you will need engineering materials for FSD Range optimization or whatever else you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easy way to get that is at &lt;a href=&#34;https://canonn.science/codex/davs-hope/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dav&amp;rsquo;s Hope&lt;/a&gt;

.
Do the round with a SRV as shown in &lt;a href=&#34;https://forums.frontier.co.uk/showthread.php/368279-UPDATED-List-of-Materials-at-DAV-S-Hope%28Pictorial%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;

 and scoop everything.
Then find yourself a Materials Trader close to you using inara.cz&amp;rsquo;s search function and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://inara.cz/cmdr-craftinglists-components/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;engineering planner&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may also want a wake scanner and position yourself outside the no-fire zone of a busy orbital and then wake-scan every Low and High Wake you can find.
This will give you a lot of encoded materials which are required in FSD engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing this gets you around the grind lock with the least amount of work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Mp7l0bSnMp_G7xWUm75M-XuihDfTdi27rm-vB9K8AX0/edit#gid=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;List of Engineering Mats and how to get them&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1yo1iHP9KUXpoBaIzJsRsDxfAcQa7cBq0YUIFy3m2NII/edit#gid=130934395&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Other Materials List&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;discovery-money&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#discovery-money&#34;&gt;
	Discovery Money
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have a ship with decent jump range, you may want to do some Exploration.
In fact, you can do a lot of that on the fly while doing other things.
Whenever you jump long distance runs, after entering the system, during FSD cooldown and fuel scooping, run the Discovery Scanner.
I have the screen usually in Analysis Mode (&amp;rsquo;m&amp;rsquo;, blue lines in HUD) and have the Discovery Scanner bound to MB1 in a fire group.
When the scan is finished, it has a very characteristic sound and after that you can jump on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This style of flying is called &amp;lsquo;Honking&amp;rsquo;.
The idea is to sync Honk times, FSD cool down times and fuel scooping times so that everything is ready at the same time, just when you get around the drop-in star to continue to jump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new system with earthlikes or terraformables can bring in around 0.3-3 MCR when scanned (you hand in the data at any station at Universal Cartographics, and you need to be more than 20ly from the system for UC to buy the data).
High Metal Content and Metal Worlds also bring a lot of money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Systems you visited before and where you already sold the data to UC hardly bring any money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can fit a Full System Scanner (FSS).
It allows you to map a system in a more detailed way.
After honking, you can enter FSS mode with (&amp;rsquo;) or where ever you have mapped it, and then scan for signal sources, bodies or other things.
There is a guide at &lt;a href=&#34;https://forums.frontier.co.uk/showthread.php/464149-The-FSS-A-pictoral-guide&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the forum&lt;/a&gt;

 that explains FSS&amp;rsquo;ing better than I can do here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may also want to fit a Detailed Surface Scanner (DSS).
When you fly close to a planet and come to an almost full stop in supercruise, you can activate the DSS and get into a new screen for the DSS minigame.
You fire probes at the planet, which map a part of the surface.
There is an efficiency target depending on the size of the body scanned, and if you manage to get 90% mapped with fewer probes than the efficiency target, you get a bonus.
See &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/EliteDangerous/comments/a8roi9/efficient_planetary_mapping_a_visual_guide_to_dss/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt;

 for help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DSS mapping will also reveal and catalogize all Points of Interest on a body, so fumaroles, alien crash sites and the likes will show up with names right on the map.
It&amp;rsquo;s useful and makes money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Honking is fast, FSSing and DSSing a system takes more time.
DSSing also takes travel time, because it can be done only up close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two names on each body:
Discovery and Mapping.
DS, FSS and DSS previously unvisited bodies etches your names onto the newly discovered body forever and for all other commanders to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;explorer-ships-and-builds&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#explorer-ships-and-builds&#34;&gt;
	Explorer Ships and Builds
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cheapest useful explorer is the Diamondback Explorer.
It is small, but has an extreme jump range and can be engineered to truly awesome range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Mid Size department, there is the Asp Explorer, which especially with Engineering can to truly impressive things and also has a decent amount of internal space, if you care to do more than just data collection.
It is a deep space capable ship, which can carry a large scoop, 2x AFMU, 2x SRV, a refinery, a DSS and a small cargo rack and still make distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need more space, go Python, but be prepared to engineer FSD and Thrusters for range and manoeuvrability.
Without that, it flies more like a brick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Anaconda required a large pad, so it can not land at Outposts.
It also is unflyable in Supercruise without serious engineering, but there are common Explorer build blueprints for it that take it over 80ly jump range.
It is also used a lot as a tanker by the Fuel Rats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more at &lt;a href=&#34;https://edastro.com/exploration&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ED Astro&lt;/a&gt;

.
Basically, an explorer build is everything D-rated except the FSD, which is A rated.
Then engineer the FSD for range and everything else for weight.
No weapons, large fuel scoop, AFMU, SRV, DSS, optionally a refinery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also learn about [synth](&lt;a href=&#34;https://elite-dangerous.fandom.com/wiki/Synthesis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://elite-dangerous.fandom.com/wiki/Synthesis&lt;/a&gt;

 &lt;a href=&#34;https://inara.cz/galaxy-synthesis/%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://inara.cz/galaxy-synthesis/)&lt;/a&gt;

, this is where you get supplies when there are no stations.&lt;br&gt;
Mats are gathered using SRV or mining equipment, so read up on that, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note how there is a FSD injection materials synth.
FSD injection increases your jump range once for each injection, hence it is also called &amp;ldquo;Jumponium&amp;rdquo; (and that makes it googleable).
When crossing through the starless depths, the rifts between the arms of the galaxy,  star density goes down and you may well find yourself in a situation where you need jumponium even in an engineered ship.
Rehearse using this and the Galaxy Map properly together before you go into the Rifts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;cooperative-player-groups&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#cooperative-player-groups&#34;&gt;
	Cooperative Player Groups
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ANWB of the Elite Dangerous Universe are the Fuel Rats. Call them at &lt;a href=&#34;https://fuelr.at&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;their site&lt;/a&gt;

.
This will drop you into WebIRC on their channel, and they will guide you through a well planned and orchestrated set of motions that will allow them to shoot you with Fuel Limpets.
Each Fuel Limpet will load 1t of FSD drive fuel into your ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fuel Rats are strictly non-combatant, and they do not charge you anything.
You do not need to be a member of anything for their help.
Basically, you provide them a mission that is more interesting than procedurally generated content.
They are the coolest faction in the game, and they have their own planet.
Their home world, Fuelum, orbits a scoopable star, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fuel Rat Wiki at &lt;a href=&#34;https://confluence.fuelrats.com/display/FRKB/How&amp;#43;to&amp;#43;Join&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;their sie&lt;/a&gt;

 (all of the Wiki, not just that page) contains a lot of useful information about the in-game, the game implementation and instancing system and how to org and run a rescue and relief organisation efficiently.
Even if you are not playing, it is a trove useful of information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.polygon.com/2017/12/25/16817700/elite-dangerous-fuel-rats-rescue-cmdr-persera&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this writeup&lt;/a&gt;

 for news about the Fuel Rats and their exploits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also check out and auth with &lt;a href=&#34;https://journal.fuelrats.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;their journal client&lt;/a&gt;

 before you run of of fuel.
In time, when you find yourself stranded in the black, it will save you precious time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other helpful people are the Hull Seals, which do for Repairs what the Fuel Rats do for fuel, and there is a lot of overlap between the players in both orgs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Iron Wing is a group of combat pilots that take it on them to protect returning explorers in their combat-weak, long-range optimized builds when they return to the bubble so that they can safely upload their data at a destination of their choice.
They help against griefers and NPC pirates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-neutron-route&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#the-neutron-route&#34;&gt;
	The Neutron Route
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neutron stars are the other thing that makes you jump far. Doing this will damage the ship each time you do it, so 1. AFMU (large) to repair the ship, and 2. AFMU (small) to repair the AFMU #1.
Use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.spansh.co.uk/plotter&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Neutron Router&lt;/a&gt;

 to plan the trip.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4vnEoFOSHIY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This video&lt;/a&gt;

 explains the Neutron Route.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

