<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>review on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/review.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in review on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 09:37:28 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/review/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: AI Superpowers</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-ai-superpowers.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 16:19:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-ai-superpowers.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This 2018 book in some aspects is already outdated: Silicon Valley Techbro Kai-Fu Lee describes what AI is and what he thinks it will do to our future, the nature of work and the job market.
But since then, the worlds view on what AI can and cannot do, what the problems to solve really are and a lot of other things have changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/AI-Superpowers-Silicon-Valley-English-ebook/dp/B0795DNWCF&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/ai-superpowers.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/AI-Superpowers-Silicon-Valley-English-ebook/dp/B0795DNWCF&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;AI Superpowers:China, Silicon Valley, and the New World Order&lt;/a&gt;

, Kai-Fu Lee&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kai-Fu Lee is a Taiwanese born, American computer scientist, and worked at Apple, SGI, Microsoft and Google before becoming a venture capitalist in China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He coined the adage &amp;ldquo;If data is the new oil, then China is the new Saudi Arabia&amp;rdquo; and in the books proposes that China has several advantages over the US in an arms race over artificial intelligence:
Generally training deep learning models seems to be better suited to the Chinese approach of brute forcing a solution than to deep engineering;
China has few data protection regulations getting in the way of data collection;
Chinese startup culture is even more aggressive than the US one; and
the chinese government funds and steers the startup industry in China into the AI of AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lee believes that a number of jobs will be modified or eliminated by a potential AI revolution, including a number of white collar (office) jobs.
The examples he gives are jobs that consist mostly of - in his opinion - simple pattern recognition, such as rough translator, bank loan officer or customer care worker.
Similarly, the blue collar (worker) jobs at risk are truck driver, cashier or clothing factory worker.
In a way, three years later, his estimates look overly optimistic:
Self-driving cars are further away than they looked three years ago, and automated customer care with natural language recognition quickly transformed into the voice-mail hell as ten or twenty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is true is that AI can support human workers a lot in taking the boring parts of these jobs away, helping to provide rough estimates and marking clear cases as such.
Still, AI in 2021 seems to be successful where it augments human workers instead of completely replacing them.
In general, Lee&amp;rsquo;s view of the world is very mechanistic, and way too optimistic in what AI can actually completely solve without having a complete model of the world it acts in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Important input and still a good overview, but overtaken quickly by the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Old Man&#39;s War</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-old-mans-war.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 13:53:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-old-mans-war.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Old-Mans-English-John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B000SEIK2S&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Old Man&amp;rsquo;s War&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; is the first &amp;ldquo;large&amp;rdquo; works by John Scalzi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Old-Mans-English-John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B000SEIK2S&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/oldmanswar.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Old-Mans-English-John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B000SEIK2S&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Old Man&amp;rsquo;s War&lt;/a&gt;

, John Scalzi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plot premise is weird, but simple: Humanity has taken to the stars, but with private enterprise.
Basically all advanced space technology is controlled by the Colonial Union.
Life on earth on the other hand goes on almost as before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Perry enlists to serve in the Colonial Defense Force at the age of 75, to protect humanity, but mostly to have the CU fight the effects of him aging with some unspecified Scifi tech.
He leaves earth and during his induction to the CDF learns that he will be indeed rejuvenated, by transferring his consciousness into a new, young, genetically engineered body tailored for planetary combat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perry&amp;rsquo;s first tour of duty sees battles on a number of CU planets and fights against various interstellar races.
He soon learns that the CU is not actually involved much in galactic politics and has only limited knowledge about the background and motivation of the various space-faring intelligences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fight against the man-eating Rraey leaves him wounded and left for dead on the contested planet Coral.
He is found by a member of the Ghost Brigades,  Jane Sagan, that he thinks looks like a younger version of his deceased wife Kathy, and befriends her.
He learns that Ghost Brigades are synthetic humans created from the DNA scans of CDF volunteers that died before they could join the CDF, but without the memory and experience of their human predecessors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While technically Mil SciFi, and therefore a genre I despise, Scalzi manages to keep the focus the story on the characters and their interactions instead of troop movements and space battles.
He is playing with the themes of generic engineering, encounters with alien races and the discovery of their motivation, and with building a connection to an image of a loved one, but without the memory and the shared experiences.
An engaging book with characters I can relate to, and a story well told.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Old-Mans-English-John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B000SEIK2S&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Old Man&amp;rsquo;s War&lt;/a&gt;

 is continued in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Ghost-Brigades-Mans-Book-English-ebook/dp/B001QS9TSE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Ghost Brigades&lt;/a&gt;

 and in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B000YJ85BI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Last Colony&lt;/a&gt;

, finishing the John Perry&amp;rsquo;s viewpoint books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story of &amp;ldquo;The Last Colony&amp;rdquo; is being retold in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B002ENBLM2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zoe&amp;rsquo;s Tale&lt;/a&gt;

 from another character&amp;rsquo;s viewpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Human-Division-Mans-Book-English-ebook/dp/B00C2RSA9C&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Human Division&lt;/a&gt;

 then continues the original storyline, from another characters point of view, dealing with the aftermath of the revelation of the CU&amp;rsquo;s scheming with earth politics. Humanity finally joins the emerging galactic society and must find a place in one of the various alliances that the different intelligent species begin to form. The resulting diplomatic complications are further told in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B00SEPVPAW&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The End of All Things&lt;/a&gt;

 in a series of Novellas from different character viewpoints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all a series very worthwhile reading, exactly sufficient for one vacation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: These Savage Shores</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-these-savage-shores.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 15:12:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-these-savage-shores.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/therightram&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ram V&lt;/a&gt;

 is a writer, sometimes for comics.
Together with artist Sumit Kumar he wrote a simple story: English Vampires vs. Indian Rakshasa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/These-Savage-Shores-English-Ram-ebook/dp/B07YYNFP38&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/savage.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/These-Savage-Shores-English-Ram-ebook/dp/B07YYNFP38&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;These Savage Shores&lt;/a&gt;

, Ram V &amp;amp; Sumit Kumar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1760&amp;rsquo;ies.
An english vampire puts his peers at risk by not having his desires unter control, and is exiled to Calicut, India.
He soon finds out that even older and fiercer beings rule the night: Rakshasa, the Vampire equivalent of Indian Myth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bishan, a Raskshasa, kills the vampire, drawing the english vampires out for revenge.
Before the background of a colonization war in India, Bishan and the vampire master Jurre Granno clash, first in India, then in England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fantastic illustrations, and a complex story well told, with rich metaphors, showing a clash of cultures and the infighting in pre-colonization India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a comic, the kindle edition does not read well on a Kindle, but works fine on Kindle for iPad or similar devices.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: This Is How You Lose The Time War</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 16:01:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Max Gladstone and Amal El-Mohtar co-authored &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/This-How-Lose-Time-English-ebook/dp/B07RTYNHRM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This Is How You Lose The Time-War&lt;/a&gt;

, not exactly a Science Fiction novel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/This-How-Lose-Time-English-ebook/dp/B07RTYNHRM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/time-war.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/This-How-Lose-Time-English-ebook/dp/B07RTYNHRM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This Is How You Lose The Time War&lt;/a&gt;

, Amal El-Mohtar and Max Gladstone&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red and Blue are representatives, spies and saboteurs of two nearly all-powerful, warring factions.
They travel through time to manipulate events at critical points in history in favor of their respective factions.
They are leaving each other messages, they taunt each other, and gradually earn mutual respect.
Eventually they grow close to each other, and love develops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red&amp;rsquo;s commanding officer learns of the interaction and forces Red to leave a message to Blue that kills her.
Red later fixes that &amp;ldquo;problem&amp;rdquo; by traveling into Blue&amp;rsquo;s childhood to give her immunity to the toxic message, and both escape the war by making off to elsewhere in time and space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an epistolary novel, written in the form of the letters Red and Blue exchange.
We only learn very gradually about the characters, their capabilities and their background, and it becomes clear that what we read is not actually the account of two humans, but rather godlike entities or avatars of forces of nature.
Red and Blue over time grow close, and solve an initially unbridgeable conflict between the cultures or forces they represent at a very personal level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a hard read, and if you were looking for an actual Science Fiction story, this isn&amp;rsquo;t one.
Telling a story in the form of letters and having characters that are only remotely human at best is not a good vehicle to create tension, of paint a clear picture of what goes on.
At multiple points the book reads more like some form of poetry as opposed a novel or regular prose.
The storytelling ultimately manages to pull off a somewhat satisfactory ending, though, even if it is visible from almost the very start of the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being so different and not fucking things up of course won the book a number of awards in 2019 and 2020, so there is that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Typeset in the Future</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-typeset-in-the-future.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 13:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-typeset-in-the-future.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dave Addey ran a Tumblr once, titled &amp;ldquo;Typeset in the Future&amp;rdquo;, in which he dissected the typography of Science Fiction films.
This has been turned into the eponymous book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Typeset-Future-Typography-Science-Fiction-ebook/dp/B07G7SGRZ2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/typeset.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Typeset-Future-Typography-Science-Fiction-ebook/dp/B07G7SGRZ2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Typeset in the Future&lt;/a&gt;

, Dave Addey&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2013, Addey nerded out over the fonts in a Science Fiction movie and discovered it was an Eurostile variant (&amp;ldquo;Eurostile Extended Bold&amp;rdquo;).
He started a Tumblr about this, and in great detail went through a number of movies, and about every sign, letter and font used in there.
The Tumblr became quite successful, and he turned the most important posts into a book, adding a lot of images with examples and a number of interviews and essays to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/typeset2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ebook is a joy to read on anything but a Kindle - I did on a 10&amp;quot; iPad, and it worked quite well.
The dead tree edition would make an excellent conversation piece.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: UNIX: A History and a Memoir</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-unix-a-history-and-a-memoir.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 15:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-unix-a-history-and-a-memoir.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The memoir of Brian Kernighan, and the story of how UNIX came to be and what working at Bell Labs was like at that time:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/UNIX-History-English-Brian-Kernighan-ebook/dp/B07ZQHX3R1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UNIX: A History and a Memoir&lt;/a&gt;

 is required reading for anyone who wants to know where Unix concepts came from and what ideas were behind its inception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/UNIX-History-English-Brian-Kernighan-ebook/dp/B07ZQHX3R1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/unix.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/UNIX-History-English-Brian-Kernighan-ebook/dp/B07ZQHX3R1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UNIX: A History and a Memoir&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;quot;, Brian Kernighan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kernighan takes us through the history and the setting of Bell Labs, why it existed and what it did.
He explains the hardware of the time, in terms of size, power and capabilities, and why Bell did get involved into writing an Operating System, and the failure of Multics.
Unix inception and its co-evolution with the C language was a kind of response to the Multics project, at the same time pioneering novel ideas and taking tested salvageable concepts from Multics, making something new and much more useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While he roughly follows the timeline of Unix releases, Kernighan takes short detours, including mini-biographies of his colleagues and the influence they had on the design of the system and the ideas embodied in it.
He finishes with the commercialization of Unix, Unix descendants - BSD, Minix, Linux and Plan 9, and with the closure of Bell Labs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you work with Linux, the C language or any Unix tools, you should read this book to understand where these things came from and what formed this environment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: 88 Names</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-88-names.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 14:18:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-88-names.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It began with a tweet by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/s_bergmann/status/1392518815897030661&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sebastian Bergmann&lt;/a&gt;

, which made me buy &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B07T6938D1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;88 names&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; by Matt Ruff.
The book is a tour of massive multiplayer online role playing games for people who do not play, and also a discussion of identity on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Chu has a small sherpa company, an outfit that helps causal players who have the coin to experience hard content in MMORPGs in an easy and successful way without investing too much time into the game.
Chu is coming out of a relationship with a borderline gamer, Darla, and is being asked by an obviously powerful and demanding anonymous client to be shown several well known MMOs to better understand their genres.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chu is trying to uncover the identity of his client, and comes to believe that he is the North Korean dictator Kim Jong Un.
In the course of his research he learns the real identities of his employees, none of which are what he thought they were, and the real identity of Darla, who is way further past the borderline that he originally assumed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a fun read for me, because it relatively accurately portrays MMOs and online games.
At the same time Ruff&amp;rsquo;s writing very causally avoids Gamer Dudebro stereotypes and shows that people playing video games are way more diverse than their cliche.
If you ever have had your Internet spaceship refueled by a 60+ year old english granny and ex-schoolteacher you will understand exactly what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B07T6938D1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;88 Names&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Matt Ruff&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: A Kim Jong-Il Production</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-a-kim-jong-il-production.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 14:52:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-a-kim-jong-il-production.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Paul Fischer writes &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B00OMH54L2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;A Kim Jong-Il Production&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, a documentary the 1978 abduction of the famous South Korean actress Madam Choi, and her ex-husband, the filmmaker Shin Sang-Ok.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before becoming the leader of North Korea, Kim Jong-Il headed the Ministry for Propaganda.
Dissatisfied with the talent available, he had the famous actress Choi Eun-Hee kidnammed.
When her ex-husband started to investigate, he had him kidnapped in Hong Kong and transported to North Korea by ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together, they made &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abduction_of_Shin_Sang-ok_and_Choi_Eun-hee#Films&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;seven films&lt;/a&gt;

 for Kim Jong-Il, gaining his trust.
During a research trip in Vienna they fled to the US embassy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book uses &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abduction_of_Shin_Sang-ok_and_Choi_Eun-hee&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this true story&lt;/a&gt;

 to shed a light on life in North Korea, and to explain how it became the hermetically sealed country it is today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seventh film of Choi and Shin, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eCKSR0JArUQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pulgasari&lt;/a&gt;

, can be found on Youtube with english subtitles. It is a Godzilla-like monster tale, in which a rice toy of a blacksmiths daugther comes to life and turns into a giant metal-eating monster fighting for the rights of poor farmers in feudal Korea. When the monster eventually turns aganst the farmers, the blacksmiths daugther sacrifices herself killing the monster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goes well with &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-88-names.html&#34;&gt;88 Names&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Mara und der Feuerbringer</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-mara-und-der-feuerbringer.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 12:51:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-mara-und-der-feuerbringer.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tommmy Krappweis ist nicht nur der Schöpfer von &amp;ldquo;Bernd, das Brot&amp;rdquo;, sondern auch ein Musiker, Stuntman, Filmemacher und Autor diverser Bücher.
In der Trilogie um &amp;ldquo;Mara und der Feuerbringer&amp;rdquo; nimmt er uns mit in die Geschichten um die 14-jährige Münchnerin Mara Lorbeer in der Welt der nordischen Sagen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B07RHCGD95&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/08/mara1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B07RHCGD95&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mara und der Feuerbringer&lt;/a&gt;

, Band 1&amp;quot;, Tommy Krappweis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mara Lorbeer ist 14, Scheidungskind und lebt bei ihrer esoterisch angehauchten Mutter in München.
Während der Rückreise von einem Baum-Umwarmungs-Seminar, auf das sie ihre Mutter mitgeschleppt hat, wird sie von einem sprechenden Zweig angesprochen, der ihr mitteilt, daß sie eine germanische Seherin ist, die den Weltuntergang, Ragnarök, verhindern muß.
Im Fortgang der Geschichte freundet sich Mara mit verschiedenen Personen an: dem Professor für germanische Mythologie Reinhold Weissinger, seiner Ex-Frau Stefanie Warnatzsch-Abra, SIegfried dem Drachentöter, dem nordischen Gott.
Zusammen treten sie gegen Loge, den Feuerbringer, den mysteriösen Dr. Thurisaz, und den Drachen Nidhöggr.
Über drei Bände entfaltet sich um Mara der Kampf der Guten gegen die Bösen im Reich der nordischen Mythologie, während sich im Weltlichen die Beziehung von Mara zu ihrer Mutter klärt und Mara zugleich lernt, sich selbst besser zu definieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mara und der Feuerbringer&amp;rdquo; ist nicht nur eine Tour durch die nordische Mythologie und wie sie sich in unserer heutigen Welt wiederspiegelt, sondern auch eine Comig-of-Age Geschichte, bunt und leicht anarchisch erzählt, wie man es von Tommy Krappweis erwarten kann.
Nicht nur für Jugendliche eine wunderbare Erzählung.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B07RHCGD95&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mara und der Feuerbringer&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Tommy Krappweis, EUR 9.99 pro Band.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Merchant Princes Omnibus</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/07/28/fertig-gelesen-the-merchant-princes-omnibus.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jul 2021 09:48:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/07/28/fertig-gelesen-the-merchant-princes-omnibus.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Charles Stross &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/kindle/series/B00WKNMLD4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Merchant Princes&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; series of six books is another &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sliders&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sliders&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; type of story, with the usual Stross-like twist.
The story follows Miriam Beckstein, a woman who thinks she is a tech journalist.
Miriam falls off a chair while looking at a strange pattern, and finds herself in a medival parallel earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/kindle/series/B00WKNMLD4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/07/merchant-princes.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/kindle/series/B00WKNMLD4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Merchant Princes Omnibus&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;quot;, Charles Stross&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the course of the story, Miriam learns that she is actually from this parallel earth, and really is the Countess Helge Thorold-Hjorth in the kingdom of Gruinmarkt, which sits in the place of her world lines Boston.
Her relatives and the other members of the six clans have the unique ability of walking between worlds, which they apparently abuse to work as uncatchable drug and money couriers in our world.
World walking involves looking at a specific pattern, which seems to activate a heritable genetic trait in their brains that make them shift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the course of the story we learn a lot about this ability:
The pattern seems to control the linked universes, the ability to walk between worlds seems to be bioengineered into the clans, but the how, who and when are unknown.
There seem to be more parallel worlds, which open up as the story unfolds, and also the mythical &amp;ldquo;lost clan&amp;rdquo; is found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things are becoming really complicated as the world of the lost clan, &amp;ldquo;New Britain&amp;rdquo;&amp;quot;, is discovered.
Miriam flees to this world, which is technologically somewhere in the 1920, and fuels a communist, anti-monarchist revolution by importing gold and ideas into this world.
Meanwhile, the clans activities on our world are becoming known to the US government, which desperately wants to get hold of worldwalkers to understand and duplicate their abilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fourth world is being discovered, in which a technologically advanced humanity died out for unknown reasons, and which currently is in the grips of an ice-age.
And in a bit of foreshadowing, a fifth world is being discovered, in which earth is gone, and something else is found instead that resembles a black hole surrounded by unidentified energetic flares.
While the clan struggles with an infight between the conservative and progressive factions, the US government finds a way to world-walk into Gruinmarkt and systematically nukes this world to secure access to the untapped oil reserves in this parallel universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story is continued in another trilogy, &amp;ldquo;Empire Games&amp;rdquo;, which is set 17 years later.
The conflicts started in the original series are being played out further, and the mysterious black hole from the fifth world is being activated by accident.
The final part of this trilogy will be published this year, End of September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Merchant Princes&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Empire Games&amp;rdquo; writing and storytelling is everything you would expect from Stross, so time and money well spent.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Outland</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/07/23/fertig-gelesen-outland.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jul 2021 09:00:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/07/23/fertig-gelesen-outland.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Outland-Dennis-Taylor-ebook/dp/B07TP6TKP1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Outland&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; is the first book by Dennis E. Taylor, preceding the Bobiverse and also &amp;ldquo;The Singularity Trap&amp;rdquo;.
It is a &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sliders&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sliders&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; storyline, much like &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2016/02/28/fertig-gelesen-the-long-earth.html&#34;&gt;Pratchett&amp;rsquo;s and Baxter&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Long Earth&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;

, in which our heroes discover a parallel dimension with a seemingly uninhabited earth, and then need to colonize it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Outland-Dennis-Taylor-ebook/dp/B07TP6TKP1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/07/outland.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Outland-Dennis-Taylor-ebook/dp/B07TP6TKP1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Outland&lt;/a&gt;

, Dennis E. Taylor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dennis E. Taylor is a computer programmer writing Scifi, and had problems finding a publishher for his debut novel, &amp;ldquo;Outland&amp;rdquo;, in 2015, so he self-published.
The story was intended as the introduction to a series of books, &amp;ldquo;World Lines&amp;rdquo;.
The original novel was withdrawn in 2018, extensively reworked, and re-publshed in 2019 as a standalone book, which is the version linked in this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story follows an ensemble cast of students that through a failed physics experiment manage to open a dimensional portal into a parallel earth, which differs from this earth mostly in that it is seemingly uninhabited.
While the students come up with schemes to get rich quick by mining gold in the parallel earth and somehow selling it locally, a global catastrophe strikes:
The Yellowstone Supervolcano activates, covering most of the United States in ashfall and changing climate globally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our students now use the portal to evacuate a number of people to start a colony in the wilderness of their parallel earth.
But bootstrapping human civilization from basically nothing with contemporary humans seems to be harder and more dangerous than anybody thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original book showcased early Dennis E. Taylor, but unpolished. The nerd humor and the the writing style were already somewhat there, but the characters were flat and a lot of things were still raw.
The rewrite fixes this, and also makes the book more standalone, while still letting the door open to optional sequels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Outland-Dennis-Taylor-ebook/dp/B07TP6TKP1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Outland&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; by Dennis E. Taylor, EUR 4.39, also on Kinde unlimited.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Montecrypto</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/06/05/fertig-gelesen-montecrypto.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 20:54:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/06/05/fertig-gelesen-montecrypto.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Wir hatten hier in &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/#review&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;den Reviews&lt;/a&gt;

 schon eine ganze Menge Tom Hillenbrand: &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2014/08/11/fertig-gelesen-drachenvater.html&#34;&gt;Drachenväter&lt;/a&gt;

, &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2014/08/17/fertig-gelesen-drohnenland.html&#34;&gt;Drohnenland&lt;/a&gt;

, und &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2015/11/29/fertig-gelesen-die-drohnen-des-monsieur-leclerq.html&#34;&gt;Die Drohnen des Monsieur Leclerq&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das aktuelle Buch von Tom Hillenbrand ist &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/dp/3462001574&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Montecrypto&lt;/a&gt;

, das sich mit dem Hype um Cryptocurrencies beschäftigt und eine Art &amp;ldquo;Der Graf von Monte Cristo&amp;rdquo;-Geschichte erzählt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/dp/3462001574&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/06/montecrypto.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/dp/3462001574&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Montecrypto&lt;/a&gt;

, von Tom Hillenbrand&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gregory Hollister, ein reicher Investor, ist verstorben. Angeblich hat er noch eine große Menge Geld, und dieses ist in Bitcoin angelegt und irgendwo versteckt. Wo genau, ist unklar, und so bekommt der Finanzdetektiv Ed Dante von Hollisters Schwester den Auftrag, den verschwundenen Schatz zu identifizieren und aufzuspüren. Dante setzt dabei aus Versehen ein auf dem Computer von Hollister installiertes Script in Gang, das eine weltweite Schatzsuche inszeniert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doch es stellt sich heraus, daß die Geschichte um das Ableben von Hollister weitaus komplizierter ist, denn Hollister hat auch noch eine andere, wesentlich kontrolliertere Cryptowährung ins Leben gerufen und am Ende ist alles ein Racheplot in einem Racheplot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gewohnt gute Kost von Hillenbrand. Schnell und spannend durchzulesen, flott inszeniert und aktuelle Themen aufgreifend. Ich habe mich gut unterhalten gefühlt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Montecrypto&amp;rdquo;, Tom Hillenbrand, Eur 12.99&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Black Count</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/06/05/fertig-gelesen-the-black-count.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 21:36:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/06/05/fertig-gelesen-the-black-count.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another Monte-Cristo-themed book, Tom Reiss&#39; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/dp/B008QYTJZO&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Black Count&lt;/a&gt;

 nicely complements the german sci-fi novel &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/06/05/fertig-gelesen-montecrypto.html&#34;&gt;Montecrypto&lt;/a&gt;

 by Tom Hillenbrand. It is a biography of the father of the French write Alexandere Dumas, Thomas-Alexandre Dumas Davy de la Pailleterie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/dp/B008QYTJZO&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/06/black-count.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/dp/B008QYTJZO&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Black Count&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;quot;, by Tom Reiss.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alexandre Dumas, the author of &amp;ldquo;The Three Musketeers&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;The Count of Monte Cristo&amp;rdquo; and many other books, is one of the most read French authors. He had it easy coming up with stories, because his father had one of the most unusual and wildest lives imaginable. Dumas was, in a way, telling episodes from his fathers adventures, toned down to become more believable, in some of his stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas-Alexandre was born on the French colony island Saint-Domingue (now Hawaii). His father was the French Marquis Alexandre Antoine Davy de la Pailletterie. His mother Marie-Cessette Dumas, an enslaved woman of &amp;ldquo;Afro-Caribbean&amp;rdquo; ancestry,  which means that she or her ancestors were enslaved somewhere in Africa and forcibly brought to the Island. Not much is known about her actual origin or history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His father, very broke, returned to France, where Thomas-Alexandre was legally freed: in France, slavery was prohibited since 1315, in the colonies not so much. He was educated in a military school and then joined the army as a young man. He also started to use his mothers name after he fell out with his father.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dumas entered the military at the age of 24 as a private, but quickly rose in rank. This was not only due to his bodily fitness, his incredible fighting skills and his immense organisational talent, but also due to the wealth of opportunities that the upheaval of the French Revolution of 1789 offered, 3 years into his military career. He held the rank of a General-in-Chief over the 53.000 troops of the French Army in the Alps, at the age of 31. Among his soldiers, he was known for upholding the ideals of the French revolution, Liberty and Equality, and the ideals of Humanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He served under the orders of the commander-in-chief General Napoleon Bonaparte in Milan in 1796, clashing with him over plundering and expropriation policies. He also fought with Napoleon&amp;rsquo;s aide-de-camp over similar matters of fairness and courage in battle. Despite that, he joined Napoleon&amp;rsquo;s Egyptian expedition in 1798, and became the cavalry commander of the French Army of the Orient. The conditions of the march from Alexandria to Cairo were harsh, and Dumas discussed with other french generals if they would refuse to march past Cairo. Napoleon later learned of that meeting, accused Dumas of treason and forced him to return to France on an unsound vessel. The ship sank slowly during the trip, and was forced aground in a storm near Taranto in Naples. Naples Cardinal Fabrizio Ruffo imprisoned Dumas and his fellow travellers for two years. In jail, Dumas was permanently injured due to infection and malnourishment. He died in 1806, five years after his release, from stomach cancer, at which time his son Alexandre Dumas was 4 years old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Thomas-Alexandre Dumas story easily has sufficient material for several of the stories his son wrote, and his son in fact used parts of his fathers biography in several of his stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before Reiss&#39; well researched book the life and exploits of this colorful hero of the French Revolution were almost forgotten. Reiss&#39; storytelling brings us back the story of Dumas, who lived through one of the most exciting parts of French history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/dp/B008QYTJZO&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Black Count&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Tom Reiss, EUR 8.59&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Linkers</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-linkers.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2021 13:06:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-linkers.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ian Lance Taylor is the author of a UUCP program that I have been using for a long time to connect to other USENET systems, long before I had access to the actual Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UUCP queues up jobs for remote execution, dials other computers with a moden, exchanges the contents of the queued up work, and after disconnect executes the jobs. The jobs are mostly invocation of &amp;ldquo;rmail&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;rnews&amp;rdquo; programs for the exchange of mail and USENET news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taylors version of UUCP had large number of protocol and interface improvement that made it hugely superior, and that made working with &amp;ldquo;high speed modems&amp;rdquo; viable in the first place. It was the backbone of my network connectivity, 30 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taylor also wrote &amp;ldquo;a book&amp;rdquo; about program linkers in 2007, in the form of a long series of blog posts. In it, he explains what happens to a program after the compiler emits an object file, and before the program actually starts to run. That is, he describes how to the object file, system libraries and runtime become one thing that actually is capable of starting up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is deeply nerdy content, and also quite interesting, because it is widely underdocumented. Taylor&amp;rsquo;s series is key to making the obscure but vital topic better understandable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a book, but a series of blog posts. Fortunately, there is an &lt;a href=&#34;https://lwn.net/Articles/276782/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;index page&lt;/a&gt;

 made available by LWN. The parent article, on the Gold linker, is also &lt;a href=&#34;https://lwn.net/Articles/274859/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;at LWN&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Needle</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-needle.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2021 14:23:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-needle.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Needle-Book-Gateway-Essentials-English-ebook/dp/B005K8H1QS/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Needle&lt;/a&gt;

 and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Through-Eye-Needle-Gateway-Essentials-ebook/dp/B005OAHE7I&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Through the Eye of a Needle&lt;/a&gt;

 are books by Hal Clement. Hal Clement was a Hard Sci-Fi author born in 1922, and &amp;ldquo;Needle&amp;rdquo; was written in 1950 as his first book, for Campbell, no less, and sold to Doubleday. The followup was produced almost 30 years later, in 1978.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Needle-Book-Gateway-Essentials-English-ebook/dp/B005K8H1QS&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/05/needle.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Needle-Book-Gateway-Essentials-English-ebook/dp/B005K8H1QS&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Needle&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story begins with two spaceships crashing into planet earth, some time in the 1950&amp;rsquo;s idea of a future, close to an island in the Pacific ocean. Both ships are mostly destroyed in the crash, but the inhabitants survive: A criminal, and a kind of headhunter/policeman. They are part of formless species that has much smaller cells than humans and that need a host from normal sized cells with which they live in symbiosis - at least those of the species that are not criminals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hunter enters the body of Bob Kincaid, a post-puberty schoolboy that parties at the beach because it&amp;rsquo;s the end of the summer vacation. The Hunter needs time to orient himself in Bob, establish communication, and find of his current situation, at which point Bob is already firmly abroad on the American continent, in School. He now needs to find a way to get Bob back to the island, and then find the Criminal who may hide in anybody on that island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We follow Bob and his symbiont through the case, exploring the life on the island, in a weird mix of Sci-Fi, Whodunnit and YA island life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second part, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Through-Eye-Needle-Gateway-Essentials-ebook/dp/B005OAHE7I&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Through the Eye of a Needle&lt;/a&gt;

, Hal Clement returns to his characters. Bob has fallen ill, which should be impossible with the Hunter symbiont living in him, and it appears that he&amp;rsquo;s showing some kind of reaction to the presence of the Hunter himself. Help is needed from specialists of the Hunters people, but because the Hunter&amp;rsquo;s ship was destroyed in the crash that seems to be impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two old school hard Sci-Fi books, that, looking past the outdated role-models, are still interesting YA reads and have aged quite okay.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Antivirus Hackers Handbook</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-the-antivirus-hackers-handbook.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2021 14:04:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-the-antivirus-hackers-handbook.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Antivirus-Hackers-Handbook-English-ebook/dp/B014MJ6AKS/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Antivirus Hackers Handbook&lt;/a&gt;

 by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/joxeankoret&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jaxeon Koret&lt;/a&gt;

 and Elias Bachaalany is part book, part a research report, detailing the findings of Jaxeon Koret and Elias Bachaalany in how Antivirus programs work, try to protect themselves and can be attacked and exploited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Antivirus-Hackers-Handbook-English-ebook/dp/B014MJ6AKS/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/05/avhh.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Antivirus-Hackers-Handbook-English-ebook/dp/B014MJ6AKS/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Antivirus Hackers Handbook&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book assumes that you have some basic knowledge how compilers produce programs, what assembler looks like and how to map that on program statements in the code you write, and have access to IDA Pro free edition, Ghidra, Hopper or some other reverse engineering and analysis tool. We are then guided through the authors journey of discovery, analyzing the cores and plugin systems of various Antivirus products, how they work, how they detect viruses, how they update themselves, and how they try to protect themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antivirus systems are terribly large and attractive targets when trying to exploit individual machines or even fleets of machines: They try to scan and understand all kinds of file formats, run analysis often in privileged mode and with system protections turned off, and they are usually installed uniformly on a large fleet of machines in corporates, as mandatory pieces of software. These days they also increasingly have cloud components they upload data to, well suited to mask exfiltration traffic. When trying to attack and subvert corporate targets, they are the ideal platform for an attacker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the authors take us on that journey, at a level of intricate detail, but also always keeping the larger goal in sight. After reading this book one is looking at corporate security software differently, questioning if it is actually making things more secure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Antivirus-Hackers-Handbook-English-ebook/dp/B014MJ6AKS/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Antivirus Hackers Handbook&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Jaxeon Koret and Elias Bachaalany, EUR 32.06&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Witcher</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-the-witcher.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2021 15:55:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-the-witcher.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So, Netflix&#39; &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netflix.com/nl-en/title/80189685&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Witcher&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; was weird, and could not decide what it wanted to be: A &amp;ldquo;Hercules Legenday Journey&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo;-like half-comedy, half-camp series, or something else, darker and denser, with more story and background. It hinted at a better story, better told, that did not make it into the final product, and died somewhere between the scriptwriting and the cutting table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigating, I got myself the equivalent of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Witcher-Boxed-Set-Destiny-Contempt/dp/1473232279&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Witcher Boxed Set&lt;/a&gt;

 on the Kindle and started reading. And indeed, just as with &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-conan-the-barbarian.html&#34;&gt;Conan, the Barbarian&lt;/a&gt;

, the book is nothing like the film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We get indeed a dense and increasingly dark story, the story of Geralt and Jennifer, both remnants from a time gone by, and Ciri, the product of an age-old arrangement of breeding and selection, gone wrong in the last few steps, all of them fighting for freedom of will and their choice in life, and ultimately failing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reading order is  &amp;ldquo;The Last Wish&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Sword of Destiny&amp;rdquo;, (&amp;ldquo;Season of Storms&amp;rdquo;, optional), &amp;ldquo;Blood of Elves&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Time of Contempt&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Baptism of Fire&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Tower of the Swallow&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;The Lady of the Lake&amp;rdquo;. And indeed, the story is good, the Netflix series is shallow and has very little to do with the books. Also, Sapkowsky pulls off a surprisingly large and mean number of storytelling trickery.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Titan</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-titan.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2021 15:06:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/05/14/fertig-gelesen-titan.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The story of &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-heavens-river.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Heaven&amp;rsquo;s River&lt;/a&gt;

, stranding in and then exploring an alien megastructure, is one that has been written before: In &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Ringworld-English-Larry-Niven-ebook/dp/B01513ZIL6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Niven&amp;rsquo;s Ringworld&lt;/a&gt;

, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Rendezvous-Rama-Book-English-ebook/dp/B0079MRDIE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Clarke&amp;rsquo;s Rama&lt;/a&gt;

, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Riverworld-Including-Scattered-Fabulous-Riverboat/dp/0765326523/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Farmer&amp;rsquo;s Riverworld&lt;/a&gt;

. John Varley&amp;rsquo;s take on this, very seventies, is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Titan-Gaia-Book-1-English-ebook/dp/B009KUXCBK&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Titan&lt;/a&gt;

, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B009KUXKAI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wizard&lt;/a&gt;

, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B009KUXAEO&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Demon&lt;/a&gt;

, the Gaia Trilogy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Titan-Gaia-Book-1-English-ebook/dp/B009KUXCBK&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/05/titan.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Titan-Gaia-Book-1-English-ebook/dp/B009KUXCBK&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Titan&lt;/a&gt;

, Wizard and Daemon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cirocco Jones is the Commander of the Earth science ship Ringmaster, and is right now approaching the orbit of Saturn, where she and her crew discover a new moon. As they approach the moon, they realize it&amp;rsquo;s a Stanford Torus like space habitat. Trying to find a way to dock, they come close and are being picked up by a giant tentacle-like arm, and dragged into the station while their ship is being destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Cirocco wakes up, literally naked and hairless, without any resouces by the metal parts that are the remains of her spacesuit, she realizes that months have elapsed since the collision. She sets out to orient herself in the strange, but extremely habitable world inside the torus, trying to find her crewmates. She manages to find them, and realizes they, like herself, have been changed in the months that they have spend somewhere in the interior of the space station.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They learn that the station is indeed a living being, older than time itself, and it is falling apart as the central intelligence is dying and the twelve subintelligences in the torus are fighting amongst themselves for control. Exploring the Flora and Fauna, it becomes obvious that all life in Gaia is constructed and preprogrammed, and at least sometimes under control of the central intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cirocco, and her surviving shipmates, are trying to reach the centre, climbing up one of the giant, kilometres thick cables that hold the torus together. On their way they learn that some of them have been changed beyond the point of sanity, and fighting starts. Cirocco manages to get to the center, and is offered to be Gaia&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Wizard&amp;rdquo;, her repair agent in torus world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the further books, this is expanded - Gaia establishes herself as a nation in the Solar system, opening a Consulate and offering medical miracle cures to humans that make the trip to Saturn and Gaia. It becomes clear that Gaia is terminally old, going slowly insane by age and boredom. Cirocco and Gaia fall out, and go to war with each other, Cirocco no longer being the &amp;ldquo;Wizard&amp;rdquo;, but the &amp;ldquo;Daemon&amp;rdquo;. During these events, Gaby, Ciroccos shipmate and later partner, is being killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story then turns into more of a Zombie movie, in which a completely crazed Gaia goes to war on the humans, and the creatures of her that managed to emancipate themselves from her waning control. It comes to light that Gaia recorded the personalities of the captured Ringmaster crew, and that Gaby&amp;rsquo;s mentral recording has become some kind of agent in the hardware that represents the actual Gaia in the center of the Titan ring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a final confrontation, Cirocco raises an army from the ring inhabitants loyal to her, conquers Gaia&amp;rsquo;s forces, and manages to distract her sufficiently so that Gaby can take over the rings central hardware and bring the rebellious subsystems under her control. Gaby offers Cirocco to become a Wizard again, but Cirocco chooses adventure instead&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story has the classic shape of this particular Sci-Fi trope, and is being echo&amp;rsquo;ed in part in multiple ways in Heaven&amp;rsquo;s River, but is also very typical in its 70-ies sex-and-drugs laden storytelling. It has aged well enough to be enjoyable to read again, but it is too long to read in one uninterrupted go, and also has lengths in the later parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Titan-Gaia-Book-1-English-ebook/dp/B009KUXCBK&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Titan&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B009KUXKAI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wizard&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B009KUXAEO&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Demon&lt;/a&gt;

 by John Varley.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Children of Ruin</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-children-of-ruin.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 21:20:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-children-of-ruin.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Children-Ruin-Time-Novels-English-ebook/dp/B07KPMJ7V9/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Children of Ruin&lt;/a&gt;

 is the second part of &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/11/07/fertig-gelesen-children-of-time.html&#34;&gt;Children of Time&lt;/a&gt;

 by english Sci-Fi author Adrian Tchaikovsky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Children-Ruin-Time-Novels-English-ebook/dp/B07KPMJ7V9/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/04/children-of-ruin.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &amp;ldquo;Children of Time&amp;rdquo;, mankind reached for the stars, almost suceeded and also almost died out. They did manage to create a digital lifeform, though, and also to seed and uplift life from earth on another world - just not the intended one. And so we ended up with a race of intelligent giant jumping spiders that manage to befriend the broken artificial intelligence orbiting their world and to rescue the remnants of humankind from themselves. Oh, and ant based computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This almost Peter-Watts-like eclectic and unlikely cast of characters is amended in &amp;ldquo;Children of Ruin&amp;rdquo;, in which a spider-human ship travels a radio source that suggests intelligent life, to find a civilisation of similarly uplifted octopodes at war with itself, and a planet with truely alien, non-terran life which at some point becomes aware of the various terran research groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tchaikovsky again manages to pull off nonhuman characters in a way that reads interesting and relatable, while at the same time completely alien.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See also &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-other-minds.html&#34;&gt;Other Minds&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Children-Ruin-Time-Novels-English-ebook/dp/B07KPMJ7V9/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Children of Ruin&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Adrian Tchaikovsky, EUR 5.99&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Conan, The Barbarian</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-conan-the-barbarian.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 22:13:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/04/07/fertig-gelesen-conan-the-barbarian.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Conan-Barbarian-Complete-Collection-English-ebook/dp/B07HCD69LQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Conan, The Barbarian&lt;/a&gt;

 by Robert E. Howard is a collection of all Conan stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Conan-Barbarian-Complete-Collection-English-ebook/dp/B07HCD69LQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/04/conan.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imaginaryworldspodcast.org/episodes/the-man-behind-the-sword&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Imaginary Worlds Ep 114: The Man Behind the Sword&lt;/a&gt;

 (&lt;a href=&#34;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5f9f06c44dd1ed19b7080797/t/5faf52831c7089551ae9c739/1605325444029/The&amp;#43;Man&amp;#43;Behind&amp;#43;the&amp;#43;Sword&amp;#43;transcript.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Episode Transcript PDF&lt;/a&gt;

) discussed Robert E. Howard, his 1930&amp;rsquo;s character Conan, The Barbarian and how Howard&amp;rsquo;s Conan is different from the Schwarzenegger character, and a much deeper and more complicated story. Go, and listen to the episode, it is well worth the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having seen the Schwarzenegger film, but never actually having read the book I went out and got this complete collection. The podcast was right, the original book Conan is much unlike the Schwarzenegger film Conan, and the book is fun to read. It&amp;rsquo;s a classic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Conan-Barbarian-Complete-Collection-English-ebook/dp/B07HCD69LQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Conan, The Barbarian&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Robert E. Howard, EUR 0.99&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

