<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>remote first on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/remote-first.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in remote first on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2023 16:09:12 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/remote-first/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Kein Homeoffice, keine Kekse</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/12/kein-homeoffice-keine-kekse.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 01:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/12/kein-homeoffice-keine-kekse.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Heise schreibt:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.heise.de/meinung/Kommentar-Massenexodus-bei-Grindr-von-den-Un-Schoenheiten-des-Homeoffice-9301244.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kommentar: Massenexodus bei Grindr – von den (Un-)Schönheiten des Homeoffice &lt;/a&gt;


Ein Kommentar, der sich am Massenexodus bei Grindr abarbeitet, aber nicht weiß, was er will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bei Grindr bildet sich eine Gewerkschaft, und viele Mitarbeiter werden Mitglied.
Aus Rache führt die Firma Hybrid mit mindestens 2 Tagen pro Woche Anwesenheit ein.
Daraufhin kündigen mehr als 50 % der Mitarbeiter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Artikel sieht das nicht als collective action der Mitarbeiter,
sondern als eine Folge von Individualentscheidungen.
Er sieht auch irgendwie Vorteile für die Firma (&amp;ldquo;Geringere Kosten&amp;rdquo; und magische &amp;ldquo;höhere Produktivität&amp;rdquo;),
und versucht dann eine Art Brücke zu schlagen (&amp;ldquo;Firmen sollten auf Mitarbeiter hören.&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist in Summe aussagelos und von der wirtschaftlichen Analyse her Quatsch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;auftragstaktik&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#auftragstaktik&#34;&gt;
	Auftragstaktik
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In den drei Covid-Jahren haben sich in allen Firmen sehr stabile und produktive Remote-First Strukturen ausgebildet.
Sehr viele Mitarbeiter haben sehr schnell gelernt,
dass zweimal eine Stunde Commute pro Tag mehr Belastung waren, als sie bewusst bemerkt haben.
Sie waren sehr froh, diese Lebenszeit zurückzubekommen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zudem haben sie gemerkt, daß Management by Objectives – nahezu die einzige Methode, die Remote First funktioniert –
viel sinnvoller ist als fast alles andere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wer mehr wissen will:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://mastodon.social/@xahteiwi&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Florian Haas&lt;/a&gt;


hat darüber ja auch schon unter Referenz auf die
&lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/F%C3%BChren_mit_Auftrag&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Auftragstaktik&lt;/a&gt;

 nachgedacht
und in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Art-Action-Leaders-between-Actions-ebook/dp/B01HPVHLHG&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Art of Action&lt;/a&gt;


beschäftigt sich quasi ein ganzes Buch mit dem Thema &amp;ldquo;Auftragstaktik in der Unternehmensführung umsetzen&amp;rdquo;
und Clausewitz &amp;ldquo;Vom Kriege&amp;rdquo; in der Wirtschaft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenn Unternehmen nun – aus welchem Grund auch immer – versuchen,
das zurückzudrehen, dann erzeugen sie damit eine große Unzufriedenheit bei ihren Mitarbeitern
und drehen die Fluktuation hoch bis zum Anschlag.
Sie machen dabei keinen Gewinn, denn sie verlieren genau die Mitarbeiter, die sie behalten müssen und wollen.
Unternehmen bluten vom Kopfe her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;arbeitsmarkt&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#arbeitsmarkt&#34;&gt;
	Arbeitsmarkt
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und sie schneiden sich von einem Arbeitsmarkt ab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In dem wegweisenden Essay
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/software-engineering-salaries-in-the-netherlands-and-europe/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Trimodal Nature of Software Engineering Salaries in the Netherlands and Europe&lt;/a&gt;


beschreibt Gergely Orosz die Struktur des Arbeitsmarktes bei Wissensarbeitern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Er tut das am Beispiel von Amsterdam,
aber meiner Erfahrung nach ist das weltweit so, mit unterschiedlichen Limits bei den lokalen Märkten.
Unternehmen müssen wissen, aus welchem Pool sie Personen ansprechen und einstellen wollen,
und sie müssen wissen, wie man mit der entsprechenden Gruppe Leute arbeitet.
Der Vorteil von Remote First Unternehmen ist, daß sie aus dem globalen Markt einstellen können,
aber oft zu Preisen aus einem nationalen Markt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein frühes Beispiel dafür war MySQL AB, die mit 500 Leuten in 26 Ländern ein extremes Beispiel für eine verteilte Firma waren,
und die weltweit eingestellt hat, aber keinen Umzug gefordert hat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stattdessen hat man bewusst Strukturen geschaffen, in denen ein verteiltes Team Gemeinschaft bildet,
sich 4x im Jahr getroffen (in Ländern, die unproblematisch mit Visa umgingen),
und man hat diese Treffen systematisch vorbereitet, damit sie effektiv waren.
Und ja, jede Menge MbO/Auftragstaktik.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eine moderne Beschreibung solcher Methoden findet man in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Effective-Remote-English-James-Stanier-ebook/dp/B09Z5F678G&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Effective Remote Work&lt;/a&gt;

 von James Stanier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;die-folgen-von-rto&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#die-folgen-von-rto&#34;&gt;
	Die Folgen von RTO
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In den drei Covid-Jahren sind in vielen Firmen ebenfalls solche Strukturen entstanden,
aber oft zufällig, partiell, nicht gesteuert und unverstanden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenn ein solcher Laden jetzt aus welchem Grund auch immer &amp;ldquo;Return to Office&amp;rdquo; ausruft, dann passieren mehrere Dinge:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Die Firma schneidet sich vom weitweiten Staffing Pool (zu nationalen Preisen) ab, Hiring wird schwierig.
Denn neue Mitarbeitys müssen umziehen und dem stehen Verpflichtungen vor Ort,
Visa und Arbeitserlaubnisse und viele andere Dinge im Weg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Die Firma erzeugt ohne Not die Situation oben für alle existierenden Mitarbeiter,
die in den drei Covid-Jahren dazu gekommen sind, aber nicht umgezogen sind.
&lt;em&gt;Alle&lt;/em&gt; die werden gehen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Die Firma bringt den Commute zurück zu Menschen, die begriffen haben,
dass der Commute notlose Verschlechterung der Lebensqualität ist.
Auch hier Kündigungswelle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welche Leute werden gehen?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zuerst immer die, die Optionen haben.
Also die hoch qualifizierten, deren Recruiter-Spam in der Inbox am größten ist.
Der Pull-Faktor ist ja schon da, den Push und den Anlass hat die Firma eben geliefert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es sind also gerade die Leute, bei denen der Arbeitgeber einen Anlass hat, Retention zu fahren,
die der Arbeitgeber zuerst verliert.
Das ist immer und für jede Firma ein sehr großer Nettoverlust, und noch dazu ein schlecht gesteuerter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenige Läden können einen Verlust von 50 % der Belegschaft verkraften,
ohne dass es zu einem massiven Verlust an Qualität, Produktivität, organisatorischem Wissen und Prozeßreife kommt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neben dem Verlust an Know-How und nicht verschriftlichtem Wissen,
der erhöhten Arbeitslast für die verbleibenden Mitarbeiter kommt noch der Druck auf alle für Interviews
und Training neuer Kollegen dazu.
Das erzeugt eine Delle in Qualität und Produktivität von 1 bis 2 Jahren, Stagnation oder gar Regress.
Es gibt kein Wertmodell für eine Firma, in der so etwas positive Auswirkungen hat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;auch-entlassungen-fördern-ungesteuerte-verluste&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#auch-entlassungen-f%c3%b6rdern-ungesteuerte-verluste&#34;&gt;
	Auch Entlassungen fördern ungesteuerte Verluste
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Etwas Ähnliches passiert bei Entlassungen:
Neben den Leuten, die man entläßt (gesteuert und nach Ansicht der Firma am unteren Ende)
wird man gewiss noch 2x mehr Leute verlieren,
aber am oberen Ende.
Für diese Menschen ist der zweite, ungeschriebene Vertrag gebrochen worden,
und sie nehmen die resultierende Unsicherheit als Anstoß, Pull-Faktoren nachzugeben.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In jedem Fall bluten Firmen bei solchen Änderungen.
Sogar dann, wenn sich nicht aus billiger Rache erfolgen,
sondern gesteuert und mit Unterstützung des Managements sanft durchgeführt werden,
kommt es leicht mit großen zweistelligen prozentualen Verlusten und jahrelangen Folgen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firmen lernen gerade, wie wichtig Personen als Individuen sind.
Viele Organisationen sind mit dieser, der kapitalistischer Ideologie widersprechenden Erfahrung sehr unzufrieden und tief in Denial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies forcing their employees back into the office will lose talent and keep wage serfs.
&amp;ndash; Volker Weber (&lt;a href=&#34;https://social.heise.de/@vowe&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@vowe@social.heise.de&lt;/a&gt;

)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Groups and Places</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/10/12/groups-and-places.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 06:07:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/10/12/groups-and-places.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a distributed, asynchronous environment, there is a need for distributed, asynchronous interaction.
This interaction is often written, but &amp;ldquo;writing&amp;rdquo; these days is actually a media-rich process that includes much more than letters.
It also needs to be able to build some structure, and some gateway to level up to more synchronous and even richer communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s have a chat about chats, and what properties they have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-01.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Historically, chat was lines of text, without much structure. Even today, many geeks often propose IRC when chat solutions are being discussed in a corporate context. That is a very myopic way of thinking.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first chat network I have been using was IRC &amp;ndash; Internet Relay Chat.
This has been in the late 80ies or early 90ies, so today I have had an interactive online presence on the upside of 25 years or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later I got to use ICQ, Jabber, Skype, Hangouts, Facebook Messenger, WhatsApp, Slack and RocketChat, among many others.
I also got exposed to a number of collaborative document processing systems with chat-like properties:
the now defunct Google Wave (alias Apache Wave, now also mostly defunct), and its heir Google Docs, and a bunch of newer collaborative brainstorming tools from the School of Miro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these applications and chat systems are different, but they can be evaluated along a number of dimensions to understand chat systems better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A screenshot of my chat desktop from 2016. There are many like it, but this is mine.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;location-and-discoverability&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#location-and-discoverability&#34;&gt;
	Location and Discoverability
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most important functions any chat system has to have is enabling the right people to find each other.
There are two large classes of chat systems here: One uses groups, and the other uses places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Groups are just that: collections of people that talk to each other.
You write a message and sent it.
It is then visible to all members of the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with groups is that they are almost impossible to find.
They are invitation only.
A member of the group must have knowledge of you looking for the group, and then invite you to it.
In some messengers this will also form a new group, destroying the messaging history of the older group, in order to protect the privacy of the conversation happening before the new member joined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-03.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Discord chat system allows you to form small scale groups with fixed membership, even without having a &amp;ldquo;Discord Server&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A better system uses Places (often called Rooms or Channels) instead of Groups.
A place is discoverable, you can &amp;ldquo;find&amp;rdquo; it, &amp;ldquo;go&amp;rdquo; to it, and &amp;ldquo;join&amp;rdquo; without being explicitly invited (permission and moderation systems often exist).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Places tend to proliferate, mechanism to group, order, tag and search them often exist.
In Discord, for example, Channels can be grouped into Categories, which are then grouped into &amp;ldquo;Servers&amp;rdquo;, the server having an owner, and often a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-04.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Discord chat system, showing the &amp;ldquo;heiseonline&amp;rdquo; discord server, with a channel named &lt;code&gt;#tierbilder&lt;/code&gt; (Animal Pictures) selected. Below that, a Category for &lt;code&gt;Sprachkanäle&lt;/code&gt; (Voice Channels) is seen.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having Places instead of Groups is crucial for any communication system.
It gives you the capability to write instructions that send people somewhere, and enables people to find and go somewhere, gives them agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebooks Messenger and Facebook at Work&amp;rsquo;s greatest flaw is their Messenger, which does not have this feature.
It relies on Groups, and tries to mitigate that by coupling groups to Facebook &amp;ldquo;Groups&amp;rdquo; (discussion boards), auto-inviting people into the Facebook Group associated chat group.
This combines worst practices of several systems into one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Places can be persistent, they can exist without anyone being in them.
Places can also have one or multiple owners, which is the root of that Places&amp;rsquo; permission system and the source of all moderator power for that Place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;presence&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#presence&#34;&gt;
	Presence
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working asynchronously means that you will not be present in a chat at all times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a feature: It allows you to focus, and think straight, cutting deeply into problems.
It also allows you to be in another timezone than your communication partners and still contribute meaningfully to a collaborative effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It poses the problem of your communication partners not knowing your current communication status, and availability.
If they are blocked, they might need you, and it would help them to have some expectation of your response times, availability and context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All modern chat systems have a presence mechanism, a semi-automatic status tagline, and the more thoughtfully engineered ones also know your timezone and show it to your peers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-05.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Slack chat system allows users to set a status in the form of an Emoji and a tagline. These are automatically cleared after some preset time, if desired. Slack also understands time zones, and will show you out-of-office times of communication partners, when necessary. Clicking on a user will also reveal their location and local time. On the right hand side, a number of status bubble examples are shown.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presence management in chat system often goes hand in hand with logging.
Messages sent to you in your absence are logged, and shown to you on reconnect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all a giant step forward from IRC, which did not manage presence well, and also did not allow sending messages to disconnected users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In IRC, being offline means not being present: people fall off the channel and what is being said with them being not there is lost to them.
That is of course a nuisance, and so people have been using programs such as screen to run an IRC client even when they have been disconnected from their computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IRC&amp;rsquo;s mechanism for presence (here: attention) is somewhat hidden &amp;ndash; the &lt;code&gt;/away&lt;/code&gt; command.
But not only is the mechanism hidden (it is another command that needs to be learned and used), but the status is somewhat hidden as well.
You can&amp;rsquo;t see if somebody is &lt;code&gt;/away&lt;/code&gt; unless you look at them with a &lt;code&gt;/whois&lt;/code&gt;.
Or you learn about the fact that they are &lt;code&gt;/away&lt;/code&gt; only after the fact, when you say something to them and get an auto-response with their &lt;code&gt;/away&lt;/code&gt; message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people do not like this, and so they use another mechanism and change their nicknames when they are not there &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;Isotopp&amp;rdquo; becomes &amp;ldquo;Isotopp|AFK&amp;rdquo; or similar.
This is less structured than &lt;code&gt;/away&lt;/code&gt;, and so some people suffix their names, some prefix them and others completely change their nicknames - &amp;ldquo;Isotopp&amp;rdquo; becomes &amp;ldquo;Awaytopp&amp;rdquo;.
The lack of facility, discoverable interface and standardization creates variant practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;logging-and-multi-device&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#logging-and-multi-device&#34;&gt;
	Logging and Multi-Device
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All modern chat clients have proper presence, even if not always as rich as in Slack.
Most also have unified logging.
That is, even absent users can receive messages and will see them when coming back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most users in 2022 have multiple devices, and multiple clients.
Most users want the entire messaging history, in order, and with all backlog, available on all their devices, so that they can switch between devices without losing context.
This usually includes new devices, to facilitate moving to new laptops or cellphones, without losing history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This often clashes with old standards, badly designed security mechanisms and other implementation details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-06.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Google Talk log, with OTR encryption, viewed in a different Jabber client. The history is truncated, and OTR encrypted messages are not available in readable form in this client.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One extreme point for synchronisation is the Discord chat system, where not only history and messages are kept in sync across all clients, but even preferences are unified:
Setting the desktop client to dark mode will also set dark mode on the cellphone application, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another, opposite extreme point is Jabber, which has no common rule for disposition of messages, and by default will send messages only to one client, using either a preference system, the last active client, or &amp;ldquo;all known clients to the server at the point in time the message was sent&amp;rdquo;. A lot depends on server and clients used here, creating an unreliable and hard to control user experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;deliverables---file-and-image-sharing&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#deliverables---file-and-image-sharing&#34;&gt;
	Deliverables - File and Image Sharing
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a corporate context, we use the communication mechanism as a vehicle to create and share documents, and have a discussion about the documents we work on collaboratively.
Mail was doing this in the past, with Quotes and with Attachments, but that is a very cumbersome, lossy and hard to discover mechanism.
Most companies have moved the collaboration process off mail, to a large extent, and towards chat and collaborative document systems such as Google Docs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google had taken this one step further with structured chat.
The pioneer application for that has been the short-lived Google Wave:
Wave allowed a group of people to create things in a kind of chat bubble, only that this bubble could not just hold a line of text, but also other media including rich documents, images, bots or other things that interfaced with the Wave API.
Other users could comment on an item in a hierarchic comments-on-comment tree like in a discussion system, or directly edit the original item, incorporating their changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changes were recorded and were undoable and replayable.
This allowed users to view the end result of a Wave, or review the process of building that result after the fact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-07.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Google Wave being used to collaboratively work on a shared document. The Wave contains the final document, but also the process that led to the end result.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a way, Wave could have been a salvation from the hell of corporate email:
Waves produce results, documents or agreements.
They also record the history of how that result had been reached, and they allow people joining the process late to catch up and review what has happened before on their own terms.
No more full quotes, 13 levels deep, and no more dozens of copies of the same Word file, all slightly different, and with diverging side remarks from people somewhere in the organisation, which never made it back into the main document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wave failed, though, and for multiple reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the bigger reasons is that Wave was all mechanism and no purpose &amp;ndash; it could to many things, and offered all of them without stating what Wave itself or the various functions are there for.
One could use Wave to manage a world building and game session in a role playing game, as well as replace corporate email, or use it as a rather clunky and over-engineered word processor.
So Wave needed explanation and contextualisation - and above all, a purpose, but none was given.
Wave died, because it confused users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-08.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A collaboratively edited document. Multiple watchers are shown as icons at the top of the screen. A chat window is open. Cursors and collaborators edits would be visible simultaneously editing the document in many places while it has been initially created.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wave&amp;rsquo;s legacy lives on, though.
Much of the functionality of Wave is present in Google Docs, including the side chat, collaborative editing, history recording and replay and many other functions.
Unlike Wave, Google&amp;rsquo;s shared document editing puts the purpose first, and the collaboration in the background.
This is matching people&amp;rsquo;s expectations much better, and is less overwhelming.
It does not have to be taught, or manually given purpose.
Instead, the purpose is built in, and immediately obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern chat systems are kind of the opposite:
They put their purpose (communication) first, and the documents ride in the back.
This happens either through URLs or through file transfer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All modern chat systems have a working file transfer, which is also aware of media types.
That means, not only can you drag and drop files into a 1:1 chat or a channel, but also images or animations, as well as audio files.
They are understood, and shown inline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together with other mechanisms, such as threads, they enable unique workflows that go way past the unstructured ASCII-limited text of IRC.
For example, in many workplaces designers use the image capabilities of Slack, together with Slack threads, to share images, mockups and other things and then criticize or approve designs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also where not only IRC, but also Jabber falls down.
Proper file sharing, inline media content and threading are things that may exist somewhere, in some Jabber extension, but are not generally interoperable or enabled without much configuration across a set of clients.
They might as well not exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;we-were-lucky&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#we-were-lucky&#34;&gt;
	We were lucky
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the place I work at, we were lucky.
By the time Covid pushed people to work from home, we already had replaced mail almost completely.
I was down from thousands of mail messages per day on almost one hundred mailing lists to less than a dozen messages, and no mailing lists at all anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have moved to &lt;strong&gt;Facebook at Work&lt;/strong&gt; for non-realtime group communication.
Teams were using their Facebook groups to communicate announcements and progress to other teams, and have discussions with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internally and for support we moved to &lt;strong&gt;Slack&lt;/strong&gt;.
This was pushed with considerable force from below, after corporate initially being very fond of Facebook messenger, mostly because it was free and included in Facebook at work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately FB messenger is utterly broken in many ways, and unsuited for any structured work communication without basically rewriting it from scratch.
There are many facets to its fractal brokenness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has groups, but no places.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Groups have limited attendance, and the limit is too small (the old &lt;code&gt;#live&lt;/code&gt; Jabber channel was mandatory for all people pushing deployments, and could not be reproduced in FB Messenger).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It ate data. Mentioning a filename &lt;code&gt;main.pl&lt;/code&gt; would inescapably turn this into a polish hostname &lt;a href=&#34;https://main.pl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;main.pl&lt;/a&gt;

. More often than not, Messenger would detect a malware phishing attempt and prevent you from sending the message.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It ate data. Mentioning URLs with array parameters (&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://example.com/bla?a=1&amp;amp;a=2&amp;amp;a=3%22&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://example.com/bla?a=1&amp;a=2&amp;a=3&#34;&lt;/a&gt;

) would make it parse the URL, representing the keys in a hash, and dropping the repeated keys, breaking the URL.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It could not handle files, code formatting and many other things well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It could not do threads, which are a necessity in high volume support channels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, corp was forced to also purchase Slack on top of FB at Work, to prevent a more or less open revolt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had been using &lt;strong&gt;Google Drive and Google Office&lt;/strong&gt;, as well, across the company, and the collaborative features in it were well understood and used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heterogeneity of all of this posed to be not a problem, somewhat surprisingly.
In fact, in many cases, the mix-and-match approach enabled us to be flexible, and work around many tools limitations, and also to expand and integrate other things easily.
Other applications (e.g. Miro, but also many others) have since been added for many users, who have other, more specialized needs and requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also used to use BlueJeans, before the pandemic, and mostly from meeting room installations with dedicated hardware.
During Covid, Zoom became popular, and offered a richer and much better set of clients, especially on mobile devices (Laptops, Tablets, Cellphones), so we switched vendors here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key learnings are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We already had tooling for Remote First, but had hardly any need to use them properly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We were hardly using Email with all its glorious brokenness anymore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By happy accident, the core tools (FB at Work, Slack) had Places, not Groups, as a core metaphor, and people structured their work around these places.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborative document editing and a rich, structured chat complement each other well. But since Facebook and Google both are unable to make such a thing, we have yet another vendor integrated. This turned out to be an actual advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our key deficits have not been discussed at length here, but are related:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google Office documents have very bad discoverability and Google Office has no places.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corollary: A process is needed and needs to be manually executed to move content from the collaborative phase to the publication phase, elsewhere.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By public decree in our place this is going to be Confluence, which has problems of its own, and also poses a document conversion problem (from Google to Confluence internal format, keeping structure).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code Collaboration is not part of other collaboration at all, and lives in a third, and entirely disconnected space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pan Narrans and Better Meetings</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/10/10/pan-narrans-and-better-meetings.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 12:13:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/10/10/pan-narrans-and-better-meetings.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When you are looking for a better &lt;em&gt;Remote First&lt;/em&gt; culture, you are looking for better meetings.
If you go for better meetings, you will also have fewer of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/362504-the-anthropologists-got-it-wrong-when-they-named-our-species&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/pan-narrans-01.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The anthropologists got it wrong when they named our species Homo sapiens (&amp;lsquo;wise man&amp;rsquo;). In any case it&amp;rsquo;s an arrogant and bigheaded thing to say, wisdom being one of our least evident features. In reality, we are Pan narrans, the storytelling chimpanzee.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going for a written culture helps, going for storytelling will help even more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;storytelling&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#storytelling&#34;&gt;
	Storytelling
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost 15 years ago, I wrote about an experience with the roleplaying game &lt;em&gt;Primetime Adventures&lt;/em&gt;.
If you are reading German, &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2008/10/05/drsrm-2008-primetime-adventures.html&#34;&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things to take away from Primetime Adventures is that &amp;ldquo;on screen&amp;rdquo; nothing happens without reason, all interactions serve the story.
And the story is always about conflict:
Anything from misunderstandings to misaligned goals, from disagreement about a mission to disagreement about fundamental values, from friendly competition to outright fighting over starved resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end it does not matter, but screen time is always about the current conflict, because to the Storytelling Chimpanzee this is what it&amp;rsquo;s about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is, at the core, also true about meetings.
If they are not about conflict, they are not worth your time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does not have to be conflict about the people in the meeting.
The meeting does not have to resolve the conflict (but should progress it somewhow).
But in every meeting there is some kind of conflict in the background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember: Not all conflict is drama, in fact, most is not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;understanding-conflict&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#understanding-conflict&#34;&gt;
	Understanding conflict
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when you go for meetings, prepare an Agenda.
If you are invited to a meeting without an Agenda, decline it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is a good Agenda?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make an agenda and make it self-contained.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It should itemize the things you would like to talk about.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each item should have a short summary (&amp;ldquo;What happened so far&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Last week on …&amp;rdquo;) or link to one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should invite the people you need to talk to about the thing, the stakeholders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then send the agenda around well in advance, maybe share a link to a shared document.
Allow people to change, amend, and comment the agenda.
Force them to interact with the document in some way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your goal, ultimately, is to either not have a meeting, because all agree.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or have a meeting, but only about the things you disagree about.
Or people have questions about things, which can only be resolved interactively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So invite people to actually comment.
Invite long form, have them write in the text.
Sidenotes are horrible to read, and basically are good for &lt;strong&gt;+1&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/strong&gt; only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Invite people to agree with you, in the document, or to specify where the disagreement is exactly.
Disagreement can take many forms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can be insecurity (&amp;ldquo;The plan looks good in principle, but I fear that…&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can be misalignment (&amp;ldquo;You want to do …, but we actually need … on our side.&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can be resource shortage (&amp;ldquo;You want … from us, but that would require us to …, and we can&amp;rsquo;t do that in this Quarter.&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can be many other things. It always signals a need to communicate more, about a specific thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;commenting-on-agendas-kills-meetings&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#commenting-on-agendas-kills-meetings&#34;&gt;
	Commenting on Agendas kills meetings
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the Agenda and the Agenda Prep to collect agreement.
If there is no disagreement, it&amp;rsquo;s fine to not have the meeting, because the reason to have one just vanished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is disagreement, you now know where, and how, and what specifically is the perceived or real problem.
You can spend interactive time exactly on these things, and go over possible reconciliations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this is all in a shared document, y&amp;rsquo;all can amend the discussion with additional writing and sidenotes as needed.
This is automatically also the meeting notes, so make sure they contain whatever the outcomes are y&amp;rsquo;all collectively agreed to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark up deliverables, deadlines and people responsible.
Set a deadline with a followup meeting (which you can then try to kill in advance, too).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;kickoffs-cannot-be-killed&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#kickoffs-cannot-be-killed&#34;&gt;
	Kickoffs cannot be killed
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One exception are kickoff meetings.
They exist to present the project, and project goals, to set the framework and to make sure you are talking to the right people, and &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the right people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They exist also for socializing, specifically to enable people to make the necessary connections.
You will be working together, you need to know each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So make it short, to the point, and make sure people can connect with each other directly afterwards, on their own.
This is important, because kickoffs cannot be killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reporting-meetings-can-focus-on-interesting-stuff&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#reporting-meetings-can-focus-on-interesting-stuff&#34;&gt;
	Reporting meetings can focus on interesting stuff
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding conflict, isolating interesting topics to talk about, also applies to reporting meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reporting meetings always read a lot of slides with a lot of numbers.
Everybody zones out.
&amp;ldquo;Last weeks SLOs for … were met completely, and we improved …&amp;rdquo;
Nobody is interested, skip that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all can look at the green in the report in advance.
Instead use the reporting meeting to speak about interesting things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be the &lt;em&gt;story&lt;/em&gt; of an outage, and what we learned.
It can be about the &lt;em&gt;story&lt;/em&gt; of an improvement, and how it will prevent a certain class of failure.
Or tell the &lt;em&gt;story&lt;/em&gt; of how you work, how you improve work, or how you work differently than other companies do, if that is useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing &lt;em&gt;stories&lt;/em&gt; about practice is much more interesting that reading numbers from a slide that is all green anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or skip the meeting.
If the numbers are all fine and there are no learnings, no interaction is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;making-it-interesting-making-it-valuable&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#making-it-interesting-making-it-valuable&#34;&gt;
	Making it interesting, making it valuable
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, finding out, in advance, what the meeting should be about, always means finding the conflict, determining its nature, and the stakes.
Uneven information, misaligned goals, differences about implementation or scope, resource allocation, whatever.
Knowing this, maybe even preparing alternatives, and then either developing or discovering them interactively, or deciding on them collectively helps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also automatically prepares the meeting minutes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Agenda collects agreement, and preparing the meeting from the residual conflict in the Agenda then makes it simple to have minutes.
We have shared documents in 2022, so there is an easy way to make sure all voices are recorded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;providing-value&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#providing-value&#34;&gt;
	Providing value
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shared documents are also a burden:
They are hard to discover, maintain and organize.
I am increasingly a supporter of the idea that Google Docs should auto-delete after 3 months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want deliverables, put them elsewhere, anywhere.
Heck, even Confluence would be a better location than a Google Drive.
In any case, you can create a consolidated version of the current state in a proper document, and then collect or link the path that led to it and attach it as documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;rsquo;t take meeting notes and call them deliverables, though.
That won&amp;rsquo;t work.
It never did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So a discussion with interactive and written elements, is also a documentation evolution process, in which we collectively work on a deliverable: the architecture, documentation and implementation of a process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a proper store, and not in shared documents, much less in volatile spoken discussion without any record or recording.
We work to distill information, to shape an idea, and to bring it into the world, in a proper deliverable and in code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because that is what a company is about:
Making agreements on how we work together on a common thing (and building infrastructure to make this easier).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we have meeting agendas to collect agreement, and to sharpen disagreement, we have interactive meetings to find and ultimately document conflict resolutions, and we then put these back into the deliverable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the heart of asynchronous distributed collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if somebody asks you:
&amp;ldquo;What did your org learn to do differently in the last 3 years?&amp;rdquo;
and the answer is unlike the above:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did you do instead? How did your org evolve?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;addenda&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#addenda&#34;&gt;
	Addenda
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This started out as a Twitter thread.
There have been reactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Florian Haas pointed to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://xahteiwi.eu/resources/presentations/devopsdays-berlin-2022/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;really good writeup&lt;/a&gt;

 about writing of his.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He also mentions: &amp;ldquo;Re project kickoffs, never do them without preparing a 5-paragraph brief. Better still, circulate it ahead of the kickoff.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spaces</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/02/21/spaces.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/02/21/spaces.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On the morning of Saturday, 22nd February 2020, two years ago, my colleagues and I woke up to the a message from the company that said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Spaces&amp;rdquo; Closed for Operations 23 Feb - 28 Feb&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the morning hours of Saturday, 22 February, a fire occurred on the first floor of the &amp;ldquo;Spaces&amp;rdquo; building.
The fire was extinguished promptly but due to smoke and residue particles that spread throughout the building, we will not be able to open &amp;ldquo;Spaces&amp;rdquo; for at least one weeks time.
The closure of the building is required to ensure we fully inspect the building, our equipment, clean the office of all smoke damage and residue and more importantly, ensure we have a safe working environment to return to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It then took exactly one month instead of one week to fix that, and the planned reopening of the building fell on the exact day of the beginning of the COVID-19 lockdown.
So it has been today two years ago that I worked in an office the last time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote into a company forum one year ago:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be keeping this up until at least October, and I would be surprised if we are not going to be doing this for much longer the way this country handles Covid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this is the cluttered mess of my Desk at home:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/02/spaces-1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Home machine, and lab equipment to the left, company Mac on the desk during the daytime, bunch of books left and right. On top, the stick for my Internet Spaceship. Under the desk to the right, the file server and gaming box.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is very… lived in. I do change things too often for any pretty cabling or other cleanup to hold up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/02/spaces-2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;At least it has a decent view. That one hour commute to Spaces did pay off with a much more rural and spacious environment for home.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But at least the view from my Desk is decent…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am sitting on a Dauphin Shape XXL, a proper office chair instead of some gaming thing, and the desk is an older IKEA standing desk, motorized.
I have cabled Internet at my desk, Wifi by Unifi in the house, and we have a 500/500 Mbit fiber connection at home, because faster Internet is not available where I live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life ain’t bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never has been, actually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back, I always had a desk to work on at home. In Berlin, an entire room (which also had an office desk for my wife).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/02/spaces-3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Geek wife doing geek wifey things on her Berlin desk.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Karlsruhe, my GF and I had work desks in an office room, and actually almost never did use our living room.
We sat back to back, because that makes it easy to roll over and look at the other screen to check things out and help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Kiel we had an office/living room double room, but the living room really saw use only on Tuesdays ever other week for the Tuesday meeting, when a bunch of Geeks were coming around for cooking and talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even as a student, having a working desk was more important than a proper living room, actually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/02/spaces-4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1996 computer science student desk (see below &amp;ndash; 1)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I am thinking about it, I believe it’s because of my Dad.
He had a Ham Radio license, and “his” place in the house always was his shack, with all the electronics, the radios and antenna controls, basically a desk and a workbench next to it.
You’d find him more often there than anywhere else in the house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do we even have living rooms?
It’s a social convention that is hard to break.
I know that I would be in for a fight to the blood suggesting that we get rid of ours, but seriously?
“My” space is that desk/shack shown above, and not the living room.
It’s the place that I’ll fight for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussing this elsewhere, a friend sends me &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CJWOWksT1x4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Space &amp;ndash; A cluttered life: Middle-Class Abundance&lt;/a&gt;

.
The video discusses space use in American middle class families, who seem to have lives centered around the kitchen/eating space, which makes a lot of sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That 1996 desk.
That version of me had a Euro-ISDN semipermanent connection to my provider (128/128 kBit/s) and I also spent 50 Deutschmark for my own /24 provider independent IPv4 range.
All my machines had public addresses.
The machine is a Nextstation with 24 MB of memory, and a 25 MHz 68040 CPU, running what later would become MacOS X.
The white tower next to it has a 1 GB SCSI HDD full height (the two top slots), a 1x SCSI CD-ROM drive (Caddies required) and a SCSI QIC drive for DC 6525 tapes (525 MB/tape).
My body hides the full height tower case for the Dual-Pentium Linux box, you can only see the beige case of the b/w monitor it has.
We were using BNC based 10 MBit/s Ethernet at that time.
This box also has the ISDN card.
Unfortunately the driver had a memory leak, and we were losing a bit of memory every time the ISDN link goes up or down, because some driver internal data structures are allocated and never deallocated.
The loss accumulates to around 1 MB per week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Die kommende Kündigungswelle</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/11/12/die-kommende-kuendigungswelle.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Nov 2021 11:28:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/11/12/die-kommende-kuendigungswelle.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ein guter Freund sinnierte gestern mit anderen Freunden von mir über die Situation auf der Arbeit und schrieb mir heute:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wie man es auch dreht und wendet: Corona ist auch ein Lackmustest für Unternehmen in ihrer Rolle als Arbeitgeber.
Anhand der vierten Welle lässt sich das hervorragend nachvollziehen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denn Unternehmen und Organisationen, denen am Wohl ihrer Mitarbeiter/-innen etwas liegt, haben schon vor Wochen überall dort, wo es möglich ist, ihre Leute kategorisch wieder ins Homeoffice geschickt und Präsenzveranstaltungen untersagt.
Das hat selten etwas damit zu tun, dass diese Unternehmen herausragend schlau wären.
Viel mehr schauen diese Unternehmen sich ausgehend vom Wunsch, die eigenen Leute nicht zu gefährden, ihr Corona-Handling dort ab, wo es funktioniert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unternehmen beispielsweise, die sich an Israel orientieren, werden ihre Leute frühestens bei flächendeckender Booster-Impfung der eigenen Belegschaft wieder in die Büros rufen, falls überhaupt.
Unternehmen hingegen, die sich an den Richtlinien der deutschen Bundesregierung orientieren, pochen oft seit Wochen schon darauf, in die sich aufbauende vierte Welle hinein die Anwesenheitszeiten in den Büros zu erhöhen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist tragisch, weil es so vorhersehbar katastrophale wie vermeidbare Folgen haben wird.
Wer Leute notlos in den ÖPNV zwingt, obwohl sie nicht geboostert sind, exponiert sie unnötig einem erhöhten Risiko.
Wer Leute notlos ins Büro ruft, obwohl diese nicht impfbare Familienmitglieder im selben Haushalt haben, exponiert sie unnötig einem erhöhten Risiko.
Unternehmen, die so agieren, machen sich schuldig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Menschen in diesen Unternehmen sollten das Corona-Handling ihres Arbeitgebers jedenfalls genau beobachten.
Wer die Belegschaft unabhängig vom Impfstatus wieder ins Büro ruft, betreibt das Geschäft der Impfgegner.
Denn dann entsteht der Eindruck, der Impfstatus sei im Wesentlichen egal.
Wer nur geimpfte Menschen notlos ins Büro ruft, schafft dadurch indirekt sogar Incentives für Impfgegner, weil Homeoffice dann zu einem Privileg für diese wird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beides wäre unerträglich.
Und Menschen in diesen Firmen sollten ihren AG durchaus wissen lassen, dass das unerträglich ist.
Falls alle Stricke reißen:
Kündigen und Namen der Manager notieren, damit man in deren Fängen sicher nie mehr landet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bei den Amis heißt das &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Resignation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Great Resignation&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic has allowed workers to rethink their careers, work conditions, and long-term goals.
As many workplaces attempted to bring their employees in-person, workers desired the freedom to work from home given during the pandemic.
With telecommuting also came schedule flexibility, which was the primary reason to look for a new job of the majority of those studied by Bankrate in August 2021.
Additionally, many workers, particularly in younger cohorts, are seeking to gain a better work–life balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist die mildeste Formulierung, die ich gefunden habe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tatsächlich arbeiten &amp;ldquo;wir&amp;rdquo; im März 2022 seit 2 Jahren von zu Hause und/oder unter Pandemie-Bedingungen, und außerhalb der traditionellen Bürostrukturen und -hierarchien.
Einige Firmen haben sich anpassen können.
Von denen hat keine ein Problem mit Churn oder Hiring, also damit, Personal halten zu können und neues anzuwerben.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es sind die Läden, die die Realität der vergangenen 2 Jahre negieren, die jetzt bluten, und zwar vom Kopfe her.
Und Mitarbeiter, die seit 2 Jahren bewiesen haben, daß sie sehr gut und erfolgreich arbeiten können,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ohne daß sie jeden Tag 2 Stunden im Berufsverkehr verschwenden,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ohne daß das Kind als Schlüsselkind nach Hause kommen muss,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ohne daß ihnen das Management auf die Bildschirme glotzt,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;und ohne daß sie 3 von 8 Stunden pro Tag in Meetings zu bringen, von denen für sie maximal 20 Minuten relevant sind,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;solche Leute brechen jetzt auf - in Firmen, die anders arbeiten, in Berufe, die das nicht notwendig machen oder in ein Umfeld, das weniger dem späten 19. Jahrhundert verhaftet ist. Die Zukunft der Arbeit ist gerade angekommen, und die Leute ziehen um.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gerade bei den Wissensarbeitern ist das so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich habe 5 Jahre studiert und danach 3 Jahre Projekte gemacht und Dir jetzt gerade 2 Jahre lang bewiesen, daß ich mich selbst organisieren kann, und jetzt willst Du mich im Büro haben, damit Du Dich nicht so alleine fühlst?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kann man machen. Nicht schlau. So gar nicht.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit:&lt;/strong&gt; Nachtrag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jemand schickt mir diesen &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sueddeutsche.de/wirtschaft/overemployed-home-office-usa-1.5461910&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;paywalled link zur SZ&lt;/a&gt;

, von dem eh nur der Anreißer interessant ist. Der Artikel beschreibt unter dem Begriff &amp;ldquo;Overemployed&amp;rdquo; Personen, die im Homeoffice so effizient sind, daß sie zwei bezahlte Vollzeitstellen besetzen, ohne Wissen der jeweiligen Arbeitgeber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das geht natürlich nur mit &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bullshit_Jobs&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;David Graeber&amp;rsquo;s Bullshit Jobs&lt;/a&gt;

, aber es ist natürlich auch ein Zeichen dafür, daß die Arbeit, die diese Personen ausführen weder produktiv, noch notwendig noch sinnstiftend ist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich antwortete mit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich kann nur den Teaser lesen, aber das ist das, was wir im Informatik-Studium Semester 2 (und 4) gemacht haben.
Also 3 Leute in die Inf 2 Vorlesung schicken, parallel 3 Leute in Inf 4.
Mit dem Rest (gut 20 Leute, Rotationssystem) die Vorlesungen von 2x 90 Minuten in 45 Minuten durchziehen, und dann in 45 Minuten die Aufgaben machen.
Das hat sehr, sehr böses Blut gegeben&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Antwort war:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dafür hatten wir [bei uns] die Mitschriften AG. Etwas anderer Studienablauf bei Nicht-Informatikern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit:&lt;/strong&gt; Nachtrag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Einige Arbeitgeber insistieren dringend, daß &amp;ldquo;Mitarbeiter wenigstens einen Tag in der Woche im Büro sind&amp;rdquo;, ohne das näher zu begründen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bohrt man unauffällig und inoffiziell nach, heißt es &amp;ldquo;Wir haben sehr viele Expats, und wenn die statt von hier von ihrem Heimatland aus arbeiten, dann kommen wir von der Unternehmenssteuer her in Teufels Küche.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unter Umständen sollte man hier offener kommunizieren, und dann versuchen, kooperativ Lösungen zu finden, denn unerklärliches blockierendes Verhalten eines Arbeitgebers ist in diesem Zusammenhang nicht produktiv und führt wieder zur Kündigungswelle.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Du weisst nichts von Homeoffice</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/01/07/du-weisst-nichts-von-homeoffice.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 09:14:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/01/07/du-weisst-nichts-von-homeoffice.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.golem.de/news/spd-arbeitsministerium-will-recht-auf-homeoffice-per-gesetz-1901-138520.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Recht auf Homeoffice&lt;/a&gt;

 schreibt Golem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das SPD-geführte Bundesarbeitsministerium plant ein gesetzlich verankertes Recht auf Home Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und alle brüllen &amp;ldquo;Jaaaa!&amp;rdquo;.
Ich glaube, den meisten ist gar nicht klar, auf was sie sich da einlassen und wie sich eine Remote First-Firma anfühlt.
Wie dem auch sei:
Die Firma, in der Ihr gerade arbeitet, kann so mit Home Office vermutlich nicht gut funktionieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich habe von 2005 bis 2008 für MySQL AB gearbeitet, und das war eine Firma, die Remote First war.
Das war eine sehr andere Arbeitsumgebung als die, die ihr in Eurem Job vermutlich habt.
Wir waren circa 500 Mitarbeiter in drei Dutzend Ländern überall auf der Erde.
Es gab einen Firmensitz in Kalifornien und einen irgendwo in Skandinavien, aber dort war nie jemand (im Büro in Kalifornien waren ein paar Leute mehr, weil die dort den Börsengang der Firma vorbereitet haben).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Als Mitarbeiter hatte man einen gesonderten Raum daheim zu haben, der als Büro dient.
Die Firma hat einen gewissen Betrag pro Jahr (2500 Euro) bereitgestellt, um diesen Raum auszustatten oder zu verbessern.
Das schließt Arbeitsmaterial (Laptop) wie Büroausstattung (Stuhl, Tisch, etc pp) mit ein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weil es faktisch keine Firmenräume gab, gab es auch kein Firmen-VPN, denn das hätte den Zugang erschwert.
Stattdessen gab es einen Haufen Webdienste, über die die Kommunikation stattfand.
Diese waren verschlüsselt und mit einem Single Sign On versehen, aber generell von überall zugänglich von wo aus man eine TLS Verbindung bekommen konnte.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alle Diskussionen, internen Abstimmungen, Meetings, und Ergebnisse wurden über diese Webdienste, Skype, IRC und andere Online-Medien getroffen.
Die Arbeitszeiten waren oft schräg, weil die Firma über alle Zeitzonen der Erde verteilt war.
Und das heißt, man mußte schon mal um 3 Uhr morgens ran, um ein Meeting mit Leuten in Shanghai, Moskau und in Kalifornien gleichzeitig zu haben &amp;ndash; da gibt es einfach keine gute Zeitzone für alle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meetings über Videokonferenzen und Chatmedien sind schwierig, und Diskussionen über Mailinglisten sind oft hitzig und schwerfällig zugleich.
Es war notwendig, bestimmte Formen zu entwickeln und mit Leuten einzuüben.
Wenn man Leute aus einem Präsenzumfeld in eine Home Office Umgebung wirft, sind sie zunächst orientierungslos, unter Druck und einsam gleichzeitig.
Sie müssen an die Hand genommen werden, und man muß Ihnen Methoden und Formen aktiv zeigen, die ihnen erlauben, in so einer Umgebung zu funktionieren und sinnvoll zu kommunizieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am schwierigsten ist der Umgang mit der Tatsache, daß es keine Serendipität und keine aufwandslose Kommunikation gibt.
Diese Dinge, die man in Präsenzfirmen &amp;ldquo;nebenbei&amp;rdquo; mitbekommt, seitwärts, top-down und bottom-up, kommen in Home Office First Firmen nicht nebenbei.
Jeder, Management, Teamleiter, aber auch jeder einzelne Mitarbeiter, müssen lernen, daß jede Kommunikation einen Aufwand und Energie kostet, und man sich das Messaging genau überlegen muß.
Tut man das nicht, wird Zusammenhalt und gerichtete Aktion einem Firmenverbandes schwierig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zentral in MySQL waren übrigens die verschiedenen All Hands und Department Meeting Veranstaltungen.
Zweimal im Jahr hat sich gesamte Firma an einem Ort getroffen (meistens ein Fünf Sterne Hotel in einem gut erreichbaren Land mit entspannter Visa-Situation, in der Nachsaison), und zweimal im Jahr haben sich gesamte Abteilungen getroffen.
Auf diesen Events (jeweils drei bis fünf Tage) haben wir uns kennengelernt, ein Netzwerk aufgebaut, zusammen Kurzprojekte (&amp;ldquo;Hackathon&amp;rdquo;) durchgezogen und natürlich auch gefeiert.
Zusammen mit anderen Treffen hatte man so in etwa alle zwei Monate ein Gruppen-, Abteilungs-, oder Firmentreffen.
Alles in allem nicht wirklich eine Verbesserung der finanziellen und der CO2-Bilanz, aber notwendig um eine funktionierende Gruppe zu schaffen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The company as a social engine</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/08/07/the-company-as-a-social-engine.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 19:34:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/08/07/the-company-as-a-social-engine.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So why is everything so complicated? At work, I mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of a small company. A single person, a founder, is building her
business. She knows her way around, it&amp;rsquo;s all in her head: The plan, the
things that are important and why, and how they are to be executed. Also,
tradeoffs to be corrected later, potential opportunities for later and a lot
of other meta: Stuff that does not get executed right now, but that informs
decisions, priorities and preferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things work with some precision, though, like a well programmed wetware CPU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moment that stuff becomes too large for a single person to handle, more
people are involved and things need to be verbalized, written down, given
form. At that point, things change quite a bit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The task at hand is to program a second CPU, wetware, with a part of the
program that the first person has been executing. That&amp;rsquo;s necessary so she
can delegate, and the entire operation can scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, as with all remote procedure call mechanisms, complicated
unfolded in-memory structures have to serialized before the can be
marshalled off to a second node and are being re-instantiated over there. In
this particular case, the language to describe the code to be executed is
informally specified, too, and the remote CPU also does not match the specs
of the first CPU, that is, English is really bad for programming computers
or people, and also each person is different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make matters worse there is no proper debugger, the same broken language
has to be used to printf-debug the remote (&amp;ldquo;Do you understand what I mean?&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Do you understand why it is important that we do things this way?&amp;rdquo;) and
there may be other, older code in the remote that interferes with the
execution of our code. People have history and they have ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think of a company as a large distributed engine to execute code that
has been extracted painfully and incompletely from the wetware engine of a
founder, and which has been mangled due to improper serialization in a
language with limited expressiveness, you have a good idea of the corporate
environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;rsquo;t see what happens in the individual nodes, you can only observe the
communication between them, and the parts of the program that made it into
writing, or at least the Wiki. You can think of processes as written down
instructions for the engine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any process (&amp;ldquo;buy more paperclips&amp;rdquo;) describes who needs to talk to whom,
about what and why, in order to make things happen (&amp;ldquo;You need to create a
purchase order, which needs to be signed by &lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt; for values over &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; EUR in
order to limit our liability. The signed order is then sent to &lt;em&gt;Z&lt;/em&gt;, who will
actually spend money to buy stuff. You get stuff, and sign here to document
that.&amp;rdquo;)
Writing instructions and process down is important, and a great improvement
actually, because writing these instructions down forces all involves
parties (including the founders) to come clear about all the details and the
meta about the details - things that might have been existing only vaguely
in some mind, previously, now have to get a precise shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, they become tangible, and by the way of tangibility, they are open to
challenge, discussion and modification - which is why some founders are
actually resisting to give tangible form to certain things. Giving tangible
shape to instructions and the meta - why instructions, why these
instructions, why these instructions in this order with these emphasis - is
a complicated, painful and slow process, precisely because the originator of
an idea - the founder or some other person with an idea - has to give up the
idea and let it out into the world, where it will be subjected to change by
others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loss of control is always violent and painful, and as with any new thing
given a permanent form, there is always negotiation about the details.
Giving birth to anything: It&amp;rsquo;s exhausting. It&amp;rsquo;s not a one step process. A
founder has an idea and a plan, but in many parts it is still early,
untested and vague.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They put things into words, and the words are being tried out - can we work
by these instructions, or are there things unclear? Can the instructions
work, or does the plan need change? Can it be improved? Can it be applied to
other, similar things? Iterations happen. Do we go deep or wide - do we
specialize and improve this application of a plan, or do we try to apply the
plan as is to as many things as possible first?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, negotiation, and consequently, exhaustion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why is everything so complicated? Because companies are broken. All of
them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their engine, their program, their processes, are magnifications of the mind
of the founder or other influential people at the top. The entire corporate
mechanism is built to do exactly this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with this mechanism not only the original idea is being magnified and
copied to many minds, but other aspects of the original mind are, too. And
because the source was a person, with flaws, they too, are being magnified
and multiplied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you like it around here? Well, that&amp;rsquo;s because like all corporate
environments, this one is broken, too. It just so happens that the breakage
around here is more compatible with your own flaws than elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, your work environment sucks. They all do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find the one that sucks in a way that suits your needs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Erfahrungen mit Nonoffice</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2006/07/05/erfahrungen-mit-nonoffice.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2006 14:35:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2006/07/05/erfahrungen-mit-nonoffice.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Seit dem 1. November 2005 arbeite ich für MySQL Deutschland GmbH als Consultant. Damit mit bin ich Teil einer Firma mit 320 Mitarbeitern in 27 Ländern.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.c0t0d0s0.org/archives/1738-Erfahrungen-mit-Homeoffice.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ein Office habe ich noch nie gesehen&lt;/a&gt;

.
Einige der Kollegen, mit denen ich am engsten zusammenarbeite habe ich auch noch nie gesehen.
Die anderen sehe ich so alle paar Monate mal.
Die Zusammenarbeit ist gut und sehr intensiv.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Als ich von web.de zu MySQL gewechselt bin, war ich am Anfang sehr skeptisch und habe meine Interviewpartner gefragt, wie das denn wohl so ist, für eine &amp;ldquo;virtuelle&amp;rdquo; Firma zu arbeiten, in der die Kollegen so weit verstreut gesät sind.
Auch in den Fällen, in denen ich neue Kollegen interviewed habe ist dies die Frage, die mir in der Regel zuerst gestellt wird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meine Antwort auf diese Frage ist inzwischen &amp;ldquo;Hast Du einmal in irgendeinem Open-Source-Projekt mitgearbeitet und Dich mit den Leuten dort abstimmen müssen?&amp;rdquo;
Wenn die Antwort &amp;ldquo;ja&amp;rdquo; lautet (und damit man von MySQL interviewed wird, muss sie in der Regel &amp;ldquo;ja&amp;rdquo; lauten), kann ich antworten &amp;ldquo;Es ist genau wie da, nur daß Du Geld dafür bekommst.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In der Praxis sieht das so aus, daß MySQL über einen von mehreren Wegen einen Lead hereinbekommt, der vom Sales-Team entweder telefonisch oder vor Ort in einen Auftrag umgewandelt wird.
Sales geht dabei mit dem Presales-Support und einigen Fragebögen daher und produziert so ein Informationspaket, bei dem die Schedulerin und Consulting meist eine relativ gute Idee haben, was das Projekt ist und welche Fähigkeiten dabei gefordert sind.
Zusammen finden wir die passenden Personen zur Abwicklung des Projektes und machen mit dem Kunden und dem Consultant einen Terminplan.
Der Consultant reist dann an, macht sein Ding und reist einen glücklichen Kunden hinterlassend wieder ab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So die Theorie, und im Regelfall auch die Praxis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MySQL als Firma besteht aus einer an mehreren Stellen konzentrierten Infrastruktur, die Sales, Presales, Scheduling, Consulting, Training, aber auch Support, Development, Maintenance und den die betriebswirtschaftlichen Dinge abwickelnden Geschäftsstellen Dienste anbietet.
Diese Dienste sind, wo immer es geht, web-basierend und so gestaltet, daß sie so Browser-unabhängig sind wie irgend möglich.
Zu diesen Diensten gehören verschiedene Firmen-Wikis, einige Eventum-Taskmanager-Instanzen, der Teamkalender für Training und Consulting und viele andere Dinge.
Auch Nicht-Webdienste, etwa Bitkeeper, Continous Build Services, ein Firmen-IRC-Server, Mail- und Newsdienste und eine verteilte Asterisk-Installation gehören dazu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am Ende ist dies keine Sache, die so verschieden wäre von etwa dem Setup, das KDE intern verwendet, plus die Sales- und BWL-Seite dazu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Für mich als Consultant bedeutet dies, daß ich Zugriff auf meine Kollegen bei Consulting, Training und im Support habe, in dem ich Skype, Mail und IRC verwende.
Bei einer Firma, die so verteilt ist wie MySQL, ist zu jeder Tages- und Nachtzeit jemand zu sprechen, der mir helfen kann.
Wir kommunizieren dabei nicht nur dienstlich, sondern ich habe so wie beim normalen ircen auch einige gute Freunde gewonnen, von denen ich einen Teil noch nicht persönlich getroffen habe.
Die Zusammenarbeit ist noch intensiver beim Support-Team:
Arbeiten heißt für die ircen, und Tom Basil hat auf seine unvergleichliche Weise aus dem Team eine Art Familie gemacht, sodass &amp;ldquo;seine&amp;rdquo; Supporter (und einige Adoptivkinder aus anderen Abteilungen) quasi im Netz leben.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meine Arbeit organisiere ich weitgehend selbst:
Ich entscheide, wann ich arbeite, wie ich arbeite und was ich wie priorisiere.
MySQL folgt sehr strikt einem management-by-objectives Ansatz, sodass es letztendlich vollkommen egal ist, wie ich die Ziele erreiche, die ich mir mit meinem Team gesetzt habe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenn ich einen Home-Office-Tag habe, haue ich meistens morgens meine Mail weg.
Konkret bleibe ich auf dem Stand, was auf den Firmenmailinglisten so passiert, verfolge einige interessante Dinge im Bitkeeper und im Worklog, um bei der Weiterentwicklung des Servercodes auf Stand zu bleiben und beantworte die Mails, die Kunden reingeschickt haben, weil sie noch Fragen haben oder einfach nur so in Kontakt bleiben wollen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nach dem Mittag ist Papierkram angesagt:
Expenses, Engagement Summaries, Knowledge Base Entries oder Whitepapers und die dazu notwendigen Experimente, oder den folgenden Einsatz vorbereiten.
Dazu gehören auch die anstehenden Kundenanrufe, die ich inzwischen routinemäßig alle über SkypeOut abwickle.
Oder ich nehme mir den Nachmittag frei und erledige die Dinge am Abend, bei denen ich mich nicht mit Kunden synchronisieren muss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es kann auch sein, dass ich einen Remote Gig habe.
Dies ist in der Regel ein Einsatz bei einem Kunden in einer anderen Zeitzone, bei dem sich die Anreise wegen der Einsatzdauer nicht lohnt, oder wegen der Dringlichkeit nicht möglich ist.
In diesem Fall verschiebt sich mein Lebenszyklus ein wenig in Richtung der anderen Zeitzone, was mir natürlich ein wenig Freizeit zu ungewöhnlichen Zeiten beschert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meistens hat der Kunde einen Sprung-Host in seiner DMZ, auf den ich per &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt; draufklettern kann, und auf dem ich ihn dann bitte einen &lt;code&gt;screen&lt;/code&gt; zu starten.
Nachdem ich mich mit &lt;code&gt;screen -x&lt;/code&gt; an seine Session angeklemmt habe, bitte ich ihn, mich huckepack mit nach drinnen in sein Netz zu nehmen.
Über seinen Firmen-IRC-Server, über Skype oder über SkypeOut können wir nun reden, während wir uns eine Shell-Session im &lt;code&gt;screen&lt;/code&gt; teilen und er sehen kann, was ich tippe.
Dies ist für die Teile der Arbeit, die synchron erledigt werden müssen, in den meisten Fällen genauso effektiv als wäre ich vor Ort.
Asynchrones Arbeiten geht im Grunde genau so, nur daß ich idR einen &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt;-Login bekomme, mit dem ich zu meinen Zeiten alleine arbeiten kann.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Für die Dinge, die ich dabei auf eigenen Systemen ausprobieren muss, damit sie beim Kunden reibungslos klappen kann ich entweder auf meinem Laptop mit vmware Instanzen simulieren oder auf Rechnern in den firmeneigenen Labors in Cupertino oder Uppsala Rechenzeit reservieren.
Auch auf diese Rechner komme ich problemlos mit &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt; oder &lt;code&gt;rdesktop&lt;/code&gt; über das Firmen-VPN drauf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bei einem regulären Kundeneinsatz bin ich nicht alleine.
Ich bin vielleicht der einzige MySQL-Mitarbeiter vor Ort, aber hinter mir steht über GSM, openvpn, https-VPN oder ssh-Tunnel der Zugriff auf Support und meine Kollegen von Training und Consulting, die gerade nicht beim Kunden sind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Auch die Katze arbeitet inzwischen bei MySQL - in ihrem Fall als Entwicklerin.
Ihre Arbeit ist damit noch näher am KDE-Modell als meine:
Bitkeeper, UnitTest-Harnesses und Continuos Build-Prozeduren auf einer ganzen Reihe von Plattformen der Buildfarm sind ihre Freunde.
Scrum im Irc und im Wiki sind ebenso Standard-Prozesse für Entwickler wie der Umgang mit einem Bugtracker.
Und wie in jedem regulären Irc in anderen Open-Source-Projekten entwickeln sich auch dort Freundschaften und persönliche Kontakte.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entwickler fahren alle mindestens einmal im Jahr zur firmeninternen Developer Conference, die dieses Jahr in Sorrento in Italien stattfand.
Dort finden sich auch Abgesandte aller anderen Abteilungen, sodass dies eine ausgezeichnete Methode ist, um bisher virtuelle Freundschaften einmal mit Personen und Gesichtern zu verbinden.
Weitere Gelegenheiten dieser Art sind die US-amerikanische und die europäische User Conference, MySQL Usergroup-Treffen, bei denen man neben Anwendern auch Kollegen aus demselben geografischen Gebiet treffen kann, und natürlich Abteilungsmeetings.
Wir in Consulting streben drei solcher Treffen im Jahr an, und für die anderen Abteilungen geschieht dies nach Bedarf&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alles in allem kann ich nach 9 Monaten MySQL sagen, daß dies die fremdartigste Firma ist, in der ich je gearbeitet habe.
Keine &amp;ldquo;casual communication&amp;rdquo;, keinen Flurfunk zu haben, ist manchmal etwas anstrengend und kostet sicherlich mehr Energie als in einer traditionellen Firma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andererseits habe ich mich sofort zu Hause gefühlt:
Während MySQL als Firma fremdartig ist, sind mir die Methoden der Zusammenarbeit vertraut, denn ich habe sie außerhalb der Firma in den Projekten, an denen ich mitgearbeitet habe, jahrelang gelebt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neu ist im Grunde nur, daß das, was vorher mein Hobby war, jetzt mein Leben ist.
Ein anstrengendes, spannendes und überaus aufregendes Leben.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also liebe Kollegen, bekannter und unbekannterweise:
Wie ist es für Euch gewesen, als ihr hier angefangen habt?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

