<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>sonos on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/sonos.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in sonos on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2022 16:38:41 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/sonos/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Sonos just got complicated</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/06/09/sonos-just-got-complicated.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 09:18:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/06/09/sonos-just-got-complicated.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So this morning the 08:10 alarm in the living room did not go off. It was set to remind the son that it is time to get going for school. We noticed in time, but when I looked into the &amp;ldquo;Why?&amp;rdquo; things got interesting. That alarm is a chime from the household Sonos system, and when I investigated, I got this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/06/sonos-s1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sonos did the split and upgraded/rebranded their controller operating system to S1.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Sonos did their thing and split their universe. There is S1, the Sonos application that is as-is and that can talk to all the hardware we have. And there is, or will be, S2, the new software. Devices running S1 cannot talk to S2 controller applications, and cannot be grouped with devices running S2 and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some older devices, notably our two Play:5.1, cannot be upgraded to S2. Some newer devices, presumably everything they build in the future, cannot be downgraded ot S1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nobody wants two apps, and two Sonos networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nobody wants to throw out perfectly good speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very unsatisfying situation, and a completely unnecessary one, to boot. I get that a single-core PPC CPU with 32 MB of memory and 32 MB of flash has limitations. I also know that newer devices are Raspi-4 like devices with up to 4 cores, 1024 MB of memory and 1024 MB of flash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sonos decided to split universes instead of dumbing down old devices to remote-controlled WAV/MP3 stream receivers and running the control software on any of the more powerful devices in a network. Sonos decided to not sell a Raspi 4-like Controller box for legacy devices in a nice chassis as a maintenance upgrade for legacy speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sonos always was known for long-term support of their devices, and Sonos was always known for making things simple and just work. They completely failed at any of these, their core values, with their S2 migration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that is not even looking at the completely botched communication around this entire thing, with the explanation-less announcement of the trade-in program, and the completely messed up bricking-program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wife decided that we are too invested into this stuff to get rid of it short term, but put a purchase moratorium on new Sonos stuff into place. &amp;ldquo;And&amp;rdquo;, she said, &amp;ldquo;even if they get out of that, say, mid-2021, it&amp;rsquo;s still IKEA only. At least that keeps the financial risk under control.&amp;rdquo; Yup, downgraded from prime tier to consumer tier and a one year term on the bench.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sonos recycled their recycle mode</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/03/06/sonos-recycled-their-recycle-mode.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2020 08:40:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/03/06/sonos-recycled-their-recycle-mode.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So I wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/12/30/sonos-recycle-mode.html&#34;&gt;the Sonos Recycle Program&lt;/a&gt;

 before Sonos announced their plans to actively discontinue support for their older Speakers. Back then, the program did make sense, because it was kind of voluntary and avoided sending stuff back to Sonos for a Trade-Up. Even then, people disliked it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then Sonos announced that they would discontinue support for these devices and it&amp;rsquo;s basically &amp;lsquo;you brick them now, or we are going to brick them for you in May and without a rebate for new equipment&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.engadget.com/2020/03/05/sonos-kills-its-device-bricking-recycle-mode/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sonos announced that they will recycle Recycle Mode&lt;/a&gt;

, that is, they will allow you to &amp;ldquo;trade up&amp;rdquo; for newer devices, but the old ones will still work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-that-does-not-answer-the-actual-question&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#but-that-does-not-answer-the-actual-question&#34;&gt;
	But that does not answer the actual question
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or won&amp;rsquo;t. From the article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, it&amp;rsquo;s worth noting that Sonos hasn&amp;rsquo;t changed its plans to stop updating those legacy products come May. As a reminder, they&amp;rsquo;ll work as they do now but won&amp;rsquo;t receive new features or software updates going forward. But if you have some of those products and are ready for new gear, you can get a discount and still keep them working as long as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So everything is still unclear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is, there will be no updates for any Play:5 (1st gen) devices, for the Connect:Amp and the Connect any more. We know that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it is unclear if these older devices will still work together with updated devices in the same network, and if you still will be able to group them. It would be a big loss of functionality if that does not work any more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is unclear, if &amp;ldquo;No Updates&amp;rdquo; means &amp;ldquo;No functional updates&amp;rdquo; or if they will effectively brick themselves when Streaming Service APIs change, a root certificate rollover has to be implemented or similar maintenance software changes are necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-sonos-focus&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#what-is-sonos-focus&#34;&gt;
	What is Sonos focus?
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, while Sonos is trying to play in the Home Voice Gadget market, their Sound Experience is increasingly looking long in the tooth. I mean, the actual sound the things make is pretty nice, but getting signals into Sonos Systems is somewhat ugly. I now have a Bluetooth Speaker (Non-Sonos) attached to my Windows Steam Machine, because I can&amp;rsquo;t Wi-Fi my &amp;ldquo;Elite: Dangerous&amp;rdquo; to my Sonos easily. How about the Desktop App being a Sound Source for the Speakers? Right, can&amp;rsquo;t do that unless the source is a Mac and the target is… the only IKEA speaker in my home. That&amp;rsquo;s pretty lame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/03/sonos-airplay.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Windows System Output can&amp;rsquo;t be used as a Sound Source for Sonos. And Airplay does not work to most of my speakers, because they are &amp;ldquo;too old&amp;rdquo; and the new Sonos equipment does not relay to the old equipment.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile I have to use the clunky Sonos App for my &amp;ldquo;Youtube Music&amp;rdquo; subscription on my phone, because while I can chromecast my Google Music to Sonos, for some reason Youtube Music can&amp;rsquo;t do that. Again, a problem with sourcing the stream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company seems to be obsessed with Home Assistants, when it should be obsessed about Sound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, yeah. What am I going to do? I don&amp;rsquo;t know. At this point, I will wait and see - I have halted all spending on them for this year, and if I am ever going to push money into the Sonos equipment at all any more, it&amp;rsquo;s probably going to IKEA. At least that are somewhat controllable sums for equipment with whatr is now an officially limited lifetime. Well, it was nice while it lasted.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sonos Recycle Mode</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/12/30/sonos-recycle-mode.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 15:02:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/12/30/sonos-recycle-mode.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sonos is a company that makes Wi-Fi Connected speakers. They
offer acceptable sound quality and an extremely good user
experience. They also so far have never cancelled support for
any of their speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hardware-lineup-and-timeline&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#hardware-lineup-and-timeline&#34;&gt;
	Hardware Lineup and Timeline
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of their speakers are now qualified for a Trade-Up program,
in particular their&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Play:5 (1st generation) speaker,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Connect:Amp and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Connect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latter two (the Connect products) are somewhat obsolete as
they were necessary when normal Wi-Fi was usually not able to
carry sound data at the required reliability, so Sonos speakers
built their own Wi-Fi Mesh network separately from the usual home
Wi-Fi. With newer Wi-Fi standards and recently also 5 Ghz this was
no longer necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Play:5 (1st generation) speaker, the only one currently
qualified for Trade-Up appeared, in 2009, 10 years ago. It was
replaced by the 2nd generation in 2015.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Play:3 appeared in July 2011, and was discontinued in July 2018.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Play:1 appeared in October 2013, and was replaced by the
Play One (1st generation) in October 2017. The second generation
Play One added Bluetooth Hardware and a much fatter SOC and even
more memory only one year later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I have no idea what kind of hardware the Play:5
platform was built on in 2009. I have only looked into a Play:3
from 2013. That box had a PPC based single core CPU and 64 MB
of memory. Current Sonos hardware is using, IIRC, Multicore ARM
SOCs and have at least four times the amount of memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of Trade-Up, currently only the Play:5 (1st gen)
qualifies. It is pretty clear that the Play:3 will be qualifying
soon, too - maybe in 2020, but in 2021 for sure. In terms of
long-term value, owners of the 1st gen Play One are probably
currently worst off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;trade-up&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#trade-up&#34;&gt;
	Trade-Up
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trade-Up is advertised as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2019/12/sonos-trade-up.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You select a device for Trade-Up, and receive a voucher for a
30% rebate on the purchase of a new device. You then have 21
days left to use the old device, after which time it will
permanently cease to function. You can use the voucher to
purchase any new Sonos device, replace the old one and ship the
old device to whatever recycling services in your area accept
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is a normal Trade-Up program, minus the part where you
uselessly ship the old hardware across the country to the maker,
which will then hand it over to a recycling service instead of
you doing this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can still continue to use the old device as long as it is
supported, you can still sell the old device to others, as long
as it is supported, and you can do whatever else is possible
with the old hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#why&#34;&gt;
	Why?
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is pretty clear where this is aiming: Sonos is looking at the
oldest hardware in their lineup and that this hardware is
becoming pretty long in the tooth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially the limited amount of memory makes it increasingly
difficult to even install the most current versions of their
software. New functionality such as Airplay 2, and new services
require more memory and, in case of Airplay 2 also more CPU and
more Wi-Fi bandwidth than 10 year old piece of hardware
has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They would like to shrink the installed base of their outdated
hardware in order to be able to move forward technologically.
They would like to offer their long-time customers some kind of
bonus and way to upgrade before they have to disable the
hardware because it cannot longer be supported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not having to ship the hardware back to Sonos should be a plus,
not a minus. Instead there is a pretty hard blowback on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people criticise that this bricks the device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is kind of the point in a Trade-Up.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

