<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>devops on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>/tags/devops.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in devops on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/devops/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Empty commits and other wrong tools for the job</title>
      <link>/2021/10/06/empty-commits-and-other-wrong-tools-for-the-job.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/10/06/empty-commits-and-other-wrong-tools-for-the-job.html</guid>
      <description>This is how you can make an empty commit:
$ git commit --allow-empty -m &amp;#34;Kick it&amp;#34; This has the disadvantage of also generating a commit message. Another way to achieve this seems to be
$ git commit --amend --no-edit &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git push -f but that will make people hate you in other ways.
So lets stop and ask: Why would you want to make an empty commit?
Most people want this because they attached a server-side action to a commit, a CI/CD activity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Python to bash</title>
      <link>/2021/01/05/using-python-to-bash.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/05/using-python-to-bash.html</guid>
      <description>Heise writes an introduction to bash programming (in german) :
 Bash ist eine vollwertige Programmiersprache, mit der Sie alltägliche Aufgaben leicht automatisieren.
Bash is a fully featured programming language that you can use to automate everyday tasks.
 Bash is not a fully featured programming language at all, and nothing in bash is ever easy. You are advised to use a proper programming language early on in development, and if possible never put bash commands into a file.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Embracing the Stream</title>
      <link>/2020/12/09/embracing-the-stream.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/12/09/embracing-the-stream.html</guid>
      <description>So this happened: CentOS Project shifts focus to CentOS Stream  The future of the CentOS Project is CentOS Stream, and over the next year we’ll be shifting focus from CentOS Linux, the rebuild of Red Hat Enterprise Linux (RHEL), to CentOS Stream, which tracks just ahead of a current RHEL release. CentOS Linux 8, as a rebuild of RHEL 8, will end at the end of 2021. CentOS Stream continues after that date, serving as the upstream (development) branch of Red Hat Enterprise Linux.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gitlab in Docker</title>
      <link>/2020/11/22/gitlab-in-docker.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/11/22/gitlab-in-docker.html</guid>
      <description>These installation notes are mostly a note to myself, documenting the installation process of a Gitlab Omnibus Container in Docker, plus Gitlab Runners.
OS Setup   We are installing into /export/gitlab, a 10G xfs slice from the local flash pool:
# lvcreate -n gitlab -L 10G data # mkfs -t xfs /dev/data/gitlab # mkdir /export/gitlab # mount /dev/data/gitlab /export/gitlab # echo &amp;#34;/dev/data/gitlab\t/export/gitlab\txfs\tbsdgroups,usrquota,grpquota,attr2,nofail,noatime 1 2&amp;#34; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; /etc/fstab # mkdir /export/gitlab/{gitlab,gitlab-runner} # mkdir /export/gitlab/gitlab/{config,data,logs} Docker   We are using docker-compose to run this, with a .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the Observability of Outliers</title>
      <link>/2020/11/19/on-the-observability-of-outliers.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/11/19/on-the-observability-of-outliers.html</guid>
      <description>At work, I am in an ongoing discussion with a number of people on the Observability of Outliers. It started with the age-old question “How do I find slow queries in my application?” aka “What would I want from tooling to get that data and where should that tooling sit?”
 As a developer, I just want to automatically identify and isolate slow queries!
 Where I work, we do have SolarWinds Database Performance Monitor aka Vividcortex to find slow queries, so that helps.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Touching Candles, And Error Budgets</title>
      <link>/2020/08/31/on-touching-candles.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/31/on-touching-candles.html</guid>
      <description>Ok, it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Dad Stories&amp;rdquo; Time (from Twitter ). When my son was somewhat older than a year, he was learning to speak. He could already say &amp;ldquo;Mama&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Papa&amp;rdquo;.
It was around Christmas, and there was a candle on the table, glowing interestingly, so he wanted to touch it. &amp;ldquo;Nein, heiß&amp;rdquo; is what you would say in German.
Of course, a toddler does not understand the meaning of &amp;ldquo;heiß&amp;rdquo;. I mean, he&amp;rsquo;s trying to imitate the sound of it, but the meaning of &amp;ldquo;heiß&amp;rdquo; is something specific.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waffle House Index of Tooling</title>
      <link>/2020/06/08/waffle-house-index-of-tooling.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/08/waffle-house-index-of-tooling.html</guid>
      <description>Charity Majors was on fire and on target, again :
 What is a Waffle House Index ?
 The Waffle House Index is an informal metric named after the Waffle House restaurant chain and is used by the Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA) to determine the effect of a storm and the likely scale of assistance required for disaster recovery.
 A &amp;ldquo;Waffle House Index for Tooling&amp;rdquo; would be an indicator how bad the situation on the ground in an IT department is.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rolling back a rollout</title>
      <link>/2020/01/17/rolling-back-a-rollout.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/17/rolling-back-a-rollout.html</guid>
      <description>Florian Haas asks on Twitter :
&amp;ldquo;How do you solve reliable rollback. The definition of a reliable rollback being: &amp;lsquo;get reset &amp;ndash;hard &amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;git push -f&amp;rsquo; and then magic happening that returns your infra to the exact state it was at .&amp;rdquo;
The problem is relatively easy to solve with modern infrastructure-as-code for anything that is stateless. It becomes a bit more involved when you are dealing with things with state, such as database instances or Zookeepers or similar things.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Be simple. Be boring. Be obvious.</title>
      <link>/2016/09/01/be-simple-be-boring-be-obvious.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/09/01/be-simple-be-boring-be-obvious.html</guid>
      <description>On Core.Infra day, I was invited to speak. This is my talk. There were many like it, but this was mine.
In operations, code is not your friend.   This is about what I did the two years I have not been around here. I first worked for Booking in 2006 as a MySQL consultant doing databasey things. I joined Booking as an employee later, in 2008. By then, I was working in Amsterdam, but living in Berlin, so I was flying around quite a bit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Go away, or I will replace you with a very small shell script</title>
      <link>/2015/03/27/go-away-or-i-will-replace-you.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/03/27/go-away-or-i-will-replace-you.html</guid>
      <description>This is the writeup for the english variant of the talk &amp;ldquo;Go away or I will replace you with a very small Shell script&amp;rdquo;. The original version of the talk was given in German at GUUG FFG 2015 in Stuttgart. A recorded version in german language has been made at Froscon in August 2015.
Go Away Or I Will Replace You With A Very Small Shell Script or There Is No Such Thing As A Devops Team</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
