<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>cycling on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>/tags/cycling.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in cycling on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/cycling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Safe Biking: It&#39;s not the right of way that&#39;s wrong</title>
      <link>/2020/10/22/safe-biking-its-not-the-right-of-way-thats-wrong.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/22/safe-biking-its-not-the-right-of-way-thats-wrong.html</guid>
      <description>Sven Geggus trolled me . A bunch of nerds were speaking about what&amp;rsquo;s wrong with biking in Germany, and he wrote:
 Tweet : Der @isotopp wohnt doch in Holland. Wo sind denn bei euch die Vorfahrtsregeln anders und könnte man da was sinnvoll für .de übernehmen? &amp;ndash; @isotopp is living in the Netherlands. So how is the right of way different and how could .de learn from this?
Biking in the Netherlands does not suck, and that is not because of any specific traffic rules being any different, but because traffic is fundamentally different, and that somehow escalated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In which we cycle shopping...</title>
      <link>/2020/02/22/in-which-we-cycle-shopping.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/22/in-which-we-cycle-shopping.html</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the Netherlands. Please excuse me, I need to fetch a few things before I have time for you. I need a few things from Lidl in Hoofddorp, do you want to come with me?
It&amp;rsquo;s not far, we are taking the bike for some six kilometres. Also, I&amp;rsquo;m going to show you a trick: Look, Mom! Not riding with the cars, and no lights.
 Let&amp;rsquo;s follow path and go down Liniepad.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to build a cycling environment</title>
      <link>/2020/02/19/how-to-build-a-cycling-environment.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/19/how-to-build-a-cycling-environment.html</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the Netherlands. We&amp;rsquo;re building roads differently. They are better, safer and less stressful for cyclists, and that also makes them better, safer and less stressful for motorists. Here is how it works:
(based on a Twitter Thread )
What does it look like?   I am living in a village. That means a speed limit of 30 km/h inside the city limits, and that is being enforced by the design of the road.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
