<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>talk on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/talk.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in talk on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/talk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Journey to Open Compute</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2018/02/21/a-journey-to-open-compute.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2018/02/21/a-journey-to-open-compute.html</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, Booking.com hosted the Open Compute Meetup in Amsterdam. My talk is on Slideshare and a recording is on Youtube.
 Slideshare: A journey to OCP  Youtube: A journey to OCP   A cleaned up and more coherent transcript of the talk is here: Booking.com started out as a small online travel agency in Amsterdam, but is now financially about 15% of Google. We have about 200 offices in 70 countries, support 46 languages and reach about any touristically interesting spot on this planet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Be simple. Be boring. Be obvious.</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2016/09/01/be-simple-be-boring-be-obvious.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2016/09/01/be-simple-be-boring-be-obvious.html</guid>
      <description>On Core.Infra day, I was invited to speak. This is my talk. There were many like it, but this was mine.
In operations, code is not your friend.   This is about what I did the two years I have not been around here. I first worked for Booking in 2006 as a MySQL consultant doing databasey things. I joined Booking as an employee later, in 2008. By then, I was working in Amsterdam, but living in Berlin, so I was flying around quite a bit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Go away, or I will replace you with a very small shell script</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2015/03/27/go-away-or-i-will-replace-you.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2015/03/27/go-away-or-i-will-replace-you.html</guid>
      <description>This is the writeup for the english variant of the talk &amp;ldquo;Go away or I will replace you with a very small Shell script&amp;rdquo;. The original version of the talk was given in German at GUUG FFG 2015 in Stuttgart. A recorded version in german language has been made at Froscon in August 2015.
Go Away Or I Will Replace You With A Very Small Shell Script or There Is No Such Thing As A Devops Team</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
