<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tv on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/tv.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in tv on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 09:27:19 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/tv/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Die Grauen Herren vs. das Internet</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2008/05/06/die-grauen-herren-vs-das-internet.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2008 07:46:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2008/05/06/die-grauen-herren-vs-das-internet.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://orionmagazine.org/article/the-gospel-of-consumption/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Gospel of Consumption&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;despite the apparent tidal wave of new consumer goods and what appeared to be a healthy appetite for their consumption among the well-to-do, industrialists were worried.
They feared that the frugal habits maintained by most American families would be difficult to break.
Perhaps even more threatening was the fact that the industrial capacity for turning out goods seemed to be increasing at a pace greater than people&amp;rsquo;s sense that they needed them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was this latter concern that led Charles Kettering, director of General Motors Research, to write a 1929 magazine article called &amp;ldquo;Keep the Consumer Dissatisfied.&amp;rdquo;
He wasn&amp;rsquo;t suggesting that manufacturers produce shoddy products.
Along with many of his corporate cohorts, he was defining a strategic shift for American industry from fulfilling basic human needs to create new ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und die Statistiken dazu:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, by 2000 the average married couple with children was working almost five hundred hours a year more than in 1979. [&amp;hellip;]
By 1991 the amount of goods and services produced for each hour of labor was double what it had been in 1948.
By 2006 that figure had risen another 30 percent. [&amp;hellip;] if as a society we made a collective decision to get by on the amount we produced and consumed seventeen years ago, we could cut back from the standard forty-hour week to 5.3 hours per day or 2.7 hours if we were willing to return to the 1948 level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noch spannender sind die historischen Hintergründe dazu in dem Aritkel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was tun mit der freien Zeit?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/jm3/6724931&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Clay Shirky&lt;/a&gt;

 schreibt dazu:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had to pick the critical technology for the 20th century, the bit of social lubricant without which the wheels would&amp;rsquo;ve come off the whole enterprise, I&amp;rsquo;d say it was the sitcom.
Starting with the Second World War a whole series of things happened&amp;ndash;rising GDP per capita, rising educational attainment, rising life expectancy and, critically, a rising number of people who were working five-day work weeks.
For the first time, society forced onto an enormous number of its citizens the requirement to manage something they had never had to manage before &amp;ndash; free time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what did we do with that free time?
Well, mostly we spent it watching TV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shirky sieht die freie Zeit als &amp;ldquo;kognitiven Überschuss&amp;rdquo;, den wir verschwendet haben, weil keine Infrastruktur da war, um ihn sinnvoll anzuwenden.
Mit dem Internet, so argumentiert er, ändert sich das nun:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how big is that surplus?
So if you take Wikipedia as a kind of unit, all of Wikipedia, the whole project &amp;ndash; every page, every edit, every talk page, every line of code, in every language that Wikipedia exists in &amp;ndash; that represents something like the cumulation of 100 million hours of human thought.
I worked this out with Martin Wattenberg at IBM; it&amp;rsquo;s a back-of-the-envelope calculation, but it&amp;rsquo;s the right order of magnitude, about 100 million hours of thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And television watching?
Two hundred billion hours, in the U.S. alone, every year.
Put another way, now that we have a unit, that&amp;rsquo;s 2,000 Wikipedia projects a year spent watching television.
Or put still another way, in the U.S., we spend 100 million hours every weekend, just watching the ads.
People asking, &amp;ldquo;Where do they find the time?&amp;rdquo; when they&amp;rsquo;re looking at things like Wikipedia don&amp;rsquo;t understand how tiny that entire project is, as a carve-out of this asset that&amp;rsquo;s finally being dragged into what Tim calls an architecture of participation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und das ist es seltsamerweise auch, was ich antworte, wenn ich gefragt werde, wo ich denn all die Zeit hernehme, um all die Dinge zu lesen und zu schreiben, die ich so mache.
Ich sehe in meinen produktiven Phasen kaum fern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aber die Veränderung geht noch weiter:
Es wächst nun eine Generation heran, für die passive Konsumentenmedien seltsam wirken:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was having dinner with a group of friends about a month ago, and one of them was talking about sitting with his four-year-old daughter watching a DVD.
And in the middle of the movie, apropos nothing, she jumps up off the couch and runs around behind the screen.
That seems like a cute moment.
Maybe she&amp;rsquo;s going back there to see if Dora is really back there or whatever.
But that wasn&amp;rsquo;t what she was doing.
She started rooting around in the cables.
And her dad said, &amp;ldquo;What you doing?&amp;rdquo;
And she stuck her head out from behind the screen and said, &amp;ldquo;Looking for the mouse.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s something four-year-olds know:
A screen that ships without a mouse ships broken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s something four-year-olds know:
Media that&amp;rsquo;s targeted at you but doesn&amp;rsquo;t include you may not be worth sitting still for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bei Netzpolitik gibt es quasi passend dazu eine
&lt;a href=&#34;http://netzpolitik.org/2008/forderungen-fuer-eine-zeitgemaesse-netzpolitik-20/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Liste von Forderungen für eine zeitgemäße Netzpolitik&lt;/a&gt;

.
Die Umsetzung dieser Forderungen in einer sinnvollen Urheberrechtsreform und einem Regulierungsrahmen würden die oben diskutierte Entwicklung noch fördern und in die richtigen Bahnen lenken:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Öffentlich geförderte Informationen müssen den Bürgern unter offenen Lizenzen bereitgestellt werden.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fernsehen und Radio sind tot! Die Inhalte des Öffentlich-Rechtlichen Systems müssen im Netz frei zugänglich sein.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Öffentlich-Rechtlich ins digitale Zeitalter überführen! Digitale Strukturen und Communities, die Informationen des öffentlichen Interesses produzieren, müssen gefördert werden.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open Source fördern! Open Source Communities sind essenziell für die Kulturproduktion des 21. Jahrhunderts und schaffen unbestreitbare gesellschaftliche Mehrwerte.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freie und anonyme Kommunikationswege erhalten&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demokratie öffnen heißt Transparenz wagen! Staatliche Informationen gehören unter offene Lizenzen. Informationsfreiheit muss praktiziert werden, geredet wurde schon genug.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Staatliche Infrastrukturen befreien! Nur offene Standards und die Verwendung freier Software garantieren einen diskriminierungsfreien und nachhaltigen Zugriff auf Vorgänge und Abläufe in Politik und Verwaltung.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Internet ist Grundversorgung. Kommunen müssen jedem Bürger einen Basiszugang zum Internet ermöglichen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Urheberrecht reformieren! Das Urheberrecht muss den gesellschaftlichen Realitäten angepasst werden - nicht die gesellschaftlichen Realitäten dem Urheberrecht.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gleiche Chancen für alle! Die Netzneutralität muss festgeschrieben werden: Es darf keine Klassengesellschaft im Netz entstehen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Medienkompetenz für Politiker: Wir brauchen Politiker, für die das Internet kein Fremdkörper ist. Wir brauchen Medien-kompetente Politiker, die es sich nicht erst ausdrucken lassen müssen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aber wie im ersten Text in den historischen Hintergründen beleuchtet ist eine partizipatorische Demokratie gar nicht gewünscht.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

