<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Work on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/work.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Work on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 13:53:55 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/work/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Practice</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2024/07/01/practice.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 05:06:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2024/07/01/practice.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some things come to me very slowly and painfully.
In this particular case, it’s because I’ve been immersed in an environment where a certain type of activity,
&lt;em&gt;Practice Building&lt;/em&gt;, was done implicitly by everyone around me.
The environment itself facilitated this implicitly as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I entered a new environment where this practice was not performed and the means to facilitate it were not present,
it became really hard to communicate what was missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-technology-radar&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#the-technology-radar&#34;&gt;
	The Technology Radar
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an old work environment, a manager was tasked with or had the idea to implement a &amp;ldquo;Technology Radar.&amp;rdquo;
A
&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/blog/technology-strategy/how-to-create-your-enterprise-technology-radar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Technology Radar&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;
is a process where companies organize the &amp;ldquo;things they use&amp;rdquo; into arbitrary quadrants that make sense to them.
For IT, &amp;ldquo;techniques,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;tools,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;platforms,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;languages and frameworks&amp;rdquo;
seem to be popular but somewhat useless for hierarchical searching.
On the other hand, it produces nicer graphics than a &amp;ldquo;Dewey Decimal System for Tech&amp;rdquo; graphed out,
even if the latter would be systematically more useful to build structure and visualize relationships and alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create a &amp;ldquo;radar-like&amp;rdquo; appearance, the &amp;ldquo;things we use&amp;rdquo; are then assigned one of four statuses,
from the inside out: &amp;ldquo;adopt,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;trial,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;assess,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;hold.&amp;rdquo;
What these mean is usually not well understood and often contested.
Actually,
75% of the time in the panel discussions for a Tech Radar is wasted
because people don&amp;rsquo;t understand what these statuses are supposed
to mean or the consequence of assigning a status to a tech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/blog/technology-strategy/how-to-create-your-enterprise-technology-radar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/07/practice-01.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What a Tech Radar looks like.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The statuses could be &amp;ldquo;test this and tell us,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;immature but shiny,&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;tried and tested,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;actually no, but some of us need it,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;hell no.&amp;rdquo;
But that is not what we got, hence the discussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It matters not.
You could repair the Tech Radar,
but it would still not be the thing that is needed, but a weak simulation of what is actually required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the other thing that comes to light as part of the technology radar is that people want more:
To understand how a certain technology fits into the company, they do not only need a recommendation,
they also need context, recommendations, and best practices, and ultimately
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/04/15/sql-engineering-guidelines.html&#34;&gt;an engineering guide&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is,
what process builds such context, recommendations, and practices,
and what is needed as a precondition for such a process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-catalog-of-skills-and-expertise&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#a-catalog-of-skills-and-expertise&#34;&gt;
	A catalog of skills and expertise
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing that happens in almost any company is
that somebody comes up with the brilliant idea
of asking people about the things they are good at and to assess themselves in these areas.
You know, like a LinkedIn résumé or skill catalog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then you end up with a database of expertise that is not only incomplete for each individual
but also never updated and ultimately useless because people do not use it.
They do not trust it.
And they are right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expertise is not cataloged and not stored in a database.
It is demonstrated.
Because that is what builds trust.
Someone demonstrating to all who care that they are actually right more often than others.
Or even better, when they are wrong, it is less painful than when others are wrong.
These are not the same thing, and in reality, the latter is more important than the former in most cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do you demonstrate expertise publicly?
And what does this have to do with a process that builds practices and documents them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;practice&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#practice&#34;&gt;
	Practice
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good companies have places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A place is a communications platform where people can talk to each other with two important properties:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is findable with keywords or through an ontology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People can join it without being invited.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it is private, unfindable, and you need to be invited, you have groups.
Groups suck; they isolate.
You want places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have written about
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/10/12/groups-and-places.html&#34;&gt;important properties of chats&lt;/a&gt;


elsewhere at length.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have places,
people will make the places they need
and then self-organize there to talk about the things they do and how they are doing this.
At least if you give them the time to do this and if you ensure
&lt;a href=&#34;https://hbr.org/2023/02/what-is-psychological-safety&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;pychological safety&lt;/a&gt;

.
That is,
if you allow them to talk in this place in a way that allows face-saving and comfortable learning experiences,
compromise finding, and civilized disagreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Places then also become locations where people give (tech) support as a public performance.
This is important for many reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People realize that things they take as a given are actually a valid bug.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s down for everyone, not just for me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These people have the problem I have solved, and I can tell them how.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other people see our discussion, and while our solution is valid, it is not actually the supported best practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These guys are using our tool, but for a purpose we haven&amp;rsquo;t anticipated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these things are visible only with support as a public performance.
If you pull these things into Jira tickets, none of this would happen, and the company would be left poorer.
I have written about
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2024/04/17/support-as-a-public-performance.html&#34;&gt;support as a public performance&lt;/a&gt;


elsewhere at length.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, chat is not a good medium for support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do support in a chat, you would want a chat with good threads and encourage people to open a thread per problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You would also need a bot that can turn a thread into a Jira ticket,
either after the fact in order to get tracing data out of the threads,
or if it turns out that the support case results in a work item that cannot be resolved immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You also want somebody whose job is technical
and whose job grade enables them to lift their gaze from the path to the horizon to go over the chat.
They would start interventions when they see questions that are unanswered or answered &amp;ldquo;wrongly.&amp;rdquo;
And by &amp;ldquo;wrong,&amp;rdquo;
I mostly mean cases where it is obvious to them
that the answer is either not efficient or not applicable to the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That person would also choose support cases of the week and by Friday morning produce a write-up.
It may be a blog article or a &amp;ldquo;medium.com&amp;rdquo; style write-up about anything that happened and is interesting.
If by Friday noon it is online,
all the people who spend Friday afternoon on their self-education will read it and possibly comment.
Using the articles and the comments,
that person can then take the output of all that discussion and update the engineering guide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the Engineering Guide is the deliverable that picks up where the Technology Radar drops off,
telling people not only what a product is good for,
but also how to use it efficiently and what specific local practices our tribe has developed
in order to make it a supportable use case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So look at your company:
How does your organization build practice?
How do practitioners meet?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;see-also&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#see-also&#34;&gt;
	See also
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/06/15/pizza-people-projects-and-processes.html&#34;&gt;Pizza, People, Projects and Processes (2018)&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/04/15/sql-engineering-guidelines.html&#34;&gt;Example: SQL Engineering Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/10/12/groups-and-places.html&#34;&gt;Properties of Chat Systems: Groups and Places&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2024/04/17/support-as-a-public-performance.html&#34;&gt;Support as a public performance&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Operations Review Meeting</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2024/04/18/operations-review-meeting.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 05:06:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2024/04/18/operations-review-meeting.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Monday Afternoon, &amp;ldquo;Operations Review Meeting&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time to nap in front of the Zoom,
because a bunch of management persons with a non-technical background
will show each other snore-inducing powerpoint slides over a vidconf for 90 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fred Whatshisname, in charge of Dunnowhatchatmacallit,
relates that the number of P1 incidents for this quarter is up by 17 percent, but the TTR is down a lot,
so this is good, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The what? Bringing up the corporatese abbreviation lexicon: TTR is the the Time To Resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, Fred.
Time to stage an intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seventeen percent is a familiar number. So in Q4 you had six P1&amp;rsquo;s and now you have seven?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fred acknowledges that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good. If it was 100 in Q4 and 117 in Q1, you&amp;rsquo;d be flipping burgers now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Fred, this is a tiny integer.
Why don&amp;rsquo;t you turn off the screen sharing,
and tell us what actually happened these seven times
that we had a loss of prod because of the Dunnowhatchatmacallit service being down?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fred does not know.
He is not technical.
He joins Jane into the conf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jane knows.
Jane is also not technical, she has the same type of MBA that Fred has,
but the critical difference is that Jane carries a pager, because Jane cares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When her team wakes up, she wakes up and that is how she knows.
She actually &lt;strong&gt;understands&lt;/strong&gt; in a very visceral and personally painful way.
(I edited Joe to Jane, because 80% of the time it&amp;rsquo;s a Jane that cares.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jane relates
that three of the Q4 incidents and four of the Q1&amp;rsquo;s are related to a problem with password provisioning
between vault and the databases.
It happens that some authentication token expires after a re-deploy,
and is not refreshed as part of the re-deploy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this is interesting, way more interesting than the number hocus-pocus by Fred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jane further relates
that the TTR is down because they now know about the problem
and have it as part of the deploy checklist, and the incident resolution documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked why the problem it not fixed at the source,
Jane relates that this is an operations problem and not part of the feature development backlog,
and hence has a low priority.
Low priority feature requests never make it into the actual sprint, ever, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, Jane,
what you are telling us is
that we have downtime that costs us money in lost business,
because we underprioritise operations by not taking them seriously.
And by not putting operations feedback into the backlog prioritization process?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jane agrees in this annoying noncommittal corpspeak lingo we all hate.
She also mentions that operations is understaffed,
because the three more people needed have been denied
and the other two have been downgraded from Senior to one Regular and one Junior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company prefers to spend money on developers, operations is just a cost center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company considers moving to AWS, because operations is hard,
and they want to focus on the business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth is that they have no idea how their business processes actually work on the ground,
and do not care, and soon they will understand even less of that,
because that is how things go from here.
All the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This happens in enterprises all around the world, and that is how the suck accumulates.
This way or one of a gazillion ways that are actually isomorphic to this experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Support as a public performance</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2024/04/17/support-as-a-public-performance.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2024 05:06:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2024/04/17/support-as-a-public-performance.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Support has been working in Slack for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;code&gt;#java&lt;/code&gt; channel where people can join and ask, a &lt;code&gt;#dba&lt;/code&gt; channel and a &lt;code&gt;#k8s&lt;/code&gt; channel, and there is of course &lt;code&gt;#live&lt;/code&gt;.
Each has a small four digit number of people attending, with &lt;code&gt;#live&lt;/code&gt; not quite reaching five digits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some pretty old and clueful people sit in these channels.
Often they just watch the questions scroll by.
But sometimes one of the Great Old Ones stirs in their slumber and raises to the surface,
stretching tentacles and grabbing a question or a support case that looks interesting or weird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Great Old Ones love their shinies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Management is annoyed by this arrangement.
They love their Jira, because Jira actually quantifies support, you know.
It makes tracking KPIs so much easier,
and then we can see if we managed to fulfill our critical TTR OKR for Q423 or not, instantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the company does not earn money with bringing down the TTR OKR for support in any quarter at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving the support from Slack to Jira
has turned a public interactive performance and discussion of operations and operational problems
into a set of highly permissioned 1:1 interactions and carefully tracked escalations.
They have carefully assigned priorities and have tracked resolution times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Great Old Ones are blindsided now, because no one,
not even they with their unnatural ancient power beyond what is allowed for mere mortals,
can read Jira horizontally across all tickets.
And if they did, and rose and grabbed a ticket, maybe that ticket is resolved.
But all the others would not have seen this spectacle of noneuclidic debugging
and knowledge about systems from before the dawn of time,
nor would they have been able to learn from this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably for good,
because people have been known to go insane from just reading the deploy scripts that drive these systems.
And let&amp;rsquo;s not even speak about the abominations that these C++ JNI methods actually hold.
As a mere Java coder you will never know,
and you should be thankful for that and every second of your life that you do not know about this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Slack questions often triggered +1&amp;rsquo;s. Somebody asks about a problem,
and others would chime in &amp;ldquo;That was me!&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;I am having the same problem,
it&amp;rsquo;s company wide&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;We know this, and for us this workaround is helpful&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving support from Slack to Jira cut that off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capability_Maturity_Model_Integration&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/04/support-01.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is that bad?
No, this was not a mature process, it was individual heroics, a 0 or 1 on the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capability_Maturity_Model_Integration&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;process maturity scale&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days, the ticket correlation process corp set up would find the same correlations,
reliably and with a maturity of 5
(quantifiably tracked and continuously improved).
Often, it takes only 4-8 weeks to get the same information as before with the immature process.
And on top,
it is now orderly documented and traceable as a KPI instead of happening coincidentally when the problem was current.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, the company now has architecture review boards,
and a tech radar that manages these kinds of things pretty successfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bunch of MBAs has been promoted on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how process and civilization work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Matrix Trashfire</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2024/02/13/the-matrix-trashfire.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 05:06:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2024/02/13/the-matrix-trashfire.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For reasons, I tried to evaluate the distributed Matrix chat and their clients.
That did not work out very well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;onboarding-experience&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#onboarding-experience&#34;&gt;
	Onboarding experience
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was told that the default Matrix chat client is called Elements, so I looked it up on the iOS App store.
Unfortunately, there are two, &amp;ldquo;Element&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Element X.&amp;rdquo;
No explanation is given, and no preference is stated.
&amp;ldquo;Element&amp;rdquo; is categorized business, &amp;ldquo;Element X&amp;rdquo; is in &amp;ldquo;Social Networking.&amp;rdquo;
Are they not the same?
They seem to be from the same company, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Element and Element X in the app store. Which one to use?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, let&amp;rsquo;s open the descriptions.
They are identical, except for one sentence at the start:
&amp;ldquo;Element X is the future Element.&amp;rdquo;
So it&amp;rsquo;s a beta?
Why is it not labeled as a Beta?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the desktop, going to &lt;a href=&#34;https://matrix.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Matrix.org&lt;/a&gt;

 plus two additional clicks take you to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://matrix.org/ecosystem/clients/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the client page&lt;/a&gt;

, which offers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The client page offers you, among others, both clients and also states which is available on what platform.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So apparently &amp;ldquo;Element X&amp;rdquo; is beta and not yet available on all platforms. I open the macOS App Store and&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-03.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;macOS does not offer Element, only Element X.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently matrix.org lied to me.
Element X is available on iOS and macOS, Element is not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, let&amp;rsquo;s install Element X and try:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-04.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Element X wants me to sign in to matrix.org. There is no &amp;lsquo;sign up&amp;rsquo; Button. There is no sign-up menu.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The client wants me to log in to matrix.org. There is no button to make an account. There is no menu to make an account.
There is zero onboarding for new users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, let&amp;rsquo;s go to matrix.org again, and see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-05.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The matrix.org Website is not very helpful. But when you notice the burger menu, there is actually a &amp;ldquo;Try Matrix&amp;rdquo; button.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The matrix.org website is a very empty clean screen that is not very helpful. There is a burger menu, though,
and if you open it, you get a &amp;ldquo;Try Matrix&amp;rdquo; button.
This leads to another screen that tells you to use your organizations server instance (What organization? I&amp;rsquo;m alone!),
or install a server,
or choose a public server.
If you opt for Public Servers, you land here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-06.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;matrix.org server instances, alphabetically sorted, with little additional information.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matrix.org is conspicuously absent from this list.
The rest I do not know anything about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can now research what server instance I want to join.
Unfortunately, I do not get information about what their country is.
I can&amp;rsquo;t see if they are subject to GDPR rules.
I don&amp;rsquo;t know if they are owned by a company or run by a single private person.
There is no indication how many users they have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can dig through their privacy policies and rules, except that some don&amp;rsquo;t provide any.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scrolling down, I end up with the option to onboard to this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-07.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Servers marked as vulnerable, unavailable and with profanity in their name.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why in heaven or earth would anybody put unavailable or vulnerable servers into an onboarding listing?
Isn&amp;rsquo;t this supposed a &amp;ldquo;secure&amp;rdquo; messenger?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;trying-to-use-it-nontheless&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#trying-to-use-it-nontheless&#34;&gt;
	Trying to use it, nontheless
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made an &amp;ldquo;isotopp&amp;rdquo; account at &lt;a href=&#34;https://chat.tchncs.de/#/login&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;tchncs.de&lt;/a&gt;

.
The password is generated and stored in Bitwarden.
A validation mail is sent to a unique address at koehntopp.de and arrives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I try to login not being validated, using Bitwarden.
The login is rejected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I validate the email.
The server says I am validated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I try to login, using Bitwarden.
The login is rejected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-09.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I am trying to recover the password for the account which I just validated, using the email from the verification mail.
The account is unknown.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I click on &amp;ldquo;forgotten password&amp;rdquo;, and supply the mail adress the validation mail was sent to.
&amp;ldquo;This email address was not found.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, since my account does not exist, I create it again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-10.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I recreate my account, using the same mail address. As you can see, the first registration mail still is in the account.
I take the validation URL, which is longer than 80 characters, and use it to successfully validate, again.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I create the account again, using the same parameters.
The account validation mail is sent to my address.
The old account validation mail is also still in the account.
I take the new URL, which is longer than 80 characters, and use it to successfully validate my account, again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time I accidentally left the &amp;ldquo;create account&amp;rdquo; window open.
This window is now suddenly logged in.
Turns out, you MUST NOT, UNDER ANY CIRCUMSTANCES, close the &amp;ldquo;create account&amp;rdquo; window until the account is validated,
or it is simply not created.
This is not stated anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To confirm the account works and the password in Bitwarden is stored successfully,
I log out and log in again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-11.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unable to verify this device&lt;/strong&gt;
It looks like you don&amp;rsquo;t have a Security Key or any other devices you can verify against.
This device will not be able to access old encrypted messages.
In order to verify your identity on this device, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to reset your verification keys.*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does that even mean?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;trying-element-x-with-my-account&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#trying-element-x-with-my-account&#34;&gt;
	Trying Element X with my account
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting Element X, it tries to onboard me to Matrix.org.
I select &amp;ldquo;Change Server&amp;rdquo;, and get a form field where it says &amp;ldquo;matrix.org&amp;rdquo;.
I am overwriting it with &amp;ldquo;chat.tchncs.de&amp;rdquo;, which supposedly is my server.
At least that is what it says in the web client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-12.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is not accepted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I take the URL from the browser and paste that instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-13.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is also not accepted, but I can learn more.
I click.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-14.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The what?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, while the Chat is running on &amp;ldquo;chat.tchncs.de&amp;rdquo;, this is not the &amp;ldquo;Identity Provider.&amp;rdquo;
That one is called &amp;ldquo;tchncs.de&amp;rdquo;.
You only learn this when you open your config menu in the web chat and look at Identifer shown there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-15.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you enter this, Element X and the web chat get hectic.
There is a new client, and both clients want to authenticate that the new device is legit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-16.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For that purpose, they display a set of Emojis, which look differently in the web client and the application,
and ask me if they are the same.
Helpful Emoji names are shown under the Emoji, and they are identical.
I simply click yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, both clients can see my Chat, but the Element X Client still has no access to any chat history.
That is, because the client is unverified (so is the web client).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I close any client, I have to re-login, re-compare the Emojis, and all chat history is gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;after-onboarding&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#after-onboarding&#34;&gt;
	After onboarding
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why have I been trying this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-08.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A friend was trying to use a Matrix messenger on their phone, and waited 9 hours for this to complete.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine was trying to re-install a Matrix messenger on their phone, and landed on the screen above.
This hung for 9 hours without any message or failure indication.
The application cannot detect if somebody is using the wrong recovery key for a different account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The friend tried to use an Android application, but the application was complaining about the account not being verified.
That is, the mail address in use was not confirmed, and for that reason the client would not be showing any chats.
At the same time, these chats were being sent to the unconfirmed mail address,
unencrypted,
as a reminder that he was missing out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to him, you can&amp;rsquo;t delete a half-made unconfirmed account.
You also can&amp;rsquo;t rename an account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, you cannot create invite links for private chat rooms,
only invite people.
To do that, vector.im uses the very same dark patterns that LinkedIn uses to convince you to share your address book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the unique mail-address used to sign up to Matrix, I am unfindable because only Matrix uses this specific mail address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside of Element, there are very few clients, most of them very old and not being updated within the last few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, this is a mess, and my recommendation is to avoid Matrix for at least two years.
It is not secure, it is actively user-hostile, and looks not well managed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a project in severe need of management changes, a thorough UX evaluation.
The design needs changes that make onboarding and usage smoother, encourage secure workflows,
keep accounts available, and encourage secure practice.
It also needs careful curation of servers and clients.
At the moment it is a trash fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;matrix-responds&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#matrix-responds&#34;&gt;
	Matrix responds
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Added on 14-Feb-2024:
People at Matrix.org and Matrix developers have picked this up and responded in a very constructive way.
They cannot address all things because they are not in the realm of Matrix, but part of Element.
So far, no responses from Element.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mastodon.matrix.org/@matrix/111924190165706931&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Matrix writes&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-17.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;well, this is a trashfire indeed.
Thanks for writing this up.
You&amp;rsquo;ve caught Element in the middle of their migration to Element X, and there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of legit feedback here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both E &amp;amp; EX should be in the macOS app store.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;EX should clearly be labelled WIP in appstores.
-It&amp;rsquo;s a mistake that matrix.org hurls people to servers.joinmatrix.org (which is not run by us);
until recently it defaulted to matrix.org for convenience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keeping the &amp;ldquo;create account&amp;rdquo; window open is a pure bug.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mastodon.matrix.org/@matrix/111924227099676114&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The continue&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-18.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Verification UX in Element is a disaster, and being reworked in EX:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/element-hq/element-meta/blob/develop/docs/FTUE.md&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Github link&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Element Android failing to compute a recovery key is clearly a bug too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your other complaints about Element UX (e.g. user discovery by email;
specifying the server URL) are also very familiar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not true to say vector.im uses &amp;ldquo;the very same dark patterns as LinkedIn&amp;rdquo; for contact discovery though;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/matrix-org/matrix-spec-proposals/blob/hs/hash-identity/proposals/2134-identity-hash-lookup.md&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Github link&lt;/a&gt;


explains how it works (and is strictly opt-in).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matrix Director of Program Development &lt;a href=&#34;https://mamot.fr/@thibaultamartin/111924256997285624&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Thibault A. Martin responds&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-19.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hej @isotopp I&amp;rsquo;m one of the maintainers of the matrix.org website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your post provides a very valuable perspective.
I gathered the following gripes that we can address on the website itself in this issue:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/matrix-org/matrix.org/issues/2178&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Matrix.Org Issue 2178&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have the time to let me know if I got things right,
that would be very useful!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for picking this up, people!
I very much hope that Matrix and Element eventually turn into something useful.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sitzende Tätigkeit</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/10/10/sitzende-taetigkeit.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 02:03:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/10/10/sitzende-taetigkeit.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ich arbeite im Sitzen, 8h am Tag beruflich, und dann noch ein wenig mehr aus Spaß:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/02/21/spaces.html&#34;&gt;Spaces&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich habe meinen eigenen Platz daheim, immer schon gehabt.
Das habe ich von meinem Vater gelernt, der Amateurfunker war und daheim seinen höchst eigenen Bastel- und Arbeitsplatz hatte,
seinen Ort und Rückzugplatz.
Zu einem ordentlichen Arbeitsplatz gehört auch ein Sitz.
Der Sitz ist ein Arbeitsgerät und da sollte man angesichts der Anzahl der darin verbrauchten Stunden nicht kaspern, sondern klotzen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meinen alten Stuhl habe ich 2003 in Karlsruhe gekauft, ein Dauphin Shape Comfort XT mit nahezu allen Optionen.
Der hat 20 Jahre gehalten.
Aber inzwischen wurde es Zeit für einen Ersatz:
Nicht nur ist die Gasdruckfeder im Eimer (die habe ich schon einige Male getauscht, sicher ist sicher),
sondern intern ist die Mechanik auch abgenudelt und verschiedene Einstellmöglichkeiten haben nicht mehr gut funktioniert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andererseits: 20 Jahre.
Das Teil hat in Karlsruhe, 2 Orten in Berlin, und in Amsterdam Dienst getan.
Dann ist auch gut.
Hier ist der neue, wieder ein Dauphin Shape XT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2023/10/sitz-01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anlieferung fertig montiert in einem sehr stabilen Monsterkarton.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2023/10/sitz-02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ausstattung, wie bestellt, via &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.objectservice.de/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.objectservice.de/&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Da der Sitz vormontiert bestellt war, gestaltete sich das Auspacken schnell und einfach.
Dachte ich, aber es gab Luftpolsterfolie!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2023/10/sitz-03.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Luftpolsterfolie!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Stuhl kommt mit einem ausführlichen Handbuch und einer Erklärung der Grundlagen der Ergonomie.
Das braucht es auch, denn dies ist ein richtiger Bürostuhl,
und kein Gamer-Stuhl oder gar, wie einige Kollegen auch im Jahr 3 der Pandemie, ein Küchenstuhl.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2023/10/sitz-04.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bild des Bürostuhls am Arbeitsort: Höhenverstellbarer Schreibtisch, jede Menge Strom, eine Rollmatte und ein ordentlicher Stuhl.
Tageslicht von Links.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Stuhl kommt mit einer Vielzahl an Einstellmöglichkeiten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2023/10/sitz-05.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Übersicht der Einstellmöglichkeiten.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sitzhöhe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sitztiefe. Die Sitzfläche gleitet nach vorn, und ich passe auf den Stuhl.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Armlehnen weit ausfahren: Ein wichtiger Handgriff, damit mein breiter Hintern in den Sessel passt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rückenlehne fixieren oder losdrehen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wenn man 4 losmacht, kann man Einstellen, wie stark die Rückenlehne Gegendruck macht.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nicht sichtbar: Armlehnen Höhe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lordosenstütze Höhe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Die Rückenlehne ist höhenverstellbar, und das ist so auch notwendig bei mir.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rückenlehne und Sitzfläche neigen sich zusammen nach vorne und hinten (&amp;ldquo;Synchromechanik&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es gibt noch besser ausgestattete Versionen von diesem Stuhl,
bei denen die Armlehnen auch in Neigung und Winkel verstellbar in mehreren Dimensionen sind,
aber das ist meiner Erfahrung nach nicht dringend.
Eine Version mit Nackenstütze ist auch zu haben.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bezüge kommen in mehreren Preiskategorien (bis &amp;ldquo;Chefsessel Leder&amp;rdquo;) und sind auf Beanspruchung ausgelegt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zum Einstellen kann man einfach die Anleitung im Handbuch befolgen.
Die Schritte sind im Grunde bei jedem Stuhl dieselben, sofern die betreffenden Einstellmöglichkeiten vorhanden sind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Die Synchronmechanik und andere Schwingteile blockieren (z.B. die Rückenlehne aufrecht fixieren) und die Armlehnen ausfahren auf maximale Breite.
Das macht Platz im Stuhl und erzeugt eine neutrale Sitzposition. Hinsetzen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sitzhöhe einstellen. Füße platt auf den Boden, dann müssen die Oberschenkel waagrecht im 90 Grad Winkel stehen.
Manche Menschen wollen die Sitzhöhe noch ein wenig höher haben.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sitztiefe einstellen, also die Sitzfläche so weit ausfahren, daß sie bis auf 2-3 Finger an die Kniekehlen heranreicht und die Beine unterstützt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nun die Position der Rückenlehne einstellen: Neigung, und wenn höhenverstellbar auch Höhe, bis die Unterstützung im Kreuz angenehm ist.
Eventuell vorhandene Lordosenstütze in die richtige Position (über dem Becken ins Kreuz) bringen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jetzt Sitzflächenneigung einstellen, also die Synchro loslösen und schaukeln, dann in einer angenehmen Position fixieren,
und danach die Rücken-Neigung noch mal nachstellen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Armlehnen einstellen - Breite, Höhe, Position.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Danach Feineinstellung justieren: Synchro los, und Rückenlehnen-Gegendruck anpassen, Lordosenstütze Druck einstellen
und was sonst noch an Hilfseinstellungen da ist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zentral sind Höhe, Sitztiefe und Stellung der fixierten Rückenlehne in Neigung und Höhe der Lordosenstütze.
Der Rest ist dann drumherum zu arrangieren.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Gospel of Efficiency vs. Actual Growth</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/19/the-gospel-of-efficiency-vs-actual-growth.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 01:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/19/the-gospel-of-efficiency-vs-actual-growth.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A decade ago, I came as a performance specialist into a rapidly growing environment.
With rapid growth, I mean anything that is larger than what Moore&amp;rsquo;s Law once delivered.
Moore&amp;rsquo;s law comes out at upwards of 45% Year-on-Year (YoY).
In my case, we experienced 80% YoY worldwide with 220% YoY in certain regions of the world for many years.
Even in 2008, when the economy stagnated, we still made 45% or more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onboarding people into such an environment is weird.
They all have been programmed by their university education and their previous work experience to build things that last,
to consider things carefully and to be efficient, and save money at all cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is not how anything works in a high-growth environment, at all.
Rapid growth kills.
The tech we build, we build it for a certain expected target size.
Good tech can sustain a 10x growth (or shrinkage), but usually not much more.
At a larger change, things tend to fall apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; bc -l
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;scale&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; l&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;10&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;/l&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;2&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;3.321
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; l&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;10&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;/l&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;1.45&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;6.204
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you double each year, 10x is 3.3 years, approximately.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you grow at Moore&amp;rsquo;s Law rate, 10x is 6.2 years, approx.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a high-growth an environment, when you write software,
you can expect it to last around 4 years or so until it needs to be re-architected in order to continue to produce the same deliverables as before.
You do not know how it will fail much in advance, nor do you know how the business environment will change much in advance:
As you grow, bottlenecks will show up in unexpected places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you grow faster than Moore&amp;rsquo;s law, buying larger computers will not help you.
You need to buy more computers, and change your code to run in a distributed environment.
That changes performance fundamentally, and code needs to be changed in order to deal with the properties of distributed environments.
Running distributed systems will add complexity that you really do not want in order to maintain growth,
because it makes change harder and slower, which you really can&amp;rsquo;t use, if you grow fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, on top of the change in technology, you also need to deal with change in organiation,
and to integrate a lot of new people which you need in order to deal with added complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means, several unusual things are important, others that people have been trained to take as important are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in such an environment, all software is ephemeral.
In four years time it will be largely useless.
You do not know how things will fail unless you are close to failure.
You have vision for about 12 months ahead, at most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will need to start to change your failing software by making architectural changes.
You do not know if they will succeed in time.
Do not follow one plan, follow all plans and hope that at least one succeeds in time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cost is relevant only in the sense that you must not pay for current expenses with future growth.
You must be cash flow positive at all times,
but actual earnings are largely irrelevant until growth flattens out below 45%.
Never paying for current expense with future growth (not even for a short time) is very important,
because you do not know if that future growth will materialize.
If you ever run into a money vaccuum, you die very suddenly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actual earnings are much less important.
Not dying from growth is already hard enough,
the objective is to have new solutions in place &lt;em&gt;in time&lt;/em&gt;,
and speed matters more than cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a rare environment and people are generally not trained for it.
It goes in fact against most of what they have been trained for.
Getting that out of people&amp;rsquo;s minds in order to prepare them for success in such an environment is hard,
much harder than what one would initially think,
because you have to break down decades of education they had.
You need to have then accept a reality that is very different from what they have learned.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kein Homeoffice, keine Kekse</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/12/kein-homeoffice-keine-kekse.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 01:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/12/kein-homeoffice-keine-kekse.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Heise schreibt:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.heise.de/meinung/Kommentar-Massenexodus-bei-Grindr-von-den-Un-Schoenheiten-des-Homeoffice-9301244.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kommentar: Massenexodus bei Grindr – von den (Un-)Schönheiten des Homeoffice &lt;/a&gt;


Ein Kommentar, der sich am Massenexodus bei Grindr abarbeitet, aber nicht weiß, was er will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bei Grindr bildet sich eine Gewerkschaft, und viele Mitarbeiter werden Mitglied.
Aus Rache führt die Firma Hybrid mit mindestens 2 Tagen pro Woche Anwesenheit ein.
Daraufhin kündigen mehr als 50 % der Mitarbeiter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Artikel sieht das nicht als collective action der Mitarbeiter,
sondern als eine Folge von Individualentscheidungen.
Er sieht auch irgendwie Vorteile für die Firma (&amp;ldquo;Geringere Kosten&amp;rdquo; und magische &amp;ldquo;höhere Produktivität&amp;rdquo;),
und versucht dann eine Art Brücke zu schlagen (&amp;ldquo;Firmen sollten auf Mitarbeiter hören.&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist in Summe aussagelos und von der wirtschaftlichen Analyse her Quatsch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;auftragstaktik&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#auftragstaktik&#34;&gt;
	Auftragstaktik
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In den drei Covid-Jahren haben sich in allen Firmen sehr stabile und produktive Remote-First Strukturen ausgebildet.
Sehr viele Mitarbeiter haben sehr schnell gelernt,
dass zweimal eine Stunde Commute pro Tag mehr Belastung waren, als sie bewusst bemerkt haben.
Sie waren sehr froh, diese Lebenszeit zurückzubekommen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zudem haben sie gemerkt, daß Management by Objectives – nahezu die einzige Methode, die Remote First funktioniert –
viel sinnvoller ist als fast alles andere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wer mehr wissen will:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://mastodon.social/@xahteiwi&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Florian Haas&lt;/a&gt;


hat darüber ja auch schon unter Referenz auf die
&lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/F%C3%BChren_mit_Auftrag&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Auftragstaktik&lt;/a&gt;

 nachgedacht
und in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Art-Action-Leaders-between-Actions-ebook/dp/B01HPVHLHG&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Art of Action&lt;/a&gt;


beschäftigt sich quasi ein ganzes Buch mit dem Thema &amp;ldquo;Auftragstaktik in der Unternehmensführung umsetzen&amp;rdquo;
und Clausewitz &amp;ldquo;Vom Kriege&amp;rdquo; in der Wirtschaft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenn Unternehmen nun – aus welchem Grund auch immer – versuchen,
das zurückzudrehen, dann erzeugen sie damit eine große Unzufriedenheit bei ihren Mitarbeitern
und drehen die Fluktuation hoch bis zum Anschlag.
Sie machen dabei keinen Gewinn, denn sie verlieren genau die Mitarbeiter, die sie behalten müssen und wollen.
Unternehmen bluten vom Kopfe her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;arbeitsmarkt&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#arbeitsmarkt&#34;&gt;
	Arbeitsmarkt
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und sie schneiden sich von einem Arbeitsmarkt ab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In dem wegweisenden Essay
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/software-engineering-salaries-in-the-netherlands-and-europe/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Trimodal Nature of Software Engineering Salaries in the Netherlands and Europe&lt;/a&gt;


beschreibt Gergely Orosz die Struktur des Arbeitsmarktes bei Wissensarbeitern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Er tut das am Beispiel von Amsterdam,
aber meiner Erfahrung nach ist das weltweit so, mit unterschiedlichen Limits bei den lokalen Märkten.
Unternehmen müssen wissen, aus welchem Pool sie Personen ansprechen und einstellen wollen,
und sie müssen wissen, wie man mit der entsprechenden Gruppe Leute arbeitet.
Der Vorteil von Remote First Unternehmen ist, daß sie aus dem globalen Markt einstellen können,
aber oft zu Preisen aus einem nationalen Markt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein frühes Beispiel dafür war MySQL AB, die mit 500 Leuten in 26 Ländern ein extremes Beispiel für eine verteilte Firma waren,
und die weltweit eingestellt hat, aber keinen Umzug gefordert hat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stattdessen hat man bewusst Strukturen geschaffen, in denen ein verteiltes Team Gemeinschaft bildet,
sich 4x im Jahr getroffen (in Ländern, die unproblematisch mit Visa umgingen),
und man hat diese Treffen systematisch vorbereitet, damit sie effektiv waren.
Und ja, jede Menge MbO/Auftragstaktik.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eine moderne Beschreibung solcher Methoden findet man in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Effective-Remote-English-James-Stanier-ebook/dp/B09Z5F678G&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Effective Remote Work&lt;/a&gt;

 von James Stanier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;die-folgen-von-rto&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#die-folgen-von-rto&#34;&gt;
	Die Folgen von RTO
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In den drei Covid-Jahren sind in vielen Firmen ebenfalls solche Strukturen entstanden,
aber oft zufällig, partiell, nicht gesteuert und unverstanden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenn ein solcher Laden jetzt aus welchem Grund auch immer &amp;ldquo;Return to Office&amp;rdquo; ausruft, dann passieren mehrere Dinge:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Die Firma schneidet sich vom weitweiten Staffing Pool (zu nationalen Preisen) ab, Hiring wird schwierig.
Denn neue Mitarbeitys müssen umziehen und dem stehen Verpflichtungen vor Ort,
Visa und Arbeitserlaubnisse und viele andere Dinge im Weg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Die Firma erzeugt ohne Not die Situation oben für alle existierenden Mitarbeiter,
die in den drei Covid-Jahren dazu gekommen sind, aber nicht umgezogen sind.
&lt;em&gt;Alle&lt;/em&gt; die werden gehen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Die Firma bringt den Commute zurück zu Menschen, die begriffen haben,
dass der Commute notlose Verschlechterung der Lebensqualität ist.
Auch hier Kündigungswelle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welche Leute werden gehen?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zuerst immer die, die Optionen haben.
Also die hoch qualifizierten, deren Recruiter-Spam in der Inbox am größten ist.
Der Pull-Faktor ist ja schon da, den Push und den Anlass hat die Firma eben geliefert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es sind also gerade die Leute, bei denen der Arbeitgeber einen Anlass hat, Retention zu fahren,
die der Arbeitgeber zuerst verliert.
Das ist immer und für jede Firma ein sehr großer Nettoverlust, und noch dazu ein schlecht gesteuerter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenige Läden können einen Verlust von 50 % der Belegschaft verkraften,
ohne dass es zu einem massiven Verlust an Qualität, Produktivität, organisatorischem Wissen und Prozeßreife kommt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neben dem Verlust an Know-How und nicht verschriftlichtem Wissen,
der erhöhten Arbeitslast für die verbleibenden Mitarbeiter kommt noch der Druck auf alle für Interviews
und Training neuer Kollegen dazu.
Das erzeugt eine Delle in Qualität und Produktivität von 1 bis 2 Jahren, Stagnation oder gar Regress.
Es gibt kein Wertmodell für eine Firma, in der so etwas positive Auswirkungen hat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;auch-entlassungen-fördern-ungesteuerte-verluste&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#auch-entlassungen-f%c3%b6rdern-ungesteuerte-verluste&#34;&gt;
	Auch Entlassungen fördern ungesteuerte Verluste
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Etwas Ähnliches passiert bei Entlassungen:
Neben den Leuten, die man entläßt (gesteuert und nach Ansicht der Firma am unteren Ende)
wird man gewiss noch 2x mehr Leute verlieren,
aber am oberen Ende.
Für diese Menschen ist der zweite, ungeschriebene Vertrag gebrochen worden,
und sie nehmen die resultierende Unsicherheit als Anstoß, Pull-Faktoren nachzugeben.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In jedem Fall bluten Firmen bei solchen Änderungen.
Sogar dann, wenn sich nicht aus billiger Rache erfolgen,
sondern gesteuert und mit Unterstützung des Managements sanft durchgeführt werden,
kommt es leicht mit großen zweistelligen prozentualen Verlusten und jahrelangen Folgen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firmen lernen gerade, wie wichtig Personen als Individuen sind.
Viele Organisationen sind mit dieser, der kapitalistischer Ideologie widersprechenden Erfahrung sehr unzufrieden und tief in Denial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies forcing their employees back into the office will lose talent and keep wage serfs.
&amp;ndash; Volker Weber (&lt;a href=&#34;https://social.heise.de/@vowe&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@vowe@social.heise.de&lt;/a&gt;

)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Great Resignation, Management Edition</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/06/22/a-great-resignation-management-edition.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2023 01:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/06/22/a-great-resignation-management-edition.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is not much of a blog post, but just a &lt;a href=&#34;https://chaos.social/@isotopp/110586700595558261&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;thread dump from Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;

 as requested by a friend,
because my Mastodon posts expire after some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on my work and the people I know, I have some (remote) view into what happens in a few companies at the C- and Mid-Level management.
And from where I sit, it seems the great resignation is not only a thing that affects workers, but also managers.
It is almost funny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These people are often pretty awesome administrative people.
Mid-level managers with amazing Jira- and Miro-skills, breaking down large work parcels of well-understood jobs into team-sized packages,
describing the requirements and planning the required hours, then mapping them onto calendars.
Or budget jugglers that take large unstructured sums of cost, and find a way to parcel them out in a halfway reasonable way into individual cost centers and items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;digital-and-other-transformations&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#digital-and-other-transformations&#34;&gt;
	Digital and other transformations
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These companies are also all in a series of transformations, at all levels of the stack simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many are moving on-premises workloads to cloud, but the workloads are not cloud-shaped.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two enterprises I happen to know about are also changing their implementation language from something exotic to something less efficient, but a lot easier to hire for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One enterprise is also breaking up a monolithic application into a set of microservices, but the cut lines are unclear and need to be found.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One enterprise is modifying the way they do business from a single product to a series of interconnected and interdependent products, some of them in highly regulated markets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another enterprise is changing the way they make their product from mostly manual labor into something based on sensor input and data science.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These transformations require a different kind of manager:
they need less of an administrative person, and more business process designer;
they require a different kind of empowerment and delegation, from the top to them, and from them on downwards – much more autonomous on the delegation poker side;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is also needed is an entirely different kind of understanding of the company itself, less interchangeable business administration skills,
and more business-specific skills about how the sausage is made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of that are traditional hierarchies and communication structures that are based on in-person attendance and mostly oral tradition,
and a skill-set that is well suited for the Clear and Complicated domains of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cynefin_framework&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the Cynefin-Model&lt;/a&gt;

,
but wrong for the Complex and Chaotic domains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Enterprise cannot perform the set of transitions it must execute to stay relevant,
when the entire Org and the people that carry and build the structure of the Org are incapable of transforming their way of working to match the problem.
So they leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which for an organization that is in the Complex and Chaotic realm of a transformation makes the problem worse,
because the intimate knowledge of the processes that make this company unique and competitive goes with them.
The people coming in have to learn these things,
but if the Org does not have &lt;em&gt;written&lt;/em&gt; account of what matters and has no way of &lt;em&gt;teaching&lt;/em&gt; these things that make this company special,
it basically loses its specialty and becomes meaningless, interchangeable and then soon extinct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-remote-work-does-for-companies&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#what-remote-work-does-for-companies&#34;&gt;
	What Remote Work does for companies
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funnily,
companies that optimize for remote work are also companies
that out of necessity optimize for a written instead of an oral culture.
They tend to have very well documented ways of specifying and teaching what they do, why and how,
and a proper self-service onboarding process complemented by a mentoring system –
and that also works for mid- and C-level management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies that optimize for remote are executing transformations easier because they understand their meta better.
Many workers understand that.
Maybe not in this way or even in words, but they can read the room, and they are reacting to their environment, especially the skilled ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A preference for remote work is useful even, or especially, if you come into the office,
because a company that can do remote properly understands what it does and how it works better than a company that executes &amp;ldquo;remote&amp;rdquo; with a &amp;ldquo;zoom harder&amp;rdquo; policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;interviewing-to-find-organizations-that-know-their-stuff&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#interviewing-to-find-organizations-that-know-their-stuff&#34;&gt;
	Interviewing to find organizations that know their stuff
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when you interview, these are useful and interesting questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How did your company change their way of working during Covid?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How did your management style evolve under Covid and after?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do you detect misalignment, disagreement or conflict or other causes for in-person meetings when working remotely,
and what are the ways you handle these situations?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do you evolve agreement from oral consensus to documentation to training material?
How do you document and teach processes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How did your way of working as a person and as a member of the Org evolve in the last 5 years?
What can you point to that illustrates process maturation and advancement?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In what way did your Org execute transformations in the last five years?
That certainly was not frictionless.
What worked, what didn&amp;rsquo;t, what did the Org learn?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that reads a lot like a reverse interview – well, that&amp;rsquo;s what it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the objective is clear:
You want to find out if the org you are about to join has access to its own meta,
and if it can change and consciously design its org structure, work, and communications culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All companies right now are executing a series of transformations at multiple levels of their business.
That is because the world right now is a lot less stable than it used to be in the last 50 years.
But only those that do not let these things happen to them, but are actively shaping the process will not be painful to work at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must find these early in the interview process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, the information you want to find when interviewing for a job is again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Does this company shape itself and its future consciously?
Does it design itself?
Or does change happen to the org accidentally?
Does it understand what it does, and why? Or are they winging it?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most management is winging it, most companies are cheating their way to the next quarterlies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You do your work, but you do have an understanding of what management is supposed to do.
Does management understand their job, tho?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you respect your current or future management?
Can they express the value they provide in a way &lt;em&gt;that is understandable and meaningful to you?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can they explain the business, and what specifically the competitive advantage is this org has within its own competitive set?
Do they know why this differentiation exists, and how it is protected or extended?
Do they understand in what way the structure they are building and upholding helps in doing this?
And how it needs to change to be able to continue?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, you want to find out if they know the C-level strategy they exist in.
If they know what direction everybody is supposed to march in, and what their local objectives are as a part of the greater whole.
You need to find out if they have context that they are making local decisions in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, it is this (and not ping-pong tables) that builds engagement and loyalty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People love to work for a company that understands how it functions,
and can talk sensibly about this – about its business and communication processes,
and the why and how of useful interaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People love to work for organizations that have an idea of how to change and into what, instead of being shaped by accident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;stressors&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#stressors&#34;&gt;
	Stressors
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another contributing factor is that transformations interrupt the value extraction process of neoliberal shareholder value,
and also upsets established hierarchies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shifting to the left side of the Cynefin model means you need smaller teams of higher qualified people.
Teams that perform work in a way that is much harder to quantify,
and create value that is hard to express in right-side organizational structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is, shareholders and their demand for dividend and rising stock value interfere with the investment needs,
increased risk and hard to measure gains that transformations require,
and thus the owners of the enterprise are an impediment to the change that the company needs to be able to continue to deliver value to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is, some individual owners always understand that problem,
but the owners as a group don&amp;rsquo;t and can&amp;rsquo;t and are working against their own best interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Side Remark:&lt;/em&gt; Similar structural pressure is currently visible in German society, at the &amp;ldquo;Berlin vs. Berlin Outskirts&amp;rdquo; conflict or at the national mobility and energy transformation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;side-remarks-from-the-pandemic-coping-discord&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#side-remarks-from-the-pandemic-coping-discord&#34;&gt;
	Side Remarks from the Pandemic Coping Discord
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-friend-gives-an-example-at-the-individual-level&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#a-friend-gives-an-example-at-the-individual-level&#34;&gt;
	A friend gives an example at the individual level
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IC: &amp;ldquo;The existing code is bad and undocumented. Three weeks for the fix, provided there are no landmines.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M: &amp;ldquo;So you commit to 3w?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IC: &amp;ldquo;No, because I don&amp;rsquo;t know if there are landmines. Usually there are.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M: &amp;ldquo;But I need a binding commitment to before the end of July!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s lack of tech understanding paired with pressure from the shareholder end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;another-friend-talks-about-stressors&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#another-friend-talks-about-stressors&#34;&gt;
	Another friend talks about Stressors
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M: &amp;ldquo;My personal theory is that we are running into some inherent limits of the current management model during the last decade and are now seeing stress fractures.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;K: &amp;ldquo;But the question is where the stress is originating.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M: &amp;ldquo;Complexity (as observed at each management level).&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;K: &amp;ldquo;Ok, that matches what I think if you accept that it is these transformations that are causing the stress. What you call stress fractures I call transformation overload.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M (responding to the three-week-commitment example above):
&amp;ldquo;A good example for what I mean by complexity at that management level:
The manager can communicate only a scalar detail upwards, but the problem is a complex data object.
The manager cannot report what happens nor the risk properly.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;K: &amp;ldquo;A command and control management is unable to handle situations that require nuance and understanding of detail?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M: &amp;ldquo;Yes. Management level A needs to reduce their stress, and forces their lower level B to simplify. That increases pressure and stress at the level of B.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M: C has called this &amp;ldquo;driven by financials.&amp;rdquo;
The only universal scalar is Euro,
but expressing all things in Euros is becoming increasingly harder and is losing information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M: A lot of fighting and pressure is actually about &amp;ldquo;simplify your reporting&amp;rdquo; vs. &amp;ldquo;accept my complexity.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M: &amp;ldquo;This is also in part why we see a preference for managed services. They are an attempt to encapsulate complexity. Often that fails, and the complexity reappears and attacks the PO consuming that service.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C: &amp;ldquo;A way to solve the conflict is to ask more &amp;lsquo;Why&amp;rsquo; questions downstack, and to create more tasks that allow for interpretation.&amp;rdquo;
That is basically a move to the left-hand side of Cynefin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M: &amp;ldquo;That requires a trust that is larger than Euro-Scalars. And ultimately that breaks at the shareholder-level, latest.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;H2: &amp;ldquo;And non-technical management also believes these things are simple. Click here, and ChatGPT will develop the software autonomously. It&amp;rsquo;s those pesky IT people making all these things that complicated.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meditations on Quitting</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/12/27/meditations-on-quitting.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2022 01:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/12/27/meditations-on-quitting.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I quit often.
At least once a year, but there have been years when I have been quitting four times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time before a performance evaluation, or before important meetings, I sit down and write myself a notice.
I pull up a word processor, start the empty business letter template, fill in the details and the date, and then write the three or four sentences necessary to inform my employer that the time has come to part ways.
I print this, collect the letter, fold it properly and put it into an empty unsealed envelope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I pull it out, unfold it and put it in front of me.
Time to start thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are the logistics of quitting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of that is about obligations and finance.
Could I actually walk out of the meeting, leaving the letter behind?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been times, when I was younger, where I easily could have done that. Not owning property, being unmarried and without child.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a consultant, with 180 travel days a year, I had to build my own personal insurance anyway.
That&amp;rsquo;s  400 in the pocket at any point in time, 4k on an unused rescue credit card &amp;ndash; enough to take me home on my own from anywhere my job would take me.
And a coordinate transformation on my checking account that sees a few 10k as Zero, to provide immediate emergency burn fuel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enough buffer against possible bumps anywhere in the world is also enough buffer to leave when necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a family and a house, things are more complicated, and no longer immediate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An exit plan cannot be &amp;ldquo;walking out and leaving the letter&amp;rdquo; when an uninterrupted cash flow is part of the requirements.
But writing the letter is still an important focus point.
So I kept the tradition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is like a business continuity management plan, but for your soul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the logistics done, it is time to lift the gaze from the path in front of my feet, up to the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did I do the last few months?
What projects do I have been part of?
What have I learned?
How have I grown?
And is the place I am in still the place that would let me grow?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are no abstract questions.
But in my mind they only become real when I sit in front of this piece of paper, and think about staying or leaving.
I have made sure I could leave if I wanted.
Now it is time to think about what I want from this place to make me stay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sometimes explain this to others as the story of the two contracts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working in IT, you always have two contracts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One is written.
It says what your job title is, where you work, and what they pay you.
It says what your notice period is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other one is unwritten.
It is the unspoken agreement about the level of autonomy you have, and the decisions you can be part of.
It is the environment you work in and what challenges you can learn from.
It is about the things you build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Autonomy, Mastery and Purpose&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working in IT, I always signed, and I always actually quit, because of this second contract.
When it expires or is violated, it is time to actually leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then it all becomes about people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies by construction are usually not loyal to their employees.
In general, as organisations they can&amp;rsquo;t.
Some people inside an org maybe secretly work against the objectives of the organisations and are loyal to other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a person, I always work with other persons.
Over the last 30 years, it has become clear that these persons stay, even when I move.
I am part of my own personal tribe.
I have been building it, maintaining it over a few decades, and when necessary they have been there for me, and I have been there for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the meditation of quitting is also remembering these people.
Maybe they need me.
Maybe I need them.
Maybe I miss them.
Maybe some of them have an invitation or an opportunity for me.
Holding the bond of my current second contract against the pulls from my relationships gives me an important calibration of where I am, who I am and if I am honest with myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually then I have come to some conclusion and I have a plan.
I can fold the notice back up into the envelope, put it into my jacket, and walk into that meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am now grounded, and I know my boundaries, and my goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know who I am.
For some reason that seems to scare people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually then I don&amp;rsquo;t actually have to quit.
But being able to do that, and understanding when and why helps a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 2023-Jan-31, after almost another seven years, my second tour of Booking.com will come to an end.
It was a different ride than the first, it was still amazing, and I met the most wonderful and amazing people.
Still, I have been called, and the second contract is up.
I have to move.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Groups and Places</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/10/12/groups-and-places.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 06:07:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/10/12/groups-and-places.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a distributed, asynchronous environment, there is a need for distributed, asynchronous interaction.
This interaction is often written, but &amp;ldquo;writing&amp;rdquo; these days is actually a media-rich process that includes much more than letters.
It also needs to be able to build some structure, and some gateway to level up to more synchronous and even richer communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s have a chat about chats, and what properties they have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-01.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Historically, chat was lines of text, without much structure. Even today, many geeks often propose IRC when chat solutions are being discussed in a corporate context. That is a very myopic way of thinking.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first chat network I have been using was IRC &amp;ndash; Internet Relay Chat.
This has been in the late 80ies or early 90ies, so today I have had an interactive online presence on the upside of 25 years or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later I got to use ICQ, Jabber, Skype, Hangouts, Facebook Messenger, WhatsApp, Slack and RocketChat, among many others.
I also got exposed to a number of collaborative document processing systems with chat-like properties:
the now defunct Google Wave (alias Apache Wave, now also mostly defunct), and its heir Google Docs, and a bunch of newer collaborative brainstorming tools from the School of Miro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these applications and chat systems are different, but they can be evaluated along a number of dimensions to understand chat systems better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A screenshot of my chat desktop from 2016. There are many like it, but this is mine.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;location-and-discoverability&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#location-and-discoverability&#34;&gt;
	Location and Discoverability
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most important functions any chat system has to have is enabling the right people to find each other.
There are two large classes of chat systems here: One uses groups, and the other uses places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Groups are just that: collections of people that talk to each other.
You write a message and sent it.
It is then visible to all members of the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with groups is that they are almost impossible to find.
They are invitation only.
A member of the group must have knowledge of you looking for the group, and then invite you to it.
In some messengers this will also form a new group, destroying the messaging history of the older group, in order to protect the privacy of the conversation happening before the new member joined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-03.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Discord chat system allows you to form small scale groups with fixed membership, even without having a &amp;ldquo;Discord Server&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A better system uses Places (often called Rooms or Channels) instead of Groups.
A place is discoverable, you can &amp;ldquo;find&amp;rdquo; it, &amp;ldquo;go&amp;rdquo; to it, and &amp;ldquo;join&amp;rdquo; without being explicitly invited (permission and moderation systems often exist).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Places tend to proliferate, mechanism to group, order, tag and search them often exist.
In Discord, for example, Channels can be grouped into Categories, which are then grouped into &amp;ldquo;Servers&amp;rdquo;, the server having an owner, and often a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-04.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Discord chat system, showing the &amp;ldquo;heiseonline&amp;rdquo; discord server, with a channel named &lt;code&gt;#tierbilder&lt;/code&gt; (Animal Pictures) selected. Below that, a Category for &lt;code&gt;Sprachkanäle&lt;/code&gt; (Voice Channels) is seen.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having Places instead of Groups is crucial for any communication system.
It gives you the capability to write instructions that send people somewhere, and enables people to find and go somewhere, gives them agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebooks Messenger and Facebook at Work&amp;rsquo;s greatest flaw is their Messenger, which does not have this feature.
It relies on Groups, and tries to mitigate that by coupling groups to Facebook &amp;ldquo;Groups&amp;rdquo; (discussion boards), auto-inviting people into the Facebook Group associated chat group.
This combines worst practices of several systems into one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Places can be persistent, they can exist without anyone being in them.
Places can also have one or multiple owners, which is the root of that Places&amp;rsquo; permission system and the source of all moderator power for that Place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;presence&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#presence&#34;&gt;
	Presence
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working asynchronously means that you will not be present in a chat at all times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a feature: It allows you to focus, and think straight, cutting deeply into problems.
It also allows you to be in another timezone than your communication partners and still contribute meaningfully to a collaborative effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It poses the problem of your communication partners not knowing your current communication status, and availability.
If they are blocked, they might need you, and it would help them to have some expectation of your response times, availability and context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All modern chat systems have a presence mechanism, a semi-automatic status tagline, and the more thoughtfully engineered ones also know your timezone and show it to your peers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-05.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Slack chat system allows users to set a status in the form of an Emoji and a tagline. These are automatically cleared after some preset time, if desired. Slack also understands time zones, and will show you out-of-office times of communication partners, when necessary. Clicking on a user will also reveal their location and local time. On the right hand side, a number of status bubble examples are shown.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presence management in chat system often goes hand in hand with logging.
Messages sent to you in your absence are logged, and shown to you on reconnect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all a giant step forward from IRC, which did not manage presence well, and also did not allow sending messages to disconnected users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In IRC, being offline means not being present: people fall off the channel and what is being said with them being not there is lost to them.
That is of course a nuisance, and so people have been using programs such as screen to run an IRC client even when they have been disconnected from their computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IRC&amp;rsquo;s mechanism for presence (here: attention) is somewhat hidden &amp;ndash; the &lt;code&gt;/away&lt;/code&gt; command.
But not only is the mechanism hidden (it is another command that needs to be learned and used), but the status is somewhat hidden as well.
You can&amp;rsquo;t see if somebody is &lt;code&gt;/away&lt;/code&gt; unless you look at them with a &lt;code&gt;/whois&lt;/code&gt;.
Or you learn about the fact that they are &lt;code&gt;/away&lt;/code&gt; only after the fact, when you say something to them and get an auto-response with their &lt;code&gt;/away&lt;/code&gt; message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people do not like this, and so they use another mechanism and change their nicknames when they are not there &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;Isotopp&amp;rdquo; becomes &amp;ldquo;Isotopp|AFK&amp;rdquo; or similar.
This is less structured than &lt;code&gt;/away&lt;/code&gt;, and so some people suffix their names, some prefix them and others completely change their nicknames - &amp;ldquo;Isotopp&amp;rdquo; becomes &amp;ldquo;Awaytopp&amp;rdquo;.
The lack of facility, discoverable interface and standardization creates variant practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;logging-and-multi-device&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#logging-and-multi-device&#34;&gt;
	Logging and Multi-Device
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All modern chat clients have proper presence, even if not always as rich as in Slack.
Most also have unified logging.
That is, even absent users can receive messages and will see them when coming back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most users in 2022 have multiple devices, and multiple clients.
Most users want the entire messaging history, in order, and with all backlog, available on all their devices, so that they can switch between devices without losing context.
This usually includes new devices, to facilitate moving to new laptops or cellphones, without losing history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This often clashes with old standards, badly designed security mechanisms and other implementation details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-06.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Google Talk log, with OTR encryption, viewed in a different Jabber client. The history is truncated, and OTR encrypted messages are not available in readable form in this client.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One extreme point for synchronisation is the Discord chat system, where not only history and messages are kept in sync across all clients, but even preferences are unified:
Setting the desktop client to dark mode will also set dark mode on the cellphone application, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another, opposite extreme point is Jabber, which has no common rule for disposition of messages, and by default will send messages only to one client, using either a preference system, the last active client, or &amp;ldquo;all known clients to the server at the point in time the message was sent&amp;rdquo;. A lot depends on server and clients used here, creating an unreliable and hard to control user experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;deliverables---file-and-image-sharing&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#deliverables---file-and-image-sharing&#34;&gt;
	Deliverables - File and Image Sharing
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a corporate context, we use the communication mechanism as a vehicle to create and share documents, and have a discussion about the documents we work on collaboratively.
Mail was doing this in the past, with Quotes and with Attachments, but that is a very cumbersome, lossy and hard to discover mechanism.
Most companies have moved the collaboration process off mail, to a large extent, and towards chat and collaborative document systems such as Google Docs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google had taken this one step further with structured chat.
The pioneer application for that has been the short-lived Google Wave:
Wave allowed a group of people to create things in a kind of chat bubble, only that this bubble could not just hold a line of text, but also other media including rich documents, images, bots or other things that interfaced with the Wave API.
Other users could comment on an item in a hierarchic comments-on-comment tree like in a discussion system, or directly edit the original item, incorporating their changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changes were recorded and were undoable and replayable.
This allowed users to view the end result of a Wave, or review the process of building that result after the fact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-07.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Google Wave being used to collaboratively work on a shared document. The Wave contains the final document, but also the process that led to the end result.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a way, Wave could have been a salvation from the hell of corporate email:
Waves produce results, documents or agreements.
They also record the history of how that result had been reached, and they allow people joining the process late to catch up and review what has happened before on their own terms.
No more full quotes, 13 levels deep, and no more dozens of copies of the same Word file, all slightly different, and with diverging side remarks from people somewhere in the organisation, which never made it back into the main document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wave failed, though, and for multiple reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the bigger reasons is that Wave was all mechanism and no purpose &amp;ndash; it could to many things, and offered all of them without stating what Wave itself or the various functions are there for.
One could use Wave to manage a world building and game session in a role playing game, as well as replace corporate email, or use it as a rather clunky and over-engineered word processor.
So Wave needed explanation and contextualisation - and above all, a purpose, but none was given.
Wave died, because it confused users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-08.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A collaboratively edited document. Multiple watchers are shown as icons at the top of the screen. A chat window is open. Cursors and collaborators edits would be visible simultaneously editing the document in many places while it has been initially created.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wave&amp;rsquo;s legacy lives on, though.
Much of the functionality of Wave is present in Google Docs, including the side chat, collaborative editing, history recording and replay and many other functions.
Unlike Wave, Google&amp;rsquo;s shared document editing puts the purpose first, and the collaboration in the background.
This is matching people&amp;rsquo;s expectations much better, and is less overwhelming.
It does not have to be taught, or manually given purpose.
Instead, the purpose is built in, and immediately obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern chat systems are kind of the opposite:
They put their purpose (communication) first, and the documents ride in the back.
This happens either through URLs or through file transfer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All modern chat systems have a working file transfer, which is also aware of media types.
That means, not only can you drag and drop files into a 1:1 chat or a channel, but also images or animations, as well as audio files.
They are understood, and shown inline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together with other mechanisms, such as threads, they enable unique workflows that go way past the unstructured ASCII-limited text of IRC.
For example, in many workplaces designers use the image capabilities of Slack, together with Slack threads, to share images, mockups and other things and then criticize or approve designs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also where not only IRC, but also Jabber falls down.
Proper file sharing, inline media content and threading are things that may exist somewhere, in some Jabber extension, but are not generally interoperable or enabled without much configuration across a set of clients.
They might as well not exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;we-were-lucky&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#we-were-lucky&#34;&gt;
	We were lucky
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the place I work at, we were lucky.
By the time Covid pushed people to work from home, we already had replaced mail almost completely.
I was down from thousands of mail messages per day on almost one hundred mailing lists to less than a dozen messages, and no mailing lists at all anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have moved to &lt;strong&gt;Facebook at Work&lt;/strong&gt; for non-realtime group communication.
Teams were using their Facebook groups to communicate announcements and progress to other teams, and have discussions with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internally and for support we moved to &lt;strong&gt;Slack&lt;/strong&gt;.
This was pushed with considerable force from below, after corporate initially being very fond of Facebook messenger, mostly because it was free and included in Facebook at work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately FB messenger is utterly broken in many ways, and unsuited for any structured work communication without basically rewriting it from scratch.
There are many facets to its fractal brokenness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has groups, but no places.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Groups have limited attendance, and the limit is too small (the old &lt;code&gt;#live&lt;/code&gt; Jabber channel was mandatory for all people pushing deployments, and could not be reproduced in FB Messenger).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It ate data. Mentioning a filename &lt;code&gt;main.pl&lt;/code&gt; would inescapably turn this into a polish hostname &lt;a href=&#34;https://main.pl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;main.pl&lt;/a&gt;

. More often than not, Messenger would detect a malware phishing attempt and prevent you from sending the message.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It ate data. Mentioning URLs with array parameters (&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://example.com/bla?a=1&amp;amp;a=2&amp;amp;a=3%22&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://example.com/bla?a=1&amp;a=2&amp;a=3&#34;&lt;/a&gt;

) would make it parse the URL, representing the keys in a hash, and dropping the repeated keys, breaking the URL.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It could not handle files, code formatting and many other things well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It could not do threads, which are a necessity in high volume support channels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, corp was forced to also purchase Slack on top of FB at Work, to prevent a more or less open revolt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had been using &lt;strong&gt;Google Drive and Google Office&lt;/strong&gt;, as well, across the company, and the collaborative features in it were well understood and used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heterogeneity of all of this posed to be not a problem, somewhat surprisingly.
In fact, in many cases, the mix-and-match approach enabled us to be flexible, and work around many tools limitations, and also to expand and integrate other things easily.
Other applications (e.g. Miro, but also many others) have since been added for many users, who have other, more specialized needs and requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also used to use BlueJeans, before the pandemic, and mostly from meeting room installations with dedicated hardware.
During Covid, Zoom became popular, and offered a richer and much better set of clients, especially on mobile devices (Laptops, Tablets, Cellphones), so we switched vendors here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key learnings are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We already had tooling for Remote First, but had hardly any need to use them properly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We were hardly using Email with all its glorious brokenness anymore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By happy accident, the core tools (FB at Work, Slack) had Places, not Groups, as a core metaphor, and people structured their work around these places.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborative document editing and a rich, structured chat complement each other well. But since Facebook and Google both are unable to make such a thing, we have yet another vendor integrated. This turned out to be an actual advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our key deficits have not been discussed at length here, but are related:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google Office documents have very bad discoverability and Google Office has no places.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corollary: A process is needed and needs to be manually executed to move content from the collaborative phase to the publication phase, elsewhere.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By public decree in our place this is going to be Confluence, which has problems of its own, and also poses a document conversion problem (from Google to Confluence internal format, keeping structure).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code Collaboration is not part of other collaboration at all, and lives in a third, and entirely disconnected space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pan Narrans and Better Meetings</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/10/10/pan-narrans-and-better-meetings.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 12:13:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/10/10/pan-narrans-and-better-meetings.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When you are looking for a better &lt;em&gt;Remote First&lt;/em&gt; culture, you are looking for better meetings.
If you go for better meetings, you will also have fewer of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/362504-the-anthropologists-got-it-wrong-when-they-named-our-species&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/pan-narrans-01.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The anthropologists got it wrong when they named our species Homo sapiens (&amp;lsquo;wise man&amp;rsquo;). In any case it&amp;rsquo;s an arrogant and bigheaded thing to say, wisdom being one of our least evident features. In reality, we are Pan narrans, the storytelling chimpanzee.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going for a written culture helps, going for storytelling will help even more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;storytelling&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#storytelling&#34;&gt;
	Storytelling
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost 15 years ago, I wrote about an experience with the roleplaying game &lt;em&gt;Primetime Adventures&lt;/em&gt;.
If you are reading German, &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2008/10/05/drsrm-2008-primetime-adventures.html&#34;&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things to take away from Primetime Adventures is that &amp;ldquo;on screen&amp;rdquo; nothing happens without reason, all interactions serve the story.
And the story is always about conflict:
Anything from misunderstandings to misaligned goals, from disagreement about a mission to disagreement about fundamental values, from friendly competition to outright fighting over starved resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end it does not matter, but screen time is always about the current conflict, because to the Storytelling Chimpanzee this is what it&amp;rsquo;s about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is, at the core, also true about meetings.
If they are not about conflict, they are not worth your time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does not have to be conflict about the people in the meeting.
The meeting does not have to resolve the conflict (but should progress it somewhow).
But in every meeting there is some kind of conflict in the background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember: Not all conflict is drama, in fact, most is not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;understanding-conflict&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#understanding-conflict&#34;&gt;
	Understanding conflict
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when you go for meetings, prepare an Agenda.
If you are invited to a meeting without an Agenda, decline it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is a good Agenda?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make an agenda and make it self-contained.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It should itemize the things you would like to talk about.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each item should have a short summary (&amp;ldquo;What happened so far&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Last week on …&amp;rdquo;) or link to one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should invite the people you need to talk to about the thing, the stakeholders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then send the agenda around well in advance, maybe share a link to a shared document.
Allow people to change, amend, and comment the agenda.
Force them to interact with the document in some way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your goal, ultimately, is to either not have a meeting, because all agree.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or have a meeting, but only about the things you disagree about.
Or people have questions about things, which can only be resolved interactively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So invite people to actually comment.
Invite long form, have them write in the text.
Sidenotes are horrible to read, and basically are good for &lt;strong&gt;+1&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/strong&gt; only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Invite people to agree with you, in the document, or to specify where the disagreement is exactly.
Disagreement can take many forms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can be insecurity (&amp;ldquo;The plan looks good in principle, but I fear that…&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can be misalignment (&amp;ldquo;You want to do …, but we actually need … on our side.&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can be resource shortage (&amp;ldquo;You want … from us, but that would require us to …, and we can&amp;rsquo;t do that in this Quarter.&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can be many other things. It always signals a need to communicate more, about a specific thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;commenting-on-agendas-kills-meetings&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#commenting-on-agendas-kills-meetings&#34;&gt;
	Commenting on Agendas kills meetings
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the Agenda and the Agenda Prep to collect agreement.
If there is no disagreement, it&amp;rsquo;s fine to not have the meeting, because the reason to have one just vanished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is disagreement, you now know where, and how, and what specifically is the perceived or real problem.
You can spend interactive time exactly on these things, and go over possible reconciliations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this is all in a shared document, y&amp;rsquo;all can amend the discussion with additional writing and sidenotes as needed.
This is automatically also the meeting notes, so make sure they contain whatever the outcomes are y&amp;rsquo;all collectively agreed to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark up deliverables, deadlines and people responsible.
Set a deadline with a followup meeting (which you can then try to kill in advance, too).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;kickoffs-cannot-be-killed&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#kickoffs-cannot-be-killed&#34;&gt;
	Kickoffs cannot be killed
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One exception are kickoff meetings.
They exist to present the project, and project goals, to set the framework and to make sure you are talking to the right people, and &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the right people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They exist also for socializing, specifically to enable people to make the necessary connections.
You will be working together, you need to know each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So make it short, to the point, and make sure people can connect with each other directly afterwards, on their own.
This is important, because kickoffs cannot be killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reporting-meetings-can-focus-on-interesting-stuff&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#reporting-meetings-can-focus-on-interesting-stuff&#34;&gt;
	Reporting meetings can focus on interesting stuff
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding conflict, isolating interesting topics to talk about, also applies to reporting meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reporting meetings always read a lot of slides with a lot of numbers.
Everybody zones out.
&amp;ldquo;Last weeks SLOs for … were met completely, and we improved …&amp;rdquo;
Nobody is interested, skip that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all can look at the green in the report in advance.
Instead use the reporting meeting to speak about interesting things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be the &lt;em&gt;story&lt;/em&gt; of an outage, and what we learned.
It can be about the &lt;em&gt;story&lt;/em&gt; of an improvement, and how it will prevent a certain class of failure.
Or tell the &lt;em&gt;story&lt;/em&gt; of how you work, how you improve work, or how you work differently than other companies do, if that is useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing &lt;em&gt;stories&lt;/em&gt; about practice is much more interesting that reading numbers from a slide that is all green anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or skip the meeting.
If the numbers are all fine and there are no learnings, no interaction is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;making-it-interesting-making-it-valuable&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#making-it-interesting-making-it-valuable&#34;&gt;
	Making it interesting, making it valuable
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, finding out, in advance, what the meeting should be about, always means finding the conflict, determining its nature, and the stakes.
Uneven information, misaligned goals, differences about implementation or scope, resource allocation, whatever.
Knowing this, maybe even preparing alternatives, and then either developing or discovering them interactively, or deciding on them collectively helps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also automatically prepares the meeting minutes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Agenda collects agreement, and preparing the meeting from the residual conflict in the Agenda then makes it simple to have minutes.
We have shared documents in 2022, so there is an easy way to make sure all voices are recorded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;providing-value&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#providing-value&#34;&gt;
	Providing value
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shared documents are also a burden:
They are hard to discover, maintain and organize.
I am increasingly a supporter of the idea that Google Docs should auto-delete after 3 months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want deliverables, put them elsewhere, anywhere.
Heck, even Confluence would be a better location than a Google Drive.
In any case, you can create a consolidated version of the current state in a proper document, and then collect or link the path that led to it and attach it as documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;rsquo;t take meeting notes and call them deliverables, though.
That won&amp;rsquo;t work.
It never did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So a discussion with interactive and written elements, is also a documentation evolution process, in which we collectively work on a deliverable: the architecture, documentation and implementation of a process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a proper store, and not in shared documents, much less in volatile spoken discussion without any record or recording.
We work to distill information, to shape an idea, and to bring it into the world, in a proper deliverable and in code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because that is what a company is about:
Making agreements on how we work together on a common thing (and building infrastructure to make this easier).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we have meeting agendas to collect agreement, and to sharpen disagreement, we have interactive meetings to find and ultimately document conflict resolutions, and we then put these back into the deliverable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the heart of asynchronous distributed collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if somebody asks you:
&amp;ldquo;What did your org learn to do differently in the last 3 years?&amp;rdquo;
and the answer is unlike the above:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did you do instead? How did your org evolve?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;addenda&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#addenda&#34;&gt;
	Addenda
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This started out as a Twitter thread.
There have been reactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Florian Haas pointed to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://xahteiwi.eu/resources/presentations/devopsdays-berlin-2022/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;really good writeup&lt;/a&gt;

 about writing of his.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He also mentions: &amp;ldquo;Re project kickoffs, never do them without preparing a 5-paragraph brief. Better still, circulate it ahead of the kickoff.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spaces</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/02/21/spaces.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2022 11:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/02/21/spaces.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On the morning of Saturday, 22nd February 2020, two years ago, my colleagues and I woke up to the a message from the company that said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Spaces&amp;rdquo; Closed for Operations 23 Feb - 28 Feb&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the morning hours of Saturday, 22 February, a fire occurred on the first floor of the &amp;ldquo;Spaces&amp;rdquo; building.
The fire was extinguished promptly but due to smoke and residue particles that spread throughout the building, we will not be able to open &amp;ldquo;Spaces&amp;rdquo; for at least one weeks time.
The closure of the building is required to ensure we fully inspect the building, our equipment, clean the office of all smoke damage and residue and more importantly, ensure we have a safe working environment to return to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It then took exactly one month instead of one week to fix that, and the planned reopening of the building fell on the exact day of the beginning of the COVID-19 lockdown.
So it has been today two years ago that I worked in an office the last time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote into a company forum one year ago:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be keeping this up until at least October, and I would be surprised if we are not going to be doing this for much longer the way this country handles Covid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this is the cluttered mess of my Desk at home:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/02/spaces-1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Home machine, and lab equipment to the left, company Mac on the desk during the daytime, bunch of books left and right. On top, the stick for my Internet Spaceship. Under the desk to the right, the file server and gaming box.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is very… lived in. I do change things too often for any pretty cabling or other cleanup to hold up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/02/spaces-2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;At least it has a decent view. That one hour commute to Spaces did pay off with a much more rural and spacious environment for home.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But at least the view from my Desk is decent…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am sitting on a Dauphin Shape XXL, a proper office chair instead of some gaming thing, and the desk is an older IKEA standing desk, motorized.
I have cabled Internet at my desk, Wifi by Unifi in the house, and we have a 500/500 Mbit fiber connection at home, because faster Internet is not available where I live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life ain’t bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never has been, actually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back, I always had a desk to work on at home. In Berlin, an entire room (which also had an office desk for my wife).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/02/spaces-3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Geek wife doing geek wifey things on her Berlin desk.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Karlsruhe, my GF and I had work desks in an office room, and actually almost never did use our living room.
We sat back to back, because that makes it easy to roll over and look at the other screen to check things out and help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Kiel we had an office/living room double room, but the living room really saw use only on Tuesdays every other week for the Tuesday meeting, when a bunch of Geeks were coming around for cooking and talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even as a student, having a working desk was more important than a proper living room, actually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/02/spaces-4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1996 computer science student desk (see below &amp;ndash; 1)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I am thinking about it, I believe it’s because of my Dad.
He had a Ham Radio license, and “his” place in the house always was his shack, with all the electronics, the radios and antenna controls, basically a desk and a workbench next to it.
You’d find him more often there than anywhere else in the house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do we even have living rooms?
It’s a social convention that is hard to break.
I know that I would be in for a fight to the blood suggesting that we get rid of ours, but seriously?
“My” space is that desk/shack shown above, and not the living room.
It’s the place that I’ll fight for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussing this elsewhere, a friend sends me &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CJWOWksT1x4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Space &amp;ndash; A cluttered life: Middle-Class Abundance&lt;/a&gt;

.
The video discusses space use in American middle class families, who seem to have lives centered around the kitchen/eating space, which makes a lot of sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That 1996 desk.
That version of me had a Euro-ISDN semipermanent connection to my provider (128/128 kBit/s) and I also spent 50 Deutschmark for my own /24 provider independent IPv4 range.
All my machines had public addresses.
The machine is a Nextstation with 24 MB of memory, and a 25 MHz 68040 CPU, running what later would become MacOS X.
The white tower next to it has a 1 GB SCSI HDD full height (the two top slots), a 1x SCSI CD-ROM drive (Caddies required) and a SCSI QIC drive for DC 6525 tapes (525 MB/tape).
My body hides the full height tower case for the Dual-Pentium Linux box, you can only see the beige case of the b/w monitor it has.
We were using BNC based 10 MBit/s Ethernet at that time.
This box also has the ISDN card.
Unfortunately the driver had a memory leak, and we were losing a bit of memory every time the ISDN link goes up or down, because some driver internal data structures are allocated and never deallocated.
The loss accumulates to around 1 MB per week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Die kommende Kündigungswelle</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/11/12/die-kommende-kuendigungswelle.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Nov 2021 11:28:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/11/12/die-kommende-kuendigungswelle.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ein guter Freund sinnierte gestern mit anderen Freunden von mir über die Situation auf der Arbeit und schrieb mir heute:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wie man es auch dreht und wendet: Corona ist auch ein Lackmustest für Unternehmen in ihrer Rolle als Arbeitgeber.
Anhand der vierten Welle lässt sich das hervorragend nachvollziehen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denn Unternehmen und Organisationen, denen am Wohl ihrer Mitarbeiter/-innen etwas liegt, haben schon vor Wochen überall dort, wo es möglich ist, ihre Leute kategorisch wieder ins Homeoffice geschickt und Präsenzveranstaltungen untersagt.
Das hat selten etwas damit zu tun, dass diese Unternehmen herausragend schlau wären.
Viel mehr schauen diese Unternehmen sich ausgehend vom Wunsch, die eigenen Leute nicht zu gefährden, ihr Corona-Handling dort ab, wo es funktioniert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unternehmen beispielsweise, die sich an Israel orientieren, werden ihre Leute frühestens bei flächendeckender Booster-Impfung der eigenen Belegschaft wieder in die Büros rufen, falls überhaupt.
Unternehmen hingegen, die sich an den Richtlinien der deutschen Bundesregierung orientieren, pochen oft seit Wochen schon darauf, in die sich aufbauende vierte Welle hinein die Anwesenheitszeiten in den Büros zu erhöhen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist tragisch, weil es so vorhersehbar katastrophale wie vermeidbare Folgen haben wird.
Wer Leute notlos in den ÖPNV zwingt, obwohl sie nicht geboostert sind, exponiert sie unnötig einem erhöhten Risiko.
Wer Leute notlos ins Büro ruft, obwohl diese nicht impfbare Familienmitglieder im selben Haushalt haben, exponiert sie unnötig einem erhöhten Risiko.
Unternehmen, die so agieren, machen sich schuldig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Menschen in diesen Unternehmen sollten das Corona-Handling ihres Arbeitgebers jedenfalls genau beobachten.
Wer die Belegschaft unabhängig vom Impfstatus wieder ins Büro ruft, betreibt das Geschäft der Impfgegner.
Denn dann entsteht der Eindruck, der Impfstatus sei im Wesentlichen egal.
Wer nur geimpfte Menschen notlos ins Büro ruft, schafft dadurch indirekt sogar Incentives für Impfgegner, weil Homeoffice dann zu einem Privileg für diese wird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beides wäre unerträglich.
Und Menschen in diesen Firmen sollten ihren AG durchaus wissen lassen, dass das unerträglich ist.
Falls alle Stricke reißen:
Kündigen und Namen der Manager notieren, damit man in deren Fängen sicher nie mehr landet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bei den Amis heißt das &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Resignation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Great Resignation&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic has allowed workers to rethink their careers, work conditions, and long-term goals.
As many workplaces attempted to bring their employees in-person, workers desired the freedom to work from home given during the pandemic.
With telecommuting also came schedule flexibility, which was the primary reason to look for a new job of the majority of those studied by Bankrate in August 2021.
Additionally, many workers, particularly in younger cohorts, are seeking to gain a better work–life balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist die mildeste Formulierung, die ich gefunden habe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tatsächlich arbeiten &amp;ldquo;wir&amp;rdquo; im März 2022 seit 2 Jahren von zu Hause und/oder unter Pandemie-Bedingungen, und außerhalb der traditionellen Bürostrukturen und -hierarchien.
Einige Firmen haben sich anpassen können.
Von denen hat keine ein Problem mit Churn oder Hiring, also damit, Personal halten zu können und neues anzuwerben.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es sind die Läden, die die Realität der vergangenen 2 Jahre negieren, die jetzt bluten, und zwar vom Kopfe her.
Und Mitarbeiter, die seit 2 Jahren bewiesen haben, daß sie sehr gut und erfolgreich arbeiten können,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ohne daß sie jeden Tag 2 Stunden im Berufsverkehr verschwenden,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ohne daß das Kind als Schlüsselkind nach Hause kommen muss,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ohne daß ihnen das Management auf die Bildschirme glotzt,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;und ohne daß sie 3 von 8 Stunden pro Tag in Meetings zu bringen, von denen für sie maximal 20 Minuten relevant sind,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;solche Leute brechen jetzt auf - in Firmen, die anders arbeiten, in Berufe, die das nicht notwendig machen oder in ein Umfeld, das weniger dem späten 19. Jahrhundert verhaftet ist. Die Zukunft der Arbeit ist gerade angekommen, und die Leute ziehen um.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gerade bei den Wissensarbeitern ist das so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich habe 5 Jahre studiert und danach 3 Jahre Projekte gemacht und Dir jetzt gerade 2 Jahre lang bewiesen, daß ich mich selbst organisieren kann, und jetzt willst Du mich im Büro haben, damit Du Dich nicht so alleine fühlst?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kann man machen. Nicht schlau. So gar nicht.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit:&lt;/strong&gt; Nachtrag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jemand schickt mir diesen &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sueddeutsche.de/wirtschaft/overemployed-home-office-usa-1.5461910&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;paywalled link zur SZ&lt;/a&gt;

, von dem eh nur der Anreißer interessant ist. Der Artikel beschreibt unter dem Begriff &amp;ldquo;Overemployed&amp;rdquo; Personen, die im Homeoffice so effizient sind, daß sie zwei bezahlte Vollzeitstellen besetzen, ohne Wissen der jeweiligen Arbeitgeber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das geht natürlich nur mit &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bullshit_Jobs&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;David Graeber&amp;rsquo;s Bullshit Jobs&lt;/a&gt;

, aber es ist natürlich auch ein Zeichen dafür, daß die Arbeit, die diese Personen ausführen weder produktiv, noch notwendig noch sinnstiftend ist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich antwortete mit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich kann nur den Teaser lesen, aber das ist das, was wir im Informatik-Studium Semester 2 (und 4) gemacht haben.
Also 3 Leute in die Inf 2 Vorlesung schicken, parallel 3 Leute in Inf 4.
Mit dem Rest (gut 20 Leute, Rotationssystem) die Vorlesungen von 2x 90 Minuten in 45 Minuten durchziehen, und dann in 45 Minuten die Aufgaben machen.
Das hat sehr, sehr böses Blut gegeben&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Antwort war:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dafür hatten wir [bei uns] die Mitschriften AG. Etwas anderer Studienablauf bei Nicht-Informatikern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit:&lt;/strong&gt; Nachtrag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Einige Arbeitgeber insistieren dringend, daß &amp;ldquo;Mitarbeiter wenigstens einen Tag in der Woche im Büro sind&amp;rdquo;, ohne das näher zu begründen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bohrt man unauffällig und inoffiziell nach, heißt es &amp;ldquo;Wir haben sehr viele Expats, und wenn die statt von hier von ihrem Heimatland aus arbeiten, dann kommen wir von der Unternehmenssteuer her in Teufels Küche.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unter Umständen sollte man hier offener kommunizieren, und dann versuchen, kooperativ Lösungen zu finden, denn unerklärliches blockierendes Verhalten eines Arbeitgebers ist in diesem Zusammenhang nicht produktiv und führt wieder zur Kündigungswelle.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vijzelbuurt is changing</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/10/08/vijzelbuurt-is-changing.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 18:11:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/10/08/vijzelbuurt-is-changing.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Back when I was still commuting to work in an office, in the far past, I used to be in the Spaces building in Vijzelgracht in Amsterdam, every day. Mark Wagenbuur of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/bicycledutch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BicycleDutch&lt;/a&gt;

 has been there today, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BicycleDutch/status/1314213038908559361&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BicycleDutch/status/1314213038908559361&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bicycledutch-tweet.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Amsterdam is changing dramatically. I was in Vijzelstraat for the first time in about 2 years and I was pleasantly surprised! Looked up the old situation in Google StreetView for some before and afters.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also linked to &lt;a href=&#34;https://archief.amsterdam/beeldbank/detail/03429525-d56a-9371-d7ba-d3258ecdc8e3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;an image from the  Stadsarchief&lt;/a&gt;

 where the situation in 1987 is shown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These works are documented on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/projecten&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;City of Amsterdam website&lt;/a&gt;

, which also has a page for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/projecten/vijzelstraat-herinrichting/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Vijzelstraat: herinrichting&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/vijzelstraat-goal.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The desired end state for the space in front of Spaces, Vijzelstraat 66.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The works are part of &lt;a href=&#34;https://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rode_Loper_%28Amsterdam%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Project Rode Loper&lt;/a&gt;

, which is the renewal and redesign of all urban space on top of the new Noord/Zuidlijn, Metro 52, after the completion of the Metro works in 2018. The Vijzelstraat works are the conclusion of this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The City of Amsterdam has a fabulous video channel on Youtube, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCkq8uEQ0rl4NiJnO8mL7y_w&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Het Verkeer&lt;/a&gt;

, which announces and explains all street works and renewal. The Vijzelgracht project of course &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-vu-ExAlzWE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;also has a video&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-vu-ExAlzWE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/vijzelstraat-video.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Video announcing the Vijzelstraat works.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly there are two more projects active that match and extend the Rode Loper in this area:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/projecten/vijzelgrachtgarage/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/vijzelgracht-garage.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/projecten/vijzelgrachtgarage/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Vijzelgracht: afbouw Vijzelgrachtgarage&lt;/a&gt;

 - The City is building a paid-for underground parking garage in the space between the metro station Vijzelgracht and the street level. This will provide paid-for parking space for 270 cars, similar to the Parkeergarage Museumskwartier, which is serving Frans-Hals-Buurt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/projecten/vijzelbuurt-parkeerluw/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Vijzelbuurt: parkeerluw&lt;/a&gt;

 - Matching the extremely successful conversion of Frans-Hals-Buurt (around 500m north of Vijzelgracht), free and paid-for on street parking is almost completely removed, freeing up public space for fietsers, pedestrians, playing children and city green. The change will affect two local neighborhoods, Weteringbuurt and Noorderbuurt. The city has &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/projecten/vijzelbuurt-parkeerluw/nieuws-vijzelbuurt/ontwerpsessies-weteringbuurt/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;local consultations&lt;/a&gt;

 with the people living there right now.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rolling back a rollout</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/01/17/rolling-back-a-rollout.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 19:53:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/01/17/rolling-back-a-rollout.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Florian Haas &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/xahteiwi/status/1217903825824120834&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;asks on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/01/rolling-back.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;How do you solve reliable rollback. The definition of a reliable rollback being: &amp;lsquo;get reset &amp;ndash;hard &lt;ref&gt;&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;git push -f&amp;rsquo; and then magic happening that returns your infra to the exact state it was at &lt;ref&gt;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is relatively easy to solve with modern infrastructure-as-code for anything that is stateless. It becomes a bit more involved when you are dealing with things with state, such as database instances or Zookeepers or similar things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My reply on Twitter begins &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/isotopp/status/1218162310956638209&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;

. I am basing my writeup on that reply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;devops-what-does-that-even-mean&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#devops-what-does-that-even-mean&#34;&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;Devops&amp;rdquo;, what does that even mean?
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2015, I gave a talk titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2015/03/27/go-away-or-i-will-replace-you.html&#34;&gt;Go away, or I will replace you with a little shell script&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; as a keynote for the GUUG FFG 2015 in Stuttgart. The german language slides are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/isotopp/go-away-or-i-will-replace-you-with-a-little-shell-script&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;

, the english slides are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/isotopp/go-away-of-i-will-replace-you-with-a-little-shell-script-english&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;

 and a Youtube video of the Froscon version of the talk is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=e0CCv7pSK4s&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;

. Unfortunately, the video is the german language version of that talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk focuses on how the sysadmin profession started to die out somewhere around 2001, when we invented horizontal scaleout and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/yesthattom&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tom Limoncelli&lt;/a&gt;

 published the first edition of &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://the-sysadmin-book.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Practice of System Administration&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;. That book explained in one chapter the role of the sysadmin in the greater corporate organisation and how to cooperate with, not fight against users. The term and the practice of Devops evolved in this decade, until in 2008 &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/patrickdebois&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Patrick Debois&lt;/a&gt;

 coined the actual term &amp;ldquo;Devops&amp;rdquo;, which we use today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term has been abused a lot, but what does it actually mean? In one slide I show this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/isotopp/go-away-of-i-will-replace-you-with-a-little-shell-script-english#19&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/01/rolling-away.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Go away or I will replace you with a little Shell Script (english) - Slide 19&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modern development environment according to Devops, and the technical meaning of the term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In todays language, I would phrase these items as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Infrastructure as code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Version Control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CI/CD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Separation of Rollout and Activation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proper Observability with centralized, structured logs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good instant communication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Infrastructure As Code&lt;/em&gt; describes a way of declaring the execution environment for your code, in code. Code that can be checked in and versioned like the application code itself. Openstack Heat Scripts, AWS Cloud Formation, Kubernetes Deployment Specifications or your Terraform all qualify as this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this, you can recreate and redeploy your execution environment together with your application, as part of the build and deployment automation. It also means that you get rid of the endlessly fragile state manipulation engines that are Puppet, Ansible, Chef, Salt and CFEngine. You create, build and deploy images and you run immutable infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because all of that code and infrastructure declaration are files, you want &lt;em&gt;Version Control&lt;/em&gt;, which in 2020 means, you want all of this in git. This is so normal by now that anything that is not git-able is considered broken and weird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you check in, you want to be processed automatically. So you push it through a &lt;em&gt;CI/CD pipeline&lt;/em&gt;, which pushes things through whatever pre-production environments you have (many have Dev, Staging and Prod). This, in 2020, probably includes formatting to coding standards, linting, sonarcubing, and whatever tests you wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, your code is rolled out. And a key invention - one that is not yet done by enough people - is &lt;em&gt;separation of Rollout and Activation&lt;/em&gt; by the means of an experiment framework. More on that below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When application code runs, it is appending messages, measurements and context to a hash of hashes. This collection will be pushed into an event processor at the end of a request. Ours is called &amp;ldquo;Booking Events&amp;rdquo;. If you happen to work elsewhere, an Observabilty tool such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://honeycomb.io&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Honeycomb.io&lt;/a&gt;

 is the closest to Booking Events I have been able to find outside of Booking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using this, you alert and push alerts out through a multitude of channels, including Pagerduty, and whatever you use instead of Slack. Humans are being alerted to a situation, and can act on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;separation-of-rollout-and-activation-and-dual-use-experimentation&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#separation-of-rollout-and-activation-and-dual-use-experimentation&#34;&gt;
	Separation of Rollout and Activation, and Dual Use Experimentation
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned above, the separation of rollout and activation is a key invention that makes rollouts possible. It also makes testing in production safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first iteration, an experiment framework allows you to push code into production that never runs. You can then, through feature flags, activate your code for yourself, or a chosen subset of customers based on whatever selectors your frame work offers. I often quote &amp;ldquo;5% of the population of guest country .jp with a user-agent string that suggests MacOS&amp;rdquo; as an example, but it is really a function of the experiment framework you build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See a very old talk from 2012 of mine: &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/isotopp/8-rollouts-a-day&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;8 rollouts a day&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6qFNwNEeG1w&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;

) for an ancient take on all of this. This is not new technology, we have been doing this for ages, and just iterated on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having an experiment framework means that the scaffolding for activation in code is formalized and tested, so errors in gating entry to new code are unlikely to happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also means that a control framework exists where you can see experiments that are active, who is exposed to them, and that participation in an experiment is recorded in a user click history. You probably want to record experiment config changes in your monitoring wallgraphs so that a change in observed behavior is linked to possible causes for that in an obvious and in-your-face way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also important for customer support: A CS agent needs to be able to see what the customers sees or has seen, if an experiment is a UI/UX experiment. UI/UX variants should be available to CS agents at will, so that they are able to match and retrace customer experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having experimentation available obviously means that variant code is in execution concurrently. Or in terms of rollouts: Old and new code run at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For state management, it means that schema changes or similar data adjustments need to be done in advance. They also need to be done in a way that is compatible with the old and the new code. That is not hard to do, and can be done in a robust testable way. You want to package it, and run a bunch of checks on schema changes automatically, so you can detect best practice violation and prevent these from being checked into staging and prod.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, you need that table change framework anyway, because SOX will eventually want that from you. You probably will end up with a web frontend and API for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/doc/percona-toolkit/LATEST/pt-online-schema-change.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;pt-online-schema-change&lt;/a&gt;

 accessible to end users in a way that also advises them automatically on best practice. This also scales better than your DBAs checking manually for the presence of a PK, NULLable columns, columns that are DOUBLE but suggest monetary values in their names, and similar things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, at this point you can push code into staging and prod in a way that the old and new variants of the code can coexist on whatever schema you have and can run concurrently, depending on what variant of which experiment the user is in. You can finally &lt;em&gt;activate&lt;/em&gt; code for a few users, and see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your second iteration of the experiment framework will therefore measure the &lt;em&gt;impact&lt;/em&gt; of the experiment, and by that I do not only mean the business impact, but also the technical impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Business impact measurements would answer questions such as &amp;ldquo;What influence has Experiment 17 on conversion?&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Does variant B of experiment 17 not only improve conversion, but also customer support call rate, and if so, it is still a positive experiment in the monetary sense&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as a gate to the entry of code paths, the experiment framework can also encapsulate Probes that collect metrics over a Span, delivering technical measurements about the performance cost of an experiment. I can ask questions such as &amp;ldquo;Show me all messages in variant B of rollout 64fd32f that never appear when running variant A&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;What messages appear since rollout 64fd32f that did not appear before&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can also carry metrics and classify them by experiment related selectors. &amp;ldquo;Show me SQL time spent in variant B compared to variant A of rollout 64fd32f in all sections guarded by experiment 13, normalized by number of executions&amp;rdquo;. In other words, what exactly is the latency contribution of experiment 13b, since 64fd32f?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And because I have access to the unshortened, unaggregated raw event data persisted elsewhere, at any point in time I can ask the framework to actually show me the SQL, once I have a selector that finds me the delta I was looking for, and highlight the things that are only present here and not elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is the Dual Use value of an experiment framework: You get the business value out of that, testing hypothesis on draft code in production before you spend engineering hours on things that aren&amp;rsquo;t going to make you richer. That is, in terms of bug stages, finding bugs in requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/01/rolling-relative-bugfix-cost.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/isotopp/8-rollouts-a-day&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;8 rollouts a day (2012), Slide 19&lt;/a&gt;

: Relative cost of a bugfix in various stages of the code lifecycle. Fixing broken requirements is the cheapest.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you also get the technical cost of that, in terms of running the prototype code. That enables you to assess the added execution cost vs. the estimated engineering effort to speed it up. In other words, your engineers only ever work on code that is proven to make you richer, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; you also know how much running it will cost you in AWS units or engineering hours and you can prioritise things properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, since A and B variants coexist, if B is known to be bad, you not only can roll that back, you don&amp;rsquo;t even have to. Simply turning off activation of B gives you instant silence in production - the known bad variant is still present, but never run for anybody. You can then triage and come up with a resolution of the situation on your own terms. Either you eliminate the B variant and roll back, or you fix B and roll forward. Either way, this is done completely out of the execution path and also without any time pressure constraints on the decision making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sum-of-all-these-parts&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#the-sum-of-all-these-parts&#34;&gt;
	The Sum of All These Parts
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sum of these parts is much more than each individual capability gives you. Together they give you an environment that allows you to roll back and forward, at will. And you will be doing this in an informed way. You can reason about code in production, and act on the outcome of that discussion. And you are doing this outside of crisis mode and any time constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separation of Rollout and Activation is a Key Invention here. Put this into an Experimentation Framework, and create a dashboard/control/overview board around this that gives information about running and disabled experiments, experiment outcomes in terms of business and technical data, and that links to raw events and metrics generated from the raw events directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marrying an experiment framework + dashboard with a Honeycomb-like observability system, and with pointers to tags, releases and rollouts in your code base allows naviagation between all of these things in an integrated way. It enables product and tech people alike in a unique way to reason about code, what that code does to the business, UX, income, and also resource consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can direct business decisions, because it allows safe rapid development and deployment of draft business expierments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can direct engineering decisions, because it tells you what is safe, and what isn&amp;rsquo;t, what is good enough and what isn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It informs product management and backlog decisions, because it links technical cost, potential business income and resource usage cost so that business and tech reason about code at eye level - one single source of truth, and one single set of metrics spanning the lowest levels of tech to business metrics like conversion, cuca call rates, cancellations and other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After doing that a while, your code will be littered with Experiment Gateways that either protect and measure code that is full-on or perma-off. All of that code is technical debt and needs to be evaluated, and cleaned up. In this way, the experiment framework, even in the final stage of its usefulness acts as visual markup for technical debt assessment and as a guide for garbage code collection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reliable-rollbacks-and-testing-in-production&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#reliable-rollbacks-and-testing-in-production&#34;&gt;
	Reliable Rollbacks and Testing In Production
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can even use this data to build predictors for expected business behavior, and alert on deviations. &amp;ldquo;According to observed growth and data from last year, last month and last week, we would expect x bookings per minute, but see m fewer, so something is likely wrong. That started 10 minutes ago at the yellow activation line of experiment 13&amp;rdquo; is a thing where I live, and turning off 13 before even looking for possible root causes is a complete no-brainer. In 95% of the cases or more it actually fixes the incident for now, so that any followup is done again outside of panic mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/01/rolling-production.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is: Testing In Production Is A Safe Thing To Do - if you build an environment that makes it survivable. The key ingredients are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Education&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awareness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Empowerment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reference that in both talks I linked above: Education means you not only need your general craft, the IT you learned at school, in university or in previous jobs. You also need to learn the local knowledge. We encapsulate that in the two questions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you break it, will you even notice?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you break it, can you fix it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first question asks if you do know you dependencies and dependents for any subsystem that you change. If you don&amp;rsquo;t that&amp;rsquo;s okay, we will teach you. That&amp;rsquo;s why we are here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you write a patch, gate it in an experiment and then ask &amp;ldquo;Is this good? Can I roll that out?&amp;rdquo;, you are asking the wrong person. There is one expert on the whole planet for that change you just wrote, and that is you. You need to be able to answer the question &amp;ldquo;If you break it, will you even notice&amp;rdquo; with a confident yes in order to be admitted to production. Nobody but you will know the proper answer to that question, ever. We can only help you to find the &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo; by teaching you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also a question of attitude, and it has to be coming from the top. Back in the day when &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/keeskoolen&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kees&lt;/a&gt;

 was CEO, he usually ate with everybody else in the canteen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A typical conversation that happened similarly more than once is Kees asking somebody: &amp;ldquo;I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen you before. Are you new?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Yes, of course. I started 3 weeks ago.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;And&amp;rdquo;, Kees would ask, in one way or the other, &amp;ldquo;did you break production already?&amp;rdquo; The newbie would of course answer &amp;ldquo;No, of course not!&amp;rdquo; and get the usual response &amp;ldquo;So what am I paying you for?&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moral in this is that errors and downtimes are a part of doing business. Of course we would like to have infrastructure where these things do not happen, or minimise impact, but velocity and risk taking are a thing of value to a fast company. By having an error budget (the integral between the predicted income and the actual income) and checking that things are within the error budget, management has a control that allows them to check on the state of the engineering culture. If we are over the error budget, we probably need to look at our ways, and the state of our education and practice. If we are under error budget a lot, we are probably not moving fast enough and are too risk averse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the instrumentation around this - CI/CD, dev and staging, experiment framework and observability framework - exist to make better use of the error budget and get most out of our invest into corporate improvement and organisational learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second question asks if you know how to fix the things that your change may break. It is not only a question about scope, but also a question about your network. That is, because in any reasonably large system you won&amp;rsquo;t be able to put it together alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should expect to need help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s people that help, not positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you should not answer &amp;ldquo;I will need a DBA around just in case&amp;rdquo;, but you should know if Debs, Greg or Simon would be better to have around in your case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With your education covered, and especially the necessary local knowledge amending your general education, you&amp;rsquo;d then have to be aware of your environment. That ties back to the upper part of this writeup. With probes and annotions from Spans covering Experiment gateways, you will have to access the data collected in your event logging system, your observability pipeline to understand the state and health of your system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it is that exact state, and the detailed data that will tell you the story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aggregations are important, they point you into a general direction. But it is the raw data that contains the evidence you need. It is the ability to slice and dice the raw data along arbitrary dimensions at will that will allow you to make the precise cut which isolates the buggy cases from the non-buggy behavior. It will allow you to look at the precise delta in exposed state of your distributed system of dependencies that causes the abnormal behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logs and metrics are good, essential for checks and alerts, to handle known cases and navigate known waters safely. Events, and the ability to search, sort, aggregate and correlate on events at will, are what enable you to see and debug a distributed and developing production system. Experiments, separation of rollout and activation, with integrated Probes in Spans, allow you to collect this data, and to act, by disabling code that introduces undesireable behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rollout is likely to be safe, because any new code you roll out is never executed in production. Unless you activate it. In the end you will find that it is not the rollout sparklines in your graphs that matter, it&amp;rsquo;s the config change sparklines that need watching. You can turn on things for yourself, for a subset of the population, or, if you have gradually built confidence, full on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Full on (or full off and writing the change off as worthless, in 19 of 20 cases) is a precondition then for cleaning up: Removing either the Experiment tooling around one new codepath, removing the old codepath completely, or the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaving experimentation instrumentation in the code, but having things full on (or off) is a very easy and visible way to assess technical debt. So even after the experiment has come to a conclusion one way or the other, the experiment framework is useful as a way to demarcate in some way or the other technical debt in source files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, empowerment. Empowerment is giving developers the power to make decisions, and at the same time demanding from them that they make them. You can do that only in a safe environment, and in a blame-free culture where this comes from the top. Hence the importance of Kees eating in the Canteen and asking the questions as told above. Hence, too, the importance of the error budget, and exposing it to all people that roll out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Du weisst nichts von Homeoffice</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/01/07/du-weisst-nichts-von-homeoffice.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 09:14:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/01/07/du-weisst-nichts-von-homeoffice.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.golem.de/news/spd-arbeitsministerium-will-recht-auf-homeoffice-per-gesetz-1901-138520.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Recht auf Homeoffice&lt;/a&gt;

 schreibt Golem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das SPD-geführte Bundesarbeitsministerium plant ein gesetzlich verankertes Recht auf Home Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und alle brüllen &amp;ldquo;Jaaaa!&amp;rdquo;.
Ich glaube, den meisten ist gar nicht klar, auf was sie sich da einlassen und wie sich eine Remote First-Firma anfühlt.
Wie dem auch sei:
Die Firma, in der Ihr gerade arbeitet, kann so mit Home Office vermutlich nicht gut funktionieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich habe von 2005 bis 2008 für MySQL AB gearbeitet, und das war eine Firma, die Remote First war.
Das war eine sehr andere Arbeitsumgebung als die, die ihr in Eurem Job vermutlich habt.
Wir waren circa 500 Mitarbeiter in drei Dutzend Ländern überall auf der Erde.
Es gab einen Firmensitz in Kalifornien und einen irgendwo in Skandinavien, aber dort war nie jemand (im Büro in Kalifornien waren ein paar Leute mehr, weil die dort den Börsengang der Firma vorbereitet haben).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Als Mitarbeiter hatte man einen gesonderten Raum daheim zu haben, der als Büro dient.
Die Firma hat einen gewissen Betrag pro Jahr (2500 Euro) bereitgestellt, um diesen Raum auszustatten oder zu verbessern.
Das schließt Arbeitsmaterial (Laptop) wie Büroausstattung (Stuhl, Tisch, etc pp) mit ein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weil es faktisch keine Firmenräume gab, gab es auch kein Firmen-VPN, denn das hätte den Zugang erschwert.
Stattdessen gab es einen Haufen Webdienste, über die die Kommunikation stattfand.
Diese waren verschlüsselt und mit einem Single Sign On versehen, aber generell von überall zugänglich von wo aus man eine TLS Verbindung bekommen konnte.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alle Diskussionen, internen Abstimmungen, Meetings, und Ergebnisse wurden über diese Webdienste, Skype, IRC und andere Online-Medien getroffen.
Die Arbeitszeiten waren oft schräg, weil die Firma über alle Zeitzonen der Erde verteilt war.
Und das heißt, man mußte schon mal um 3 Uhr morgens ran, um ein Meeting mit Leuten in Shanghai, Moskau und in Kalifornien gleichzeitig zu haben &amp;ndash; da gibt es einfach keine gute Zeitzone für alle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meetings über Videokonferenzen und Chatmedien sind schwierig, und Diskussionen über Mailinglisten sind oft hitzig und schwerfällig zugleich.
Es war notwendig, bestimmte Formen zu entwickeln und mit Leuten einzuüben.
Wenn man Leute aus einem Präsenzumfeld in eine Home Office Umgebung wirft, sind sie zunächst orientierungslos, unter Druck und einsam gleichzeitig.
Sie müssen an die Hand genommen werden, und man muß Ihnen Methoden und Formen aktiv zeigen, die ihnen erlauben, in so einer Umgebung zu funktionieren und sinnvoll zu kommunizieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am schwierigsten ist der Umgang mit der Tatsache, daß es keine Serendipität und keine aufwandslose Kommunikation gibt.
Diese Dinge, die man in Präsenzfirmen &amp;ldquo;nebenbei&amp;rdquo; mitbekommt, seitwärts, top-down und bottom-up, kommen in Home Office First Firmen nicht nebenbei.
Jeder, Management, Teamleiter, aber auch jeder einzelne Mitarbeiter, müssen lernen, daß jede Kommunikation einen Aufwand und Energie kostet, und man sich das Messaging genau überlegen muß.
Tut man das nicht, wird Zusammenhalt und gerichtete Aktion einem Firmenverbandes schwierig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zentral in MySQL waren übrigens die verschiedenen All Hands und Department Meeting Veranstaltungen.
Zweimal im Jahr hat sich gesamte Firma an einem Ort getroffen (meistens ein Fünf Sterne Hotel in einem gut erreichbaren Land mit entspannter Visa-Situation, in der Nachsaison), und zweimal im Jahr haben sich gesamte Abteilungen getroffen.
Auf diesen Events (jeweils drei bis fünf Tage) haben wir uns kennengelernt, ein Netzwerk aufgebaut, zusammen Kurzprojekte (&amp;ldquo;Hackathon&amp;rdquo;) durchgezogen und natürlich auch gefeiert.
Zusammen mit anderen Treffen hatte man so in etwa alle zwei Monate ein Gruppen-, Abteilungs-, oder Firmentreffen.
Alles in allem nicht wirklich eine Verbesserung der finanziellen und der CO2-Bilanz, aber notwendig um eine funktionierende Gruppe zu schaffen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where do you see yourself in five years?</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/09/11/where-do-you-see-yourself-in-five-years.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 19:49:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/09/11/where-do-you-see-yourself-in-five-years.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;seriously-hr-people-ask-the-weirdest-questions&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#seriously-hr-people-ask-the-weirdest-questions&#34;&gt;
	Seriously, HR people ask the weirdest questions.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Where do you see yourself in five years?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a Twentysomething with no owned property and no family the
truthful answer is of course &amp;ldquo;In a different company, twice
removed. Not because you suck more than anywhere else, but,
like, statistically.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/LionKingLee/status/906220573637971968&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/09/five-years.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Where do you see yourself in five years?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Week 27 or 28?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/LionKingLee/status/906220573637971968&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LionKingLee&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That time when you finish school and university and before you
settle down with dependencies that make you immobile - it is an
important time in your life. Use it wisely: Change jobs every
two to three years, and make it count.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is: understand that the people you work with are more
important than the companies you work for - you are building
your professional network. The companies you work for will
change every few years, but the network you build will be with
you for the rest of your life. It will be an important part of
you and your career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These people you are with in your wild years, they are the
people who will recommend you to the company you are aiming for
next. They will make sure that your CV is at least read, if you
send it there. They will make sure that you have at least the
first interview with that new shop. They are the people who will
ask you, when they have a professional question regarding your
area of expertise, and who will listen to your recommendations -
for hiring, for purchase, or just for grounding some goofball
ideas which may or may not turn into a startup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;seriously-hr-people-have-the-weirdest-ideas&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#seriously-hr-people-have-the-weirdest-ideas&#34;&gt;
	Seriously, HR people have the weirdest ideas.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I met some once, who were wondering why self-assessment and 360º
reviews and management reviews diverge so much. There are things
like
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.impraise.com/team-performance-analytics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;

 for
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.impraise.com/feedback-behaviour-report/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;example&lt;/a&gt;


(and that&amp;rsquo;s already one of the better solutions).
But you are effectively typing feedback about your future
network peers into a SaaS solution, and you know that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there is a third party company which collects data about me
at work, and what others think about me. This company may or may
not keep it around when we leave our current engagement,
depending on legislation, this companies operational skills and
culture:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would you trust a company with an Uber-like culture with this data?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you know if they are an Uber or not? If they keep it, and
they are successful in their market, they will build a profile
over my networks and my entire career, over each of our
professional engagements over time. Yeah, one more profile to
worry about, on top of the Google shadow, the Github and the
Linkedin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, back when I was 20 (that was 1988), I learned the value
of feedback - it is what helps you grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I also learned that negative feedback is always delivered over
coffee and beer, privately, face to face, and never, ever,
written down.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially not in some random 3rd parties SaaS interface.
You have no idea where it is going to end up, how long it is
being kept or who is going to buy whom in the end. So, anything
that goes into reports and reviews will of course be formatted
in a way such that it does not damage the current and future
relationship between my network and me. It&amp;rsquo;s not real and can&amp;rsquo;t
ever be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that was true already before systems like these, when HR was
still working with paper folders and kept data in-house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;seriously-hr-people-have-the-weirdest-jobs&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#seriously-hr-people-have-the-weirdest-jobs&#34;&gt;
	Seriously, HR people have the weirdest jobs.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever technology you build, theirs can&amp;rsquo;t be automated, and in
many ways not even effectively assisted.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The company as a social engine</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/08/07/the-company-as-a-social-engine.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 19:34:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/08/07/the-company-as-a-social-engine.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So why is everything so complicated? At work, I mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of a small company. A single person, a founder, is building her
business. She knows her way around, it&amp;rsquo;s all in her head: The plan, the
things that are important and why, and how they are to be executed. Also,
tradeoffs to be corrected later, potential opportunities for later and a lot
of other meta: Stuff that does not get executed right now, but that informs
decisions, priorities and preferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things work with some precision, though, like a well programmed wetware CPU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moment that stuff becomes too large for a single person to handle, more
people are involved and things need to be verbalized, written down, given
form. At that point, things change quite a bit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The task at hand is to program a second CPU, wetware, with a part of the
program that the first person has been executing. That&amp;rsquo;s necessary so she
can delegate, and the entire operation can scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, as with all remote procedure call mechanisms, complicated
unfolded in-memory structures have to serialized before the can be
marshalled off to a second node and are being re-instantiated over there. In
this particular case, the language to describe the code to be executed is
informally specified, too, and the remote CPU also does not match the specs
of the first CPU, that is, English is really bad for programming computers
or people, and also each person is different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make matters worse there is no proper debugger, the same broken language
has to be used to printf-debug the remote (&amp;ldquo;Do you understand what I mean?&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Do you understand why it is important that we do things this way?&amp;rdquo;) and
there may be other, older code in the remote that interferes with the
execution of our code. People have history and they have ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think of a company as a large distributed engine to execute code that
has been extracted painfully and incompletely from the wetware engine of a
founder, and which has been mangled due to improper serialization in a
language with limited expressiveness, you have a good idea of the corporate
environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;rsquo;t see what happens in the individual nodes, you can only observe the
communication between them, and the parts of the program that made it into
writing, or at least the Wiki. You can think of processes as written down
instructions for the engine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any process (&amp;ldquo;buy more paperclips&amp;rdquo;) describes who needs to talk to whom,
about what and why, in order to make things happen (&amp;ldquo;You need to create a
purchase order, which needs to be signed by &lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt; for values over &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; EUR in
order to limit our liability. The signed order is then sent to &lt;em&gt;Z&lt;/em&gt;, who will
actually spend money to buy stuff. You get stuff, and sign here to document
that.&amp;rdquo;)
Writing instructions and process down is important, and a great improvement
actually, because writing these instructions down forces all involves
parties (including the founders) to come clear about all the details and the
meta about the details - things that might have been existing only vaguely
in some mind, previously, now have to get a precise shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, they become tangible, and by the way of tangibility, they are open to
challenge, discussion and modification - which is why some founders are
actually resisting to give tangible form to certain things. Giving tangible
shape to instructions and the meta - why instructions, why these
instructions, why these instructions in this order with these emphasis - is
a complicated, painful and slow process, precisely because the originator of
an idea - the founder or some other person with an idea - has to give up the
idea and let it out into the world, where it will be subjected to change by
others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loss of control is always violent and painful, and as with any new thing
given a permanent form, there is always negotiation about the details.
Giving birth to anything: It&amp;rsquo;s exhausting. It&amp;rsquo;s not a one step process. A
founder has an idea and a plan, but in many parts it is still early,
untested and vague.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They put things into words, and the words are being tried out - can we work
by these instructions, or are there things unclear? Can the instructions
work, or does the plan need change? Can it be improved? Can it be applied to
other, similar things? Iterations happen. Do we go deep or wide - do we
specialize and improve this application of a plan, or do we try to apply the
plan as is to as many things as possible first?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, negotiation, and consequently, exhaustion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why is everything so complicated? Because companies are broken. All of
them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their engine, their program, their processes, are magnifications of the mind
of the founder or other influential people at the top. The entire corporate
mechanism is built to do exactly this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with this mechanism not only the original idea is being magnified and
copied to many minds, but other aspects of the original mind are, too. And
because the source was a person, with flaws, they too, are being magnified
and multiplied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you like it around here? Well, that&amp;rsquo;s because like all corporate
environments, this one is broken, too. It just so happens that the breakage
around here is more compatible with your own flaws than elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, your work environment sucks. They all do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find the one that sucks in a way that suits your needs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twitter so: Testing in Production</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/08/01/twitter-so-testing-in-production.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2017 09:25:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/08/01/twitter-so-testing-in-production.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/matthewrdutton/status/892007581639737344&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Matthew Dutton:&lt;/a&gt;


»@mipsytipsy I thought &amp;ldquo;You have to test in production&amp;rdquo; was a bold statement
and would love to hear more of your thoughts on the
topic.«&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mipsytipsy/status/892048269651484672&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Charity Majors:&lt;/a&gt;


»Hmmm, you&amp;rsquo;re not the only one to call this out. I&amp;rsquo;ll add it to my list of
&amp;ldquo;articles to write someday&amp;rdquo; ? but here&amp;rsquo;s the gist: We have always tested in
production, just not well. And obviously, I&amp;rsquo;m not advising anyone to do
&lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; of the usual pre-production testing methods, but at some point, esp
with distributed systems, you just can&amp;rsquo;t usefully mimic the qualities of
size and chaos that tease out the long thin tail of bugs. Imagine trying to
spin up a staging copy of Facebook, or the national electrical grid! You
can&amp;rsquo;t, and have sharply diminished returns. If you can catch 80-90% of the
bugs with 10-20% the effort (and you can), the rest is more usefully poured
into making production resilient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[How do you do testing in production?] Canarying; automated canarying and
promotion in stages; empowering your developers to explore live production
systems with e.g. @honeycombio (hi), making rollbacks wicked fast and
reliable; instrumentation; education and training, feature flags a la
@launchdarkly. all great use of time. Basically what I&amp;rsquo;m trying to say is,
embrace failure. Get used to the inevitability and lean into it, &lt;em&gt;iff&lt;/em&gt; you
have a system like this. If you&amp;rsquo;ve got a rails app and five engineers then
ignore everything I&amp;rsquo;m saying until the moment is right :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/f3ew/status/892277138329612289&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Devdas Bhagat:&lt;/a&gt;

 »Just
tagging potental speakers who know a bit about that topic.«&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/isotopp/status/892281239109083136&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kristian Köhntopp:&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decouple rollout and activation (feature flags, experiment framework)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low latency monitoring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monitor the shit out of everything&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement schema changes with old and new version being live simultaneously&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For each change, know your providers, know your consumers Strategy: Make testing in
production as safe as you can possibly make it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That has manifold returns: It makes developers production aware; builds
knowledge in handling real catastrophes in regular operational situations;
builds confidence and competence; you get actual measurements, which is good
calibration. In general, you build antifragility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Testing in Production also allows testing of features for commercial
viability fast, before you invest lots of development resources to build
them out. So it enables you to throw away 95% of the code before it is
written. That&amp;rsquo;s actually the most valuable part of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Content slightly edited to make it easier to read.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rolling out patches and changes, often and fast</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/05/18/rolling-out-patches-and-changes-often-and-fast.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 10:44:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/05/18/rolling-out-patches-and-changes-often-and-fast.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Fefe had a &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.fefe.de/?ts=a7e82d0e&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;short pointer&lt;/a&gt;

 to an article
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.columbia.edu/~smb/blog/2017-05/2017-05-12.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Patching is Hard&lt;/a&gt;

.
It is, but you can make it a lot easier by doing a few things right. I did s small
writeup (&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.fefe.de/?ts=a7e262f4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;in German&lt;/a&gt;

) to explain this,
which Fefe posted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do have an older talk on this, titled &amp;ldquo;8 rollouts a day&amp;rdquo; (more like
30 these days). There are
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/isotopp/8-rollouts-a-day&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;

 and a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rzU1UtUpyTI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;recording&lt;/a&gt;

. The Devops talk
&amp;ldquo;Go away or I will replace you with a little shell script&amp;rdquo; addresses it,
too, but from a different angle
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/isotopp/go-away-of-i-will-replace-you-with-a-little-shell-script-english&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;

,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=e0CCv7pSK4s&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;recording&lt;/a&gt;

).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the english version of my writeup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.columbia.edu/~smb/blog/2017-05/2017-05-12.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Patching is Hard&lt;/a&gt;

 article
says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Patching is hard? Yes—and every major tech player, no matter
how sophisticated they are, has had catastrophic failures when
they tried to change something. Google once bricked
Chromebooks with an update. A Facebook configuration change
took the site offline for 2.5 hours. Microsoft ruined network
configuration and partially bricked some computers; even their
newest patch isn&amp;rsquo;t trouble-free. An iOS update from Apple
bricked some iPad Pros. Even Amazon knocked AWS off the air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where I am working we made the same observation. 100% uptime is
impossible, but management needs metrics and controls to
understand if we are still on the right track. We do have an
outage budget. That means we are measuring the actual current
business and compare with the predicted business. If a failed
rollout creates a loss of (potential) income, we can tell how
much that is and deduct that from the outage budget. We are
trying to make the budget as precisely as possible. That does
not mean we are trying to create outages on purpose, but having
fewer outages than the budget allows may mean that we are not
moving fast enough and have become complacent in what we are
doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rolling out often is useful, because then change sets are small
and easy to check, much easier than large and hard to understand
changes. So we do need to roll out often in order to maintain
speed. Rollout problems tend to manifest in subsystems where we
do not roll out often enough. Usually secondary changes, changes
in dependencies and libraries, accumulate and then the rollout
fails. The solution is to roll out even if the code did not
change (that is, we roll out for the sake of keeping
dependencies current).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very tangible form of representing technical debt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the larger the diff between production and trunk is, the more
likely moving trunk to production is going to result in a
failure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To make patching safe you have to do it often.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To be able to patch often, you need to make patching and
rolling out an operative process and not an upgrade/migration
project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To make rollouts and operative thing it is useful to
make testing in production safe and survivable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To be able to test in production, the following things are
useful:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;have at most two versions of a change to a certain system.
Do not do three phase or multiphase rollouts. Finish one
change before you do the next one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;have overcapacity. A change might make it necessary to
provide more machinery or more computer power or more memory
for a short time. You need to have that or be able to
provision this on short notice. Being efficient means having
no reserves, no elasticity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;separation of code distribution and code activation. That means feature
flags and experiments in your code. The same rollout must be
able to switch at runtime between old and new behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;changes to persistent data structures require that you update both
versions of the structure concurrently in order for old and
new code to be able to co-exist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you need to know what is going on. Have a good monitoring, central log
collection, good search on all of that. There is a thing
called monitoring lag, the distance in time between a thing
happening and the time you will see this in your monitoring.
Measure that lag and have it shown on each screen. Alert on
monitoring lag.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;have a culture of failure that focuses on improvement and
learnings. Check out the search term &amp;ldquo;blameless postmortem&amp;rdquo;
and read up on this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not actually rocket science, but it will make things a lot better
around you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stört euch bitte nicht an dem Denglisch, das ist in der Ops-Abteilung von
internationalen Firmen durchaus normal :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed. The office is in Amsterdam, and the language at work is English.
When I am thinking about work, I am doing it in English. Writing about work
in German means that I will use a lot of english terms for the things I am
trying to describe, because I&amp;rsquo;d have to search for appropriate German terms
and concepts first and that would interrupt the flow. Sorry about that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

