<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>iot on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>/tags/iot.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in iot on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/iot/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>My home sensor network</title>
      <link>/2020/11/15/my-home-sensor-network.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/11/15/my-home-sensor-network.html</guid>
      <description>I have been asked to document my home sensor network. Being married to a person with a background in web security sets boundary conditions:
 No cloud. We are running all services locally. No control, only metrics.  I am collecting data from a number of plugs with power meters over Wi-Fi, using the MQTT protocol. I am also collecting data from a number of temperature sensors over Zigbee, and convert to MQTT.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Air Quality Sensors</title>
      <link>/2020/05/25/air-quality-sensors.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/25/air-quality-sensors.html</guid>
      <description>In an earlier episode I asked for Plugs with Wi-Fi and ended up with Gosund and Tasmota . Considering this to be a success, I asked the Twitters for Temperature and Humidity Sensors. Of course, this got complicated.
 Now that I have Powermeter Plugs everywhere: What are good sensors for temperature, humidity and CO2 that can be tasmotified? Wi-Fi, http or mqtt?
I was pointed to Xiaomi Aqara , but these do not do Wi-Fi, but Zigbee - whatever that is, it is spoken by Zigbee USB Gateway Sticks and works with Raspi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gosund and Tasmota</title>
      <link>/2020/05/20/gosund-and-tasmota.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/20/gosund-and-tasmota.html</guid>
      <description>(continued from Plugs with Wi-Fi ) So the Gosund plugs came, as did the Raspi 4. I did cancel the Shelly plug and decomissioned the TP-Link Kaka, because Tasmota on Gosund is awesome and the Gosund hardware is dirt cheap.
Power consumption of the local data grave, with too old a mainboard and CPU and way too much storage
But lets start at the beginning:
4 Pack of Gosund SP111 V1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plugs with Wi-Fi</title>
      <link>/2020/05/12/plugs-with-wifi.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/12/plugs-with-wifi.html</guid>
      <description>So we are baking bread, and for that we have a Wiesheu minimat oven that comes in at a full 16A - supposedly it is using 3kW or more peak plus the condenser hood that comes in at another 500W top power draw. On the other hand, when running the thing is hardly lukewarm, it is running much cooler than the Neff household oven/microwave combo we have.
Wiesheu minimat with condenser hood.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
