<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>gaming on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>/tags/gaming.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in gaming on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/gaming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gespielt: Assassins Creed: Odyssey</title>
      <link>/2020/10/19/fertig-gespielt-assassins-creed-odyssey.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/19/fertig-gespielt-assassins-creed-odyssey.html</guid>
      <description>Ok, so the title is a bit of an exaggeration, I am about 80% done with the main games quests. Still, the shape and feel of the story is firmly established and it is fascinating. I have some 110 hours in &amp;ldquo;Assassins Creed: Origin&amp;rdquo;, and some 65 hours or so in &amp;ldquo;Assassins Creed: Odyssey&amp;rdquo;.
You can play &amp;ldquo;Assassins Creed: Odyssey&amp;rdquo; as Alexios or Kassandra, and the change is permanent for the playthrough for storytelling reasons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ELI5: Epic vs Apple and Google</title>
      <link>/2020/08/14/eli5-epic-vs-apple-and-google.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/14/eli5-epic-vs-apple-and-google.html</guid>
      <description>@jpmens asked on Twitter:
 What is Fortnite? #outingmyself
Assuming XKCD 1053 .
Fortnite   Fortnite is a game made by Epic Games. They also make the Unreal Engine, which powers many modern computer games. Fortnite together with Roblox and Minecraft it is the set of games played most by people under 20.
You want to follow Matthew Ball .
Fortnite is a Battle Royal game, a 1st person shooter, in which a matchmaker puts you together with a set of other people of similar skill, drops you into an arena of ever shrinking size.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disable Saitek X.52 pro Clutch Mode</title>
      <link>/2020/01/15/disable-saitek-x52-clutch-mode.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/15/disable-saitek-x52-clutch-mode.html</guid>
      <description>This post is a memo to self, and describes how to disable the X.52 clutch mode. I am flying with a Saitek/Logitech X.52 pro HOTAS , and this stick has a &amp;lsquo;clutch button&amp;rsquo; (labelled &amp;ldquo;i&amp;rdquo;) in the thumb position of the throttle (image: clutch highlighed in red)
&amp;ldquo;Clutch mode&amp;rdquo; for this button means that it is usable as a modfier for the other buttons, when pressed together with a second button.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Rockforth Fertilizer Incident</title>
      <link>/2019/09/26/how-not-to-handle-an-ingame-incident.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/26/how-not-to-handle-an-ingame-incident.html</guid>
      <description>So I have been playing this Internet Spaceships Game. No, the other one . It also has NPC Backstory, and on 13-Sep-3305 , a multiplanetary food crisis was predicted, as a prep for the introduction of a new tradeable good on 18-Sep-3005 .
 Distribution of the fertiliser has started at Marshall Dock in the Riedquat system. We encourage traders to take advantage of our introductory prices.”
 That went wrong.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Harebrained Battletech</title>
      <link>/2018/04/26/harbebrained-battletech.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/26/harbebrained-battletech.html</guid>
      <description>So two days ago Harebrained Schemes&#39; Battletech came out.
Harebrained Schemes is an Indie Game Dev Studio from Seattle, previously known for the very successful Shadowrun Games . I found time to play the intro and the first few chapters in the campaign, and the game is exceptionally nice. It feels like one of those over designed simulation games, where you can minmax the player characters and their gear to the limit, but the computer is taking over the task of all the bookkeeping, so the bookkeeping is not going to pull you down.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What GPUs can do…</title>
      <link>/2017/10/12/what-gpus-can-do.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/12/what-gpus-can-do.html</guid>
      <description>Pcgamer reports &amp;ldquo;Nvidia CEO says Moore’s Law is dead and GPUs wi replace CPUs &amp;rdquo;.
Now, Jensen Huang might be a bit biased here, but he reminded us that &amp;ldquo;GPUs are advancing at a much faster pace than CPUs&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;that GPUs will replace CPUs soon, adding that at this point, designers can hardly work out advanced parallel instruction architectures for CPUs.&amp;rdquo; So what can a modern GPU do? Well, apparently Font Rendering is still a hard problem for GPUs, and a bottleneck in modern browsers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When Video Games are not quite playing things straight…</title>
      <link>/2017/10/12/when-video-games-are-not-quite-playing-things-straight.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/12/when-video-games-are-not-quite-playing-things-straight.html</guid>
      <description>]
Computer Games are cheating A lot of computer games are cheating, so that you can actually have fun with the game. Read the thread.
»Hey #gamedev, tell me about some brilliant mechanics in games that are hidden from the player to get across a certain feeling.«
»This is probably somewhere way down the list, but third person game thumbstick correction is a favourite. Pretty standard in AAA. (know you know but extrapolation for readers) game detects collision blocks and steers player around them, ignoring direction of input.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kris, where are the posts?</title>
      <link>/2017/05/08/kris-where-are-the-posts.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/08/kris-where-are-the-posts.html</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s not my fault, really. It&amp;rsquo;s Schenker , and Urban Games . They sent me my Nvidia 1070 (with a side of CPU and Memory), and now there is a Windows Shoebox (well, Clown Shoe sized showbox) somewhere in our home, and Steam Streaming is busy. I&amp;rsquo;m off laying tracks with the family, now the screen updates are not jumpy any more.
 XMG Prime </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gamification</title>
      <link>/2012/02/28/gamification.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/28/gamification.html</guid>
      <description>Neu in Google Maps: Leaderboard, bei dem man um Checkin-Punkte kämpfen kann.
Wenn man auf so ein Management-Simulationsseminar geht, dann haben die da gerne so Rollenspiele zum Einüben des Gesagten. Vor einigen Jahren haben sie uns kurz vor Schluß einer solchen Veranstaltung die Aufgabe gegeben, einen Jahresbonus auf Mitarbeiter zu verteilen. Es gab also einen Topf, der war kleiner als &amp;lsquo;letztes Jahr&amp;rsquo;, und wir hatten alle &amp;lsquo;Mitarbeiter&amp;rsquo;, komplett mit einer Hintergrundgeschichte, persönlichen Problemen und solchen Sachen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defaultseitenhieb(&#34;Post-Privacy&#34;)</title>
      <link>/2011/11/16/defaultseitenhieb-post-privacy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/16/defaultseitenhieb-post-privacy.html</guid>
      <description>Es begannt mit einem Google Plus Artikel zum Thema EA und Origin. Origin ist ein Pflichtbestandteil von neueren Spielen von Electronic Arts, und geht über einen normalen Kopierschutz insofern hinaus, als daß es anfängt, die Platte des Kunden zu durchsuchen und unbekannte Mengen Daten aufzusammeln und an EA zu schicken.
Mein Post spießte die Tatsache auf, daß sich unsere Politik an Facebook hochzieht, inkonsequenterweise aber solche Dinge wie Origin ignoriert. Selbst dann, wenn sie wie in FIFA 12 auf die Rechner von 12 Jahre alten Kindern angewendet werden - wäre dies keine Firma, sondern eine natürliche Person, hätten wir hier einen Cyberstalking-Prozeß am Laufen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Counterstrike am Hindukusch</title>
      <link>/2006/03/10/counterstrike-am-hindukusch.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2006/03/10/counterstrike-am-hindukusch.html</guid>
      <description>Zwei Jahre später   Aus dem Heise-Forum :
Du bist sechzehn Jahre alt Man muss dich schützen vor Gewalt, Vor allem vor unglaublich vielen Unsäglich bösen Killerspielen. Doch zwei Jahre später dann, Statt rumzuhängen stehst du stramm, Statt weit geschnitten und lasziv Trägst du braun gefleckt oliv. Man zeigt dir, wie du richtig zielst Mit Spitzentechnik und du spielst Nicht mit Joystick, Maus und Browser Doch mit Hi-Tech Marke Mauser.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
