<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chat on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/chat.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Chat on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 19:44:16 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/chat/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Matrix Trashfire</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2024/02/13/the-matrix-trashfire.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 05:06:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2024/02/13/the-matrix-trashfire.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For reasons, I tried to evaluate the distributed Matrix chat and their clients.
That did not work out very well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;onboarding-experience&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#onboarding-experience&#34;&gt;
	Onboarding experience
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was told that the default Matrix chat client is called Elements, so I looked it up on the iOS App store.
Unfortunately, there are two, &amp;ldquo;Element&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Element X.&amp;rdquo;
No explanation is given, and no preference is stated.
&amp;ldquo;Element&amp;rdquo; is categorized business, &amp;ldquo;Element X&amp;rdquo; is in &amp;ldquo;Social Networking.&amp;rdquo;
Are they not the same?
They seem to be from the same company, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Element and Element X in the app store. Which one to use?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, let&amp;rsquo;s open the descriptions.
They are identical, except for one sentence at the start:
&amp;ldquo;Element X is the future Element.&amp;rdquo;
So it&amp;rsquo;s a beta?
Why is it not labeled as a Beta?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the desktop, going to &lt;a href=&#34;https://matrix.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Matrix.org&lt;/a&gt;

 plus two additional clicks take you to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://matrix.org/ecosystem/clients/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the client page&lt;/a&gt;

, which offers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The client page offers you, among others, both clients and also states which is available on what platform.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So apparently &amp;ldquo;Element X&amp;rdquo; is beta and not yet available on all platforms. I open the macOS App Store and&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-03.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;macOS does not offer Element, only Element X.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently matrix.org lied to me.
Element X is available on iOS and macOS, Element is not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, let&amp;rsquo;s install Element X and try:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-04.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Element X wants me to sign in to matrix.org. There is no &amp;lsquo;sign up&amp;rsquo; Button. There is no sign-up menu.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The client wants me to log in to matrix.org. There is no button to make an account. There is no menu to make an account.
There is zero onboarding for new users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, let&amp;rsquo;s go to matrix.org again, and see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-05.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The matrix.org Website is not very helpful. But when you notice the burger menu, there is actually a &amp;ldquo;Try Matrix&amp;rdquo; button.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The matrix.org website is a very empty clean screen that is not very helpful. There is a burger menu, though,
and if you open it, you get a &amp;ldquo;Try Matrix&amp;rdquo; button.
This leads to another screen that tells you to use your organizations server instance (What organization? I&amp;rsquo;m alone!),
or install a server,
or choose a public server.
If you opt for Public Servers, you land here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-06.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;matrix.org server instances, alphabetically sorted, with little additional information.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matrix.org is conspicuously absent from this list.
The rest I do not know anything about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can now research what server instance I want to join.
Unfortunately, I do not get information about what their country is.
I can&amp;rsquo;t see if they are subject to GDPR rules.
I don&amp;rsquo;t know if they are owned by a company or run by a single private person.
There is no indication how many users they have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can dig through their privacy policies and rules, except that some don&amp;rsquo;t provide any.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scrolling down, I end up with the option to onboard to this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-07.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Servers marked as vulnerable, unavailable and with profanity in their name.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why in heaven or earth would anybody put unavailable or vulnerable servers into an onboarding listing?
Isn&amp;rsquo;t this supposed a &amp;ldquo;secure&amp;rdquo; messenger?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;trying-to-use-it-nontheless&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#trying-to-use-it-nontheless&#34;&gt;
	Trying to use it, nontheless
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made an &amp;ldquo;isotopp&amp;rdquo; account at &lt;a href=&#34;https://chat.tchncs.de/#/login&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;tchncs.de&lt;/a&gt;

.
The password is generated and stored in Bitwarden.
A validation mail is sent to a unique address at koehntopp.de and arrives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I try to login not being validated, using Bitwarden.
The login is rejected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I validate the email.
The server says I am validated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I try to login, using Bitwarden.
The login is rejected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-09.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I am trying to recover the password for the account which I just validated, using the email from the verification mail.
The account is unknown.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I click on &amp;ldquo;forgotten password&amp;rdquo;, and supply the mail adress the validation mail was sent to.
&amp;ldquo;This email address was not found.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, since my account does not exist, I create it again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-10.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I recreate my account, using the same mail address. As you can see, the first registration mail still is in the account.
I take the validation URL, which is longer than 80 characters, and use it to successfully validate, again.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I create the account again, using the same parameters.
The account validation mail is sent to my address.
The old account validation mail is also still in the account.
I take the new URL, which is longer than 80 characters, and use it to successfully validate my account, again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time I accidentally left the &amp;ldquo;create account&amp;rdquo; window open.
This window is now suddenly logged in.
Turns out, you MUST NOT, UNDER ANY CIRCUMSTANCES, close the &amp;ldquo;create account&amp;rdquo; window until the account is validated,
or it is simply not created.
This is not stated anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To confirm the account works and the password in Bitwarden is stored successfully,
I log out and log in again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-11.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unable to verify this device&lt;/strong&gt;
It looks like you don&amp;rsquo;t have a Security Key or any other devices you can verify against.
This device will not be able to access old encrypted messages.
In order to verify your identity on this device, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to reset your verification keys.*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does that even mean?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;trying-element-x-with-my-account&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#trying-element-x-with-my-account&#34;&gt;
	Trying Element X with my account
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting Element X, it tries to onboard me to Matrix.org.
I select &amp;ldquo;Change Server&amp;rdquo;, and get a form field where it says &amp;ldquo;matrix.org&amp;rdquo;.
I am overwriting it with &amp;ldquo;chat.tchncs.de&amp;rdquo;, which supposedly is my server.
At least that is what it says in the web client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-12.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is not accepted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I take the URL from the browser and paste that instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-13.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is also not accepted, but I can learn more.
I click.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-14.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The what?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, while the Chat is running on &amp;ldquo;chat.tchncs.de&amp;rdquo;, this is not the &amp;ldquo;Identity Provider.&amp;rdquo;
That one is called &amp;ldquo;tchncs.de&amp;rdquo;.
You only learn this when you open your config menu in the web chat and look at Identifer shown there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-15.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you enter this, Element X and the web chat get hectic.
There is a new client, and both clients want to authenticate that the new device is legit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-16.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For that purpose, they display a set of Emojis, which look differently in the web client and the application,
and ask me if they are the same.
Helpful Emoji names are shown under the Emoji, and they are identical.
I simply click yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, both clients can see my Chat, but the Element X Client still has no access to any chat history.
That is, because the client is unverified (so is the web client).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I close any client, I have to re-login, re-compare the Emojis, and all chat history is gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;after-onboarding&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#after-onboarding&#34;&gt;
	After onboarding
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why have I been trying this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-08.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A friend was trying to use a Matrix messenger on their phone, and waited 9 hours for this to complete.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine was trying to re-install a Matrix messenger on their phone, and landed on the screen above.
This hung for 9 hours without any message or failure indication.
The application cannot detect if somebody is using the wrong recovery key for a different account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The friend tried to use an Android application, but the application was complaining about the account not being verified.
That is, the mail address in use was not confirmed, and for that reason the client would not be showing any chats.
At the same time, these chats were being sent to the unconfirmed mail address,
unencrypted,
as a reminder that he was missing out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to him, you can&amp;rsquo;t delete a half-made unconfirmed account.
You also can&amp;rsquo;t rename an account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, you cannot create invite links for private chat rooms,
only invite people.
To do that, vector.im uses the very same dark patterns that LinkedIn uses to convince you to share your address book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the unique mail-address used to sign up to Matrix, I am unfindable because only Matrix uses this specific mail address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside of Element, there are very few clients, most of them very old and not being updated within the last few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, this is a mess, and my recommendation is to avoid Matrix for at least two years.
It is not secure, it is actively user-hostile, and looks not well managed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a project in severe need of management changes, a thorough UX evaluation.
The design needs changes that make onboarding and usage smoother, encourage secure workflows,
keep accounts available, and encourage secure practice.
It also needs careful curation of servers and clients.
At the moment it is a trash fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;matrix-responds&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#matrix-responds&#34;&gt;
	Matrix responds
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Added on 14-Feb-2024:
People at Matrix.org and Matrix developers have picked this up and responded in a very constructive way.
They cannot address all things because they are not in the realm of Matrix, but part of Element.
So far, no responses from Element.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mastodon.matrix.org/@matrix/111924190165706931&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Matrix writes&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-17.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;well, this is a trashfire indeed.
Thanks for writing this up.
You&amp;rsquo;ve caught Element in the middle of their migration to Element X, and there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of legit feedback here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both E &amp;amp; EX should be in the macOS app store.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;EX should clearly be labelled WIP in appstores.
-It&amp;rsquo;s a mistake that matrix.org hurls people to servers.joinmatrix.org (which is not run by us);
until recently it defaulted to matrix.org for convenience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keeping the &amp;ldquo;create account&amp;rdquo; window open is a pure bug.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mastodon.matrix.org/@matrix/111924227099676114&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The continue&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-18.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Verification UX in Element is a disaster, and being reworked in EX:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/element-hq/element-meta/blob/develop/docs/FTUE.md&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Github link&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Element Android failing to compute a recovery key is clearly a bug too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your other complaints about Element UX (e.g. user discovery by email;
specifying the server URL) are also very familiar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not true to say vector.im uses &amp;ldquo;the very same dark patterns as LinkedIn&amp;rdquo; for contact discovery though;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/matrix-org/matrix-spec-proposals/blob/hs/hash-identity/proposals/2134-identity-hash-lookup.md&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Github link&lt;/a&gt;


explains how it works (and is strictly opt-in).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matrix Director of Program Development &lt;a href=&#34;https://mamot.fr/@thibaultamartin/111924256997285624&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Thibault A. Martin responds&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/02/element-19.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hej @isotopp I&amp;rsquo;m one of the maintainers of the matrix.org website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your post provides a very valuable perspective.
I gathered the following gripes that we can address on the website itself in this issue:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/matrix-org/matrix.org/issues/2178&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Matrix.Org Issue 2178&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have the time to let me know if I got things right,
that would be very useful!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for picking this up, people!
I very much hope that Matrix and Element eventually turn into something useful.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Groups and Places</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/10/12/groups-and-places.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 06:07:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/10/12/groups-and-places.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a distributed, asynchronous environment, there is a need for distributed, asynchronous interaction.
This interaction is often written, but &amp;ldquo;writing&amp;rdquo; these days is actually a media-rich process that includes much more than letters.
It also needs to be able to build some structure, and some gateway to level up to more synchronous and even richer communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s have a chat about chats, and what properties they have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-01.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Historically, chat was lines of text, without much structure. Even today, many geeks often propose IRC when chat solutions are being discussed in a corporate context. That is a very myopic way of thinking.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first chat network I have been using was IRC &amp;ndash; Internet Relay Chat.
This has been in the late 80ies or early 90ies, so today I have had an interactive online presence on the upside of 25 years or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later I got to use ICQ, Jabber, Skype, Hangouts, Facebook Messenger, WhatsApp, Slack and RocketChat, among many others.
I also got exposed to a number of collaborative document processing systems with chat-like properties:
the now defunct Google Wave (alias Apache Wave, now also mostly defunct), and its heir Google Docs, and a bunch of newer collaborative brainstorming tools from the School of Miro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these applications and chat systems are different, but they can be evaluated along a number of dimensions to understand chat systems better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A screenshot of my chat desktop from 2016. There are many like it, but this is mine.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;location-and-discoverability&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#location-and-discoverability&#34;&gt;
	Location and Discoverability
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most important functions any chat system has to have is enabling the right people to find each other.
There are two large classes of chat systems here: One uses groups, and the other uses places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Groups are just that: collections of people that talk to each other.
You write a message and sent it.
It is then visible to all members of the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with groups is that they are almost impossible to find.
They are invitation only.
A member of the group must have knowledge of you looking for the group, and then invite you to it.
In some messengers this will also form a new group, destroying the messaging history of the older group, in order to protect the privacy of the conversation happening before the new member joined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-03.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Discord chat system allows you to form small scale groups with fixed membership, even without having a &amp;ldquo;Discord Server&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A better system uses Places (often called Rooms or Channels) instead of Groups.
A place is discoverable, you can &amp;ldquo;find&amp;rdquo; it, &amp;ldquo;go&amp;rdquo; to it, and &amp;ldquo;join&amp;rdquo; without being explicitly invited (permission and moderation systems often exist).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Places tend to proliferate, mechanism to group, order, tag and search them often exist.
In Discord, for example, Channels can be grouped into Categories, which are then grouped into &amp;ldquo;Servers&amp;rdquo;, the server having an owner, and often a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-04.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Discord chat system, showing the &amp;ldquo;heiseonline&amp;rdquo; discord server, with a channel named &lt;code&gt;#tierbilder&lt;/code&gt; (Animal Pictures) selected. Below that, a Category for &lt;code&gt;Sprachkanäle&lt;/code&gt; (Voice Channels) is seen.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having Places instead of Groups is crucial for any communication system.
It gives you the capability to write instructions that send people somewhere, and enables people to find and go somewhere, gives them agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebooks Messenger and Facebook at Work&amp;rsquo;s greatest flaw is their Messenger, which does not have this feature.
It relies on Groups, and tries to mitigate that by coupling groups to Facebook &amp;ldquo;Groups&amp;rdquo; (discussion boards), auto-inviting people into the Facebook Group associated chat group.
This combines worst practices of several systems into one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Places can be persistent, they can exist without anyone being in them.
Places can also have one or multiple owners, which is the root of that Places&amp;rsquo; permission system and the source of all moderator power for that Place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;presence&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#presence&#34;&gt;
	Presence
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working asynchronously means that you will not be present in a chat at all times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a feature: It allows you to focus, and think straight, cutting deeply into problems.
It also allows you to be in another timezone than your communication partners and still contribute meaningfully to a collaborative effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It poses the problem of your communication partners not knowing your current communication status, and availability.
If they are blocked, they might need you, and it would help them to have some expectation of your response times, availability and context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All modern chat systems have a presence mechanism, a semi-automatic status tagline, and the more thoughtfully engineered ones also know your timezone and show it to your peers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-05.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Slack chat system allows users to set a status in the form of an Emoji and a tagline. These are automatically cleared after some preset time, if desired. Slack also understands time zones, and will show you out-of-office times of communication partners, when necessary. Clicking on a user will also reveal their location and local time. On the right hand side, a number of status bubble examples are shown.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presence management in chat system often goes hand in hand with logging.
Messages sent to you in your absence are logged, and shown to you on reconnect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all a giant step forward from IRC, which did not manage presence well, and also did not allow sending messages to disconnected users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In IRC, being offline means not being present: people fall off the channel and what is being said with them being not there is lost to them.
That is of course a nuisance, and so people have been using programs such as screen to run an IRC client even when they have been disconnected from their computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IRC&amp;rsquo;s mechanism for presence (here: attention) is somewhat hidden &amp;ndash; the &lt;code&gt;/away&lt;/code&gt; command.
But not only is the mechanism hidden (it is another command that needs to be learned and used), but the status is somewhat hidden as well.
You can&amp;rsquo;t see if somebody is &lt;code&gt;/away&lt;/code&gt; unless you look at them with a &lt;code&gt;/whois&lt;/code&gt;.
Or you learn about the fact that they are &lt;code&gt;/away&lt;/code&gt; only after the fact, when you say something to them and get an auto-response with their &lt;code&gt;/away&lt;/code&gt; message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people do not like this, and so they use another mechanism and change their nicknames when they are not there &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;Isotopp&amp;rdquo; becomes &amp;ldquo;Isotopp|AFK&amp;rdquo; or similar.
This is less structured than &lt;code&gt;/away&lt;/code&gt;, and so some people suffix their names, some prefix them and others completely change their nicknames - &amp;ldquo;Isotopp&amp;rdquo; becomes &amp;ldquo;Awaytopp&amp;rdquo;.
The lack of facility, discoverable interface and standardization creates variant practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;logging-and-multi-device&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#logging-and-multi-device&#34;&gt;
	Logging and Multi-Device
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All modern chat clients have proper presence, even if not always as rich as in Slack.
Most also have unified logging.
That is, even absent users can receive messages and will see them when coming back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most users in 2022 have multiple devices, and multiple clients.
Most users want the entire messaging history, in order, and with all backlog, available on all their devices, so that they can switch between devices without losing context.
This usually includes new devices, to facilitate moving to new laptops or cellphones, without losing history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This often clashes with old standards, badly designed security mechanisms and other implementation details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-06.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Google Talk log, with OTR encryption, viewed in a different Jabber client. The history is truncated, and OTR encrypted messages are not available in readable form in this client.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One extreme point for synchronisation is the Discord chat system, where not only history and messages are kept in sync across all clients, but even preferences are unified:
Setting the desktop client to dark mode will also set dark mode on the cellphone application, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another, opposite extreme point is Jabber, which has no common rule for disposition of messages, and by default will send messages only to one client, using either a preference system, the last active client, or &amp;ldquo;all known clients to the server at the point in time the message was sent&amp;rdquo;. A lot depends on server and clients used here, creating an unreliable and hard to control user experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;deliverables---file-and-image-sharing&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#deliverables---file-and-image-sharing&#34;&gt;
	Deliverables - File and Image Sharing
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a corporate context, we use the communication mechanism as a vehicle to create and share documents, and have a discussion about the documents we work on collaboratively.
Mail was doing this in the past, with Quotes and with Attachments, but that is a very cumbersome, lossy and hard to discover mechanism.
Most companies have moved the collaboration process off mail, to a large extent, and towards chat and collaborative document systems such as Google Docs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google had taken this one step further with structured chat.
The pioneer application for that has been the short-lived Google Wave:
Wave allowed a group of people to create things in a kind of chat bubble, only that this bubble could not just hold a line of text, but also other media including rich documents, images, bots or other things that interfaced with the Wave API.
Other users could comment on an item in a hierarchic comments-on-comment tree like in a discussion system, or directly edit the original item, incorporating their changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changes were recorded and were undoable and replayable.
This allowed users to view the end result of a Wave, or review the process of building that result after the fact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-07.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Google Wave being used to collaboratively work on a shared document. The Wave contains the final document, but also the process that led to the end result.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a way, Wave could have been a salvation from the hell of corporate email:
Waves produce results, documents or agreements.
They also record the history of how that result had been reached, and they allow people joining the process late to catch up and review what has happened before on their own terms.
No more full quotes, 13 levels deep, and no more dozens of copies of the same Word file, all slightly different, and with diverging side remarks from people somewhere in the organisation, which never made it back into the main document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wave failed, though, and for multiple reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the bigger reasons is that Wave was all mechanism and no purpose &amp;ndash; it could to many things, and offered all of them without stating what Wave itself or the various functions are there for.
One could use Wave to manage a world building and game session in a role playing game, as well as replace corporate email, or use it as a rather clunky and over-engineered word processor.
So Wave needed explanation and contextualisation - and above all, a purpose, but none was given.
Wave died, because it confused users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/10/groups-places-08.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A collaboratively edited document. Multiple watchers are shown as icons at the top of the screen. A chat window is open. Cursors and collaborators edits would be visible simultaneously editing the document in many places while it has been initially created.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wave&amp;rsquo;s legacy lives on, though.
Much of the functionality of Wave is present in Google Docs, including the side chat, collaborative editing, history recording and replay and many other functions.
Unlike Wave, Google&amp;rsquo;s shared document editing puts the purpose first, and the collaboration in the background.
This is matching people&amp;rsquo;s expectations much better, and is less overwhelming.
It does not have to be taught, or manually given purpose.
Instead, the purpose is built in, and immediately obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern chat systems are kind of the opposite:
They put their purpose (communication) first, and the documents ride in the back.
This happens either through URLs or through file transfer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All modern chat systems have a working file transfer, which is also aware of media types.
That means, not only can you drag and drop files into a 1:1 chat or a channel, but also images or animations, as well as audio files.
They are understood, and shown inline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together with other mechanisms, such as threads, they enable unique workflows that go way past the unstructured ASCII-limited text of IRC.
For example, in many workplaces designers use the image capabilities of Slack, together with Slack threads, to share images, mockups and other things and then criticize or approve designs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also where not only IRC, but also Jabber falls down.
Proper file sharing, inline media content and threading are things that may exist somewhere, in some Jabber extension, but are not generally interoperable or enabled without much configuration across a set of clients.
They might as well not exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;we-were-lucky&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#we-were-lucky&#34;&gt;
	We were lucky
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the place I work at, we were lucky.
By the time Covid pushed people to work from home, we already had replaced mail almost completely.
I was down from thousands of mail messages per day on almost one hundred mailing lists to less than a dozen messages, and no mailing lists at all anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have moved to &lt;strong&gt;Facebook at Work&lt;/strong&gt; for non-realtime group communication.
Teams were using their Facebook groups to communicate announcements and progress to other teams, and have discussions with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internally and for support we moved to &lt;strong&gt;Slack&lt;/strong&gt;.
This was pushed with considerable force from below, after corporate initially being very fond of Facebook messenger, mostly because it was free and included in Facebook at work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately FB messenger is utterly broken in many ways, and unsuited for any structured work communication without basically rewriting it from scratch.
There are many facets to its fractal brokenness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has groups, but no places.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Groups have limited attendance, and the limit is too small (the old &lt;code&gt;#live&lt;/code&gt; Jabber channel was mandatory for all people pushing deployments, and could not be reproduced in FB Messenger).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It ate data. Mentioning a filename &lt;code&gt;main.pl&lt;/code&gt; would inescapably turn this into a polish hostname &lt;a href=&#34;https://main.pl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;main.pl&lt;/a&gt;

. More often than not, Messenger would detect a malware phishing attempt and prevent you from sending the message.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It ate data. Mentioning URLs with array parameters (&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://example.com/bla?a=1&amp;amp;a=2&amp;amp;a=3%22&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://example.com/bla?a=1&amp;a=2&amp;a=3&#34;&lt;/a&gt;

) would make it parse the URL, representing the keys in a hash, and dropping the repeated keys, breaking the URL.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It could not handle files, code formatting and many other things well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It could not do threads, which are a necessity in high volume support channels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, corp was forced to also purchase Slack on top of FB at Work, to prevent a more or less open revolt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had been using &lt;strong&gt;Google Drive and Google Office&lt;/strong&gt;, as well, across the company, and the collaborative features in it were well understood and used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heterogeneity of all of this posed to be not a problem, somewhat surprisingly.
In fact, in many cases, the mix-and-match approach enabled us to be flexible, and work around many tools limitations, and also to expand and integrate other things easily.
Other applications (e.g. Miro, but also many others) have since been added for many users, who have other, more specialized needs and requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also used to use BlueJeans, before the pandemic, and mostly from meeting room installations with dedicated hardware.
During Covid, Zoom became popular, and offered a richer and much better set of clients, especially on mobile devices (Laptops, Tablets, Cellphones), so we switched vendors here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key learnings are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We already had tooling for Remote First, but had hardly any need to use them properly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We were hardly using Email with all its glorious brokenness anymore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By happy accident, the core tools (FB at Work, Slack) had Places, not Groups, as a core metaphor, and people structured their work around these places.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborative document editing and a rich, structured chat complement each other well. But since Facebook and Google both are unable to make such a thing, we have yet another vendor integrated. This turned out to be an actual advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our key deficits have not been discussed at length here, but are related:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google Office documents have very bad discoverability and Google Office has no places.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corollary: A process is needed and needs to be manually executed to move content from the collaborative phase to the publication phase, elsewhere.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By public decree in our place this is going to be Confluence, which has problems of its own, and also poses a document conversion problem (from Google to Confluence internal format, keeping structure).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code Collaboration is not part of other collaboration at all, and lives in a third, and entirely disconnected space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

