<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Netherlands on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/netherlands.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Netherlands on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2024 13:22:47 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/netherlands/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>City of Amsterdam and Combustion Engines</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/05/11/city-of-amsterdam-and-combustion-engines.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 01:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/05/11/city-of-amsterdam-and-combustion-engines.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Electrive.net had an article about Copenhagen banning combustion engines in the city, starting 2030:
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.electrive.net/2023/05/08/kopenhagen-will-verbrenner-autos-ab-2030-aussperren/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Article in German&lt;/a&gt;

).
So I had to check what is the current state in Amsterdam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;current-state&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#current-state&#34;&gt;
	Current state
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Netherlands has a central register for license plates.
It is public, and anyone can check.
There are many places that allow you to do that for car, not owner data.
For &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.autoweek.nl/kentekencheck/P-664-rg/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;example&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The city of Amsterdam also allows you to check if a given license plate is allowed to enter the cities milieuzone.
You can &lt;a href=&#34;https://ontheffingen.amsterdam.nl/publiek/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;check yourself&lt;/a&gt;

.
And so can any license plate scanner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/verkeer-vervoer/milieuzone-amsterdam/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;overview page&lt;/a&gt;

 for the milieuzone,
the city helpfully explains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let op:&lt;/strong&gt; dat u de Milieuzone mag inrijden betekent niet dat u ook in aanmerking komt voor een parkeervergunning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attention:&lt;/strong&gt; Note that being allowed to enter the Environmental Zone does not mean you are also eligible for a parking permit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;after-2030&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#after-2030&#34;&gt;
	After 2030
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rules for the milieuzone are becoming stricter &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/verkeer-vervoer/milieuzone-amsterdam/aanscherping-milieuzones/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;starting 2025&lt;/a&gt;

,
and by 2030 no combustion engines are being allowed in the city at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NL-wide license plate check for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.opwegnaarzes.nl/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;commercial vehicles&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New lorries will need to be electric starting 2025 to be allowed into the city.&lt;br&gt;
Existing lorries will have to be Euro 6 or better. There are some more rules for easing the changeover.
Starting 2030, no lorries with combustion engines are allowed into the city.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small commercial delivery vehicles (vans, Sprinters) with Diesel must be Euro 4 or better already.
New cars must be electric starting 2025. Euro 5 is required starting 2027, Euro 6 starting 2028,
no combustion starting 2028.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bus lines are in the process of being converted to electric, and this is nearly complete.
It will be finished by 2025.
Rules for charter buses are to follow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taxis electric starting 2025.
Tax incentives and better starting places as well as priority for parking and taxi licenses are provided already.
This is going well, most Taxis are electric already.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scooters (25 km/h and 45 km/h) must be electric by 2025.
Get a pedelec, maybe?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ships (tourist and transport) must be electric by 2025.
Ferries over the river Ij are already being converted.
70% rebate for harbor fees for electric ships right now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cars must be Euro 4 or better right now.
Only electric cars are allowed into the city by 2030.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;important-advice&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#important-advice&#34;&gt;
	Important advice
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2023/05/scanauto.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;em&gt;Scanautos are being used to automatically enforce parking rules inside the city.
They are checking around 800x more effective than an unaugmented parking enforcement human.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Amsterdam, most major streets do not allow you to park on public ground.
Side streets often have only a limited number of public parking spots,
the others require a residential parking permit.
Parking in parking structures or in the street costs around 50 Euro/day if you find a space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parking permits are &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; shown on the dashboard, and similarly, parking violations are &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; ticketed in paper behind the windshield wiper.
Instead, everything is based on automated license plate scanning:
Enter your license plate at the parking fee collector terminal,
the scanauto will countercheck what it scanned with the central database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://algoritmeregister.amsterdam.nl/parkeercontrole/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Enforcement is automatic&lt;/a&gt;

, and the coverage is excellent.
If you do not pay, or overpark, you will be caught.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/parkeren/parkeerbon/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;That will cost you&lt;/a&gt;

 at minimum 72.90 Euros in punishment,
plus fees, plus the unpaid parking fee.
In total this usually ends up between 110 Euros and 150 Euros
.
The target for processing (between parking violation and notification) is officially two days.
But it often is &amp;ldquo;while you still park&amp;rdquo; (20 minutes or less),
so near realtime.
This has the effect of ruining whatever you are currently doing in the city, so just park legally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2023/05/overtoom.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;em&gt;S106, Overtoom. A major inroad into the city. Note how this is one lane per direction, and no parking at the side.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cheapest way to do that is to park at a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/en/parking/park-ride/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Park and Ride&lt;/a&gt;

,
and then take the tram or subway into the city.
Or just use the bus, tram, subway or train, starting at your door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The city does not believe into building roads to places that have more capacity than can be parked at the destination.
So most major inroads into Amsterdam are single lane.
Not only will you not be able to park in the city.
Most likely, you will also hate every minute of getting there before you have to turn around.
Be sensible, use OV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#summary&#34;&gt;
	Summary
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2023/05/electric-charge-points.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Map of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/parkeren/elektrische-oplaadpunten-amsterdam/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;electric charge points&lt;/a&gt;

 in Amsterdam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for anybody but private individual transport, Amsterdam will be fully electric by 2025,
and the final conversion will take another 5 years.
This is not an unrealistic goal.
If you walk through the city, you can see how the conversion is already in full swing at an amazing and still increasing speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The city has built the required infrastructure in terms of charge points already,
and provides maps to prove it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But individual motorized transport does not scale to a city with the density of Amsterdam.
Cities are for humans, not for cars, and Amsterdam makes it very clear that cars are not welcome.
Use public transport to get around in Amsterdam.
That is already fully electric, and except for the buses always has been.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good Energy News</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/08/15/good-energy-news.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2022 05:06:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/08/15/good-energy-news.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two good news in one day. First, my energy provider tells me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Levert u meer terug dan u van het net afneemt, dan betalen we u vanaf die datum 16.8 eurocent per kWh.
De oude vergoeding was 7 eurocent per kWh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If you push energy into the grid, we now pay you 16.8 Eurocent per kWh. The old payment was 7.0 Eurocent per kWh.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other good news is that it is very likely that the existing &amp;ldquo;Salderingsregeling&amp;rdquo; may be continued until 2025.
At least that seems to be the plan, says &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.milieucentraal.nl/energie-besparen/zonnepanelen/salderingsregeling-voor-zonnepanelen/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;milieu centraal&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Salderingsregeling&amp;rdquo; says that for power that I feed back into the grid I can draw back without cost.
You can imagine that as using the grid as a battery with infinite capacity, or as the counter going backwards.
There are a few limits and regulations, but more on that below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original plan was to end the Salderingsregeling at the End of &amp;lsquo;22.
This was then extended to the End of &amp;lsquo;23, and it seems that it is now being discussed to extend it to the End of &amp;lsquo;24.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when I am consuming 5000 kWh from the grid and push 2000 kWh into the grid, I will have to pay only 3000 kWh.
It does not matter that I actually withdrew 4000 kWh from the grid, because some consumption was at night, or because I overshot the production of my panels at a certain point in time.
Only the net Saldo matters, the difference between production and consumption over the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also works the other way around:
If I am producing 5000 kWh and consume only 2000 kWh from the grid, my Saldo will be 3000 kWh in my favor.
For that I am supposed to get a &amp;ldquo;reasonable compensation&amp;rdquo;, says the law.
At the same time the goverment made noises that basically said that &amp;ldquo;80% of the purchase price seem to be reasonable&amp;rdquo;.
Apparently this prompts my energy provider to make the above change, offering 75% of the purchase price to preempt regulation.
You know what, I am actually somewhat okay with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the entire specific regulation seems to be not fixed, yet, and the actual handling and pricing is still subject to change.
We will see how this will actually play out, but right now the change has been entirely pro consumer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also clear that we will not keep the Salderingsregeling ad infinitum.
The original plan was to gradually switch it from 100% Saldering to 9% less each year.
That still seems to be the case, so we expect to see this table to be implemented:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;%Saldering&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;100%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;100%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;2024&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;100%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;2025&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;64%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;2026&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;64%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;2027&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;55%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;2028&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;46%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;2029&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;37%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;2030&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;28%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;2031+&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of a gradual decline we see a big initial jump from 100% to 64%.
That&amp;rsquo;s because the original plan was to decrease by 9% starting 2022, and while the end deadline was kept, the initial full Saldering was kept alive for several years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time the government says it expects a reasonable compensation for the other power that is no longer part of the Salderingsregeling, and that&amp;rsquo;s the above 80% (or now 75% number).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a bit unclear how that now will work out:
Will there be two kinds of tariff for power pushed to the grid that is part of the Saldering, and a second tariff for the other power that is not part of the Saldering, or one tariff for everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will see how that works out soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The new energy bill</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/06/28/the-new-energy-bill.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 08:09:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/06/28/the-new-energy-bill.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We got our solar roof around 1st of April.
I am describing our setup &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/02/a-solar-roof.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;

.
Today we got the bill for Summer 2021 to Summer 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-i-measured&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#what-i-measured&#34;&gt;
	What I measured
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I installed a P1 interface on my electricity counter late in April, so my data does not cover all of the lifetime of the Solar Roof.
Starting the graph at 01-Apr-2022, I get this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/06/bill-in-and-out.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;At this resolution, not very helpful.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is visible is the fact that we do not have a battery, and therefore each day we produce energy, but also consume energy from the grid.
What is not visible is the relation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/06/bill-counter.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the absolute counter values is more helpful.
The total production is on the right hand side, the consumption on the left hand side, and the important number is the Range value below the graph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We produced 1.66 MWh during the range between 01-Apr and now. We consumed 279 kWh in that interval.
That leaves us with slightly under 1.5 MWh pushed to the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/06/bill-gas-meter.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heating consumed around 10 m^3 in one evening, otherwise we use gas for warm water. Not a lot.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We consumed 28.7 m^3 (around 287 kWh) of gas since the begin of metering.
This includes one day of runaway heating worth around 10 m^w, and the rest is warm water.
Warm water is not the cost driver, heating with gas is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let&amp;rsquo;s look at the financials:
We get back 561 Euro, because we paid 2297 Euro in 12 monthly installments, and used 1735 Euro worth of power and gas.
Mostly gas, but more on that further down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our monthly installment two years ago was 192 Euro, last year 202 Euro, and this year it will be 213 Euro.
Of these 213 Euro, 199 Euro will be for gas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So already, without knowing details, we have our mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;get-off-gas-now&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#get-off-gas-now&#34;&gt;
	Get off Gas, now!
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is our electricity intake for the last 5 years:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/06/bill-electricity.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Down to 2.052 MW/a from 4.850 MW/a.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Active since April 2022, the solar array has fed back sufficient electricity to compensate for more than half our consumption.
Do I believe in overprovisioning?
Well, yes, kind of.
The array has been built with future use-cases in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, in the last 12 months we used 3881 kWh, and pushed 1834 kWh back to the grid for the set consumption you see in the bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/06/bill-gas.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Down to 1251 m^3 of gas.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out gas consumption also fell, but that is mostly due to a mild winter and not heating much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;doing-the-math&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#doing-the-math&#34;&gt;
	Doing the math
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are paying around 22 ct per kWh of electricity, and while there is a bit of fixed cost, it hardly matters – 22.5 ct per kWh all in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gas costs around 108 ct per m^3, which is an energy equivalent of 10-12 kWh warmth depending on the type of gas.
Fixed cost here is substantial, and we end up at 132 ct per m^3 overall cost (1349.88 Euro for 1251 m^3, and 274.58 Euro of fixed cost).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heating&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;Electricity&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;Heat Pump&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;Gas&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Heat generated&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;10 kWh&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;10 kWh&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;10 kWh&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Energy used&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;10 kWh&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;2-3 kWh&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;1^3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Cost per unit&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;0.225 Euro&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;0.225 Euro&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;1.32 Euro&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Total cost&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;2.25 Euro&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;0.5-0.75 Euro&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:right&#34;&gt;1.32 Euro&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to create 10 kWh of warmth from a heat pump, you have to expend 2-3 kWh of electricity, coming in at 50 ct to 75 ct per m^3 gas-equivalent of heating.
That would be around 1.75 to 2.5 times cheaper than heating with gas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A heat exchanger can be a air-water-air system, so a heat exchanger that uses energy from outside air to heat water that is fed into the existing heating.
This will work to around -10 C to -20 C outside temperatur, but for temperatures below zero, it will become successively inefficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your area permits it, you can take energy not from outside air, but from the water or earth below the house.
This is virtually always frost-free and hence relatively efficient.
So if you have a houseboat or are allowed to install an earth circuit, this can be a completely painless solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Existing radiators driven by heat exchangers almost always need adjustment or exchange, because the water-in temperature of the system is substantially lower than a preexisting gas burner.
So somebody with actual clue will have to do the math and adjustment during installation, and some people will have to either change radiators, or install active venting (fans, basically) that push air through the radiators as a leisurely pace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need air condition anyway, because for example there is a roof room that needs active cooling in summer, you can make sure that you get an airco unit that can operate in reverse mode.
Most of the units that support it are as efficient as heat exchangers, and heat air directly.
Here the work factor is comparable to normal heat exchangers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either system will get you off gas, or (with the airco) work in parallel to an existing gas or oil heating – which is nice in case you do not trust the new system and need backup.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A solar roof</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/02/a-solar-roof.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 08:42:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/02/a-solar-roof.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I live in a house in a rural village somewhere in &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Randstad&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Randstad&lt;/a&gt;

.
We are paying around 70 Euro per month in electricity, and up to 380 Euro per month in gas.
We are using the latter for heating and warm water, but we are already cooking with electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The house has a decent energy rating and a heat exchanger in the forced ventilation system.
That is to keep the warmth in when getting fresh air in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Energy cost of 2021. Electricity remains largely unchanged in 2022, but gas cost rose a lot.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are using a lot of electricity for a 3-person household &amp;ndash; 5500 kWh, a lot of which can be attributed to &amp;ldquo;always on&amp;rdquo; electronics at home.
In particular, one file server consumes around 100W, which accumulates to not quite 1 MWh per year.
Outsourcing that to a cloud service would be too slow, and a lot more expensive, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-situation-and-the-configuration&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#the-situation-and-the-configuration&#34;&gt;
	The situation and the configuration
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The house has a rather steep roof.
One solar installation service, recommended to us via a colleague, declined to make an offer for installation because they were not equipped to handle the roof steepness.
In the end, we went with Zonneplan, who did not have any objections to the general situation at all, and were able to handle it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-03.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Roof steepness, as seen from the south.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roof itself is oriented at 155 deg, pointing the roof ridge line to south/southeast.
The west side is getting better light, but the first half of the day lights up the eastern roof as well.
According to &lt;a href=&#34;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/ephemeris-moon-and-sun-seeker/id1488277219&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;basic astronomy tooling&lt;/a&gt;

, the sun crosses the houses ridge line at 11:45 CEST, and solar noon (sun at 180 deg) is at 13:45.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-04.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ridge line of the house, and the solar panel configuration.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We opted for a solution that places 9 panels on the eastern roof, and 16 on the western side.
The east side of the house got a 3x3 configuration, the west side a 4x4.
The lower two rows on the western side can get shadow from the neighbor and from the house wings (see the shadow on the image above), so they need &amp;ldquo;optimizers&amp;rdquo; to handle shade.
This is what it looks like on the west side:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-05.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Panels on the west side of the roof.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The installed panel type has a size of 1.75m x 1.03m, and a Wp rating of 370W, so we get 200W/qm as expected from current tech.
This is good for 3330Wp on the eastern side and 5920Wp on the western side, for a theoretical total of 9250Wp.
In practice the configuration will never reach that level of output, because both sides of the roof cannot receive direct lighting at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-06.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The type sticker of one of the panels.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inverter is a three-phase Huawei SUN2000-10KTL.
It weighs 16kg and measures 52.5cm x 47.0cm x 16.6 cm, is rated IP65 and could in theory work from -25 to +60 degC.
It still likes to sit inside, dry and warm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-07.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Huawei SUN 2000 inverter.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The device makes no perceptible sound, even under load.
When producing 4500 Watt, it gets a bit warm, but not so much that it will feel painful to the touch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-08.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;FLIR image of the inverter while transforming 4500W from the roof.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Installing the solar panels on the roof catches energy that otherwise has been hitting the roof and reaching the rooms inside.
The rooms directly under the roof are now about 1.5C cooler, a great improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The panels themselves, even when in full sunlight, do not get particularly warm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-09.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;FLIR images of the solar panels while in full sunlight.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;production-and-consumption&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#production-and-consumption&#34;&gt;
	Production and consumption
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a spotless day in April, still on MET, and hardly any clouds.
We have sunrise at 6:40, around 7:00 we see a sharp rise of energy produced on the eastern panels.
This peaks around 9:00 at ~2300W, then falls off a bit until around 11:30 the western panels start to kick in.
From here on the production switches over from eastside to westside, for a peak of 5300W around 16:00.
Sunset is at 20:40, and indeed we get at least a bit of energy almost to the end, though the decline is rather steep starting at 19:40 or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total production is 44.5 kWh over the day.
Around 10 kWh can be attributed to the modules on the eastern side, and their power comes in early when we need it for breakfast.
They help a great deal to even out production over the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-10.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inverter has a GSM module and feeds into the systems of Zonneplan.
That also means I get no direct access to the Modbus in the Inverter without interfering with their warranty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can access the electricity counter of our house, though, through the Dutch P1 interface.
This is done, for example, with a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zuidwijk.com/product/p1-reader-ethernet/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;P1 reader ethernet&lt;/a&gt;

 by Marcel Zuidwijk, connecting the P1 interface from the counter to a free power on the DSL modem.
The data is put onto the &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/11/15/my-home-sensor-network.html&#34;&gt;house MQTT bus&lt;/a&gt;

, using &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Lalufu/p1-mqtt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;software&lt;/a&gt;

 written by a friend and colleague.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading the counters, I get a good overview of what happens during the day:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-11.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Red line: Power drawn from the grid. Green line: Power sent into the grid. You can see how between 6:00 and 20:00 we are sending power to the grid at almost all times. The &amp;ldquo;Range&amp;rdquo; data shows we have drawn 6.25 kWh from the grid over the day, and sent around 30.1 kWh into the grid over the day.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the image above, we can see that we sent 30.1 kWh into the grid yesterday.
The Zonneplan app gives me a total production of 39.42 kWh for that day.
We also took 6.25 kWh from the grid on top of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That gives us a usage of (6.25 kWh + 39.42 kWh - 30.1 kWh =) 15.57 kWh for the day.
Out of this, we covered (39.42 kWh - 30.1 kWh =) 9.32 kWh internally.
We pushed a net surplus of (30.1 kWh - 6.25kWh = ) 23.85 kWh into the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the current counters, I can get a more detailed graph over the day.
You can see a base load in the house of around 300W &amp;ndash; around 100W can be attributed to one server, the rest is various other electronics that is always on.
Great spikes show household appliances doing things: Dishwasher, washing machine, espresso maker, microwave, cooking plates and ovens all draw around 2kW to 3kW, mostly to heat up water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-12.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Up: drawing power from grid. Down: Sending power into the grid. You can see how clouds and internal consumption take their bites of the &amp;ldquo;perfect&amp;rdquo; production curve.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the day-curve this way you can see that we would profit from a household battery.
On this day in April, we could maybe do with a battery of 5kWh or less, but in darker times a larger battery would be more effective.
We could achieve complete autonomy from Equinox to Equinox, and charge the missing energy from the grid during cheap times in the darker half of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The matching piece of equipment would be a Huawei LUNA2000-15-S0 battery pack.
It is a 15 kWh piece of equipment that is 137cm high, 67cm wide and 14cm deep, coming in at 164kg and around 7200 Euro plus shipping.
The pack is based on LFP technology, not on Li-Ion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;legal-and-financials&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#legal-and-financials&#34;&gt;
	Legal and financials
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We purchased the entire solution through Zonneplan at 10162 Euro, so around 1100 Euro per 1 kWp.
This could be a noticeably less, if we did not have shade on the west side &amp;ndash; these optimizers are expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zonneplan not only installed the whole thing, which took less than a day, but also took care of all the planning, and all the paperwork.
That was very comfortable, and they handled all the things professionally and competently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In April, we produced 871.1 kWh, and sent 718 kWh into the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Netherlands, power sent into the grid &amp;ldquo;turns the counter backwards&amp;rdquo;.
That is, you can treat the network like a battery, 1 kWh sent in is 1 kWh you can get back later for free.
This is called &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rijksoverheid.nl/onderwerpen/duurzame-energie/zonne-energie&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Salderingsregeling voor huishoudens en MKB&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Households and small businesses are allowed to feed self-generated electricity back into the grid until January 1, 2023. And offset it against their consumption at another time. This is called offsetting.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This rule was supposed to end at 1. January 2023, but will be prolonged at least one year more, says &lt;a href=&#34;https://solarmagazine.nl/nieuws-zonne-energie/i26235/startdatum-afbouw-salderingsregeling-zonnepanelen-niet-haalbaar-ambtenaren-adviseren-1-jaar-uitstel&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Solar Mag&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Startdatum afbouw salderingsregeling zonnepanelen niet haalbaar, ambtenaren adviseren 1 jaar uitstel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start date for phasing out solar panel feed-in scheme not feasible, officials advise 1 year postponement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phasing out the salderingsregeling to Zero is supposed to be done in 9% steps, not all at once.
So in the first year, 91% of the power would be part of the salderingsregeling, the rest the electricity provider would pay for, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law says that the provider must pay &amp;ldquo;redelijke vergoeding&amp;rdquo; (a reasonable compensation).
At this point, a compensation of 80% of what you pay for electricity to them is considered reasonable by the lawmaker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That would mean, I get paid at least 18.0 ct/kWh when I am paying them 22.5 ct/kWh.
That&amp;rsquo;s workable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;outlook&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#outlook&#34;&gt;
	Outlook
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now we have solved our  electricity problem, and manage to have solid overproduction (at least in the brighter part of the year).
We are also getting a tiny electric car this year, which will eat into our budget.
That also means we are not getting a Huawei battery this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will have to eventually change the house heating from a central gas burner to a different system, likely air conditioners/heat exchangers that use electricity to warm up and cool air directly.
They work as heat pumps, and produce between 3 kWh and 5 kWh heat for each 1 kWh they consume.
This will considerably increase our consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warming up 1l of water by 1C takes around 1.16 Wh, and the cooking gas we use provides around 10 to 12 kWh per cubic metre (1000l).
So a shower that uses 240l (0.24 cubic metres) of gas consumes around 2.4kWh.
Similar math can be applied to dishwashers and washing machines (&amp;ldquo;uses 0.885kWh to heat up 15l of water by 50C&amp;rdquo;), and to cooking plates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be using a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; more electricity if we are going to eliminate cooking gas completely in this household.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A solar roof 2</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/02/a-solar-roof-2.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 09:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/02/a-solar-roof-2.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Zum vorhergehenden Artikel bekam ich einen Leserbrief als Github Issue, das ist hier inhaltlich unverändert veröffentliche,
weil ich glaube, daß es wichtige Informationen und Überlegungen enthält.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Von &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/typxxi&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@typxxi&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich schreibe einmal auf Deutsch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;akku-lebensdauer&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#akku-lebensdauer&#34;&gt;
	Akku Lebensdauer
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Großer Speicher heißt nicht immer gut, weil der LFP Akku dann eher über kalendarische Alterung stirbt,
und nicht in Folge der Zyklen.
Ein LFP-Akku schafft um die 3500 bis 6000 Zyklen.
Das hiesse bei Dir im Idealfall, Du schaffst so 200 Zyklen pro Jahr und damit 17 bis 30 Jahre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;200 ist schon viel, denn durch die Ost-West-Teilung und Verschattungen wird das im Winter recht schwierig,
weil nicht genug hineinkommen wird, da die PV zu klein ist und eine 15 kWh Batterie zu groß bei dem aktuellen Lastprofil von 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich bezweifele, dass Du überhaupt 200 Zyklen bei der 15 kWh voll kriegen wirst, weil Dein Nachtverbrauch im Sommer gering ausfällt -
wegen der Kürze der Nacht.
So bleiben dann nur noch die Übergangs-Jahreszeiten mit längeren Nächten und guten Sonnenerträgen,
wo Du bei 5500 kWh und damit grob 15 kWh / Tag landest, was für die Nacht ja aber kaum 50% = 7,5 kWh bedeuten wird.
Wahrscheinlich ist es so. daß das Haus in 6h auf Grundlast zurückfällt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;grundlast-und-strom-sparen&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#grundlast-und-strom-sparen&#34;&gt;
	Grundlast und Strom sparen
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grundlast ermittelt man am besten beim nächsten Familienurlaub durch Aufschreiben des Zählerstandes bei der Abreise und
Ablesen bei Rückkehr.
Der Verbrauch in der Zeit, den Stunden Eurer Abwesenheit ergibt Deine Grundlast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist elektrisch nicht ganz korrekt, weil zyklische Verbraucher wie Kühlgeräte mitgezählt werden,
die der Definition nach kein Teil der Grundlast sind.
In diesem Fall schon, weil wir die Zyklen für den Akku per Überschlag bestimmen wollen,
und wir auch versteckten Verbrauchern durch Messen und Rechnen auf die Spur kommen wollen.
Denn dort liegt das größte Potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Da reicht es nicht, den Server mit 100W zu schätzen, sondern zu messen und um jedes Watt zu
kämpfen (wobei in NL vielleicht nicht, solange jede PV kWh 91 % oder 82 % oder 73 % Wert behält).
Dann beginnt auch der Kampf um jeden einzelnen eurer Stromsauger, die 24/7 Verbraucher wie eine Fritz!Box
mit 11 W, oder deren Repeater, die gern einmal 10 W und mehr nehmen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daumenregel: 1 W Verbrauch im 24/7 Betrieb = 9 kWh p.a.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genauer: 1 Watt x 24 h / Tag x 365 Tage / 1000 = 8,76 kWh,
oder einfacher: 1 Jahr = 8760 Stunden und in kWh eben 8,8 kWh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Server kostet dann fix 880 kWh/a,
und da sollte eine Menge zu sparen sein durch eine passende Energiesparplattform,
denn gerade da kam ja auch der Erfolg des Raspi her.
Ein Raspi 4 liegt grob 4 W als unterem Ende, also 96 W Einsparung,
nur kann da ja auch ein Fileserver Rack dran hängen,
sodass andere Kaliber Sinn machen, nur ist das der 1. Punkt, Strom zu sparen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zum Raspi Verbrauch hier ein guter Beitrag , der die verschiedenen Lastsituation betrachtete:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://buyzero.de/blogs/news/was-kostet-mich-der-pi-4-an-strom-im-jahr-how-much-does-power-usage-cost-for-the-pi-4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Was kostet mich der Pi 4 an Strom im Jahr?&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, zuerst bei Verbrauch schauen und sparen, gibt lächerliche Dinge, aber sie bringen was.
Natürlich in Deutschland mehr als in NL, weil hier die kWh eingespeist mit 8 cent vergütet wird und aktuell so 35 Cent kostet,
wenn sie in der Nacht gebraucht wird.
Daher ist der Druck hier größer, Strom zu sparen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wer Alexa in Form von Echo Show &amp;amp; Co hat, der kann sich fragen, ob er 1. die Display-Helligkeit braucht,
mit der die läuft, oder es mit weniger auch geht.
3 Watt sind nirgendwo fixer gespart als da.
Und noch viel mehr, wenn man die Frage der Helligkeit richtig zu Ende denkt für sich: Display ist immer aus, außer es schallt &amp;ldquo;Alexa!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Einstellung gibt es tatsächlich, den Nachtmodus, den wir auf 12:00 bis 11:59 gesetzt haben,
sodass der Echo Show 1x pro Tag mittags erwacht und Lebenszeichen von sich gibt.
Schont das Display (unser 1. Show mit 5 Zoll hat ein leidendes Display) und spart so grob 6 Watt
, wenn ich mich recht entsinne: 54 kWh p.a. bzw. 18€&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und die Kids lernen das nur so, was wir selber in der Jugend nie lernten,
denn Wasser und Strom flossen ja immer gut und reichlich und nur die Eltern hatten 1x im Jahr Kopfschmerzen,
woher nur dieser Anstieg stammte.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;batteriebedarf-abschätzen&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#batteriebedarf-absch%c3%a4tzen&#34;&gt;
	Batteriebedarf abschätzen
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, zurück zur Batterie.
Ich gehe von sagen wir 220 W Grundlast aus, dann hast Du vereinfacht in 6 Monaten eine Dunkelphase mit 7 h Kernnacht und 3h Abendprogramm,
wo die Batterie liefern darf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wir nehmen an: 7h x 220 W + 3h x 750W&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist schon eher viel für TV schauen, 120 W bei 65&amp;quot; mit Sky Receiver &amp;amp; Licht an + 50&amp;quot; Monitor &amp;amp; Laptop an = 90W = 1540 + 2250 =3790 Wh
ergibt einen Bedarf von 4 kWh pro Nacht in den 6 Monaten.
Im Sommer aber auch weniger, weil die Sonne eher und länger Strom liefern kann, die Batteriephasen kürzer ausfallen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kontrollrechnung: die übrigen 14h x 750 W ergäben 10,5 kWh und damit Tagesverbrauch 15 kWh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, damit sollte klar sein, dass die 15 kWh Batterie zu groß sein dürfte, außer die Dinge ändern sich wie angedeutet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;batteriebedarf-mit-wärmepumpe-splitklima&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#batteriebedarf-mit-w%c3%a4rmepumpe-splitklima&#34;&gt;
	Batteriebedarf mit Wärmepumpe (Splitklima)
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fangen wir mal damit an, dass Du einen gleitenden Übergang bei der Heizung siehst,
dann gäbe es da als 1. Weg die Nachrüstung einer Split Klimaanlage als Heizung.
Für die großen Räume vor allem im EG, wofür Du selber nicht viel Geschick brauchst,
weil es nur 1 Kernbohrung braucht und danach nur noch Kabel verbinden und Maulschlüssel nutzen, ggf. mit Drehmomentschlüssel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Anlage kann dann heizen und im Sommer kühlen, was alle südeuropäischen Länder seit Jahren nutzen,
weil deren Heizlast geringer ist.
Der Wirkungsgrad ist sehr hoch, weil aus der Außenluft die Energie gezogen und direkt nebenan im Raum abgegeben wird
ohne 20 m Heizungsleitungen und Verluste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wir haben 5,4 kWh große Mitsubishi nachgerüstet - im Altbau der 70er, der aber schon damals mit über 10 cm Wand und Decke gedämmt war.
Die Kosten liegen incl. WLAN und aller Quick Connect Leitungen bei circa. 1100 € -
wenn Du hier jemanden beauftragst, dann sind es 3000 €, sodass Du siehst, wie sehr sich da das lohnt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nimm aber eine Marke.
In der Regel reicht aber das Basisgerät, denn Du kannst da viel Geld in Design investieren mit begrenztem Nutzen,
denn für 500 € mehr bekommst Du die gleiche Anlage, die aber per Fernbedienung den Luftstrom nicht nur vertikal,
sondern auch seitlich lenken kann.
Wer das braucht, bitte, aber 1600 € heben die Hemmschwelle, so etwas mal zu probieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und: große Räume eignen sich besser, weil 1. Wärme aufsteigt,
und die Anlagenkosten sich nicht linear verteilen, also kleinere 2,2 kW Anlage für 4 0% zu haben ist.
Sie kostet stattdessen dann 800 € statt 1100 €, macht also kaum Sinn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Von daher Split-Klimaanlagen immer größer auslegen als der Heizbedarf wäre, weil Du immer noch mit Tür auf das Haus als solches mit wärmen kannst,
besonders bei Euren wohl vielen Etagen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Na klar, für 500 € mehr bekommst Du auch noch einen kleinen Bonus bei der Effizienz,
denn statt COP 4,1 gibt es dann vielleicht 4,4 - also 1 kWh elektrisch bringt 4,1 oder 4,4 kWh Wärme.
Du brauchst aber lange, um mit der 10 % höheren Effizienz die 500 € reinzuholen,
da hast Du mehr von vielen kleinere Anlagen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bei Multisplit-Anlagen muss man wissen, dass Du da auch 2 oder 3 Innenräume heizen kannst,
wobei jeweils 2 oder 3 Innengeräte an 1 Außengerät angeschlossen werden.
Funktioniert gut, kostet aber auch und hat Schwächen, wenn ein Raum kalt und der andere auf Vollgas / Vollstrom laufen soll.
Mag sich bei benachbarten Räumen lohnen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bei Quickconnect musst Du wissen, dass sich das Kühlmittel im Außengerät befindet.
Mit der Quickconnect Leitung kannst Du die beiden Geräteteile selber verbinden und in Betrieb nehmen - außer Du lebst in Deutschland,
da brauchst Du den Klimaschein.
In Italien war das für uns nicht der Fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es muss Dank Quickconnect kein Vacuum erzeugt oder kontrolliert werden, solange Du mit 7 m Rohrlänge klar kommst.
denn für 7m packt Mitsubisih Kältemittel in das Außengerät.
Ansonsten muss der Klimatechniker kommen und nachfüllen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lange Vorgeschichte, um zu zeigen, dass man auch elektrisch zuheizen kann,
oder gar mit 3 Anlagen a 5,4 kW den alten Heizkessel an Heizleistung mit 16 kW erreichen kann.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An den sehr kalten Tagen, die Du an 2 Händen zählen kannst, wenn es unter 5° C geht,
verliert die WP ihren Wirkungsgrad und Arbeitsleistung, da sollte dann was helfen?
Gas heizen und mit elektrischem Heizlüfter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das alles nur, um zu sagen, dass diese Heizung sinnvoll sein kann,
und dann auch teils von Batteriestrom profitieren kann.
Das ist vor allen Dingen in der Übergangszeit sinnvoll,
wenn morgens die Sonne noch weg ist oder abends schon wieder.
Jedoch braucht eine 5,4 kW Heizung mit COP 4 maximal Strom von 1,6 kW -
wenn Du bei 12 ° heim kommst und das Ding auf 28° drehst und mit voller Drehzahl Wärme brauchst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die 1,6 kW machen es Dir auch leicht, dieses Gerät nachträglich an eine normale Unterputzdose in den Stromkreis einzubinden.
Damit will ich sagen, dass hier eine 5,4 kW Anlage im Winter einen Wohnraum konstant auf 23° C hielt.
Der Verbrauch lag dabei bei 4 kWh am Tag, in der Übergangszeit weniger: 2 bis 3 kWh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Für die Rechnung ist das wichtig, ja der Akku auch morgens noch voll sein sollte, wenn man die Nachtzeit von Batterie versorgen will.
Von den 2 bis 3 kWh entfallen dann vielleicht 40 % auf die Nacht oder weniger, wenn man Nachtabsenkung der Temperatur in Kauf nimmt.
Nimm einfach mal 1,3 kWh für die Nacht je Gerät und schwups bist Du bei 3 Geräten bei 4 kWh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mit den 4 kWh Alltagsverbrauch und mit 4 kWh fürs Heizen per Split Klima in 3 Räumen und mehr landest Du bei 8 kWh Bedarf,
und irgendwie ist der 15 kWh Akku immer noch verdammt groß, liegen also 3600 € Kapital brach herum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daher der Rat, das ganze mal mit 10 kWh zu denken, die Dir vielleicht 2400 € sparen, die reichen, um dafür Splitklima zu kaufen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wasserbereitung&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#wasserbereitung&#34;&gt;
	Wasserbereitung
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jetzt mag noch die Frage kommen, wie es mit dem warmen Wasser wäre.
Genau, das ist dann auch so eine noch einfachere Sache.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es gibt vor allen in Südeuropa Monoblockanlagen, die meist in einem wärmeren Raum aufgestellt werden.
In Frage kommen Heizungskeller oder ähnlich.
Die Anlage zieht dort aus der Umluft die Wärme ziehen, und heizt einen 100 Liter Wasserbehälter auf.
Diese werden an nur 2 Rohren in den bestehen Warmwasserkreislauf eingebunden, was Du auch selber machen kannst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keine weitere Veränderung erforderlich, alles beim Alten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein solches Gerät hat Abmessungen von etwa 50 x 50 cm x 120 cm Höhe, und wird meist an die Wand gehängt, in Südeuropa auch gern in die Küche.
Entsprechend gestalten die Anbieter aus Südeuropa das auch gern mal wie ein Interieur Möbel,
schönere Oberfläche und Bedienung als die typischen Heizungen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Preis liegt um die 900-1100 € von Ariston, in der einfachsten Variante.
Ich rate Dir aber sofort, da genau zu schauen, denn die kommen ohne WLAN und SMART,
haben mitunter aber eine Steuerleitung, sodass Du bei PV Überschuss eben auch das Wasser warm machen kannst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lohnt sich alles für NL heute nicht so sehr , aber mit jedem Jahr weiter un 9% weniger Wert der eingespeisten kWh um so eher und mehr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Für die Rechnung nimmst Du einfach an:
Du hast da 100 Liter, die mit 15° C reinkommen und auf 55°C erwärmt werden müssen. 40° C x 1,1 Wh/ °C und 100 Liter
enden bei Wärmebedarf von 4400 Wh, wobei so eine Ariston Nuos Primo mit COP 3 als Wirkungsgrad kommt.
Das bedeutet, Du brauchst 1,5 kWh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ist die Frage aber, wie viel kWh Du morgens brauchst, bevor die Sonne aufgeht, um den Behälter aufzuheizen.
Da sind die 40° C ja selten fällig, weil nicht immer abends noch geduscht worden ist und 100 Liter 15° Wasser nachgefüllt worden sind,
sondern Du mit 100 Liter 40° C warmen Wasser aus der Nacht kommst und dann nur noch 1/3 der Heizlast hättest, eben 15° C erwärmen
statt 40 °C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Strombedarf sinkt dann auf 0,600 kWh wären.
Und damit ist 3/4 des Jahres, wenn im Akku auch Strom sein wird, der Akku mit 9 kWh ausgelastet.
Im Sommer noch weniger, im Spätherbst und frühen Frühling mehr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;auto&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#auto&#34;&gt;
	Auto
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ach ja, der Elektroflitzer soll ja auch eher tagsüber geladen werden als mit Verlusten aus der Batterie in die Batterie,
sodass man dessen Bedarf als Ausnahmen vergessen kann.
Er ist im Übrigen die viel billigere Batterie, stell Dir mal einen 50 kWh PKW vor,
der aus den HUAWEI 15 kWh Speichern gebaut würde, denn dann wären das schon 25000 €,
also ist der günstigste Speicher Dein Auto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selbst in Deutschland wird Vehicle 2 Load als Rückspeisen ins Haus bzw. als Vehicle 2 Grid ins Netz kommen.
Zuerst VW, die sich gegen die Stromlobby durchsetzten.
Von daher baue den Akku nicht zu groß, wenn in 1 Jahr VW und dann andere Vehicle 2 Load Fahrzeuge liefern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein Ford F150 Lightning Truck kann ein ganzes Haus versorgen, weil bis zu 9 kW aus dem Fahrzeug gehen können, wobei klares Negativbeispiel.
Ein MG4 in Golf Größe kommt in der Basis mit einer 51 kWh LFP battery und einer 2,3 kW Leistung Vehicle 2 Load (kein 2 Grid).
Der MG4 Akku mit 3500 Zyklen und mehr kann dann die Hausbatterie ersetzen.
Noch ein Grund mehr, eine NICHT ZU GROSSE HAUSBATTERIE zu kaufen.
(Nebenrechnung: 300 km WLTP hieße bei 3500 Zyklen aber eine Akkulebensdauer von 1.250.000 km,
die das AUto nie fahren wird.
Der Akku hält also länger als das Auto mechanisch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;überschüsse-handhaben&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#%c3%bcbersch%c3%bcsse-handhaben&#34;&gt;
	Überschüsse handhaben
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nun der Punkt, der ebenso wichtig ist: Wenn Überschuss, dann bestimmte Verbraucher mit Überschuss Strom betreiben&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das nennt sich bei Auto und Wallbox Überschussladen.
Die Softwarelösung heißt wohl EVCC, wenn Du nicht eine teure, an den Wechselrichterhersteller gebundene Lösung kaufst.
Nur läuft die dann meist nur mit einer Huawei Wallbox, so es die gibt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der nächste Verbraucher wäre ein Problem, von daher schau Dir EVCC an, die einen Raspi braucht oder einen SonOff ihost,
der ein lokales Smarthome ohne China Cloud für aktuell noch heute 55 € bietet.
Also eine grob Pi 3 / Pi 4 vergleichbare Leistung mit einer Docker Einbindung und Zigbee, WLAN und BT an Bord,
sowie anderem Zeug.
Heute noch im Release Angebot, was seit März gelaufen ist.
Ansonsten wohl etwas teurer, aber günstiger als Pi 4 neu von ebay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EVCC erlaubt Dir das Laden von einem oder mehreren Fahrzeugen bzw. Verbrauchern mit Regeln
&amp;ldquo;Wie lade nur das, was an Überschussstrom sonst ins Netz ginge (die Fahrzeuge können meist erst ab 6A)&amp;rdquo;
und das auch intelligent.
Denn neben dem reinen grünen Überschuss gibt es noch andere Ladeprogramme, um das Fahrzeug schnell zu laden
auch mit Strom vom Netz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und Deine Splitklima, ggf. aber auf alle Fälle die Warmwasser-Wärmepumpe sind ein Super Überschussverbraucher&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dieser Energymaster ist die Zentrale, denn nur diese Überschussverbraucher lassen sich wirklich gut mit Überschuss betreiben.
Eine Spülmaschine oder Waschmaschine nur und erst dann ein zuschalten, wenn der Strom reicht,
ist im Alltag eher ein Alptraum in der Steuerung und muss man bzw. alle in der Familie wollen.
Abends nach Haus und die Maschine ist nicht gelaufen, da kippt die Stimmung dann fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Von daher schau mal EVCC an, ist Open Source und bestimmte Funktionen brauchen einen Sponsor,
was der Wallbox Hersteller übernommen haben kann, sodass alle Produkte des Herstellers das gratis können -
oder kostet Dich maximal $2 p.a. und ist Open Source made in Germany mit sehr lebendiger Community.
Du findest die Site auf &lt;a href=&#34;evcc.io&#34;&gt;evcc.io&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;steuerung-und-modellierung&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#steuerung-und-modellierung&#34;&gt;
	Steuerung und Modellierung
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;War es das ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All das ist die alte, händische Art so was anzudenken und zu durchplanen.
Es hätte Dir vor 1 Jahr vielleicht auch mehr geholfen, das so zu finden, aber sei es drum.
Da auf dem Blog nichts Neues stand, sah es erst einmal nach dem Stand der Dinge aus,
wo sich ein Akku kaum rentiert, wenn man von 1 kWh eingespeist morgen oder im Dezember noch 0,91 kWh zurück bekommt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Von daher mag das jetzt Sinn machen und Dich auch schon länger fragen lassen,
was noch geht und wie in welcher Reihenfolge.
Nur der Rat, dass Du lieber einen eng bemessenen Hausakku kaufst,
und im Hinterkopf hast, dass die PKW das künftig von Haus mitbringen werden,
und zwar vor 2030, denn VW ist ein Big Player wie ein F150 Lightning in den USA bei Trucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All das hier ist die alte, einfache Art, weil jeder der Dein Blog dazu liest, dem auch folgen kann.
Willst Du mehr und genauer, also auch PV Anlage planen und vergleichen können,
dann kannst Du sozusagen Dein Haus an Deinem Ort einfach in 3 D planen.
Deine Anlage, wie sie ist, nachbauen und passend dazu Deine Verbrauchsprofile hinterlegen,
wann welcher Verbraucher am Tag oder in der Woche läuft und was an Strom braucht,
oder aber Du nimmst die 5500 kWh und lässt die für einen 3 Personenhaushalt mit 1 auf Achse und der Rest zu Haus runterbrechen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diese Software errechnet dann auf Basis der Einstrahlungsdaten an Deinem Ort die Erträge je Minute aus der PV,
und stellt dem ggü. die Verbräuche , sodass das System für jede Minute eine Bilanz erstellt und das ganze zu einem Jahresergebnis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Da kannst Du dann alternative Module simulieren, alternativ Belegungen und Wechselrichter, ebenso Batteriegrößen,
DIY Akkus und die Wärmepumpe bzw. Dein Auto elektrisch fahren lassen mit wöchentlich 500 km und Ladeprofilen und Zeiten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das findest Du auf bei Valentin Software in Berlin - gratis als 30 Tage Demo,
wobei Du die Kundenprofil-Auswertungen halt nicht drucken kannst, aber mit Screenshot kriegst Du alles auch so.
Alle Versionen gibt es dort zum Download und laufen prima.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Anbieter hat auch alle Daten der Module und Wechselrichter hinterlegt.
Du sparst Dir das fehlerträchtige Abtippen der Specs, die das System braucht, um zu simulieren.
Du mussst nur Modul Daten etc. auswählen, und dann sollte das System signalisieren,
dass alle Komponenten passen oder woran es scheitert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das Ergebnis der Simulation ist super, die Daten sind realistisch, also die Planung zuverlässig,
die Modul, Batterie, Wechselrichterdaten werden teils von den Herstellern eingepflegt und laufend aktualisiert,
weshalb alles von deren Servern zur Laufzeit kommt.
Ist dann Dein Wechselrichter dabei mit neuen Specs oder verbesserter Version,
dann wirst Du gefragt, mit welchem Modell Du weiter arbeiten willst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Planung selber ist da schon was anderes.
Man braucht, um sich da einzufinden, aber am Ende geht es oder Du kennst Leute und kannst fragen.
Von daher halt der Hinweis, dass Du PV SOL in der PREMIUM Version.
Nimm nicht die kleineren, sondern gleich das Profi-Tool,
das Du sehr gut nutzen kannst, um Dein System von heute zukunftssicher zu gestalten durch u.a. Simulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;wechselrichter-brauchen-strom&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#wechselrichter-brauchen-strom&#34;&gt;
	Wechselrichter brauchen Strom
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lange Geschichte, aber ich denke, dass Du was daraus machen wirst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dazu hast Du noch bedingte Reserveflächen, die auf den Garagen / Carport etc.
Je weniger die eingespeiste kWh wert sein wird, je eher wirst Du mehr Leistung auf dem Dach haben wollen.
Und von daher hast Du jetzt Zeit, die Zukunft so zu planen, dass Du Dir ad hoc auch nix verbaust wie mit einem teuren, zu großen Speicher, denn:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;im Winter wirst Du den ausschalten,
weil ein Hybrid Wechselrichter dann auch fix 70 oder über 120 Watt in der Nacht jede Stunde aus der Batterie ziehen kann,
um nur bereit zu sein, Strom zu erzeugen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jetzt passiert nix dergleichen, denn die PV Module liefern keinen Strom und Dein Wechselrichter legt sich schlafen.
Kommt die Batterie, dann will der aber 24/7 seinen Anteil zum Betrieb und der kann hoch sein:
höher als Dir lieb ist, weshalb dann viele gerade mit so einer eingeschränkten Ost -Westleistung wie bei Dir eben die Kiste im Winter aussschalten,
weil der Überschuss zum Laden zu gering sein wird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daran denken die wenigsten und fallen nachher aus allen Wolken,
wenn die Monatsauswertungen plötzlich hohe Verluste zeigen wie 200 kWh für den Betrieb des Akkus im Monat,
weil ja der Verbrauch des Wechselrichters nur durch den Akku provoziert wird.
Ohne Akku wären die nicht da.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;schluß&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#schlu%c3%9f&#34;&gt;
	Schluß
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gutes Studium und Gelingen - ich schaue mal bei Gelegenheit vorbei und wenn Fragen sind,
dann kann ich vielleicht mit Antworten helfen oder sagen, wo Du die Antworten findest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Klar, das macht alles heute noch nicht wirklich Sinn in NL,
weil eben 91 % oder 82 % jeder eingespeisten kWh gratis zurückkommen,
wann immer Du die im Jahr brauchen könntest.
Aber mit jedem Jahr weiter kommst Du deutschen Verhältnissen näher, wo eben die kWh vom Netz das 4,x fache dessen kostet,
was Deine eben eingespeiste kWh bringt, von daher endet das in derselben Richtung früher oder später.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Safe Biking: It&#39;s not the right of way that&#39;s wrong</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/10/22/safe-biking-its-not-the-right-of-way-thats-wrong.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 17:06:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/10/22/safe-biking-its-not-the-right-of-way-thats-wrong.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sven Geggus &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/realgiggls/status/1319205107318378498&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;trolled me&lt;/a&gt;

. A bunch of nerds were speaking about what&amp;rsquo;s wrong with biking in Germany, and he wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/realgiggls/status/1319205107318378498&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-troll.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/realgiggls/status/1319205107318378498&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;

: Der @isotopp wohnt doch in Holland. Wo sind denn bei euch die Vorfahrtsregeln anders und könnte man da was sinnvoll für .de übernehmen? &amp;ndash; @isotopp is living in the Netherlands. So how is the right of way different and how could .de learn from this?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biking in the Netherlands does not suck, and that is not because of any specific traffic rules being any different, but because traffic is fundamentally different, and that somehow escalated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It starts here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-osha.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The OSHA hierarchy of mitigations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The OSHA hierarchy of mitigations for safety risks, as shown &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.osha.gov/shpguidelines/hazard-prevention.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;

 and approximately everywhere else where workplace safety and risks are discussed also applies to traffic risks. Of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eliminate - build car free cities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Substitute - build better public transport.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Isolate - build bike paths that are completely intersection free with car traffic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engineer Controls - build intersections with barriers, traffic lights. Build speed bumps into streets that destroy shocks of speeding cars.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Administrative Controls - install warning signs, train bikers to avoid cars. Change right of way rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Personal Protectice Equipment - require bike helmets and high viz vests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-it-came-to-be&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#how-it-came-to-be&#34;&gt;
	How it came to be
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is the famous &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/cities/2015/may/05/amsterdam-bicycle-capital-world-transport-cycling-kindermoord&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Guardian article&lt;/a&gt;

 that explains the history of &lt;a href=&#34;https://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stichting_Kinderen_Voorrang&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stop De Kindermoord&lt;/a&gt;

 and there is the video &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YY6PQAI4TZE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Namens De Kinderen Van De Pijp, 1972&lt;/a&gt;

 that tries to explain and to capture the amount of outrage in the Netherlands in the early 70&amp;rsquo;ies regarding the destruction of the urban environment created by a car culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jokinen_Plan&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-jokinen.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is the infamous &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jokinen_Plan&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Plan Jokinen&lt;/a&gt;

, which would have completely destroyed the old town of Amsterdam (which is now a Unesco World Heritage Site) and replaced it with a giant tumor of highway intersection, killing the city completely. Its realization was averted, thankfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other cities were less lucky, and took heavy damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bicycledutch.wordpress.com/2016/01/05/motorway-removed-to-bring-back-original-water/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-utrecht.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Utrecht Catharijnesingel was destroyed and turned into an Autobahn. It took more than 40 years to restore this part of the city to something not insane. &lt;a href=&#34;https://bicycledutch.wordpress.com/2016/01/05/motorway-removed-to-bring-back-original-water/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Article at Bicycledutch&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Amsterdam, the same story is told, slightly differently. We have &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/10/08/vijzelbuurt-is-changing.html&#34;&gt;Vijzelbuurt is changing&lt;/a&gt;

 here in this blog, explaining the construction of &lt;a href=&#34;https://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rode_Loper_%28Amsterdam%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;De Rode Loper&lt;/a&gt;

 as an extension of the Metro 52 construction. At station Vijzelstraat, the room between the street and the very deeply located metro station is now turned into a parking garage. On street parking will be dialled back or completely removed, and people that still want a car can rent space down there - but it will of course cost substantially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is systematic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/339735964&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-amsterdam-removal.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The city of Amsterdam is about to remove 10.000 parking spaces inside the inner city. &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/339735964&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you want to read more? &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/i/lists/777177965138436096&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;I have a Twitter List for that&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we currently are seeing in the Netherlands is the result of a fight. It took more than 10 years from the 1972 De Pijp video and the Stop De Kindermoord Die-Ins to visible, rideable biking improvements. That was 40 years ago, and when you ride through the Netherlands you can roughly see the decade the bike infrastructure was built when riding it. There have been learnings and improvements all the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Germany, right now, is building 1980&amp;rsquo;ies bike lanes, on a NL scale, using paint on streets. There is no physical separation, there are zero improvements in intersections. And that is the core of the problem: The critical parts are the intersections, see the OSHA hierarchy above, this is where people die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you cannot improve intersections with paint. You need an excavator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;osha-3---isolate---avoid-intersections&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#osha-3---isolate---avoid-intersections&#34;&gt;
	OSHA #3 - Isolate - avoid intersections
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s bike from Hoofddorp Floriande to Vijfhuizen, and have a look at the scenery. Here is the video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9TbKlBZ7H-U&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-segregated1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9TbKlBZ7H-U&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some key points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We never really interact with car traffic, barring one situation near Spaarne Gasthuis, and even that could have been avoided choosing one bike lane to the left.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We never interact with any of the two national streets (N201, N205). We have a tunnel and a bridge for bikes instead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-segregated2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Typical bike lane in Hoofddorp. The bike path is segregated from any car lane, and is bi-directional. Cyclists can ride two-up side by side, and talk.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-segregated3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Underpass under the N201. The N201 is a multilane national road. It could have been a crossing with a traffic light, but building an underpass removes all risk to cyclists from cars.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-segregated4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The same spot, as seen by a car driver. The bubble indicates where we emerge from under the road, passing the underpass.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-segregated5.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Later we pass over the N205, across the bike bridge. Underneath are 2x2 lanes of the N205 and the 2x1 lane of the reserved bus lane.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not an unusual trip in the Netherlands. In another article in this blog, &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/02/22/in-which-we-cycle-shopping.html&#34;&gt;we cycle shopping&lt;/a&gt;

, and the experience is much the same. We never interact with cars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-these-bike-paths-are-empty&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#but-these-bike-paths-are-empty&#34;&gt;
	But these bike paths are empty!
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;But, Kris! All these bike paths are always empty!&amp;rdquo; Yes, they are. It&amp;rsquo;s awesome. You get to ride at your own speed, and without disturbance. It also is a great example that shows how incredibly space efficient bikes are, compared to cars. In fact, how incredibly space efficient &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; is, compared to cars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-60people.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prinzipalmarkt, City of Münster, Germany. 60 people are shown when using cars, using a bus and using bikes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using cars means you use 20 sqm of space when parking, 140 sqm of space when riding. Using a bike, you are using 2 sqm when parking, and 5 sqm when riding. Because cars are so incredibly wasteful with space, &lt;a href=&#34;https://usa.streetsblog.org/2016/04/01/why-bike-lanes-with-lots-of-bike-traffic-can-still-appear-empty/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;car lanes look full&lt;/a&gt;

. We simply cannot afford to have cars where many people live, that is, we cannot have cars in cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-space.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;But, Kris! Can you prove that bikes are used in the Netherlands?&amp;rdquo; Sure, let&amp;rsquo;s go places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=S1xGsDyT4PI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-haarlem-station.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=S1xGsDyT4PI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;

 - a look at Haarlem Station and the bike parking underneath.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This bike parking is only a fraction of the bike parking. There is more inside the train station building and there is a multilevel bike parking at the back of the station. All of them are as full as this underground bike parking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not the exception, this is the rule. Rush Hour in Amsterdam is horribly busy. It looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H31UFT2wnWM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-ams-rush.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H31UFT2wnWM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;

 - Rush Hour in Amsterdam.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-GDbI7OvPak&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Amsterdam in Rain&lt;/a&gt;

, Thomas Schlijper is an awesome chronicler of Amsterdam street life in video and photos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=92RvILIZ2jk&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Paris in 2020&lt;/a&gt;

, again by Schlijper. This is &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_Hidalgo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Anne Hidalgo&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;

 legacy, completely transforming the city of Paris from a gridlock hellscape back into a liveable city by pushing cars out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-there-is-no-room-in-our-city&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#but-there-is-no-room-in-our-city&#34;&gt;
	But there is no room in our city
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;But, Kris! This may work where you live, with wide streets and much room and many trees, but not in our crowded and narrow city. We have no room to segregate traffic!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/marcogroenewege/status/1319298417894383616&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-de-nl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/marcogroenewege/status/1319298417894383616&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;

 - Marco Groenewege contrasting a major city artery in Germany and the S107, a major Amsterdam artery, and of comparable size. The dutch street separates traffic types, makes impossible for cars to leave the lane and overtake, or abuse or block the tram. Area use of both constructs is comparable, one is much safer.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is room in every city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You get it &lt;em&gt;by taking away space from cars&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then people do no longer die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the whole secret.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;%28https://www.google.com/maps/@52.3746636,4.8724909,3a,75y,23.52h,77.55t/data=!3m7!1e1!3m5!1s1jLXsDUxpzMsLOdAZ1dPtA!2e0!6s%2F%2Fgeo3.ggpht.com%2Fcbk%3Fpanoid%3D1jLXsDUxpzMsLOdAZ1dPtA%26output%3Dthumbnail%26cb_client%3Dmaps_sv.tactile.gps%26thumb%3D2%26w%3D203%26h%3D100%26yaw%3D226.72017%26pitch%3D0%26thumbfov%3D100!7i16384!8i8192%29&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-amsterdam1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/@52.3746636,4.8724909,3a,75y,23.52h,77.55t/data=!3m7!1e1!3m5!1s1jLXsDUxpzMsLOdAZ1dPtA!2e0!6s%2F%2Fgeo3.ggpht.com%2Fcbk%3Fpanoid%3D1jLXsDUxpzMsLOdAZ1dPtA%26output%3Dthumbnail%26cb_client%3Dmaps_sv.tactile.gps%26thumb%3D2%26w%3D203%26h%3D100%26yaw%3D226.72017%26pitch%3D0%26thumbfov%3D100!7i16384!8i8192&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Amsterdam, Hugo De Grootplein&lt;/a&gt;

 - click for Streetview. The S105 artery crosses right to left. A roundabout is cut in two by tram tracks, and cycle traffic has to be routed through, safely.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/@52.3748806,4.8719663,3a,75y,320.42h,71.83t/data=!3m6!1e1!3m4!1sZiOdE7QjfWPtuvvBtuN1kw!2e0!7i16384!8i8192&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-amsterdam2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/@52.3748806,4.8719663,3a,75y,320.42h,71.83t/data=!3m6!1e1!3m4!1sZiOdE7QjfWPtuvvBtuN1kw!2e0!7i16384!8i8192&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Amsterdam, on S105&lt;/a&gt;

 - click for Streetview. The residential streets around Hugo De Grootplein are narrow. Many of them are one-way, like this one on the right (exit only). Construction of the street makes it very clear what the situation is and who has priority.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/@52.3751321,4.871899,3a,75y,351.18h,64.18t/data=!3m6!1e1!3m4!1s3BSv4KQx7xJJJw7pm-dVmg!2e0!7i16384!8i8192&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-amsterdam3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/@52.3751321,4.871899,3a,75y,351.18h,64.18t/data=!3m6!1e1!3m4!1s3BSv4KQx7xJJJw7pm-dVmg!2e0!7i16384!8i8192&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Amsterdam, inside the one-way street&lt;/a&gt;

 - click for Streetview. The pavement signals that this is a bike-priority lane, in which cars are guests. The direction of car parking indicates that this is a one way street. Parked cars clog the street.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also clear that the cars do not belong here. Elsewhere &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/isotopp/status/1181984858270289920&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;they have been removed&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-2014-2019.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Again, we look to Thomas Schlijper&amp;rsquo;s excellent chronicles to see what happens when you remove cars from the urban environment: You get the city back. People can live.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cities in the Netherlands have room for people, because they made room for people by removing the cars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bike-is-part-of-a-system&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#the-bike-is-part-of-a-system&#34;&gt;
	The Bike is Part of a System
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is very important to have a second, closer look at these bike parks at Train Stations and Bus Stops. They are crucial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am 50+, fit, and have a Pedelec. I have few problems riding 22km from a village near Schiphol to central Amsterdam and back. It takes me around 2h to do that, one hour in each direction. The same amount of time as spent in public transport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the Netherlands build this AAA - All Ages and Abilities. Not everyone can do what I do. So multimodal transport is the rule. You can bike to a train station or bus stop. The design speed is 15 km/h, the design distance is 20min or less - so within 5 km radius you are supposed to be able to jump onto public transport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the OV point, you will find bike parking. Covered at Bus Stops, covered, guarded and often with a bike repair shop in Train Stations. You jump on the &lt;em&gt;Openbaare Vervoer&lt;/em&gt; (OV, Public Transport) using &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OV-chipkaart&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the chipcard&lt;/a&gt;

: All transport in the Netherlands can make their own tariff and zones, but the collection is unified with the Chipcard. That means: One ticket for the entire country, one method of billing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At your destination, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ns.nl/en/door-to-door/ov-fiets/how-it-works.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;OV fiets&lt;/a&gt;

 is likely to be available - there are more than 300 stations all across the country where you can have this. This is a public transport bike that can be rented &lt;em&gt;using the same train ticket&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It costs € 3.85 per 24-hour period to use an OV-fiets. If you keep the OV-fiets for more than 24 hours, you will be charged for an extra rental period (up to 72 hours). After 72 hours, you will incur an additional charge of € 5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not expensive at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting to an OV station by bike means the catchment area of these stations is around 10x larger than on foot. That means the stations can be further apart. That means the Bus or Train has to stop less often. Than means it goes faster, a lot faster actually - especially true for trains. That makes public transport way more attractive. That makes more people use the bike/public transport combo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The public transport in the Netherlands is purposefully designed to enable this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it is well tracked: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ovzoeker.nl/locatie/52.35173:4.67726:14&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Where is my OV?&lt;/a&gt;

 - live tracking for public transport in the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how popular is this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bike-usage.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://government.nl/binaries/government/documents/reports/2018/04/01/cycling-facts-2018/Cycling&amp;#43;facts&amp;#43;2018.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;

 of the Cycling Facts and Figures 2018. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/en/policy/policy-traffic/policy-cycling/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Amsterdam City Cycling Policy&lt;/a&gt;

 has links to the Mobility Plan for 2030 and the Long Term Cycle Plan for the City. All of this illustrates&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this is desired&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this is policy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this is no accident&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this is hard work, stakeholder management, long term planning and urban development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a pretty nifty video &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c1l75QqRR48&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Invisible Bike Infrastructure of the Netherlands&lt;/a&gt;

 by &amp;ldquo;Not Just Bikes&amp;rdquo;, which explains how this came to be and how this is not an accident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the best thing is: This is engineering. That means, it can be reproduced, taught, adjusted and ported into your urban environment. There is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.crow.nl/thema-s/contracteren&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CROW&lt;/a&gt;

, which is the private engineering partner organisation for Dutch city planners. They have documentation in German, English, Dutch and other languages, they have classes and they have people that you can pay to do the work for you - depending on your cities needs and preferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;osha-4-in-german-safe-intersections-discussed&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#osha-4-in-german-safe-intersections-discussed&#34;&gt;
	OSHA #4 in German: Safe intersections discussed
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Germany, there is &amp;ldquo;Darmstadt fährt Rad&amp;rdquo;, which has german languge article series on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.darmstadtfaehrtrad.org/?p=671&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;dutch protected intersections&lt;/a&gt;

, explains how &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.darmstadtfaehrtrad.org/?p=2446&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;protected intersections work&lt;/a&gt;

, and also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.darmstadtfaehrtrad.org/?p=3628&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;refutes&lt;/a&gt;

 the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tagesspiegel.de/berlin/protected-intersections-im-praxistest-unfallforscher-warnt-vor-hollaendischen-kreuzungen-fuer-radfahrer/26071942.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tagesspiegel article&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BicycleDutch has a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7RLqOgAW9wY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;german video&lt;/a&gt;

 explaining how things work in the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vijzelbuurt is changing</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/10/08/vijzelbuurt-is-changing.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 18:11:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/10/08/vijzelbuurt-is-changing.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Back when I was still commuting to work in an office, in the far past, I used to be in the Spaces building in Vijzelgracht in Amsterdam, every day. Mark Wagenbuur of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/bicycledutch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BicycleDutch&lt;/a&gt;

 has been there today, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BicycleDutch/status/1314213038908559361&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BicycleDutch/status/1314213038908559361&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/bicycledutch-tweet.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Amsterdam is changing dramatically. I was in Vijzelstraat for the first time in about 2 years and I was pleasantly surprised! Looked up the old situation in Google StreetView for some before and afters.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also linked to &lt;a href=&#34;https://archief.amsterdam/beeldbank/detail/03429525-d56a-9371-d7ba-d3258ecdc8e3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;an image from the  Stadsarchief&lt;/a&gt;

 where the situation in 1987 is shown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These works are documented on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/projecten&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;City of Amsterdam website&lt;/a&gt;

, which also has a page for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/projecten/vijzelstraat-herinrichting/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Vijzelstraat: herinrichting&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/vijzelstraat-goal.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The desired end state for the space in front of Spaces, Vijzelstraat 66.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The works are part of &lt;a href=&#34;https://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rode_Loper_%28Amsterdam%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Project Rode Loper&lt;/a&gt;

, which is the renewal and redesign of all urban space on top of the new Noord/Zuidlijn, Metro 52, after the completion of the Metro works in 2018. The Vijzelstraat works are the conclusion of this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The City of Amsterdam has a fabulous video channel on Youtube, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCkq8uEQ0rl4NiJnO8mL7y_w&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Het Verkeer&lt;/a&gt;

, which announces and explains all street works and renewal. The Vijzelgracht project of course &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-vu-ExAlzWE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;also has a video&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-vu-ExAlzWE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/vijzelstraat-video.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Video announcing the Vijzelstraat works.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly there are two more projects active that match and extend the Rode Loper in this area:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/projecten/vijzelgrachtgarage/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/10/vijzelgracht-garage.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/projecten/vijzelgrachtgarage/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Vijzelgracht: afbouw Vijzelgrachtgarage&lt;/a&gt;

 - The City is building a paid-for underground parking garage in the space between the metro station Vijzelgracht and the street level. This will provide paid-for parking space for 270 cars, similar to the Parkeergarage Museumskwartier, which is serving Frans-Hals-Buurt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/projecten/vijzelbuurt-parkeerluw/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Vijzelbuurt: parkeerluw&lt;/a&gt;

 - Matching the extremely successful conversion of Frans-Hals-Buurt (around 500m north of Vijzelgracht), free and paid-for on street parking is almost completely removed, freeing up public space for fietsers, pedestrians, playing children and city green. The change will affect two local neighborhoods, Weteringbuurt and Noorderbuurt. The city has &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amsterdam.nl/projecten/vijzelbuurt-parkeerluw/nieuws-vijzelbuurt/ontwerpsessies-weteringbuurt/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;local consultations&lt;/a&gt;

 with the people living there right now.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In which we cycle shopping...</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/02/22/in-which-we-cycle-shopping.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 08:14:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/02/22/in-which-we-cycle-shopping.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the Netherlands. Please excuse me, I need to fetch a few things before I have time for you. I need a few things from Lidl in Hoofddorp, do you want to come with me?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-route.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not far, we are taking the bike for some six kilometres. Also, I&amp;rsquo;m going to show you a trick: Look, Mom! Not riding with the cars, and no lights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Spieringweg&amp;#43;%26&amp;#43;Liniepad,&amp;#43;2141&amp;#43;EB&amp;#43;Vijfhuizen/@52.3462107,4.6716007,20.48z/data=!4m5!3m4!1s0x47c5e60e7d1dfe7d:0x33dd4942d97522d9!8m2!3d52.3462134!4d4.6716484&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-liniepad0.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s follow path and go down Liniepad. Take care, unusual for the Netherlands we don&amp;rsquo;t actually have the right of way when crossing. See the green sign with the circle and the number? This is our route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/@52.3435576,4.6727783,20.48z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-liniepad1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fietspad is a cycle path which is not mandatory to use. In the Netherlands, this often means a cycle path that is running completely separated from any car infrastructure, so no noise, no exhaust fumes and no interaction with car traffic at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/@52.3386639,4.6737899,19.03z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-driemeeren-bridge.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where we are crossing the N205, but for this we have a bridge instead of an intersection and traffic lights. Also note that our bike path has lighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/@52.3341893,4.6747681,18.32z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-driemeeren2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is that car doing on a bike and foot path in the middle of a park? Oh, it&amp;rsquo;s the Toezicht, the park inspection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we follow the bike path, there is in fact an intersection where the Liniepad ends, crosses Ijweg and becomes Geniedijk. Not that you would notice. Also, no traffic lights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/@52.3231814,4.6791906,18.32z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-geniedijk0.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we go on as before. Note that the fietspad is not up to code: It is too small, in need of some minor maintenance and it is the wrong color. We will come back to that, soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-geniedijk1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today it&amp;rsquo;s dry, 10 deg Centigrade, and 5 bft right in our faces. I am thankful for the motor, it&amp;rsquo;s helping quite a bit with the wind. Also, battery on board means no reason to go without lights, ever, basically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/@52.3187838,4.6809613,18.32z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-geniedijk2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This used to be a roadblock for construction. As you can see, it has been removed. Had it not been removed, we would have had to follow the signs - of course, if a fietspad is blocked, there is an alternative route planned and signed before construction begins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/@52.3141836,4.6843711,17.27z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-geniedijk3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only later on our trip we would have seen why there was blockage. This looks like there is going to be a fietspad improvement - wider, and closer up to code than this old road we are on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But first things first:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/@52.3141836,4.6843711,17.27z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-n201.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to cross the N201, and we don&amp;rsquo;t do intersections when other solutions are viable. Remember the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/02/19/how-to-build-a-cycling-environment.html&#34;&gt;hierarchy of mitigations&lt;/a&gt;


from OSHA? We can Isolate (#3), so we don&amp;rsquo;t have to Engineer Controls (#4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same thing happens again at Kruisweg:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-kruisweg.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, an underpass completely takes us out of harms way and there is no traffic light, no intersection and no interaction with car traffic. At &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Geniedijk&amp;#43;%26&amp;#43;Wilsonpad,&amp;#43;2131&amp;#43;BJ&amp;#43;Hoofddorp/@52.3068788,4.6819541,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x47c5e7b2169b7763:0x1903ce7f4d2df711!8m2!3d52.3068788!4d4.6841428&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Geniedijk and Wilsonpad&lt;/a&gt;

 we are leaving our fietspad and turn left into Hoofddorp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See these things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Geniedijk&amp;#43;%26&amp;#43;Wilsonpad,&amp;#43;2131&amp;#43;BJ&amp;#43;Hoofddorp/@52.3068788,4.6819541,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x47c5e7b2169b7763:0x1903ce7f4d2df711!8m2!3d52.3068788!4d4.6841428&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-ramaerstraat.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will find them all over the Netherlands. They are giant underground trash collectors, around 1.5mx1.5mx1.5m. One is for plastic, one is for glass sorted by color, and one is for paper. They have sensors, and when they are close to full, they will signal &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.meerlanden.nl/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Meerlanden&lt;/a&gt;

 and ask for cleanup. A trash compactor truck will pull them up and empty them, put the thing back and take the trash away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ramaer connects to Ter Veenlaan,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Ter&amp;#43;Veenlaan&amp;#43;%26&amp;#43;Ramaerstraat,&amp;#43;2131&amp;#43;BH&amp;#43;Hoofddorp/@52.307515,4.6840549,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x47c5e7ad8e7d0c6f:0x5c0c7f82e9b6c59e!8m2!3d52.307515!4d4.6862436&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-ter-veenlaan.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and while this is a street that carries car traffic, by construction and connection through traffic is discouraged &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summary_execution&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;with extreme prejudice&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Ter&amp;#43;Veenlaan&amp;#43;%26&amp;#43;Eigenhuisstraat,&amp;#43;2131&amp;#43;WL&amp;#43;Hoofddorp/@52.3065383,4.6862245,19z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x47c5e7ade8bf3b8f:0x40533320318d9884!8m2!3d52.3065383!4d4.6867717&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-ter-veenlaan2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The road design as well as access to it makes it very extremely clear that this is an access road for people living here, but it is not a good plan to go through this. Also, parking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-ter-veenlaan3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unexpectedly, &lt;a href=&#34;https://haarlemmermeergemeente.nl/taak/parkeren&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this is quite cheap&lt;/a&gt;

, but Hoofddorp is not Amsterdam and space it not at premium here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ter Veenlan opens into Hoofdweg Westzijde, a bicycle street. While this can be used by cars, all other traffic takes precedence. It&amp;rsquo;s basically a fietspad that cars are allowed to use, carefully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Ter&amp;#43;Veenlaan&amp;#43;%26&amp;#43;Hoofdweg&amp;#43;Westzijde,&amp;#43;2132&amp;#43;DH&amp;#43;Hoofddorp/@52.303865,4.6877628,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x47c5e7aec2789dd3:0xa7fc6d62eeed0c4c!8m2!3d52.303865!4d4.6899515&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-hoofdweg-westzijde.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see from the dead end sign (uitgezonderd fiets and bromfiets), it&amp;rsquo;s also modally filtered. Which means there is some bollard somewhere, blocking car access to prevent through traffic, but which is easily bypassed by bikes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-hoofdweg-westzijde2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, basically it&amp;rsquo;s a road with red asphalt and modal filtering. So where are the cars? On the other side of the canal, over the bridge, on Hoofdweg Oostzijde:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Ter&amp;#43;Veenlaan&amp;#43;%26&amp;#43;Hoofdweg&amp;#43;Oostzijde,&amp;#43;2132&amp;#43;DH&amp;#43;Hoofddorp/@52.3036725,4.6881317,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x47c5e7aec355c851:0xe9426c6a869e23f7!8m2!3d52.3036725!4d4.6903204&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-hoofdweg-ostsijde.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There still is a cycle lane, tho, and this takes us north the few meters to Councourslaan, and into the shopping centre of Hoofddorp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-concourslaan.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a one-way street, for cars, but it&amp;rsquo;s open for bikes in all directions. It is also speed bumped and limited to 30 km/h, so bike and car traffic, what little there is, can mix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We turn left into the pedestrian zone, and cross over to LIDL at Marktplein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-lidl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After shopping, can I invite you to a typical dutch restaurant? :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-febo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yup, they fry all the things. Everything you heard about it is true. Just kidding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On our way back, we are going differently - we are following the signage for the alternate route to circumvent the Geniedijk constructions. While Geniedijk is finished, the signs are still up. They take us to Buitenschot:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Parkeerplaats&amp;#43;Groene&amp;#43;Carr%C3%A9&amp;#43;Zuid&amp;#43;-&amp;#43;Westzijde/@52.313244,4.7009037,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x47c5e783857eec97:0xab8dd27a9710a13c!8m2!3d52.313244!4d4.7028626&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-buitenschot.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the exit, at Pad om de Noord and Ijweg, we find an info sign explaining the bike route network of the area, numbers and routes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/search/pad&amp;#43;om&amp;#43;de&amp;#43;noord&amp;#43;and&amp;#43;ijweg/@52.3245634,4.6799518,19.22z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-ijweg1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To continue we have to follow Ijweg north for a few meters, on an abysmally bad bike path, until we can cross over and enter Plesmanhoek:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Mysteryland&amp;#43;Camping/@52.3272018,4.6820808,18.87z/data=!4m5!3m4!1s0x47c5e64154e12711:0x258aa12f9501a6f0!8m2!3d52.3273953!4d4.6821509&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-ijweg3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time, the wind is not in our face, so we are faster. Quite a lot:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-plesmanhoek1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our fietspad goes through a park that has some kind of agricultural botanical garden, and passes by a playground. We then come back to Liniepad and follow it back over the bridge passing the N205.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The road here is quite interesting, because we have N205, with two lanes per direction, directions separated, and then one additional road labelled &amp;ldquo;R-Net&amp;rdquo;. This is a bus lane, used by the 300 line. It goes every 6 minutes, and is led outside of regular car traffic where possible. The tiny red dot just before the road climbs to cross the N205 itself is one of those buses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/@52.3356459,4.6752882,19.04z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-n205.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time we leave Liniepad early and turn right into the village, coming to Waterlinie:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/@52.3435011,4.6731546,19.41z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-waterlinie1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are crossing Waterlinie. It is very clear who has right of way here. Also, note the ubiquitous presence of WhatsApp. This country runs on WhatsApp. There is no escape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/@52.3435926,4.6743971,19.41z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-waterlinie2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We follow the fietspad on it&amp;rsquo;s way between the Villa&amp;rsquo;s. There is a pedwalk on the right, and a pedwalk on the left, and the fietspad meanders through the middle, where there is not one, but two small outdoor play areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Citadel&amp;#43;14,&amp;#43;2141&amp;#43;MC&amp;#43;Vijfhuizen/@52.3435885,4.6748634,20.23z/data=!4m5!3m4!1s0x47c5e61278a9dd4f:0x8cdddea91d86d152!8m2!3d52.343587!4d4.6747602&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-waterlinie3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how does the owner of a 1.5 Megaeuro Villa get their Tesla to their house, you ask? Well, from the private road access in the back of the houses, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Waterlinie&amp;#43;4,&amp;#43;2141&amp;#43;MA&amp;#43;Vijfhuizen/@52.3447025,4.6766681,19z/data=!4m5!3m4!1s0x47c5e60d71d9c8a5:0xfd38257290a197fd!8m2!3d52.3444133!4d4.6761558&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-waterlinie4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re about to cross the R-Net bus lijn to venture into the not quite as well off part of the village, but wait. There&amp;rsquo;s an ambulance crossing, racing along the buslijn towards the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Spaarne&amp;#43;Hospital&amp;#43;Hoofddorp/@52.3249369,4.6538161,17z/data=!4m5!3m4!1s0x47c5e62615501753:0x3ce45feaaa9c821d!8m2!3d52.324344!4d4.6536074&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Spaarne Gasthuis Hoofddorp&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/search/vijfhuizen&amp;#43;bus&amp;#43;stop/@52.3443078,4.676534,19.63z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-vijfhuizen1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And right behind: The bus. Line 300 is very busy, and hence has special buses. They are three meter longer than what is allowed on European Roads, and require a special permit. Also, roads along their road (eg. in Haarlem) had to be modified in multiple places to allow for increased turn radiuses. But on the other hand, they run every 6 minutes and can carry 186 people, each, from Haarlem via Hoofdorp through Schiphol towards Amsterdam Arena.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-vijfhuizen2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the day bike parking in this tiny village. On the Haarlem side. There is more on the other side. Multimodal transport is a thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-vijfhuizen3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, we&amp;rsquo;re home. Excuse the disorderly garden. Spring is early this year and we have not been keeping up. Still, it&amp;rsquo;s cold and windy. Come in. Espresso or Tea?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/shopping-vijfhuizen4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Under the sea...</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/02/21/under-the-sea.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 13:22:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/02/21/under-the-sea.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the Netherlands.
I am living at the bottom of a lake, 3.50 meters below the sea level, and there are sea shells in my garden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/haarlemmermeer-muschel.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When I dig in my garden, it looks like this.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Netherlands (low lands) or Holland (hollow lands) are formed in large part by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhine%E2%80%93Meuse%E2%80%93Scheldt_delta&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Rhine Delta&lt;/a&gt;

.
This is an estuary delta (tidal delta), which means it is formed as much by erosion as it is formed by sedimentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The erosion is a strong power, and was often seen as a living evil force working against the works of men &amp;ndash; the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterwolf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Waterwolf&lt;/a&gt;

, devouring the land.
The waterwolf often refers specifically to the effect of peaty bogs and costal lake swamps growing and merging lakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/haarlemmermeer-oldmap.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The situation before the lakes merge.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is exactly the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haarlemmermeer#History&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;historic situation of the Haarlemmermeer&lt;/a&gt;

, where you have a peat bog, the relic of a northern arm of the Rhine, and several smaller lakes.Through flooding and erosion these lakes grew into one single large lake between Haarlem, Amsterdam, Amstelveen, Aalsmeer and Leiden.
This was a fast process and happened within 100 years: In 1531 the Haarlemmermeer and the smaller lakes had a combined surface area of 31 square kilometers.
In 1647 the combined Haarlemmermeer had a surface of 150 square kilometers, and within another 100 years it would add another 20 square kilometers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussions about draining the swamp started in 1643, and went on in one way or the other for around 200 years, but the efforts were strongly opposed by several cities for which the lake was an important waterway.
After a &lt;a href=&#34;https://noord-hollandsarchief.nl/partners/haarlemmermeer/geschiedenis-haarlemmermeer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;hurricane in November 1836&lt;/a&gt;

 drove the waters basically to the gates of Amsterdam, and the ever growing Haarlemmermeer was threatening to integrate other low lying lands and lakes into its surface, King Willem I had had enough.
He appointed a royal commission and tasked it with making plans to drain the lake once and for all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early 1840 work was begun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Haarlemmermeer/@52.3239983,4.6148638,12z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x47c5e0cde9ceff8f:0x3bbab97e58eb764b!8m2!3d52.3003784!4d4.6743594&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/haarlemmermeer-map.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Haarlemmermeer is the area of the former lake, as defined by the Ringvaart, plus the area in the north extending it to the Ij&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ringvaart&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ringvaart&lt;/a&gt;

 is a 61 kilometer long ring canal that was being dug with manual labour, defining the shore of the Haarlemmermeer.
Today it defines the border of the Gemeente, mostly, plus some area in the north extending the Gemeente towards the Ij.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/haarlemmermeer-ringvaart.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Ringvaart today, between Cruquius and Vijfhuizen.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The earth removed was used to build a dike around the polder-to-be.
The canal was completed in 1845, and three large steam pump stations were built and started to drain the lake:
Leeghwater aan de Kaag (1845), Lijnden (1848) and Cruquius (1849).
Until 1852, 800 billion litres of water have been pumped away and &amp;ldquo;the fish could be collected by hand&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/haarlemmermeer-cruquius.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Steam Pump in Cruquius (1849) with a James Watt Steam Engine.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today the steam pump in Cruquius is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.haarlemmermeermuseum.nl/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;museum&lt;/a&gt;

.
Entry is 7 EUR (or free, if you have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.museumkaart.nl/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;museumkaart&lt;/a&gt;

).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But of course land that is up to 3.50 below sea level and is in former a peat bog right next to the North Sea is not stable, and needs pumps and active water management around the clock to keep dry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/haarlemmermeer-willemi.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gemaal Koning Willem I&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today that is achieved by the pump station (Gemaal) Willem I, among others.
It is named after the king who initiated the dry pumping of the Haarlemmermeer.
It is much more modern and efficient, but also quite less impressive than the pump in Cruquius.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the image I am standing with my back to the Ringvaart, a bit down from the dikes crest.
The water level of the Ringvaart is approximately at my hip, or somewhere around the second window of the pump station.
The water you can see behind the pump station is the main drainage channel for Haarlemmermeer, and you can see how low it is compared to my position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gemeente Haarlemmermeer is only one of many &lt;a href=&#34;https://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Droogmakerij#Nederlandse_droogmakerijen&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Droogmakerijen&lt;/a&gt;

.
It is a anthropogene cultural landscape, not an uncommon thing in the Netherlands - a quarter of the Netherlands are below sea level, and 65% of the population are living in areas that need to be protected against storm and flood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this also means:
when you look at the landscape, there is nothing natural about it whatsoever.
The natural state of this land is brackish water, 3.50m deep.
It is completely designed and constructed and ongoing human effort is necessary to keep it dry and working.
This is a relationship to nature and &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; that is very different from other parts of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also requires a different mentality, because it needs to maintained at all cost, even in conflict.
It absolutely requires people to cooperate even if they disagree:
The North Sea is an equal opportinity drowner, the Waterwolf does not care if the people it devours agree or disagree about some thing or the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polder_model&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cooperation despite differences&lt;/a&gt;

 has been deeply ingrained into the society in the Netherlands, and affects all forms of conflict handling.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to build a cycling environment</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/02/19/how-to-build-a-cycling-environment.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2020 11:38:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/02/19/how-to-build-a-cycling-environment.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the Netherlands. We&amp;rsquo;re building roads differently. They are better, safer and less stressful for cyclists, and that also makes them better, safer and less stressful for motorists. Here is how it works:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(based on a &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/isotopp/status/1229819834239770624&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Twitter Thread&lt;/a&gt;

)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-does-it-look-like&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#what-does-it-look-like&#34;&gt;
	What does it look like?
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/fiets-drempel.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am living in a village. That means a speed limit of 30 km/h inside the city limits, and that is being enforced by the design of the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The red path is only a subordinate cycle path. On the other side of the canal, to the left, is the real cycle path. The bridge in the background is leading over to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/fiets-drempel2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the background you can see the traffic sign on the right hand side of the road, and the bridge. I am standing on the footpath, the bike path is on the left hand side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s move forward to the bridge:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/fiets-bridge.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mornings this is a very busy spot, because there are two basic schools down the road over the bridge, and of course all the children are biking to school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;School begins the day after the fourth birthday (and groep 1 and 2 is what in germany would be preschool, but it&amp;rsquo;s mandatory) and it can be reasonably expected from children of this age to be able to bike to school under their own power, but supervised. Children of group 3 and over can be expected to bike school unsupervised, and the environment must be built to enable this, and to allow them to roam around the city limits in order to go to sports or visity friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;dynamic-traffic-lights&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#dynamic-traffic-lights&#34;&gt;
	Dynamic traffic lights
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My village is next to the N205. That is a multilane motorway, a national street, an A-road. On the other side is the Schiphol runway &amp;ldquo;Polderbaan&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cycling traffic light in the Netherlands looks like this. The &amp;ldquo;tikker&amp;rdquo; (call button) is only a formality, but good to hold yourself upright on the bike should you ever have to wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/fiets-n205-1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually you don&amp;rsquo;t. That&amp;rsquo;s because of the sensors in the road: Two here (in order to measure direction and speed), and one more directly where the Tikker is. If you are driving the design speed of the cycle path (In the Netherlands that&amp;rsquo;s 15 km/h), and the traffic allows that, you will have green exactly when you are reaching the light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/fiets-n205-2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is because almost all traffic lights around here are dynamically controlled and have variable cycle times. The moment the last car or bike is clearing the crossing the light goes yellow and the waiting time for crossing traffic is shortened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of that under the principle that pedestrians and cyclists have priority over car traffic at all times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/fiets-n205-3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;intersection-design&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#intersection-design&#34;&gt;
	Intersection Design
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly enough: Cycle path design and rules make it possible for a cyclist to turn right at a crossing even when the light is red for motorists. It&amp;rsquo;s in the design of their crossings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&#34;https://bicycledutch.wordpress.com/2012/10/25/cycling-past-red-lights-its-legal-in-the-netherlands/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;article at Bicycle Dutch&lt;/a&gt;

 explains it in detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XpQMgbDJPok&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Youtube Video&lt;/a&gt;

 (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7RLqOgAW9wY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;same in German&lt;/a&gt;

) that shows this in practice and with traffic in motion. It&amp;rsquo;s beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go watch the video. But even then, let me highlight a few things from the video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/fiets-parking-protected-lane.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what is called a parking protected bike lane. The parked cars act as a protective wall against the cars on the street. Where there is room enough there is an exit zone that prevents dooring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, everyone here is being drilled with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dooring#Dutch_Reach&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dutch Reach&lt;/a&gt;

, to the point where you fail your driving test in the last second if you do not exit the car properly after passing the final practical exam otherwise faultlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intersections in the Netherlands are a construct that is full of waiting pockets, staging areas that allow you to stop and wait without being pressured from the traffic behind you, until you are sure it is safe to move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/fiets-pocket.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is true for cyclists. Here waiting cyclists can stop for the red light without being in the way of traffic that is moving straight on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it is even more true for cars. Motorists can handle one task (turning), and then the next one (handling crossing cyclists), avoiding dangerous multitasking and dangers from multiple directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are used to driving in Germany, that is unexpected and initially confusing. Take your time, and take the traffic step by step, it is designed this way. If the traffic designer did their job, there is only one dangerous thing happening at a time, and there is always a safe place to stop and double check. Also, the other drivers are &lt;em&gt;expecting you to stop and take your time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;danger-zone-and-the-importance-of-consistency&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#danger-zone-and-the-importance-of-consistency&#34;&gt;
	Danger Zone and the importance of consistency
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, when driving in the Netherlands you will eventually notice that the main spot to check for dangers is usually 45 degrees to the right over the hood. That is, because whenever space allows it the situation is designed so that you can wait without being pressured from behind, handle one situation at the time, and the situation is coming up at approximately this position from the front-right (or, where traffic makes it necessary, from the front-left).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/fiets-crossing.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here an intersection, also with staging areas. The marked car has passed the cycle path and is now waiting to be able to safely merge, out of the way of the cycle path. A second car is coming up, waiting before the cycle path, making sure there are no cyclists coming and that the staging area is clearing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The design and the marking of the cycle path with continous red color and shark teeth before the crossing make it clear to anyone that the cyclists have the right of way, even if the traffic signs weren&amp;rsquo;t there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raised curbs and patterning make the road visually smaller, encouraging drivers to stay below the speed limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cycle paths are separated from the road, where possible with a soft shoulder and lawn in order to communicate that there is no roadside parking here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The raised curb on the cycle path side also encourages cyclists to stay in the lane and make use of the marked path for crossing. That way separated types of traffic cross only in spots that are designed to make the crossing safely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/fiets-residential-zone.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same design language is applied everywhere, making roads readable to everyone intuitively. Here a car is turning right into a residential area. The curb is raised from street level with a bump and different paving, making it visually and haptically clear to a driver that the environment is changing. There is of course a staging area, so that turning and clearing the cycle path are two different, sequential tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cycle path makes a slight swerve to the right to allow for this. In the video it becomes clear that this does not slow down the cyclist. Again, soft lawn is being used to discourage drivers from shorting the turn and crossing the cycle path at a different angle that a clear 90 degrees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, narrow roads in the Netherlands are a design tool. They make sure traffic types cross at a safe angle so that eye contact can be made, and together with speed bumps and raised curbs they help to keep speed down to safe levels. The design is built specifically so that drivers &lt;em&gt;do not accelerate into a conflict zone&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation is built so that potential conflicts happen the 45 degress-to-the-right-over-the-hood angle that motorists are trained to double and triple check in urban areas, and with the car at rest or close to rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consistent design language helps to make safety habitually automatic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/fiets-urban-roundabout.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roundabouts are safer and faster than intersections, but the same design principles and design language can be applied to this situation as well, even in historic old towns such as Amsterdam shown here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see the familiar Dutch design: Staging area for cars, separating the action of leaving the roundabout and clearing the cycle path. Road marking communicates bike priority. Shark teeth also help to communicate priority. The curb extension and the middle island separating the car lanes both keep the roads visually narrow and encourages drivers to position themselves properly and not cut corners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The danger zone is positioned to the right-front for the car leaving the roundabout, traffic types intersect at 90 degree angle and with the car at rest or almost at rest. For the car entering the roundabout, the danger zone is the left-front, because there is no other option to make this possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hierarchy-of-mitigations&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#hierarchy-of-mitigations&#34;&gt;
	Hierarchy of Mitigations
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, according to the OSHA Hierarchy of Mitigations, none of this is the best solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/fiets-osha-hierarchy.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;OSHA Hierarchy of Mitigations&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;OSHA Hierarchy of Controls&lt;/em&gt; for workplace safety. In german &lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ma%C3%9Fnahmenhierarchie#Ma%C3%9Fnahmenhierarchie_nach_TRBS&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Maßnahmenhierarchie nach TRBS&lt;/a&gt;

. (after an &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/isotopp/status/1169871272735436800&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;older tweet&lt;/a&gt;

)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eliminate:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Remove the cause of danger completely.&lt;/em&gt; A car-free environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Substitute:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Replace the hazardous work practice or machine with an alternative.&lt;/em&gt; Encourage and promote public transport.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Isolate:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Separate the hazard from the people at risk from injury.&lt;/em&gt; Cycle paths are separated from car roads with alternative routing, curbs, underpasses or other means of physical separation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engineer controls:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Physical changes, eg. redesign machine by adding safeguards.&lt;/em&gt; Speed bumps, and physical intersection design reduce risk of collision and injury.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Administrative controls:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Install signs, rotate jobs.&lt;/em&gt; Road signs (&amp;ldquo;Cyclists crossing!&amp;rdquo;, speed limit signs)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PPE (Personal Protective Equipment):&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Provide gloves, earplugs, helmets.&lt;/em&gt; Bike helmets and high viz vests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So while we have been speaking about intersection design, we have been essentially been speaking about level 4 methods from the OSHA hierarchy. Where space allows it, level 3 methods would be better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And again, we can see them in the Dutch road design:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/fiets-separation.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roundabout shown in the video leads the cycle path through underpasses underneath the street, completely separating the car and bicycle traffic. That means no danger of collision, no traffic lights and no wait times for cyclists, ever. A way better solution that any intersection design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video finishes with two children passing an intersection on bikes. Again, we can see the dynamic traffic light control: The moment the second cyclist enters the intersection, the green phase is shortened and the light turns yellow. As soon as the intersection has been cleared, cross traffic can start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/fiets-yellow.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a space intensive design. It works in many historic old towns in the Netherlands, and any design up to code in the US (or Germany) can be converted to a safer Dutch design within the same space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FlApbxLz6pA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;second video&lt;/a&gt;

 (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yCzi1Q4xCTA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;same video in German&lt;/a&gt;

) demonstrates this. This video also reiterates the various design choices shown above, and explains them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;did-you-say-15-kmh&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#did-you-say-15-kmh&#34;&gt;
	Did you say 15 km/h?
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;design&lt;/em&gt; speed for cycle paths in the Netherlands is for an average speed of 15 km/h.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cycle infrastructure is excellent, and you can often and for long stretches read a much higher speed, but there are two core ideas behind the entire network that lead to the 15 km/h design speed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;AAA&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;All Ages and Abilities&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; For a high cycling rates, it is important that anybody can cycle and feels safe doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That leads to a design requirement in which a 4-year-old can cycle to school supervised, and a 6-year-old can cycle to school unsupervised, or an 80-year-old can use the cycle path safely and comfortably on a bike, trike or a suitable electrically assisted personal transport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also leads to the design requirement that two cyclists can ride abreast - parents riding with their children, or just two people riding together and chatting, like they would do in a car. A cycle path that wide (per direction) also enables overtaking, and has sufficient space for transport bikes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key idea is that bike paths are a system for the many, not for the fittest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multimodal Transport&lt;/strong&gt; The bike system in the Netherlands and the public transport (OV) system are designed to work together. The designers envision the bike trip of commuters to be &amp;lt;7.5km (&amp;lt;30m travel time on bike, &amp;lt;20m at 25 km/h), ending at a train station.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Train stations have large covered parking structures (free to use), and often offer additional services (&amp;ldquo;Bike repair while you are away to work&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Sale of small service parts such as inner tubes or LED lights&amp;rdquo;). Haarlem station has a fairly typical station, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=S1xGsDyT4PI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;I made a video&lt;/a&gt;

. Note how the design language of the cycle tracks extends down even to the racks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also usually have NS OV Fiets lending stations. While public transport in the Netherlands is being run by a number of municipal and commercial operators, which are free to set prices and define zones as they see fit, the billing is unified and works via the nationwide OV Chipkaart - all trains, trams, buses and also the rental bikes offered at almost all train stations are being billed via one single card. Getting a rental is as easy as swiping your card, at a price of less than 3.60 EUR per day billed to the OV card.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eltis explains &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eltis.org/discover/case-studies/how-dutch-railway-stations-encourage-multimodality&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;multimodality in Dutch rail&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dutch government provides Cycling Facts (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.government.nl/binaries/government/documents/reports/2018/04/01/cycling-facts-2018/Cycling&amp;#43;facts&amp;#43;2018.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;

).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/fiets-use-nation.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bike use is x2.5 higher in the Netherlands than in Germany, on the average&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2020/02/fiets-use-spatial.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bike use is regionally different, and in some zones the usage quota is more than 50% of all trips shorter than 7.5km&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-sources-in-german-language&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#other-sources-in-german-language&#34;&gt;
	Other Sources (in german language)
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for a more in depth discussion of all of this in german language, have a look at Wunderlösung Schutzkreuzung? by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.darmstadtfaehrtrad.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Darmstadt fährt Rad&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.darmstadtfaehrtrad.org/?p=2446&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Die Schutzkreuzung, Teil 1&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.darmstadtfaehrtrad.org/?p=2594&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Die Schutzkreuzung, Teil 2&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be sure to also check out the detailed background references in the footers of the articles, and the details &amp;ldquo;view from the car&amp;rdquo; addenda in Teil 2, which show deadzones of cars and lorries in detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also at &amp;ldquo;Darmstadt fährt Rad&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.darmstadtfaehrtrad.org/?p=671&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kreuzung Deluxe 1: Einleitung&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.darmstadtfaehrtrad.org/?p=961&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kreuzung Deluxe 2: Designelemente&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.darmstadtfaehrtrad.org/?p=1070&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kreuzung Deluxe 3: Funktion&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.darmstadtfaehrtrad.org/?p=1279&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kreuzung Deluxe 4: Fallbeispiele&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.darmstadtfaehrtrad.org/?p=1787&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kreuzung Deluxe 5: Neugestaltung einer deutschen Kreuzung&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.darmstadtfaehrtrad.org/?p=1938&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kreuzung Deluxe 6: Neugestaltung einer großen deutschen Kreuzung&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These articles are a treasure trove of traffic design information in german language, and again are backed by a wealth of illustrations and linked sources.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shared Space Experiment at Alexanderplein</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/09/27/shared-space-experiment-at-alexanderplein.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2017 16:44:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/09/27/shared-space-experiment-at-alexanderplein.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/bike-blog/2017/sep/22/what-happens-if-you-turn-off-the-traffic-lights&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/09/alexanderplein-640x397.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/bike-blog/2017/sep/22/what-happens-if-you-turn-off-the-traffic-lights&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Shared Space Experiment&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Guardian has
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/bike-blog/2017/sep/22/what-happens-if-you-turn-off-the-traffic-lights&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;an article&lt;/a&gt;


about a Shared Space Experiment at Amsterdam Alexanderplein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shared_space&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Shared Space&lt;/a&gt;

 is an approach
to urban traffic design in which segregation of traffic modes is minimized
and signage or other regulation is taken away, leaving traffic participants
to make up rules and agreements on the spot through interaction. Several
preconditions need to be there in order for Shared Spaces to have a chance
of working:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The general population involved must have a good traffic &lt;strong&gt;education&lt;/strong&gt; :
They must be, at least in principle, capable of handling traffic on their
own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The traffic situation must be designed so that the various participants in
traffic are aware of each other - they must have &lt;strong&gt;visibility&lt;/strong&gt; of each
other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ideally, they should have need to deal with only one problem or danger at
a time - problems need to be &lt;strong&gt;sequential&lt;/strong&gt; , and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;things need to happen at human speed. Traffic needs to be &lt;strong&gt;slow&lt;/strong&gt; and
everybody needs to be comparable in speed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If these things are given, if you take away traffic lights and signage, the
intention of getting people to interact and agree on how to safely proceed -
to &lt;strong&gt;empower&lt;/strong&gt; them - usually works out very favorably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new setup forced people to engage with their surroundings. They had to
change the behavioural rituals they had fallen into in order to adapt.
Instead of relying on traffic lights, they now relied on their own
abilities and the cues of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A paper referenced in the article &lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/1206331210374149&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Negotiation in Motion&lt;/a&gt;


explains what goes on in more depth. The outcome: removing signals from a
busy junction, it made journeys faster and interactions more pleasant. Now
the approach is being copied across the city.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Separate Infrastructure</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/09/08/separate-infrastructure.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 20:31:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/09/08/separate-infrastructure.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/09/separate-infrastructure-640x423.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cargobike mum with child cycling independently on Upper Thames Street.
Unimaginable before cycling infrastructure. &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AsEasyAsRiding/status/905444434288009216&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mark Treasure&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of people in Germany, especially Bike Activists, are stuck in the
80ies, victims of the Kampfradler mentality. Let&amp;rsquo;s have a look at
that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The german word Kampfradler literally is made up from &amp;ldquo;Kampf&amp;rdquo; (fight) and
&amp;ldquo;Radler&amp;rdquo; (cyclist) . A Kampfradler is a fighting cyclist, or confrontational
cyclist. Wikipedia dates the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kampfradler&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kampfradler&lt;/a&gt;

 to 2011, but it&amp;rsquo;s
much older. I remember having used the term during my time as a student in
Kiel, and that would date it to the mid-90ies at least. The Wikipedia
article also puts it into the context of a bike rowdy, but it&amp;rsquo;s really older
and it&amp;rsquo;s also being used by the Kampfradlers themselves with much more
positive connotations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cyclists are being marginalised in many places in Germany, and it takes
personal courage to be a presence in a car-centric traffic design and to
reclaim the road. Roads designed for cars often leave cyclists no way to
drive legal and safe at the same time. Kampfradler &amp;ldquo;know&amp;rdquo; that bike paths
are multiple times more deadly than painted bike lanes on the road, claiming
that bike paths hide cyclists until they suddenly appear when crossing a
road, and the way this stuff is being constructed in Germany it is true that
visibility of cyclists is suboptimal and often outright dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/09/altec-basic-28-inch-omafiets-zwart-52cm_1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Omafiets is being used by everyone, Omas as well as Jongens or
businessmen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a German living in the Netherlands, I have a direct comparison between
bike paths constructed for example in Kiel, in Berlin and in places like
urban and historic Amsterdam and rural, recently built Vijfhuizen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of observations to be made:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;casual-and-everyday&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#casual-and-everyday&#34;&gt;
	Casual and everyday
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biking in the Netherlands means casual biking at casual speeds. The goal
is to move swiftly, but relaxed. The Omafiets lets you sit upright, with
handlebars that curve gently towards you like the wings of a swallow -
unless you get wind from the front, in which case you might put the lower
arms onto the handlebars to have a lower and more aerodynamic profile. The
Objective is to move, but not to sweat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;all-ages-and-abilities-aaa&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#all-ages-and-abilities-aaa&#34;&gt;
	All Ages and Abilities (AAA)
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bike paths in the Netherlands are being built for everyone. That not only
includes, but specifically means weak participants in traffic - elderly
people as well as very young children. The image at the top of this
article is not from the Netherlands, but might have been shot around here
as well. The thinking expressed in the tweet coming with the image is also
fitting for the Netherlands. A situation like in this image will simply
never happen with bike lanes that are painted on a street - it is a thing
that only happens with separated biking infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;segration---paint-is-never-enough&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#segration---paint-is-never-enough&#34;&gt;
	Segration - paint is never enough
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biking infrastructure is not just separated bike paths. It also includes
ways of crossing roads in a safe way. A lot has been learned about this in
the last 25 years - see
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/03/13/we-learned-a-few-things-about-cycle-path-design-in-the-last-25-years.html&#34;&gt;this article in my blog&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally, a bike path crosses the road on a bridge
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/maps/qS68d34Edop&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;N205 near Vijfhuizen&lt;/a&gt;

) or in a tunnel
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/maps/FUUVBsc14V92&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;N205 near Vijfhuizen&lt;/a&gt;

), so that cyclists and cars
cannot even conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When bikes and cars share a road without any kind of separation, car traffic
is limited to 30 km/h. Usually not just by signage, but also using physical
limitations, such as drempels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roundabouts are being used more a lot, compared to Germany and they can be
an awesome tool control car traffic speed, simplify intersections and keep
traffic flowing in residential areas. &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/maps/c2Sjn3s84xq&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;A small roundabout in
Vijfhuizen&lt;/a&gt;

 shows the red bikepath leaving
the road, crossing at the side of the roundabout and the continuing again
directly on the road. This solution is less than ideal, but safe enough at
the local traffic density and speed to be mastered by a 7 year old on a bike
alone, safely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/maps/VhmPazGRoJA2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This roundabout in Amsterdam&lt;/a&gt;

 is very
busy and crosses a tram line, two major inner city roads and quite some
bit of bike traffic on the same floor level. Building the bike path as a
road, wide and with two directions, next to a road, makes biking more
comfortable, also also simplifies leading traffic across intersections and
does not even necessarily use more space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example can be seen &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/maps/VhmPazGRoJA2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here next to Haarlem&lt;/a&gt;

,
leaving for the Dunes. They also
make other &amp;ldquo;typical&amp;rdquo; problems that Kampfradler experience immaterial -
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dooring&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;dooring&lt;/a&gt;

 does not exist in bike
infra built this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More examples in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/09/06/world/europe/bicycling-utrecht-dutch-love-bikes-worlds-largest-bike-parking-garages.html?smid=tw-share&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;


about cycling infrastructure (also parking!) from Utrecht - a city with a
historic city center that has built itself into one of the most bike
friendly environments in the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How many chargers are necessary to convert the Netherlands to electric cars?</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/09/04/how-many-chargers-are-necessary-to-convert-the-netherlands-to-electric-cars.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2017 21:51:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/09/04/how-many-chargers-are-necessary-to-convert-the-netherlands-to-electric-cars.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pepijnvloemans.wordpress.com/2017/07/08/charging-infrastructure/amp/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt;

 is the question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How much infrastructure do we need when ALL 8 million vehicles
(and buses and trucks!) in the Netherlands go electric? The
answer will surprise you: we could get to 100% electric
transportation in the Netherlands, just by converting the 4000
existing gast stations to fast charging stations which have an
average of 14 fast chargers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;article then plays with numbers a bit: Kilometers driven,
electricity used, number of chargepoints, charging rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(for germans: The Netherlands compare in area and population
pretty well to Nordrhein-Westfalen)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The bike as a feeder system to the train system</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/04/29/the-bike-as-a-feeder-system-to-the-train-system.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2017 10:36:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/04/29/the-bike-as-a-feeder-system-to-the-train-system.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A talk by Marco te Brömmelstroet and others about how neither the Bike nor
the train themselves are a viable transport alternative, but how they
together are much more than the sum of their parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://cyclingacademics.blogspot.nl/2015/03/nine-arguments-for-seeing-bicycle-train.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/04/Bildschirmfoto-2017-04-29-um-11.30.40.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://cyclingacademics.blogspot.nl/2015/03/nine-arguments-for-seeing-bicycle-train.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nine Arguments for seeing bicycle-train as one mobility system&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biking increases the catchment area of train stations, allowing
an increase of the distance between stops for stop-trains, and consequently
also for all higher-order trains. This speeds up the train system, making it
a lot more attractive and a lot more viable. Both bike-use and train-use
increase, making the high-density urban environment more liveable and
attractive as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BrentToderian/status/858118219348848640&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/04/helstraat-1978.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Helstraat, Amsterdam, 1978&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BrentToderian/status/858118219348848640&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/04/helstraat-2015.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same place, 40 years later (2015, so it&amp;rsquo;s 37 years really)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strong weak ties</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/04/05/strong-weak-ties.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2017 11:42:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/04/05/strong-weak-ties.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A long time ago, I wrote a text on the German Blog and on Carta:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carta.info/41830/wieso-wir-uns-veroffentlichen/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wieso wir uns veröffentlichen&lt;/a&gt;


(Why we publish ourselves).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the middle of a discussion about privacy I was explaining why people
publish themselves, why they publicly reveal (sometimes intimate) facts
about themselves. They are doing this, I wrote, to find other like-minded
people, to become searchable and to become approachable, to build trust.
Trust is a wonderful thing. It is the powerful assumption that most people
most of the time want to help you and that falsely trying out to trust
people is a recoverable mistake. Having trust and being in a trustworthy
environment keeps transactional costs low and makes cooperation possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s rewarding and awesome. How does this work in practice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So tomorrow there is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.messefrankfurt.com/frankfurt/en/besucher/welcome/messeveranstaltungen/messen/entertainment-media-creation/prolight_sound2017.html?nc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pro Light and Sound in Frankfurt&lt;/a&gt;

.
Sammy wants to go there, and gets the combination ticket. That&amp;rsquo;s admission
to the trade show, plus a ticket for German rail. That ticket is being
delivered as a Bahn Tix code, which you can
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ypxepZLxff8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;punch into any German ticket machine&lt;/a&gt;


and get a printout. We are in the Netherlands. The next ticket machine is in
Venlo. The route she&amp;rsquo;s going to use does not pass Venlo. There is
&lt;a href=&#34;http://praxistipps.chip.de/bahntix-online-ausdrucken-geht-das_44999&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;no way to get Bahn Tix online&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am asking on Google plus for help, and because I know at least one person
following me is a Train Driver I mention them into the thread. Sammy, me and
that person get into a Hangout. Ticket is being picked up and given the
train driver of ICE 220 FFM -&amp;gt; Amsterdam Centraal. Shift change at the
border, ticket travels on to Amsterdam, +30 platform change 7b -&amp;gt; 2.
Printed Ticket is being successfully delivered from the engine to Sammy at
11:58.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a direct application of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interpersonal_ties&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Interpersonal Ties&lt;/a&gt;


theory (pointing to article by
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sociology.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/publications/the_strength_of_weak_ties_and_exch_w-gans.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Granovetter&lt;/a&gt;


(1973) and in a way to the works of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Ultrasociety-Years-Humans-Greatest-Cooperators/dp/0996139516&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Peter Turchin&lt;/a&gt;

.
High trust societies are societies where people have
&lt;a href=&#34;http://changingminds.org/explanations/theories/weak_ties.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;many weak ties&lt;/a&gt;

,
that can be strengthened as demand arises. It&amp;rsquo;s these strong weak ties that
enable (inter-) action and where cooperation wins between people are
highest. In order to have strong weak ties, a society needs to have a
relatively low and controlled wealth difference
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gini_coefficient&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gini coefficient&lt;/a&gt;

) and a
working judicial system and low corruption. This creates social cohesion,
and enables &amp;ldquo;random&amp;rdquo; cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, you win friends. Looking forward to a visit, soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

