<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>netherlands on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>/tags/netherlands.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in netherlands on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/netherlands/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Safe Biking: It&#39;s not the right of way that&#39;s wrong</title>
      <link>/2020/10/22/safe-biking-its-not-the-right-of-way-thats-wrong.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/22/safe-biking-its-not-the-right-of-way-thats-wrong.html</guid>
      <description>Sven Geggus trolled me . A bunch of nerds were speaking about what&amp;rsquo;s wrong with biking in Germany, and he wrote:
 Tweet : Der @isotopp wohnt doch in Holland. Wo sind denn bei euch die Vorfahrtsregeln anders und könnte man da was sinnvoll für .de übernehmen? &amp;ndash; @isotopp is living in the Netherlands. So how is the right of way different and how could .de learn from this?
Biking in the Netherlands does not suck, and that is not because of any specific traffic rules being any different, but because traffic is fundamentally different, and that somehow escalated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vijzelbuurt is changing</title>
      <link>/2020/10/08/vijzelbuurt-is-changing.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/08/vijzelbuurt-is-changing.html</guid>
      <description>Back when I was still commuting to work in an office, in the far past, I used to be in the Spaces building in Vijzelgracht in Amsterdam, every day. Mark Wagenbuur of BicycleDutch has been there today, and tweeted :
 Amsterdam is changing dramatically. I was in Vijzelstraat for the first time in about 2 years and I was pleasantly surprised! Looked up the old situation in Google StreetView for some before and afters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In which we cycle shopping...</title>
      <link>/2020/02/22/in-which-we-cycle-shopping.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/22/in-which-we-cycle-shopping.html</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the Netherlands. Please excuse me, I need to fetch a few things before I have time for you. I need a few things from Lidl in Hoofddorp, do you want to come with me?
It&amp;rsquo;s not far, we are taking the bike for some six kilometres. Also, I&amp;rsquo;m going to show you a trick: Look, Mom! Not riding with the cars, and no lights.
 Let&amp;rsquo;s follow path and go down Liniepad.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Under the sea...</title>
      <link>/2020/02/21/under-the-sea.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/21/under-the-sea.html</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the Netherlands. I am living at the bottom of a lake, 3.50 meters below the sea level, and there are sea shells in my garden.
When I dig in my garden, it looks like this.
The Netherlands (low lands) or Holland (hollow lands) are formed in large part by the Rhine Delta . This is an estuary delta (tidal delta), which means it is formed as much by erosion as it is formed by sedimentation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to build a cycling environment</title>
      <link>/2020/02/19/how-to-build-a-cycling-environment.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/19/how-to-build-a-cycling-environment.html</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the Netherlands. We&amp;rsquo;re building roads differently. They are better, safer and less stressful for cyclists, and that also makes them better, safer and less stressful for motorists. Here is how it works:
(based on a Twitter Thread )
What does it look like?   I am living in a village. That means a speed limit of 30 km/h inside the city limits, and that is being enforced by the design of the road.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shared Space Experiment at Alexanderplein</title>
      <link>/2017/09/27/shared-space-experiment-at-alexanderplein.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/09/27/shared-space-experiment-at-alexanderplein.html</guid>
      <description>Shared Space Experiment The Guardian has an article about a Shared Space Experiment at Amsterdam Alexanderplein.
A Shared Space is an approach to urban traffic design in which segregation of traffic modes is minimized and signage or other regulation is taken away, leaving traffic participants to make up rules and agreements on the spot through interaction. Several preconditions need to be there in order for Shared Spaces to have a chance of working:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Separate Infrastructure</title>
      <link>/2017/09/08/separate-infrastructure.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/09/08/separate-infrastructure.html</guid>
      <description>Cargobike mum with child cycling independently on Upper Thames Street. Unimaginable before cycling infrastructure. &amp;ndash; Mark Treasure A lot of people in Germany, especially Bike Activists, are stuck in the 80ies, victims of the Kampfradler mentality. Let&amp;rsquo;s have a look at that:
The german word Kampfradler literally is made up from &amp;ldquo;Kampf&amp;rdquo; (fight) and &amp;ldquo;Radler&amp;rdquo; (cyclist) . A Kampfradler is a fighting cyclist, or confrontational cyclist. Wikipedia dates the Kampfradler to 2011, but it&amp;rsquo;s much older.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How many chargers are necessary to convert the Netherlands to electric cars?</title>
      <link>/2017/09/04/how-many-chargers-are-necessary-to-convert-the-netherlands-to-electric-cars.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/09/04/how-many-chargers-are-necessary-to-convert-the-netherlands-to-electric-cars.html</guid>
      <description>Here is the question:
 How much infrastructure do we need when ALL 8 million vehicles (and buses and trucks!) in the Netherlands go electric? The answer will surprise you: we could get to 100% electric transportation in the Netherlands, just by converting the 4000 existing gast stations to fast charging stations which have an average of 14 fast chargers.
 article then plays with numbers a bit: Kilometers driven, electricity used, number of chargepoints, charging rates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The bike as a feeder system to the train system</title>
      <link>/2017/04/29/the-bike-as-a-feeder-system-to-the-train-system.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/29/the-bike-as-a-feeder-system-to-the-train-system.html</guid>
      <description>A talk by Marco te Brömmelstroet and others about how neither the Bike nor the train themselves are a viable transport alternative, but how they together are much more than the sum of their parts:
 Nine Arguments for seeing bicycle-train as one mobility system Biking increases the catchment area of train stations, allowing an increase of the distance between stops for stop-trains, and consequently also for all higher-order trains. This speeds up the train system, making it a lot more attractive and a lot more viable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strong weak ties</title>
      <link>/2017/04/05/strong-weak-ties.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/05/strong-weak-ties.html</guid>
      <description>A long time ago, I wrote a text on the German Blog and on Carta: Wieso wir uns veröffentlichen (Why we publish ourselves).
In the middle of a discussion about privacy I was explaining why people publish themselves, why they publicly reveal (sometimes intimate) facts about themselves. They are doing this, I wrote, to find other like-minded people, to become searchable and to become approachable, to build trust. Trust is a wonderful thing.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
