<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>advertising on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/advertising.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in advertising on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2021 16:46:21 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/advertising/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>So what is the state of the Ads mess?</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/10/13/so-what-is-the-state-of-the-ads-mess.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 12:36:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/10/13/so-what-is-the-state-of-the-ads-mess.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ads on the web have many problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ad selection criteria have been abused for dissemination of propaganda,
for targeted malware attacks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Content sites have basically lost the control over what kind of stuff they
deliver through the ad-space on their site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tracking is increasingly a concern for users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ads bloat sites, slow down page display times and mess with peoples mobile
data plans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ads use power and create heat in devices with a tight power budgets
(basically, anything that runs on a battery and has no fans, phones,
tablets, laptops).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ads play unwanted video and audio, open layers and windows, popovers and
popunders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ads destroy usability and layout on content sites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The market is collapsing: basically nobody is running a browser without an
adblocker any more, and those that don&amp;rsquo;t adblock in their minds -
clickthrough rates are nonexistent. So when everything is on fire, is there
a unified group of stakeholders - content sites, browser makers, ad-industry
leaders - at work to make things &amp;ldquo;better&amp;rdquo; or at least fix their broken
non-business?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, no. &lt;a href=&#34;https://marketingland.com/industry-groups-self-regulatory-program-coalition-for-better-ads-226109&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Says Marketingland&lt;/a&gt;


in their article,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Association_of_National_Advertisers&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ANA&lt;/a&gt;

,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Association_of_Advertising_Agencies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;4As&lt;/a&gt;


and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interactive_Advertising_Bureau&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IAB&lt;/a&gt;

 want
to talk to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.betterads.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CAB&lt;/a&gt;

 about their Better Ads program,
but request being exempt from Chrome&amp;rsquo;s coming integral Adblock feature in
exchange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Mozilla and Safari are not part of CAB, and have little interest in
joining, and also put a different focus on how to handle things: Safari
tries to address tracking with their new
&lt;a href=&#34;https://marketingland.com/apple-safari-intelligent-ad-tracking-what-we-know-216865&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tracking Prevention&lt;/a&gt;

,
and it&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;a href=&#34;https://martechtoday.com/digital-advertising-industry-responds-apple-intelligent-tracking-prevention-204141&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;good enough to be widely hated&lt;/a&gt;

.
Other initiatives such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Do_Not_Track&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;DNT&lt;/a&gt;


were a failure - not because of a lack of interest on the user side, but
because advertisers and sites were boycotting it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google SVP of Ads and
Commerce Sridhar Ramaswamy said, “Our hope is once this is in place, there’s
no need for ad blocking on mobile.” On the other hand, things like &lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.puzzlingapps.spelling.nl.free&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
Brainy Ape Apps&lt;/a&gt;


play uninterruptible video ads for Free-To-Play (&amp;ldquo;Pay To Win&amp;rdquo;) apps with
install buttons in the middle of educational games targeted age 4-10.
Ramaswamy clearly is a very optimistic person. And as long as the
Advertisers and their channels do not realize the depth of the shit they are
in it still has to get worse before it can become better.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Malvertising - we have only seen the beginning</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/03/21/malvertising-we-have-only-seen-the-beginning.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 10:50:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/03/21/malvertising-we-have-only-seen-the-beginning.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://netzpolitik.org/2017/interview-ueber-adblocker-und-das-wohlergehen-der-schadsoftware-branche-das-problem-malvertising-nicht-aussitzen/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Netzpolitik.org has an article&lt;/a&gt;


(in German) in which they are interviewing IT-Security Consultant Thorsten
Schröder on Adblockers, wasted capped mobile bandwidth and Malvertising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;netzpolitik.org&lt;/strong&gt; : Neben dem Schutz vor Malware, welche weiteren Gründe
für die Nutzung von Adblockern findest Du wichtig?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thorsten Schröder&lt;/strong&gt; : Wenn wir als Malware all das klassifizieren, was
Nutzer ausspioniert, täuscht, kompromittiert oder finanziell schädigt,
haben wir im Grunde schon mal eine ganze Reihe an Gründen abgehakt. Nutzer
müssen die Möglichkeit haben, selbstbestimmt das Schutzniveau ihres
Computers bestimmen zu dürfen. Hat die Bundesregierung vielleicht mal das
Bundesamt für Sicherheit in der Informationstechnik (BSI) gefragt? Es wäre
eine gute Gelegenheit für das BSI, zu zeigen, was es drauf hat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;»netzpolitik.org: Besides the protection against malware, what other reasons
for using Adblockers are important to you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thorsten Schröder: If we classify things as malware which spy on users,
deceive them, compromise them or harm them financially, we have in principle
covered all reasons. Users you have the right to determine the level of
protection their computers need. Did our administration ask their Bundesamt
für Sicherheit in der Informationstechnik (BSI)? It would be a good
opportunity for the BSI to show what they can do.«&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article goes on to discuss numbers and percentages. That is actually not
helpful. The numbers stated are by construction too low, and that can not be
helped. Also, the numbers are ultimately irrelevant, because Malvertisements
are not distributed randomly and evenly. The point being that Ad-Networks
generate their value not only from the raw number of eyeballs reached, but
quite a lot comes from being able to reach the right kind of eyeballs. The
better the Ad-Network, the better their targetting. 10.000 drive-by
impressions are worth quite a lot more when I can make sure that all 10.000
of them hit explotable XP/MSIE 6 combos, even if the relative number of
installations left in world with these characteristics is quite low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And 10.000 impressions for ads containing this or that scam are worth a lot
more, when I can select an audience for these 10.000 expressions that is
badly educated, old or otherwise wrangling to stay on top of this Internet
thing and thus more likely to fall for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Targeted advertising and Malware Distribution are a match made in hell, they
amplify each other synergetically. This is an effect we need to push more to
the front of this discussion. Content Sites are responsible for the ads
integrated into their content and shown &amp;ldquo;as their own&amp;rdquo;. Ad Networks are
responsible for the way the selectors they offer are being used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The German construct of Störerhaftung works in all directions, not just
against private Wi-Fi offerings.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

