<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Advertising on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/advertising/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Advertising on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</managingEditor>

    
    <webMaster>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</webMaster>

    
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 15:14:57 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/advertising/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Recommended</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2025/06/04/recommended/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 04:05:06 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2025/06/04/recommended/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.europesays.com/uk/156725/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;France forces TikTok to ban #SkinnyTok but harmful content still persists&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under pressure from the French government, TikTok has banned the hashtag #SkinnyTok,
a controversial trend linked to the glorification of extreme thinness and unhealthy weight-loss advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tiktok bans many words and tags.
People notice and work around it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Babbel: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.babbel.com/en/magazine/tiktok-language&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;How Censorship Is Creating A New TikTok Language&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From here, people will always find ways to use language that allows them to get around auto-censorship.
Whether anyone will be saying “cornucopia” or “nip nops” a decade from now is anyone’s guess,
though it’s probably unlikely.
Still, certain terms could stand the test of time if they fill a specific need.
If social media companies keep cracking down, however, the terminology will continue to evolve.
No matter what the barrier to communication put in place is,
language (and the people who use it) will find a way through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In face, language matters even less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LLMs encode the meanings of terms as vectors along many semantic dimensions in a semantic space (&amp;ldquo;latent space&amp;rdquo;).
A concept, then, is a position in that space with a certain diameter — a kind of fuzziness or vagueness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I type something into ChatGPT or a recommender system, the input is broken down into tokens,
and these tokens are mapped to such vectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I want pizza” becomes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;I&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;want&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;pizza&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;.&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The tokens are then internally mapped to embeddings, vectors that encode meaning.
So this happens:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;cat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;”&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;→&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;0.24&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;0.58&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;dog&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;”&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;→&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;0.22&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.09&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;0.60&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;That is, a list of numbers (often normalized between -1 and 1).
But usually there are far more dimensions than shown here — an embedding typically has thousands of dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latent space — the semantic space, what things mean — is self-organizing.
That happens during training.
We don’t know what each dimension in the space represents,
but to the LLM it&amp;rsquo;s how it stores things, their meaning and their relation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The encoding has some kind of meaning.
We can check that:
When we look at the vectors for &amp;ldquo;man&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;woman&amp;rdquo;
and for &amp;ldquo;king&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;queen&amp;rdquo;,
we can substract &amp;ldquo;man&amp;rdquo; from &amp;ldquo;woman&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;king&amp;rdquo; from &amp;ldquo;queen&amp;rdquo;
and compare the difference vectors.
They are almost, but not quite the same –
because the difference between these words to us is almost, but not quite the same, in meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LLMs use these embeddings and their internal model to “compute the next output token.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommender systems use such embeddings to compare vectors
and find things that are similar to the thing we already have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So a recommender learns everything that’s relevant to a user,
and a modern recommender represents the user through a collection of vectors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;This user is interested in travel, digital policy, databases, bikes.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These concepts may have other concepts nearby concepts in latent space.
To the model this means they are conceptually related.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A modern recommender separates a user’s various interests into distinct areas
and can decide what the user is interested in right now —
meaning,
which of the various user interests is currently active.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A modern recommender will also deliberately serve content that almost — but not quite —
matches the user’s interests, to test how wide the bubble is around the center of that interest vector.
The recommender will watch carefully to see what kind of response that triggers —
refining its recommendations based on that feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A modern recommender will also know where the available content clusters are,
and prioritize content that is both relevant to the user and performs well or has current production capacity.
In other words, where user interest and available content overlap well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(“Pomodoro”, or “method shift” in educational theory) and attempt to shift the theme —
to test whether another known interest can be reactivated.
If that works, the recommender may manage to keep the user active for a longer time,
exposing them to more ads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s how TikTok works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can ban a hashtag on TikTok (&lt;code&gt;#skinnytok&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as you browse categories like “model,” “weight loss”, “fitness”, &amp;ldquo;thigh gap&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;visible collarbone&amp;rdquo;,
and the end result will be the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actual language, the meaning,
is encoded in the tokens of the latent space of the model, not in the words that are used
(or prohibited).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the content density in the models coordinate system will gently push things into certain clusters.
If you feed the system with the right interests, you will always drift – relatively quickly even –
into the same neighborhood and then learn their current slang to get there with a single word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter what the word actually is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar example, using GenAI instead of a recommender:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Draw a superheroine, an Amazon warrior that can fly and deflect bullets,
running over a battlefield in the first world war.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These 21 words do not say &amp;ldquo;Wonder Woman&amp;rdquo;, they do not even go near comics, DC, or similar things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet they draw a thousand-dimensional hyberbubble in latent space, the totality of knowledge known to ChatGPT,
and the end result leaves just one choice – produce this blatant copyright violation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;2025/06/recommender-01.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can trigger content with intent, not even going near the keywords that would be associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how jailbreaks work in LLMs, and that is also how you jailbreak Tiktok bans.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sell your users, or sell to your users</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/03/25/sell-to-users/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2019 09:12:34 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/03/25/sell-to-users/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a big change currently happening in the industry, and it is what drives and enables Facebooks &amp;ldquo;pivot to privacy&amp;rdquo; at the moment.
It&amp;rsquo;s less the public criticism of their methods, that&amp;rsquo;s just a justification, it&amp;rsquo;s more a broader shift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of people misunderstand what&amp;rsquo;s going on: &lt;a href=&#34;http://theconversation.com/facebooks-pivot-is-less-about-privacy-and-more-about-profits-113144&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt; Facebook’s ‘pivot’ is less about privacy and more about profits&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A plan to integrate the technical infrastructure of WhatsApp and Messenger with Instagram would allow users to seamlessly communicate across three platforms for the first time.
More importantly for Zuckerberg, though, it would link billions of detailed Facebook accounts with WhatsApp users – opening stockpiles of data to mine for advertisers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s nice for current Facebook, but not actually the point.
The actual point is more here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theverge.com/2019/3/19/18271840/instagram-checkout-shopping-facebook-business&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Instagram adds in-app checkout as part of its big push into shopping&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instagram took its next step to becoming a full-fledged commerce business today, announcing that it is bringing a checkout feature to its mobile apps.
With checkout, you can store your payment information with Instagram to make purchases more quickly.
In return, Instagram is charging retailers a selling fee.
More than 20 brands will use checkout to start, including Nike, Adidas, Dior, H&amp;amp;M, MAC Cosmetics, Michael Kors, Oscar de la Renta, Prada, Uniqlo, Warby Parker, and Zara.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same thing happens at Google, Google Maps in this case, and in the customary bungled, half-assed way that is so characteristically socially inept Google: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hotelminder.com/google-maps-for-your-hotel-all-you-need-to-know&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Maps for your hotel: All you need to know!&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Book on Google is an option from your Google Hotel Ads account (at no additional cost).
It allows your hotel to have a direct “booking button” which appears on the Google profile from the search results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies that actually care about the model, because their entire business depends on getting it right are doing it slightly more engaged.
Witness this analysis of Discord: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1108776370929164288.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ThreadreaderApp&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As is common for start-ups, Discord is free + monetization hasn&amp;rsquo;t been a top priority&amp;hellip; but less common is Discord&amp;rsquo;s aversion to monetizing user data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the thread you will find the various approaches of selling to users and to devs, instead of selling them out, that Discord tried and continues exploring.
It&amp;rsquo;s like a blueprint for Facebook (and especially their Instagram efforts) and for many other &amp;ldquo;social&amp;rdquo; things.
Meanwhile, Google continues to close all the halfway working things they ever had in this realm - Google plus, their collection of failed chat apps and small sharing environments.
Without a structure for people to interact, you will not get access to people and their interactions, and you are outside the recommender system that really matters - their peer network and personal recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If, as a global meta-strategy, you refuse to interact with people like people and through other people, you are ultimately being driven into irrelevance, and no amount of AI compute power will change that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So what is the state of the Ads mess?</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/10/13/so-what-is-the-state-of-the-ads-mess/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 12:36:42 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/10/13/so-what-is-the-state-of-the-ads-mess/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ads on the web have many problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ad selection criteria have been abused for dissemination of propaganda,
for targeted malware attacks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Content sites have basically lost the control over what kind of stuff they
deliver through the ad-space on their site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tracking is increasingly a concern for users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ads bloat sites, slow down page display times and mess with peoples mobile
data plans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ads use power and create heat in devices with a tight power budgets
(basically, anything that runs on a battery and has no fans, phones,
tablets, laptops).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ads play unwanted video and audio, open layers and windows, popovers and
popunders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ads destroy usability and layout on content sites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The market is collapsing: basically nobody is running a browser without an
adblocker any more, and those that don&amp;rsquo;t adblock in their minds -
clickthrough rates are nonexistent. So when everything is on fire, is there
a unified group of stakeholders - content sites, browser makers, ad-industry
leaders - at work to make things &amp;ldquo;better&amp;rdquo; or at least fix their broken
non-business?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, no. &lt;a href=&#34;https://marketingland.com/industry-groups-self-regulatory-program-coalition-for-better-ads-226109&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Says Marketingland&lt;/a&gt;


in their article,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Association_of_National_Advertisers&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ANA&lt;/a&gt;

,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Association_of_Advertising_Agencies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;4As&lt;/a&gt;


and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interactive_Advertising_Bureau&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IAB&lt;/a&gt;

 want
to talk to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.betterads.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CAB&lt;/a&gt;

 about their Better Ads program,
but request being exempt from Chrome&amp;rsquo;s coming integral Adblock feature in
exchange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Mozilla and Safari are not part of CAB, and have little interest in
joining, and also put a different focus on how to handle things: Safari
tries to address tracking with their new
&lt;a href=&#34;https://marketingland.com/apple-safari-intelligent-ad-tracking-what-we-know-216865&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tracking Prevention&lt;/a&gt;

,
and it&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;a href=&#34;https://martechtoday.com/digital-advertising-industry-responds-apple-intelligent-tracking-prevention-204141&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;good enough to be widely hated&lt;/a&gt;

.
Other initiatives such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Do_Not_Track&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;DNT&lt;/a&gt;


were a failure - not because of a lack of interest on the user side, but
because advertisers and sites were boycotting it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google SVP of Ads and
Commerce Sridhar Ramaswamy said, “Our hope is once this is in place, there’s
no need for ad blocking on mobile.” On the other hand, things like &lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.puzzlingapps.spelling.nl.free&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
Brainy Ape Apps&lt;/a&gt;


play uninterruptible video ads for Free-To-Play (&amp;ldquo;Pay To Win&amp;rdquo;) apps with
install buttons in the middle of educational games targeted age 4-10.
Ramaswamy clearly is a very optimistic person. And as long as the
Advertisers and their channels do not realize the depth of the shit they are
in it still has to get worse before it can become better.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Malvertising - we have only seen the beginning</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/03/21/malvertising-we-have-only-seen-the-beginning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 10:50:16 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/03/21/malvertising-we-have-only-seen-the-beginning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://netzpolitik.org/2017/interview-ueber-adblocker-und-das-wohlergehen-der-schadsoftware-branche-das-problem-malvertising-nicht-aussitzen/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Netzpolitik.org has an article&lt;/a&gt;


(in German) in which they are interviewing IT-Security Consultant Thorsten
Schröder on Adblockers, wasted capped mobile bandwidth and Malvertising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;netzpolitik.org&lt;/strong&gt; : Neben dem Schutz vor Malware, welche weiteren Gründe
für die Nutzung von Adblockern findest Du wichtig?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thorsten Schröder&lt;/strong&gt; : Wenn wir als Malware all das klassifizieren, was
Nutzer ausspioniert, täuscht, kompromittiert oder finanziell schädigt,
haben wir im Grunde schon mal eine ganze Reihe an Gründen abgehakt. Nutzer
müssen die Möglichkeit haben, selbstbestimmt das Schutzniveau ihres
Computers bestimmen zu dürfen. Hat die Bundesregierung vielleicht mal das
Bundesamt für Sicherheit in der Informationstechnik (BSI) gefragt? Es wäre
eine gute Gelegenheit für das BSI, zu zeigen, was es drauf hat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;»netzpolitik.org: Besides the protection against malware, what other reasons
for using Adblockers are important to you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thorsten Schröder: If we classify things as malware which spy on users,
deceive them, compromise them or harm them financially, we have in principle
covered all reasons. Users you have the right to determine the level of
protection their computers need. Did our administration ask their Bundesamt
für Sicherheit in der Informationstechnik (BSI)? It would be a good
opportunity for the BSI to show what they can do.«&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article goes on to discuss numbers and percentages. That is actually not
helpful. The numbers stated are by construction too low, and that can not be
helped. Also, the numbers are ultimately irrelevant, because Malvertisements
are not distributed randomly and evenly. The point being that Ad-Networks
generate their value not only from the raw number of eyeballs reached, but
quite a lot comes from being able to reach the right kind of eyeballs. The
better the Ad-Network, the better their targetting. 10.000 drive-by
impressions are worth quite a lot more when I can make sure that all 10.000
of them hit explotable XP/MSIE 6 combos, even if the relative number of
installations left in world with these characteristics is quite low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And 10.000 impressions for ads containing this or that scam are worth a lot
more, when I can select an audience for these 10.000 expressions that is
badly educated, old or otherwise wrangling to stay on top of this Internet
thing and thus more likely to fall for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Targeted advertising and Malware Distribution are a match made in hell, they
amplify each other synergetically. This is an effect we need to push more to
the front of this discussion. Content Sites are responsible for the ads
integrated into their content and shown &amp;ldquo;as their own&amp;rdquo;. Ad Networks are
responsible for the way the selectors they offer are being used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The German construct of Störerhaftung works in all directions, not just
against private Wi-Fi offerings.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Google verkauft Deine Daten an den Teufel!</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2011/07/14/google-verkauft-deine-daten-an-den-teufel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2011 08:27:41 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2011/07/14/google-verkauft-deine-daten-an-den-teufel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sueddeutsche.de/digital/gespeichterte-nutzerdaten-google-plant-die-super-datenbank-1.1119600&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google plant die Super-Datenbank&lt;/a&gt;


schreibt die SZ,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zeit.de/digital/datenschutz/2011-07/google-ddp-nutzerdaten&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google rückt dem Benutzer noch mal näher&lt;/a&gt;


schreibt die Zeit und
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.fefe.de/?ts=b0e30243&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fefe verlinkt bloß, ohne zu recherchieren&lt;/a&gt;

.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://tarzun.de/archives/366-Google-plant-die-Super-Datenbank.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tarzun hat recherchiert&lt;/a&gt;

,
gelesen und verstanden, und darum brauche ich den Artikel nicht zu schreiben.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stattdessen
&lt;a href=&#34;http://tarzun.de/archives/366-Google-plant-die-Super-Datenbank.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;bei tarzun&lt;/a&gt;


lesen, was wirklich passiert ist und mit dem vergleichen, was unsere
leistungsgeschützten &amp;ldquo;Qualitätsmedien&amp;rdquo; draus machen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Update:&lt;/b&gt; Zum selben Thema ein Dialog im IRC:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A hat mal bei einer Firma angerufen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B&amp;gt; Aha?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A&amp;gt; Die sagten &amp;ldquo;Fuer 50.000 Datensätze echter Personen mit persönlichen Daten
100 EUR&amp;rdquo;. Rechnet man das mal auf Facebooks Profile hoch (750 mio), davon
10% wahrscheinlich Fake, dann wird das plötzlich ganz wenig. Auf jeden Fall
sind 1,5 Mio EUR jetzt nicht gerade die Bombe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B&amp;gt; Google: &amp;ldquo;Wir verdienen mehr Geld damit, Eure Datensätze zu behalten.&amp;rdquo;
meinst Du?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A&amp;gt; Davon kann man nicht mal die Angestellten bezahlen. Ziehst Du 10% ab,
wird&amp;rsquo;s plötzlich ganz uebel. Wobei, nicht /ganz/, aber lachenswert.
&amp;ldquo;Nichtmal anderthalb mio, muahahaha&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A&amp;gt; Ich meine, klar, die koennten das wohl sogar an andere Firmen noch
verkaufen. Und damit halt noch einen Vielfachfaktor einbauen. Aber das
rentiert /nicht mal dann/.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B&amp;gt; Laß es 100mio sein und vergleiche das mit Googles Quartalszahlen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A&amp;gt; LOL, eben. Da fehlen einfach noch ein paar 0en.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;gt; A: Ein Kundenprofil ist so viel Wert wie Du potentiellen Gewinn damit
machen kannst, das ist sehr variabel. Aber Umsatz pro kunde bei Amazon ist
dreistellig im Mittel, bei den anonymen Amazonikern sogar vierstellig. Da
muß man natürlich nun auch auf die Margen sehen, die sind im Einzelhandel
eher dünn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;gt; A: Will sagen: 50k echte Personen sind sehr unspezifisch. Aber 50k
Kundenrecords von High-Volume Voice Kunden aus der E+ datenbank an, sagen
wir T-Mobile verkaufen&amp;hellip; Das ist dann schon sehr substantiell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A&amp;gt; ok. ja.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;gt; A: Oder halt 50k Kundenrecords von BMW Erstwagenkäufern an Mercedes und
Audi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B&amp;gt; I: Aber das ist doch ein Deal, den Google genau einmal machen kann, oder?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;gt; Ja. Ja, das ist vielen Leuten nicht klar. Gehandelte Unternehmen
unterliegen sehr weitgehenden Wirtschafts- und Datenschutzprüfungen, in den
USA wie auch hier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;gt; Schon alleine um die Nachhaltigkeit ihres Geschäftsbetriebes
sicherzustellen. Also im Sinne von &amp;lsquo;ist der Aktienkurs denn auch
gerechtfertigt mit Blick auf die Zukunft&amp;rsquo;. Zudem muß bei Einnahmen ja auch
verbucht werden wofür. Die können sich nicht mal so 100 Mio aus dem Arsch
ziehen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;gt; Das ist aber ein Artikel, den ich schon ganz lange mal schreiben will und
wo ich nie zu gekommen bin, das ist mir einfach zu fachfremd. Also, die
rechtliche und wirtschaftliche Seite, ich habe das nur von der Security
Engineer/Privacy Watchdog Seite von Innen gesehen. Ich bearbeite das Log
hier mal und hau das nach +, warum nicht mal was Kollaboratives versuchen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Die Nachrichtenverlage bringen sich um</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2009/11/17/die-nachrichtenverlage-bringen-sich-um/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Nov 2009 10:58:03 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2009/11/17/die-nachrichtenverlage-bringen-sich-um/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.niemanlab.org/2009/08/can-newspaper-publishers-survive-this-revenue-freefall-perhaps-if-they-embrace-a-digital-future/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Can Newspaper publishers survive this revenue freefall?&lt;/a&gt;

 stellt Martin Langeveld fest, daß in den letzten 50 Jahren der Anteil der gesamten verfügbaren Budgets in der Werbebrance bei ziemlich konstant 2% des Bruttosozialproduktes lag. Jedoch: Die Verteilung der Werbebudgets ist nicht konstant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;newspaper-decline.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Medienanteile am Werbebudget in den letzten 50 Jahren.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Reaktion der Zeitungsverlagsbranche ist nicht eine Modernisierung, sondern der Ruf nach einem Leistungsschutzrecht. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.heise.de/newsticker/meldung/Verlage-rechnen-mit-Gesetzentwurf-fuer-Leistungsschutzrecht-noch-in-diesem-Jahr-861101.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Das werden sie nun bekommen&lt;/a&gt;

, gegen den Rat zahlreicher Expertengutachten. Und obwohl noch unklar ist, wie dieses Recht genau aussieht, ist eines schon klar: Falls es wirksam ist, werden effektiv aufgestellte digitale Medienkonzerne wie Microsoft und Google es eher zu ihren Gunsten nutzen können als regionale Zeitschriftenverlage. Falls es nicht wirksam ist, ist es auch egal. Unausweichlich wird es den Niedergang der traditionellen Nachrichtenredaktionen beschleunigen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; Unterdessen beginnen einige deutsche Buchverlage zu merken, daß es vielleicht nur so untermittelgut ist, wenn sie bei Google in der Buchsuche nicht gefunden werden. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.heise.de/newsticker/meldung/Hoffmann-und-Campe-erwartet-Vorschlaege-von-Google-861040.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hoffmann und Campe erwartet Vorschläge von Google&lt;/a&gt;

 heißt es dann mit der üblichen Holzmedienarroganz, wenn Verlage Angst bekommen, in den nächsten paar Jahren mitsamt ihrem gesamten Programm dem Vergessen anheim zu fallen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; Eine recht gute Erklärung dessen, was wirklich passiert, findet man bei &lt;a href=&#34;http://netzwertig.com/2009/11/08/strukturwandel-die-folgen-der-digitalen-disruption-fuer-die-volkswirtschaft/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Netzwertig: Strukturwandel: Die Folgen der digitalen Disruption für die Volkswirtschaft&lt;/a&gt;

. Die Erklärung dort zeigt, wie spezialisierte Dienste den Mix Zeitung entbündeln und durch Einzeldienste ersetzen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Craigslists entzieht dem Kleinanzeigen-Markt Milliarden. Wikipedia zerstört das Geschäftsmodell von Verlagen in aller Welt. Interpreten mit Web- und Marketing-Kompetenz geben ihren Plattenfirmen den Laufpass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
