<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>advertising on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/advertising.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in advertising on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/advertising/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>So what is the state of the Ads mess?</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/10/13/so-what-is-the-state-of-the-ads-mess.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/10/13/so-what-is-the-state-of-the-ads-mess.html</guid>
      <description>Ads on the web have many problems:
 Ad selection criteria have been abused for dissemination of propaganda, for targeted malware attacks. Content sites have basically lost the control over what kind of stuff they deliver through the ad-space on their site. Tracking is increasingly a concern for users. Ads bloat sites, slow down page display times and mess with peoples mobile data plans. Ads use power and create heat in devices with a tight power budgets (basically, anything that runs on a battery and has no fans, phones, tablets, laptops).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Malvertising - we have only seen the beginning</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/03/21/malvertising-we-have-only-seen-the-beginning.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/03/21/malvertising-we-have-only-seen-the-beginning.html</guid>
      <description>Netzpolitik.org has an article (in German) in which they are interviewing IT-Security Consultant Thorsten Schröder on Adblockers, wasted capped mobile bandwidth and Malvertising.
 netzpolitik.org : Neben dem Schutz vor Malware, welche weiteren Gründe für die Nutzung von Adblockern findest Du wichtig?
Thorsten Schröder : Wenn wir als Malware all das klassifizieren, was Nutzer ausspioniert, täuscht, kompromittiert oder finanziell schädigt, haben wir im Grunde schon mal eine ganze Reihe an Gründen abgehakt.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
