<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>germany on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>/tags/germany.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in germany on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/germany/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Normalitär</title>
      <link>/2020/03/09/normalitaer.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/09/normalitaer.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Normalitär&amp;rdquo;, ein Begriff, der von @beimwort geprägt wurde. Nach einem Twitter Thread . In seinem Artikel auf T-Online propagiert Schaible eine Bruchlinie innerhalb der &amp;ldquo;rechten&amp;rdquo; Parteien, weil Teile der Mitglieder die Weltbildverschiebung der frühen 2000er mitgemacht haben, andere sie ablehnen.
Er beschreibt die Welt von 1990, die Nachwendezeit:
 Vergewaltigung in der Ehe nicht strafbar, Diercke Weltatlas redet von Menschenrassen, unter den 250 Positionen der politischen Elite in Deutschland war nur eine Frau; alles weiße, angeblich heterosexuelle und angeblich christliche Männer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to build a cycling environment</title>
      <link>/2020/02/19/how-to-build-a-cycling-environment.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/19/how-to-build-a-cycling-environment.html</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the Netherlands. We&amp;rsquo;re building roads differently. They are better, safer and less stressful for cyclists, and that also makes them better, safer and less stressful for motorists. Here is how it works:
(based on a Twitter Thread )
What does it look like?   I am living in a village. That means a speed limit of 30 km/h inside the city limits, and that is being enforced by the design of the road.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Militant capitalist attacked german soccer bus</title>
      <link>/2017/04/21/militant-capitalist-attacked-german-soccer-bus.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/21/militant-capitalist-attacked-german-soccer-bus.html</guid>
      <description>The bomb attack on the bus of the german soccer club BVB has been solved. The attacker was not an islamist extremist, as the fake letters found on site suggested. They also weren&amp;rsquo;t Neo-Nazis, as the fake letters to two german newspapers claimed. The perpetrator was instead a militant capitalist who tried to influence BVB stock in order, after he purchased 15k put options on BVB stock. An english language article with background can be found at the BBC.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
