<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>science on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/science.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in science on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 11:41:15 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/science/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Nur eine Theorie</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/03/02/nur-eine-theorie.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2019 02:03:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/03/02/nur-eine-theorie.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Die Frage war:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wieso nennt man die Relativitätstheorie und Evolutionstheorie eigentlich immer noch &amp;lsquo;Theorie&amp;rsquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Antwort muss lauten:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weil sie das sind.
Ein System von Theoremen, die ein Modell der Realität darstellen, das es erlaubt Vorhersagen über die Welt zu machen.
In voller Länge ausgeführt in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/dp/0349106495&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Quark And The Jaguar: Adventures in the Simple and the Complex&lt;/a&gt;

.
Das Buch geht auf diesen Aspekt und noch viel mehr ausführlich ein und ist generell hilfreich um zu verstehen, was Wissenschaft ist und was nicht.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich glaube, es wird noch sehr lange dauern, bis wir über den Punkt hinaus sind, nur mit Modellen unser Universum beschreiben zu können.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wir sind an diesem Punkt schon lange.
Genau genommen seit der &lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aufkl%c3%a4rung#Naturwissenschaften&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Aufklärung&lt;/a&gt;

.
Es ist das Wesen des Modells, einen Gültigkeitsbereich und Fehler zu haben, und Vorhersagen zu liefern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was soll das bedeuten?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Vorhersagen&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Die Newton&amp;rsquo;schen Gesetze beschreiben die Bewegung von Dingen mit Masse im Vakuum bei subrelativistischen Geschwindigkeiten.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Scope&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Die Vorhersagen dieser Gesetze funktionieren nicht in einer Atmosphäre, weil dort Reibung ins Spiel kommt.
Sie funktionieren nicht bei relativistischen Geschwindigkeiten, weil dort Fehler dazu kommen, die die Gleichungen von Newton nicht berücksichtigen.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Fehler&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Wir wissen, daß Newtons Theorien eine Vereinfachung sind, und daß Einsteins Formeln den Sachverhalt genauer beschreiben.
Aber Einsteins Formeln degenerieren für v&amp;laquo;c zu denen von Newton, die relativistischen Terme von Einstein sind nahezu Null,
wenn sich Objekte viel langsamer als das Licht bewegen.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es ist der Sinn von Modellen, Vorhersagen zu machen wie sich die Welt verhält.
Das Modell ist dabei oft beschränkt und ungenau,
was aber seine Anwendbarkeit nicht einschränken muss.
Wir können oft Fehler hinnehmen oder Beschränkungen im Anwendungsgebiet akzeptieren,
wenn wir so schnell und mit einfacher Rechnung zu Abschätzungen kommen, die für die intendierte Anwendung genau genug sind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ist eine Theorie, die bewiesen wurde, nicht mehr von alleine keine Theorie mehr? Sondern vielmehr ein Fakt?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Du meinst „Hypothese“, wo du „Theorie“ schreibst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nope.
Man hat eine Hypothese.
Dann stellt man eine Theorie auf, forscht und beweist diese.
Oder auch nicht.
Dann beantragt man mehr Forschungsgelder &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eine Theorie, ein System von Theoremen, ist nicht bewiesen und oft auch nicht korrekt.
Es ist oft bekannt falsch, beschränkt oder ungenau, oder alles davon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Darum mein Abzielen auf Vorhersagen.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Dalton#Zur_Atomtheorie&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Daltons Atommodell&lt;/a&gt;

 ist beschränkt,
war aber in der Lage, Dinge zu modellieren, die vorher nicht modellierbar waren.
&amp;ldquo;Wieso reagieren Wasserstoff und Sauerstoff immer im Verhältnis 2:1 in der Knallgasreaktion?&amp;rdquo;
ist eine Frage, die Dalton&amp;rsquo;s Atommodell ganz wunderbar beantworten kann.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thompson, Rutherford, und dann Bohr haben bessere (genauere) Modelle,
die an Ende als Verfeinerungen oder Verkomplizierungen von Dalton aufgefasst werden können.
Diese Modelle leisten, was ihre Vorgänger jeweils konnten und mehr (größeres Anwendungsgebiet, bessere Genauigkeit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Du kannst eine Theorie “beweisen”, indem Du sie für Vorhersagen verwendest und dann schaust, ob die taugen.
Du kannst sie widerlegen: Die Vorhersagen sind unzutreffend oder für den Zweck zu ungenau.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Du kannst nichts tun, wenn die Theorie keine Vorhersagen liefern kann.
Das Wesen von Wissenschaft ist, dass Theorien Weltmodelle liefern, die Vorhersagen machen, die sich in Experimenten prüfen lassen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deswegen bleiben Theorien dennoch immer Theorien, Systeme von Theoremen,
und sie bleiben unvollkommen.
Sie sind Modelle, also effektiv Vereinfachungen der Realität,
mit Anwendungsgebiet (sie &amp;ldquo;modellieren&amp;rdquo; etwas) und Genauigkeitsgrenzen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating the Changing Causes of Photovoltaics Cost Reduction</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/08/08/evaluating-the-changing-causes-of-photovoltaics-cost-reduction.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2017 13:44:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/08/08/evaluating-the-changing-causes-of-photovoltaics-cost-reduction.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2891516&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/08/pv-module-cost.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2891516&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Evaluating the Changing Causes of Photovoltaics Cost Reduction&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is PV Solar Energy getting cheaper and cheaper?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We find that increased module efficiency was the leading low-level cause
of cost reduction in 1980-2001, contributing almost 30% of the cost
decline. The most important high-level mechanism was R&amp;amp;D in these earlier
stages of the technology. After 2001, scale economies became a more
significant cause of cost reduction, approaching R&amp;amp;D in importance.
Policies that stimulate market growth have played a key role in enabling
the cost reduction in PV, through privately-funded R&amp;amp;D and economies of
scale, and to a lesser extent learning-by-doing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Story of CO2 (and other Greenhouse Gas Emissions)</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/08/08/the-story-of-co2-and-other-greenhouse-gas-emissions.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2017 10:35:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/08/08/the-story-of-co2-and-other-greenhouse-gas-emissions.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ourworldindata.org/co2-and-other-greenhouse-gas-emissions/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/08/co2-per-capita-640x455.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ourworldindata.org/co2-and-other-greenhouse-gas-emissions/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Our World in Data&lt;/a&gt;


has a very nice long read with many interactive visualisations giving
context to CO2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We begin with exploring CO2 cumulative (how much CO2 did each nation produce
over its industrial history), scaling it to annual emission and then scaling
it by population, too. We also learn about CO2 produced vs. CO2 in the
atmosphere, which is a delayed system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second part then deals with CO2 and industrialisation: Emission vs.
Properity, vs. Growth, and also with CO2 from trade and transport, and from
meat production. As always with Our World in Data, the article concludes
with Definitions, Methods and pointers to raw data sources.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fermi vs. Fhtagn</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/06/26/fermi-vs-fhtagn.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 12:25:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/06/26/fermi-vs-fhtagn.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are things, Lovecraft hypothesizes, that Man is not meant to know.
This paper is touching on these subjects: &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1705.03394&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;That is not dead which can
eternal lie: the aestivation hypothesis for resolving Fermi&amp;rsquo;s
paradox.&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a civilization wants to maximize computation it appears rational to
aestivate until the far future in order to exploit the low temperature
environment: this can produce a 10^30 multiplier of achievable
computation. We hence suggest the &amp;ldquo;aestivation hypothesis&amp;rdquo;: the reason we
are not observing manifestations of alien civilizations is that they are
currently (mostly) inactive, patiently waiting for future cosmic eras.
This paper analyzes the assumptions going into the hypothesis and how
physical law and observational evidence constrain the motivations of
aliens compatible with the hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the Great Old starfaring civilizations exist, the paper suggests, but
they are sleeping, waiting until the stars are, literally, right. So much of
Lovecraft is about astronomy and cosmology, and it did not stop with his
death, if he actually died.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Measles vs your immune system</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/05/26/the-measles-vs-your-immune-system.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2017 10:04:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/05/26/the-measles-vs-your-immune-system.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/sections/goatsandsoda/2015/05/07/404963436/scientists-crack-a-50-year-old-mystery-about-the-measles-vaccine&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NPR has an article&lt;/a&gt;


about the measles. It is already known that after a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Measles&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;measles infection&lt;/a&gt;

 the immune system goes
down for a few weeks and followup infections are common. It seems that what
the infection does is worse than that. With the introduction of measles
vaccination it has been observed that &lt;em&gt;other infections&lt;/em&gt; went down within
2-3 years after measles immunization took place. Researchers wanted to know
why and found evidence that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many viruses, measles is known to suppress the immune system for a
few weeks after an infection. But previous studies in monkeys have
suggested that measles takes this suppression to a whole new level: It
erases immune protection to other diseases, Mina says. So what does that
mean? Well, say you get the chicken pox when you&amp;rsquo;re 4 years old. Your
immune system figures out how to fight it. So you don&amp;rsquo;t get it again. But
if you get measles when you&amp;rsquo;re 5 years old, it could wipe out the memory
of how to beat back the chicken pox. It&amp;rsquo;s like the immune system has
amnesia, Mina says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So parents putting their children into a &amp;ldquo;measles party&amp;rdquo; in order for them
to &amp;ldquo;gain natural immunzation&amp;rdquo; may actually achieve the exact opposite of
that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No such thing as a wilderness, part II</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/03/21/no-such-thing-as-a-wilderness-part-ii.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 08:47:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/03/21/no-such-thing-as-a-wilderness-part-ii.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2017/03/170314111320.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Science Daily writes&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New research investigating the transition of the Sahara from a lush, green
landscape 10,000 years ago to the arid conditions found today, suggests
that humans may have played an active role in its desertification. [&amp;hellip;]
As more vegetation was removed by the introduction of livestock, it
increased the albedo (the amount of sunlight that reflects off the earth&amp;rsquo;s
surface) of the land, which in turn influenced atmospheric conditions
sufficiently to reduce monsoon rainfall. The weakening monsoons caused
further desertification and vegetation loss, promoting a feedback loop
which eventually spread over the entirety of the modern Sahara.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar effects are being discussed in
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.abc.net.au/radionational/programs/scienceshow/effects-of-the-changing-climate-in-south-western-australia/8175170&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Science Show of January 21&lt;/a&gt;

,
about current day South Western Australia:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europeans began altering the landscape following settlement of the region
in 1829. Vast areas of eucalypt forest were cleared for crops and pasture.
Cleared land produces less turbulence as storms move across the landscape.
And fewer big trees means less transpiration. The atmosphere is drier, the
storms slip by, with less rain produced. Now global effects mean cold
fronts are passing further south, some missing the continent altogether.
The water table is falling by half a metre a year. If the trend continues,
there are predictions of a 17% drop in agricultural production in future
decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No such thing as a wilderness?</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/03/21/no-such-thing-as-a-wilderness.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 08:12:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/03/21/no-such-thing-as-a-wilderness.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some 40 authors are listed in the title of
&lt;a href=&#34;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/355/6328/925&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Persistent effects of pre-Columbian plant domestication on Amazonian forest composition&lt;/a&gt;

 in Science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TL;DR is: The Amazonas Rain Forest is a 10.000 year old garden, which
has been left untended for the last 500 years after the Amerindian genocide
of European conquistadors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The extent to which pre-Columbian societies altered Amazonian landscapes
is hotly debated. We performed a basin-wide analysis of pre-Columbian
impacts on Amazonian forests by overlaying known archaeological sites in
Amazonia with the distributions and abundances of 85 woody species
domesticated by pre-Columbian peoples. Domesticated species are five times
more likely than nondomesticated species to be hyperdominant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across the basin, the relative abundance and richness of domesticated
species increase in forests on and around archaeological sites. In
southwestern and eastern Amazonia, distance to archaeological sites
strongly influences the relative abundance and richness of domesticated
species. Our analyses indicate that modern tree communities in Amazonia
are structured to an important extent by a long history of plant
domestication by Amazonian peoples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full article is unfortunately behind a pay wall.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Salted Doorknobs kill MRSA</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/03/21/salted-doorknobs-kill-mrsa.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 07:34:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/03/21/salted-doorknobs-kill-mrsa.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2017/03/salt-vs-superbugs/518427/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/03/salty-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2017/03/salt-vs-superbugs/518427/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Salted Doorknobs kill MRSA&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Says this article at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2017/03/salt-vs-superbugs/518427/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Superbugs like Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus, or MRSA, have
wreaked havoc on the health-care system in recent years. [&amp;hellip;] How do you
stop them? Frequent hand washing is one option, but that requires a
behavior change, which can be difficult, even for hospital staff. Another
option is to coat those frequently fondled objects most likely to carry
the bugs—doorknobs, bed rails, toilet handles—with a special
anti-microbial surface, like copper. [&amp;hellip;] Whitlock found that salt killed
off the bug 20 to 30 times faster than the copper did, reducing MRSA
levels by 85 percent after 20 seconds, and by 94 percent after a minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>That&#39;s no moon!</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/03/13/thats-no-moon.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 21:56:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/03/13/thats-no-moon.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So Saturn has a &amp;lsquo;moon&amp;rsquo;. At least that&amp;rsquo;s what They want us to believe. But we
know better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pan_%28moon%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/03/Pan_by_Cassini_March_2017.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pan_%28moon%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Supposedly Pan&lt;/a&gt;

, a Saturn Moon,
as seen by Cassini.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/03/basis_rhodan.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sketchfab.com/models/7038ac3cb7a448f1beefd523201c8263&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BASIS&lt;/a&gt;

, as
we know it from
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.perrypedia.proc.org/wiki/BASIS&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Rhodan&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Video: 20 Years of continuous improvement in crash safety</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/02/09/video-20-years-of-continuous-improvement-in-crash-safety.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2017 07:56:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/02/09/video-20-years-of-continuous-improvement-in-crash-safety.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Continual improvement is sometimes hard to see, because each iteration, each
incremental step itself is tiny so that the actual change escapes our
attention. Also, just living our lives, our time sense is sometimes
distorted. Me for example, I was almost 30 already in the late Nineties, and
while that is already 20 years ago, it feels like yesterday to me. So car
safety in the Nineties, compared to now? It was crap. Check this out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pwGgRUkrnng&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;We do learn, and things do get better. Change is not radical, most of the
time it&amp;rsquo;s evolutionary. And to make it visible, you have to look really hard
and contract now and then.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maya empire remains</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/02/06/maya-empire-remains.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 21:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/02/06/maya-empire-remains.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.seeker.com/ancient-mayan-superhighways-found-in-the-guatemala-jungle-2219303581.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/02/maya-ruins.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lidar Image&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two articles about the Maya civilization:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.seeker.com/ancient-mayan-superhighways-found-in-the-guatemala-jungle-2219303581.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Seeker article&lt;/a&gt;


about LiDAR being used to reveal ancient structures on the Jungle ground: A
network of 150km of prehistoric Autobahn ran through the Jungle, binding the
Mayan Empire together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;These causeways are 130 feet wide, up to 20 feet high and in some cases
they extend as far as 25 miles,&amp;rdquo; Hansen said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A causeway is a raised road across difficult, often wet or unstable ground.
Because of the raised structure LiDAR can find these roads even
today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org/content/early/2017/01/17/1618022114&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PNAS&lt;/a&gt;

,
another article about radiocarbon dating of several Maya sites, illuminating
the time and speed of two collapses of the Maya civilization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through this chronology, we traced the trajectories of the Preclassic
collapse around AD 150–300 and the Classic collapse around AD 800–950,
revealing similar patterns in the two cases. Social instability started
with the intensification of warfare around 75 BC and AD 735, respectively,
followed by the fall of multiple centers across the Maya lowlands around
AD 150 and 810. The population of Ceibal persisted for some time in both
cases, but the center eventually experienced major decline around AD 300
and 900.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unlearning Descriptive Statistics</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/02/06/unlearning-descriptive-statistics.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 13:41:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/02/06/unlearning-descriptive-statistics.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anscombe%27s_quartet#/media/File:Anscombe%27s_quartet_3.svg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/02/640px-Anscombes_quartet_3.svg_.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anscombe&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Anscombe&amp;rsquo;s Quartet&lt;/a&gt;

 by
Schutz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://debrouwere.org/2017/02/01/unlearning-descriptive-statistics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Unlearning Descriptive Statistics&lt;/a&gt;


explains many things you should know about working with Numbers that your
Statistics Class in University probably did not explain properly. If they
did, maybe Graphite would not hurt so much, with all the Averaging going on
where it shouldn&amp;rsquo;t, and maybe Gill Tene would not have had to give talks
like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lJ8ydIuPFeU&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;How NOT to measure latency&lt;/a&gt;


(which is awesome, by the way and if you haven&amp;rsquo;t seen this talk, do it right
now).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the Intro of Unlearning:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever used an arithmetic mean, a Pearson correlation or a
standard deviation to describe a dataset, I&amp;rsquo;m writing this for you. Better
numbers exist to summarize location, association and spread: numbers that
are easier to interpret and that don&amp;rsquo;t act up with wonky data and
outliers. Statistics professors tend to gloss over basic descriptive
statistics because they want to spend as much time as possible on margins
of error and t-tests and regression. Fair enough, but the result is that
it&amp;rsquo;s easier to find a machine learning expert than someone who can talk
about numbers. Forget what you think you know about descriptives and let
me give you a whirlwind tour of &lt;em&gt;the real stuff&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go, read the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Racing our galaxy</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/02/02/racing-our-galaxy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2017 12:25:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/02/02/racing-our-galaxy.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Why is our galaxy moving through space, and into which directions is
everything else moving?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientists at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem have been mapping these
forces, and found a very empty region in space that seems to push a lot of
galaxies away from it, as well as a (previously known) region thats
attracting them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result looks like a billion light year magnet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2017/01/170130110921.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/02/170130110921_1_900x600-300x169.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2017/01/170130110921.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The dipole repeller&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What causes these forces is as of now not well understood. Original Paper in
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/articles/s41550-016-0036&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nature Astronomy&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chinese New Year, and birthrate anomalies</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/01/26/chinese-new-year-and-birthrate-anomalies.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 13:17:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/01/26/chinese-new-year-and-birthrate-anomalies.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/01/f9463344d3ed41479d28dcd7.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming up: Chinese New Year on 28. January. The coming year is a
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chinahighlights.com/travelguide/chinese-zodiac/rooster.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;year of the Fire Rooster&lt;/a&gt;

,
and apparently these things mean a lot to a lot of people. So
what influence does the Chinese Zodiac have? Well, one sign that
is supposed to be very unlucky is the Fire Horse. An
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tofugu.com/japan/fire-horse-zodiac/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;article from 2012&lt;/a&gt;


explains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People born during the year of the Fire Horse are notorious
for being bad luck. People born during a Fire Horse years are
said to be irresponsible, rebellious, and overall bad news.
And for some reason, women are said to be especially dangerous
Fire Horses. They supposedly sap their family’s finances,
neglect their children, and drive their father and husband to
an early grave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution? Don&amp;rsquo;t make babies in a Fire Horse year, and especially
no female babies. So 1966 was a Fire Horse, and that&amp;rsquo;s what 1966
stats look like:
&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/01/japan-birthrate-graph.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Religion Virus</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2012/08/17/fertig-gelesen-the-religion-virus.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2012 21:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2012/08/17/fertig-gelesen-the-religion-virus.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/The-Religion-Virus-evolutionist-ebook/dp/B0046A9JMA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Religion Virus&lt;/a&gt;

,
Craig A.  James, USD 4.75&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/religion_virus.png&#34; alt=&#34;James: The Religion Virus&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das Buch behandelt Religion, und insbesondere das Christentum als
Mem-Komplex, also als ein ideologisches Gen, daß auf unserem Bewußtsein und
in unserer Kultur mitreitet.  Der Mem-Komplex entwickelt sich dabei nach
evolutionären Regeln weiter, indem er mit anderen, verwandten Memen
konkurriert, und generell mit allen Ideen um Aufmerksamkeit wettstreitet.
Untersucht werden die grundsätzlichen Teil-Meme, die das Judentum und später
das Christentum geprägt haben, und dabei an Bibelstellen und der
aufgezeichneten objektiven Geschichte des Christentums nachgewiesen, wann
und wo diese Meme entstanden sind und wie sie dabei halfen, den Memplex
&amp;ldquo;Christentum&amp;rdquo; erfolgreicher und gegen andere Religionen und Ideen
durchsetzungsstärker zu machen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In der Aufklärung und der Moderne ist Religion unter Druck geraten und so
hat der Memplex Mechanismen entwickeln müssen, mit denen er sich gegen
Angriffe und gegen &amp;ldquo;Disbelief&amp;rdquo; wehren kann.  Die Mechanismen, mit denen
Glaubensgemeinschaften diesen Druck abzuwehren versuchen und sich zu
stabilisieren versuchen werden ebenfalls dargestellt und ihre geschichtliche
Entwicklung wie auch ihre Wirkmechanismen offengelegt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dadurch, daß das Buch die innere ideologische Wirkstruktur von Religionen im
Allgemeinen und des Christentums im Besonderen offenlegt, hilft es sehr
dabei, Religion und die Argumentationen von religiösen Personen zu
verstehen.  Ich fand das sehr erhellend.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

