<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>macos on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>/tags/macos.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in macos on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/macos/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>MacOS: Deleting Relocated Items</title>
      <link>/2020/09/02/macos-relocated-items.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/02/macos-relocated-items.html</guid>
      <description>I had to upgrade my company issued MacBook pro to Catalina for fleet unity reasons. The upgrade left me with a folder Relocated Items in /Users/Shared/Desktop and a link to that prominently on my Desktop.
Deleting that folder moved it to trash. Trying to empty trash then failed. That is because in that folder was several levels deep a folder or link to X11R6.
Apple considers that file outdated, which is why it ended up in Relocated Items.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So I am a Windows User now</title>
      <link>/2020/07/07/so-i-am-a-windows-user-now.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/07/so-i-am-a-windows-user-now.html</guid>
      <description>So I am a Windows User now. I have an old MacBook pro, Late-2013 13&amp;quot; Retina, i7, 16 GB, 1 TB SSD, and the battery is done now, after 7 years. Also, the hardware is aging, and I want it refurbished and upgrade the son&amp;rsquo;s equipment (which is the previous 2010 MBP I had at that time).
Modern Apple is not my thing. I have a company MBP, 2018 Retina 13&amp;quot; Four-Port, i7, 16 GB, and everything about this device is wrong.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time Machine Editor</title>
      <link>/2020/05/26/time-machine-editor.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/26/time-machine-editor.html</guid>
      <description>I have an embedded Mac mini, it drives the local TV screen by doing OpenVPN to Germany, Netflix, Amazon and the local Subsonic . It does not really do much with the local disk, and it does not need to wake up every hour to make a Time Machine backup over the network.
To change the backup interval, install Time Machine Editor .
 Time Machine Editor can change the Time Machine Backup interval.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ignoring Catalina nags</title>
      <link>/2019/10/15/ignoring-catalina-nags.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/10/15/ignoring-catalina-nags.html</guid>
      <description>Note to self: Ignoring the Catalina Nagscreens is done like this:
$ sudo softwareupdate --ignore &amp;#34;macOS Catalina&amp;#34; $ defaults write com.apple.systempreferences AttentionPrefBundleIDs 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; killall Dock And that should make MacOS ignore Catalina until further notice. Further notice does look like this:
$ /usr/sbin/softwareupdate --reset-ignored </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Catalina: Upgrade carefully.</title>
      <link>/2019/10/08/catalina-upgrade-carefully.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/10/08/catalina-upgrade-carefully.html</guid>
      <description>Catalina is here. It fixes many things, among them iTunes. On the other hand, it drops support for 32-Bit MacOS applications.
Consider the upgrade carefully.
$ system_profiler SPApplicationsDataType … Steam: Version: 1.5 Obtained from: Identified Developer Last Modified: 23.08.16, 20:32 Kind: Intel 64-Bit (Intel): No Signed by: Developer ID Application: Valve Corporation, Developer ID Certification Authority, Apple Root CA Location: /Applications/Steam.app … Anything listed with 64-Bit (Intel): No will stop working after the upgrade.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Watchman</title>
      <link>/2018/02/01/watchman.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/02/01/watchman.html</guid>
      <description>Today I was looking for a way to subscribe to file changes in a directory in MacOS, in order to trigger automatically running commands whenever files change. Turns out Homebrew has &amp;ldquo;fswatch&amp;rdquo;, which tells you when things change, but little else.
Turns out Homebrew has &amp;ldquo;watchman&amp;rdquo;, which does all this, and on multiple trees, finds changes across restarts and automatically manages a set of commands for different file endings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Knock, Knock</title>
      <link>/2018/01/15/knock-knock.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/15/knock-knock.html</guid>
      <description>What does your Mac do on Startup? Knockknock knows .
It&amp;rsquo;s not properly updated for current versions of MacOS, but it is still useful. &amp;ldquo;git clone https://github.com/synack/knockknock&#34; and &amp;ldquo;/usr/bin/python knockknock.py&amp;rdquo; is sufficient to test.
TOTAL ITEMS FOUND: 44 That&amp;rsquo;s quite a bit. Apparently, I am starting
 Google Music Manager, AirServer, Karabiner, Alfred 3, a Chrome app_mode_loader, the Android File Transfer Agent, Dropbox, Divvy, Expandrive, Chrome itself, Soundflower, an AX88179 USB GBit Ethernet adapter driver, Steam Drivers, /Library/PrivilegedHelperTools/org.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Command line access to the Mac keychain</title>
      <link>/2017/01/26/command-line-access-to-the-mac-keychain.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/26/command-line-access-to-the-mac-keychain.html</guid>
      <description>I am getting my payslips in electronic form, as an encrypted, password protected PDF. It&amp;rsquo;s not a super secret password, and the encryption is more against accidentally opening the file than it is to keep the content of the file actually secret.
After shipping the PDF home, I am archiving it for tax purposes, but in order to make the archival safe, I am storing the original file as well as the decrypted cleartext version of it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adventures in Mac OS X maintenance</title>
      <link>/2010/02/19/adventures-in-mac-os-x-maintenance.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/19/adventures-in-mac-os-x-maintenance.html</guid>
      <description>Nachdem ich neulich meinen Mac in den Service geben mußte, ich für die Zeit einen Ersatz-Mac hatte und ich also zwischen beiden Systemen hin- und her installieren mußte, hier die deutsche Übersetzung einer kleinen Zusammenfassung, die ich für die Firma geschrieben habe.
Offensichtlich ist es sehr praktisch, dem großen Mac-Gott Time Machine eine Platte zu opfern, weil niemand Backup will und Time Machine sehr gut in Restore ist. In meinem Fall verwende ich eine WD Elements 1TB dafür (etwa 85€), andere in der Firma wollen was kleineres und mit USB Power, nehmen also eine WD Passport (500G @ 92€).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
