<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Book on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/book.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Book on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2024 13:23:59 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/book/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Starter Villain</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/10/01/fertig-gelesen-starter-villain.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 01:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/10/01/fertig-gelesen-starter-villain.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mastodon.social/@scalzi&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;John Scalzi&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;

 latest book is currently
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Starter-Villain-turbo-charged-supervillains-minions-ebook/dp/B0BJDXRGX8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Starter Villain&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2023/10/starter-villain.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The premise is simple: Charlie&amp;rsquo;s estranged Uncle Jake died.
Charlie and his uncle are estranged because Charlie&amp;rsquo;s father and Jake had a fallout at the funeral of Charlie&amp;rsquo;s mom,
and Charlie has not had much contact at all with Jake ever since.
Now, with Jake also dead, it turns out that Charlie somehow is his only heir.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then Charlie is holding watch at Jake&amp;rsquo;s funeral, and the entire story turns quickly into a James Bond novel,
with strange brutes trying to stab the corpse of Jake, ensuring he&amp;rsquo;s really dead,
and a collection of very weirdly imprinted flower bouquets &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;See you in hell&amp;rdquo; being one of the nicer ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charlie quickly learns that his uncle was a Villain, complete with a lair on a volcano island,
laser weapons to destroy satellites, and a collection of very nice and special cats (and Dolphins, but they are special and not nice).
He also learns that &amp;ldquo;Villain&amp;rdquo; does not exactly mean what he thinks that it means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scalzi spent his pages playing nicely with the clichés and expectations around James-Bond-like supervillains,
and turning them into a fun story with a number of expected and unexpected twists.
He wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be Scalzi if there is no stuff to think about lurking in the background.
In this case, fairly obviously the relationship between 1950&amp;rsquo;s supervillains and present day billionaires, oligarchs
and our survival as a species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A nice two-afternoon read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Starter-Villain-turbo-charged-supervillains-minions-ebook/dp/B0BJDXRGX8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Starter Villain&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;,
John Scalzi, EUR 9,99.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: A Life with Footnotes</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/30/fertig-gelesen-a-life-with-footnotes.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2023 01:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/30/fertig-gelesen-a-life-with-footnotes.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Rob Wilkins was the assistant and a good friend of Terry Pratchett.
He wrote a posthumous biography, titled
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B09R2B8J17&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;A Life With Footnotes&lt;/a&gt;

.
Wilkins is now the manager of the Pratchett literary estate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2023/09/pratchett.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book does what a biography is supposed to do:
It traces the life of Terry Pratchett,
illuminating his origins and the experiences that shaped his worldview.
Filled with anecdotes and tales from his readings, from conventions, and other encounters with fans,
it sketches a portrait of a lovable, quirky personality who crafted stories in his mind and then simply penned them down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rob Wilkins then takes on the challenging segment of the biography and guides us through the tragic phase of Terry Pratchett:
his Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s diagnosis, the mental and physical decline, the ever-increasing loss of control, and the interplay of good and bad days,
leading up to the emotional farewell that occurred long before his physical passing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B09R2B8J17&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Terry Pratchett: A Life With Footnotes&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Rob Wilkins, EUR 9,49.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Combat Ready Kitchen</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/29/fertig-gelesen-combat-ready-kitchen.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2023 01:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/29/fertig-gelesen-combat-ready-kitchen.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B00TY3ZOQE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Combat Ready Kitchen&lt;/a&gt;

,
Anastacia Marx de Salcedo traces the history of food preservation from an american point of view,
and demonstrates the co-development of combat rations and modern U.S. supermarket food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2023/09/combat-ready.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book takes us through the history of U.S. combat rations, from before the invention of the tin can, through canned,
better preserved, but incredibly heavy food to what soldiers have today.
It shows how these military innovations have been seeded, purposefully, into the civilian food industry,
in order to enable the military to source food from civilian companies for their purposes, in formats that suit them.
This also had influence on how the industry preserves food for civilian consumption and enabled a multitude of convenience foods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the development of food preservation for military and civilian needs was somewhat systematic,
the book is not.
It goes through the history not chronologically, but anecdotally, roughly ordered by kind of food,
but with plenty of sidelines, side stories and other distractions.
It still is an entertaining read, but it makes it hard to put down the book and take stock of what you just learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I took away is that food preservation as we understand it today is much more recent than most people think.
It is a thing humanity only learned in the late 80ies and early 90ies, and even today fundamental progress is being made.
Also, a lot of the stuff we do is not actually bad for the food, the nutrients or the taste,
it is in fact perfectly fine.
Still, other things amount to basically breaking down the food to constituent parts, and then reassembling something
from the parts, and that&amp;rsquo;s maybe less good, given how little we actually understand what makes a meal nourishing or healthy,
even today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entertaining and interesting, but structured in a way that makes it harder than necessary for me to pull value out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;%28https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B00TY3ZOQE%29&#34;&gt;Combat Ready Kitchen: How the U.S. Military Shapes The Way You Eat&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;,
Anastacia Marx de Salcedo, EUR 5.25.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Blue Machine</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/26/fertig-gelesen-blue-machine.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 01:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/26/fertig-gelesen-blue-machine.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://fediscience.org/@helenczerski&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Helen Czerski&lt;/a&gt;

 wrote a book.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Blue-Machine-Ocean-Shapes-English-ebook/dp/B0BCTPP3DH&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Blue Machine: How the ocean shapes our world&lt;/a&gt;


occupies the weird space between memoir, travel blog and science outreach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the middle of this she manages to explain the biggest machine on our planet:
The collection of oceans in which the continents are embedded.
But also the deep love of science, the desire to understand how our world functions,
and the connection between all people than live on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is the story of a person who literally travelled the world, from the poles to the equator,
and from the surface of the oceans to their dark cold depths.
It also is the story of a physicist with knowledge about bubbles and how they work,
and how that line of research led her around the world, and into the oceans.
It also is a gentle introduction into climate science,
showing us how the ocean can be seen as a machine that manages the thermals of the planet,
capturing and transporting heat, feeding the weather machine in the atmosphere with energy and water vapor,
and also capturing and releasing carbon dioxide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following her travels and experiences, we learn about the vertical layering structure of the oceans,
about the ability of water to capture fantastic amounts of energy,
about currents and how they transport water, energy, nutrients and life around the world,
and how humans have been living off all this on the surface of something much greater, deeper and larger than we ever imagined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an amazing and entertaining book that shares a unique and personal perspective of our world,
and at the same time manages to convey how something this vast and enormous can be at the same time fragile and in need our or care and understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strongly recommended read, well worth the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Blue-Machine-Ocean-Shapes-English-ebook/dp/B0BCTPP3DH&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Blue Machine&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Helen Czerski, EUR 15.62&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Crafting Interpreters</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/16/fertig-gelesen-crafting-interpreters.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/16/fertig-gelesen-crafting-interpreters.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Robert Nystrom is a language developer who works at Google on the Dart programming language.
In his book &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Robert-Nystrom-ebook/dp/B09YLQSGKL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Crafting Interpreters&lt;/a&gt;

 he explains lexing, parsing and executing a programming language in an accessible way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Robert-Nystrom-ebook/dp/B09YLQSGKL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/crafting-interpreters.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Robert-Nystrom-ebook/dp/B09YLQSGKL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Crafting Interpreters&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;quot;, Robert Nystrom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nystrom sets out with the (correct) observation that the matter of handling and executing code is a complex topic that is not made easier with all the theory that surrounds it.
In his book, he takes the reader on a journey to implement a toy language, Lox, two times.
First with a tree walker execution algorithm, not unlike PHP 3 or early Ruby.
Then, again, with a bytecode executor written in C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book starts out by defining an intentionally very basic, but complete programming language, and then chapter by chapter builds the infrastructure to scan, parse and execute the code.
All explanations are very practical and on the code, but a lot of boxes, asides and cross-references make the theory behind all this discoverable, while at the same time keeping it out of the way.
One of the nicest and most practical introductions to programming language interpretation and compilation that I have seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Robert-Nystrom-ebook/dp/B09YLQSGKL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Crafting Interpreters&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Robert Nystrom, EUR 25.84&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Fietsparkeren bij Stations</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/07/fertig-gelesen-fietsparkeren-bij-stations.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/07/fertig-gelesen-fietsparkeren-bij-stations.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Netherlands realized around 2000 that they have a problem with bike parking around train stations, and with parking around stations in general.
A program was set up to fix that, assuming things would be done with in ten years.
The program was a great success, and people taking the bike to use the train, and to use a bike after they arrived at their destination by train increased greatly.
This created more needs, and so the program is, changed, still active today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Folkert-Piersma/dp/9068688286&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fietsparkeren bij Stations&lt;/a&gt;

, Folkert Piersma and Wout Ritzema&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Title Page&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book talks, in one chapter each, about analyzing customer needs, the history of the program, guidelines and goals, the plannning process, typical bike parking facilities, architecture and design, investment costs, facility operations, technical resources, innovative solutions and finally an outlook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;em&gt;Table of Content&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What matters to cycling train travellers?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Historic review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Policy for the development and construction of bicycle parking facilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Types of bicycle parking facilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Architecture and design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investment costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Operation, maintenance and enforcement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technical resources and innovations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Innovative types of parking facilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Challenges and opportunities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overview of bicycle parking facilities at railway stations, numbers of bicycle parking spaces per station to storage type&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-03.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Bike/Train combination is special.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bike/train combination is special in many ways.
First, as a mode of transport, they have more in common than you would think.
Both have a low impact on air quality, and they are also propelled in a natural manner:
The electric trains of the Dutch Railways run on 100% wind energy,
while bikes are propelled by muscle power, at times supported with a bit of electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both cyclists and train travelers like speed and convenience;
cyclists want to get to their train as fast as possible without encountering any obstacles,
while train travelers move fast while they read a newspaper, prepare for work or take a nap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Dutch Railways, nearly 50% of all train travelers (in 2019, about 1.5 million journeys were made each day)
get to the station by bike and in some places, that figure is 70%.
Approximately 16% of those travelers use the bike to get from the station to their final destination.
Twenty years ago, those figures were 30 % and 10 % respectively.
Because of the growing popularity of the bike and growing consideration for health and sustainability,
we expect these percentages in the bike/train combination to rise further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This combination already means that the car has fierce competition,
especially for city-to-city connections.
A study by the University of Amsterdam shows that the travel time from,
for example, the centre of Arnhem to the Rijksmuseum in Amsterdam (approximately 100 km)
is virtually the same for both the bike/train combination and the car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-04.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Load diagrams and station plan with the bike parking in relation to the platforms.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-05.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Groot, licht, dichtbij. Dit is ideaal!&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; Christien&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protected and unprotected bike parking.
People coming to the station can park their bike protected or unprotected.
Protected bike parking can be with personnel or without.
An example of protected bike parking without personnel would be bike boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-06.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ik kom hier graag. Er is gewoon altijd plek!&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; Xiaohe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planability and reliable availability of bike slots are important to customers and commuters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-07.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bike parking in the 1970s.
Fietsenstalling bij station Koudum Molkwerum (boven) en fietsenstalling bi station Dronrip (jaren zeventig van de vorige euw).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Times and usage-patterns change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand where the Netherlands are today, we have to look at the past.
These photos from the 1970s show the situation in typical stations from that time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-08.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Station Kampen, 1982.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Dutch word for a bike park is &amp;ldquo;stalling&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;stable&amp;rdquo;), and in this case it is meant quite literally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-09.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Replanning and rebuilding bike parking at station Deventer.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Situation shown in 2002, and in 2012 after renovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-10.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Programma fietsparkeren bij Stations&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The change is not accidental, but the consequence of the program &amp;ldquo;Bike Parking at Stations&amp;rdquo;,
which started off around 2000.
It has changed the nature of bike parking at stations in the Netherlands fundamentally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it also had different, further reaching aspects,
and that is why it is still ongoing after 20 years:
Not only is the sea of bikes around the train stations gone
despite more people arriving by bike at the train than ever before,
also the quality of the area around the train stations improved.
The dark and seedy underpasses and the general feeling of insecurity around many train stations areas in other cities is no longer present here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-11.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What works and what doesn&amp;rsquo;t?
After gaining experience with the initial construction program and being pleasantly surprised by its success,
the program was expanded to a broader basis, and the learnings were implemented.
Financially, the group also improved its position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It quickly became clear that not all conditions included in the &amp;ldquo;Taking Your Bike to the Train&amp;rdquo; directive were functioning well or efficiently.
In Chapter 3, we already discussed the aisle widths in the bicycle storage facilities,
which were found to be able to be narrower, allowing for a more efficient layout of the storage area.
Another important adjustment was the positioning of the monitored and unmonitored storage facilities
in relation to the station entrance and the prescribed covered walking route from the monitored storage to the station.
It also turned out to be necessary to equip the indoor monitored storage with tiered racks,
which was already the case in virtually all existing monitored storage facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-12.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Planning and exploration phases for a bicycle parking facility are presented and explained&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-13.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Target audience and their needs.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Highlighting some important research&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding the Target Audience&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bicycle parking facilities at stations have a very specific target audience with distinct needs,
as also mentioned in Chapter 1.
We know that train travelers are &amp;ldquo;time travelers&amp;rdquo;
and we assume that cyclists heading to the station are almost always in a hurry
because the train won&amp;rsquo;t wait.
It starts with the route from home to the station:
Cyclists prefer the shortest and fastest route from home to the station.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, cyclists want to get on the train as quickly as possible
and spend as little time as possible parking their bikes.
Therefore, we place the bicycle parking facility as close as possible to the station entrance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-14.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Capacity planning using the example of the fictional station Amperveen.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Case STATION AMPERVEEN: Local Customization for Projections&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fictional station Amperveen and its surroundings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the current observed usage, this station requires 3630 spots.
With the currently available 3000 spots, there is already a shortage of 630 spots.
It would not be surprising if the long-term projection ends up at 5750 spots
(20 % increase in travelers, 20 % increase in bicycle usage, and 10 % latent demand).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-15.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Real Simulations: Amsterdam Centraal Station. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EqwasBTzZS8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ZW1A with a capacity of 7000 parking spaces has just been completed&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-16.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Case Station Amperveen: Distance to the Station&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the analysis of parking locations, the distance to the station is also important.
We try to create parking facilities as close as possible to the station entrance,
but sometimes it is not possible to meet the full demand.
Offering &amp;lsquo;first 24 hours free&amp;rsquo; parking is also considered a form of unpaid parking.
If a station has a significant number of weekend parkers, which is often the case in student cities,
it may be considered to provide a free unguarded parking facility at a slightly greater distance,
up to a maximum of 400 meters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-17.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Types, by Prevalence and Price:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ground-Level Parking (as seen in the 1970s photos)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bicycle Flat (Multi-story Bicycle Parking)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indoor Parking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Underground Parking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mega Parking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-18.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pedestrian Flow Analysis for the bike-parking &amp;ldquo;Stationsplein Eindhoven Central (south side)&amp;rdquo;.
Variations in the Layout of bike lots.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-19.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what did we learn in the last 20 years?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Typical 90&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Trend 2020&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not all ground level parking has a roof&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;All ground level parking has a roof&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Concrete stairs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Natural stone finished stairs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No technical aids to bridge height differences&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Technical aids to bridge height differences, such as brush ramps, moving walkways, or escalators (if required and funded by the municipality)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Unfinished concrete ceiling&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Finished with a system ceiling or a smooth finished ceiling&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Concrete tiles on the floor&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Smooth concrete floor&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Unfinished retaining walls visible&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Retaining walls coated or finished with a cladding&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cables and pipes visible&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cables and pipes concealed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Unfinished interior walls&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(Light) Art on the interior walls&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Partition wall made of aerated concrete blocks or system wall&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Partition wall made of glass in an aluminum frame&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Windows in a portion of the wall&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Floor-to-ceiling windows&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Turnstile at pedestrian exit with low steel revolving gate&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Full-height glass turnstile&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-20.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And this is what it looks like.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Folkert-Piersma/dp/9068688286&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fietsparkeren bij Stations&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Folkert Piersma and Wout Ritzema, EUR 29.40 Hardcover&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Pale Rider</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/06/fertig-gelesen-pale-rider.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/06/fertig-gelesen-pale-rider.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A book from 2017, about the Spanish Flu, which in the wake of the first world war turned into a global pandemic, killing between 50 and 100 million people on all continents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/pale-rider.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Laura-Spinney-ebook/dp/B01GH07CG6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pale Rider&lt;/a&gt;

, Laura Spinney&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spinney describes the situation in the world in 1918, and how the Spanish Flu came into the world, and was experienced by people in various parts of the world.
The flu returned in several waves, some of which behaved unlike normal flu seasons and also had weirdly shaped killing patterns in the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also describes reactions of the population to pandemic fighting measures &amp;ndash; and we know them all from personal experience by now.
There have been people protecting mask mandates, self-isolation and social distancing on purpose, &amp;ldquo;mah freedums&amp;rdquo; criers and so on, just like with Covid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In parts 5 and 6, she looks at the flu from a modern perspective:
We now know about viruses, and specific the influenza A virus and its variants.
We understand its genetics and which parts of the virus are relevant for infection of humans, and they mutate.
We catalogue them &amp;ndash; the spanish flu was H1N1.
Spinney then looks at SARS, MERS and bird flu, and other viruses, and how they ramp up for another pandemic, strangely prescient of the Covid pandemic of 2020.
Also addresses, again spot on, anti-science propaganda and ossified politics unable to integrate new findings into existing rule frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An enlightening and at the same time very frustrating read, written and published 3 years before Covid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Laura-Spinney-ebook/dp/B01GH07CG6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pale Rider&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Laura Spinney, EUR 9.49 on Kindle&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Kaiju Preservation Society</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/05/fertig-gelesen-the-kaiju-preservation-society.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/05/fertig-gelesen-the-kaiju-preservation-society.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On an alternate earth alternate biology produces beings that can grow up to 150 meters tall and that are powered by natural biological nuclear reactor: The Kaiju.
Whenever anything, humans or Kaiju, uses nuclear energy, the boundary between the alternate realities is weakened and things can cross over.
That happened the first time late in the second world war, and that is how the legend of Godzilla came into the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B09DD2DK5Z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/kps.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B09DD2DK5Z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Kaiju Preservation Society&lt;/a&gt;

, John Scalzi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s Covid times, it&amp;rsquo;s New York, and Jamie got fired from his management position of a delivery service and has to deliver things himself now.
Doing that, he meets an old acquaintance of him, which offers him a&amp;hellip; different job.
The job turns out to involve secrecy, a dimensional portal and working in an alternate world in which he meets things that usually live in SciFi novels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a fun read, from a fun Scalzi from earlier times woken up again.
Doubly so when contrasted with the rather exhausting Interdependency.
Action, Dad joke puns and an improbable premise delivered masterfully, with the parts clicking nicely into each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A strong recommendation, and time well spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B09DD2DK5Z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Kaiju Preservation Society&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, John Scalzi, EUR 8.99 on Kindle&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Sid Meier&#39;s Memoir!</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/04/fertig-gelesen-sid-meier-memoir.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/04/fertig-gelesen-sid-meier-memoir.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The subtitle of &amp;ldquo;Sid Meier&amp;rsquo;s Memoir!&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ldquo;A Life in Computer Games&amp;rdquo;.
And that is exactly what we get:
Sid Meier lists, chronologically and very systematically, all the games he has been working on during his lifetime.
And tells us what happened to him, the game and the game development process while he worked on it.
Somehow that becomes a Memoir, even if some things are only implied or appear out of order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/memoir.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Sid-Meier-ebook/dp/B085845CX9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sid Meier&amp;rsquo;s Memoir!&lt;/a&gt;

, Sid Meier&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Born in 1954, Sid Meier is a prolific writer of computer games.
Together with Bill Stealey, he funded Microprose in 1982, and write a number of flight simulators - among them Solo Flight and F-15 Strike Eagle.
Growing tired of flight sim, he eventually &amp;ldquo;invents&amp;rdquo; the turn based strategy category of games by writing Pirates and Civilization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaving MicroProse after it merged with Spectrum, he funded Firaxis, and was able to pick up the Civilization trademark and some co-developers dissatisfied with MicroProse.
They were able to continue Civilization and turn it into what is has become today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is, as promised, some kind of Memoir and a fun read.
It also gives some insight into Meiers thought processes and what is important to him in game development.
An interesting person, producing an interesting and insightful book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Sid-Meier-ebook/dp/B085845CX9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sid Meier&amp;rsquo;s Memoir!&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Sid Meier, EUR 8.49 on Kindle&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Pattern on the Stone</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/03/fertig-gelesen-the-pattern-on-the-stone.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/03/fertig-gelesen-the-pattern-on-the-stone.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is an old book, from 1998, and much of the technology referred to directly has evolved since then.
But, as this a book that deals with basics, in terms of metaphor and analogy, it is still valuable.
It explains how computers work, and how we make the tech that powers them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/pattern.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/W-Daniel-Hillis-ebook/dp/B06XC774TQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Pattern on the Stone&lt;/a&gt;

, W. Daniel Hillis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computers are really easy.
There is just Zero and One, and it does not get any more complicated than that.
The complexity in Computers and how they work comes instead from using simple rules, making them combinable, and then arranging them into more complicated structures by reusing previous building block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book makes that very clear.
It starts at Zeroes and Ones, and takes the reader on a tour, explaining how we get the things we have (or had, 25 years ago), and how they are made by reusing stuff we build previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/W-Daniel-Hillis-ebook/dp/B06XC774TQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Pattern on the Stone: The Simple Ideas that Make Computers Work&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, W. Daniel Hillis, EUR 9.99 on Kindle&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Undersea Network</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/02/fertig-gelesen-the-undersea-network.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/02/fertig-gelesen-the-undersea-network.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Where is the Internet coming from and how and when was it built?
It&amp;rsquo;s a network of tubes, or rather cables, and these days they are mostly fiber.
Much of it was built during the dotcom boom, but little has been written.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/network.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Nicole-Starosielski-ebook/dp/B00WO58MBI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Undersea Network&lt;/a&gt;

, Nicole Starosielski&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicole Starosielski is a professor at New York University Steinhardt, and specializes in Internet Infrastructure, specifically underwater sea cables.
In her book, she documents the history and development of the infrastructure that carries more than 99% of todays Internet data, the backbone that defines the global transport capacity of the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starosielski not only explores the technology, but also the topography and history of the cables, and of course the policts that follow inevitably if you plug a cable that connects to remote locations.
The book meanders between travel report, history book and sociotechnical politics brief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A companion to the book, the Website &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.surfacing.in/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Surfacing&lt;/a&gt;

 allows the reader to interactively follow and explore the structures the book explains.
Search terms at the beginning of each chapters imagery link the chapter in the book to the interactive display on the Surfacing website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Nicole-Starosielski-ebook/dp/B00WO58MBI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Undersea Network&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Nicole Starosielsky, EUR 19.61 on Kindle&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: AI Superpowers</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-ai-superpowers.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 16:19:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-ai-superpowers.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This 2018 book in some aspects is already outdated: Silicon Valley Techbro Kai-Fu Lee describes what AI is and what he thinks it will do to our future, the nature of work and the job market.
But since then, the worlds view on what AI can and cannot do, what the problems to solve really are and a lot of other things have changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/AI-Superpowers-Silicon-Valley-English-ebook/dp/B0795DNWCF&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/ai-superpowers.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/AI-Superpowers-Silicon-Valley-English-ebook/dp/B0795DNWCF&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;AI Superpowers:China, Silicon Valley, and the New World Order&lt;/a&gt;

, Kai-Fu Lee&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kai-Fu Lee is a Taiwanese born, American computer scientist, and worked at Apple, SGI, Microsoft and Google before becoming a venture capitalist in China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He coined the adage &amp;ldquo;If data is the new oil, then China is the new Saudi Arabia&amp;rdquo; and in the books proposes that China has several advantages over the US in an arms race over artificial intelligence:
Generally training deep learning models seems to be better suited to the Chinese approach of brute forcing a solution than to deep engineering;
China has few data protection regulations getting in the way of data collection;
Chinese startup culture is even more aggressive than the US one; and
the chinese government funds and steers the startup industry in China into the AI of AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lee believes that a number of jobs will be modified or eliminated by a potential AI revolution, including a number of white collar (office) jobs.
The examples he gives are jobs that consist mostly of - in his opinion - simple pattern recognition, such as rough translator, bank loan officer or customer care worker.
Similarly, the blue collar (worker) jobs at risk are truck driver, cashier or clothing factory worker.
In a way, three years later, his estimates look overly optimistic:
Self-driving cars are further away than they looked three years ago, and automated customer care with natural language recognition quickly transformed into the voice-mail hell as ten or twenty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is true is that AI can support human workers a lot in taking the boring parts of these jobs away, helping to provide rough estimates and marking clear cases as such.
Still, AI in 2021 seems to be successful where it augments human workers instead of completely replacing them.
In general, Lee&amp;rsquo;s view of the world is very mechanistic, and way too optimistic in what AI can actually completely solve without having a complete model of the world it acts in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Important input and still a good overview, but overtaken quickly by the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Old Man&#39;s War</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-old-mans-war.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 13:53:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-old-mans-war.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Old-Mans-English-John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B000SEIK2S&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Old Man&amp;rsquo;s War&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; is the first &amp;ldquo;large&amp;rdquo; works by John Scalzi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Old-Mans-English-John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B000SEIK2S&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/oldmanswar.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Old-Mans-English-John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B000SEIK2S&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Old Man&amp;rsquo;s War&lt;/a&gt;

, John Scalzi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plot premise is weird, but simple: Humanity has taken to the stars, but with private enterprise.
Basically all advanced space technology is controlled by the Colonial Union.
Life on earth on the other hand goes on almost as before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Perry enlists to serve in the Colonial Defense Force at the age of 75, to protect humanity, but mostly to have the CU fight the effects of him aging with some unspecified Scifi tech.
He leaves earth and during his induction to the CDF learns that he will be indeed rejuvenated, by transferring his consciousness into a new, young, genetically engineered body tailored for planetary combat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perry&amp;rsquo;s first tour of duty sees battles on a number of CU planets and fights against various interstellar races.
He soon learns that the CU is not actually involved much in galactic politics and has only limited knowledge about the background and motivation of the various space-faring intelligences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fight against the man-eating Rraey leaves him wounded and left for dead on the contested planet Coral.
He is found by a member of the Ghost Brigades,  Jane Sagan, that he thinks looks like a younger version of his deceased wife Kathy, and befriends her.
He learns that Ghost Brigades are synthetic humans created from the DNA scans of CDF volunteers that died before they could join the CDF, but without the memory and experience of their human predecessors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While technically Mil SciFi, and therefore a genre I despise, Scalzi manages to keep the focus the story on the characters and their interactions instead of troop movements and space battles.
He is playing with the themes of generic engineering, encounters with alien races and the discovery of their motivation, and with building a connection to an image of a loved one, but without the memory and the shared experiences.
An engaging book with characters I can relate to, and a story well told.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Old-Mans-English-John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B000SEIK2S&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Old Man&amp;rsquo;s War&lt;/a&gt;

 is continued in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Ghost-Brigades-Mans-Book-English-ebook/dp/B001QS9TSE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Ghost Brigades&lt;/a&gt;

 and in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B000YJ85BI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Last Colony&lt;/a&gt;

, finishing the John Perry&amp;rsquo;s viewpoint books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story of &amp;ldquo;The Last Colony&amp;rdquo; is being retold in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B002ENBLM2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zoe&amp;rsquo;s Tale&lt;/a&gt;

 from another character&amp;rsquo;s viewpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Human-Division-Mans-Book-English-ebook/dp/B00C2RSA9C&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Human Division&lt;/a&gt;

 then continues the original storyline, from another characters point of view, dealing with the aftermath of the revelation of the CU&amp;rsquo;s scheming with earth politics. Humanity finally joins the emerging galactic society and must find a place in one of the various alliances that the different intelligent species begin to form. The resulting diplomatic complications are further told in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B00SEPVPAW&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The End of All Things&lt;/a&gt;

 in a series of Novellas from different character viewpoints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all a series very worthwhile reading, exactly sufficient for one vacation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: These Savage Shores</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-these-savage-shores.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 15:12:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-these-savage-shores.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/therightram&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ram V&lt;/a&gt;

 is a writer, sometimes for comics.
Together with artist Sumit Kumar he wrote a simple story: English Vampires vs. Indian Rakshasa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/These-Savage-Shores-English-Ram-ebook/dp/B07YYNFP38&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/savage.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/These-Savage-Shores-English-Ram-ebook/dp/B07YYNFP38&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;These Savage Shores&lt;/a&gt;

, Ram V &amp;amp; Sumit Kumar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1760&amp;rsquo;ies.
An english vampire puts his peers at risk by not having his desires under control, and is exiled to Calicut, India.
He soon finds out that even older and fiercer beings rule the night: Rakshasa, the Vampire equivalent of Indian Myth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bishan, a Raskshasa, kills the vampire, drawing the english vampires out for revenge.
Before the background of a colonization war in India, Bishan and the vampire master Jurre Granno clash, first in India, then in England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fantastic illustrations, and a complex story well told, with rich metaphors, showing a clash of cultures and the infighting in pre-colonization India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a comic, the kindle edition does not read well on a Kindle, but works fine on Kindle for iPad or similar devices.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: This Is How You Lose The Time War</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 16:01:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Max Gladstone and Amal El-Mohtar co-authored &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/This-How-Lose-Time-English-ebook/dp/B07RTYNHRM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This Is How You Lose The Time-War&lt;/a&gt;

, not exactly a Science Fiction novel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/This-How-Lose-Time-English-ebook/dp/B07RTYNHRM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/time-war.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/This-How-Lose-Time-English-ebook/dp/B07RTYNHRM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This Is How You Lose The Time War&lt;/a&gt;

, Amal El-Mohtar and Max Gladstone&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red and Blue are representatives, spies and saboteurs of two nearly all-powerful, warring factions.
They travel through time to manipulate events at critical points in history in favor of their respective factions.
They are leaving each other messages, they taunt each other, and gradually earn mutual respect.
Eventually they grow close to each other, and love develops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red&amp;rsquo;s commanding officer learns of the interaction and forces Red to leave a message to Blue that kills her.
Red later fixes that &amp;ldquo;problem&amp;rdquo; by traveling into Blue&amp;rsquo;s childhood to give her immunity to the toxic message, and both escape the war by making off to elsewhere in time and space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an epistolary novel, written in the form of the letters Red and Blue exchange.
We only learn very gradually about the characters, their capabilities and their background, and it becomes clear that what we read is not actually the account of two humans, but rather godlike entities or avatars of forces of nature.
Red and Blue over time grow close, and solve an initially unbridgeable conflict between the cultures or forces they represent at a very personal level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a hard read, and if you were looking for an actual Science Fiction story, this isn&amp;rsquo;t one.
Telling a story in the form of letters and having characters that are only remotely human at best is not a good vehicle to create tension, of paint a clear picture of what goes on.
At multiple points the book reads more like some form of poetry as opposed a novel or regular prose.
The storytelling ultimately manages to pull off a somewhat satisfactory ending, though, even if it is visible from almost the very start of the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being so different and not fucking things up of course won the book a number of awards in 2019 and 2020, so there is that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Typeset in the Future</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-typeset-in-the-future.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 13:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-typeset-in-the-future.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dave Addey ran a Tumblr once, titled &amp;ldquo;Typeset in the Future&amp;rdquo;, in which he dissected the typography of Science Fiction films.
This has been turned into the eponymous book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Typeset-Future-Typography-Science-Fiction-ebook/dp/B07G7SGRZ2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/typeset.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Typeset-Future-Typography-Science-Fiction-ebook/dp/B07G7SGRZ2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Typeset in the Future&lt;/a&gt;

, Dave Addey&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2013, Addey nerded out over the fonts in a Science Fiction movie and discovered it was an Eurostile variant (&amp;ldquo;Eurostile Extended Bold&amp;rdquo;).
He started a Tumblr about this, and in great detail went through a number of movies, and about every sign, letter and font used in there.
The Tumblr became quite successful, and he turned the most important posts into a book, adding a lot of images with examples and a number of interviews and essays to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/typeset2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ebook is a joy to read on anything but a Kindle - I did on a 10&amp;quot; iPad, and it worked quite well.
The dead tree edition would make an excellent conversation piece.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: UNIX: A History and a Memoir</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-unix-a-history-and-a-memoir.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 15:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-unix-a-history-and-a-memoir.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The memoir of Brian Kernighan, and the story of how UNIX came to be and what working at Bell Labs was like at that time:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/UNIX-History-English-Brian-Kernighan-ebook/dp/B07ZQHX3R1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UNIX: A History and a Memoir&lt;/a&gt;

 is required reading for anyone who wants to know where Unix concepts came from and what ideas were behind its inception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/UNIX-History-English-Brian-Kernighan-ebook/dp/B07ZQHX3R1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/unix.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/UNIX-History-English-Brian-Kernighan-ebook/dp/B07ZQHX3R1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UNIX: A History and a Memoir&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;quot;, Brian Kernighan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kernighan takes us through the history and the setting of Bell Labs, why it existed and what it did.
He explains the hardware of the time, in terms of size, power and capabilities, and why Bell did get involved into writing an Operating System, and the failure of Multics.
Unix inception and its co-evolution with the C language was a kind of response to the Multics project, at the same time pioneering novel ideas and taking tested salvageable concepts from Multics, making something new and much more useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While he roughly follows the timeline of Unix releases, Kernighan takes short detours, including mini-biographies of his colleagues and the influence they had on the design of the system and the ideas embodied in it.
He finishes with the commercialization of Unix, Unix descendants - BSD, Minix, Linux and Plan 9, and with the closure of Bell Labs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you work with Linux, the C language or any Unix tools, you should read this book to understand where these things came from and what formed this environment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: 88 Names</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-88-names.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 14:18:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-88-names.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It began with a tweet by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/s_bergmann/status/1392518815897030661&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sebastian Bergmann&lt;/a&gt;

, which made me buy &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B07T6938D1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;88 names&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; by Matt Ruff.
The book is a tour of massive multiplayer online role playing games for people who do not play, and also a discussion of identity on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Chu has a small sherpa company, an outfit that helps causal players who have the coin to experience hard content in MMORPGs in an easy and successful way without investing too much time into the game.
Chu is coming out of a relationship with a borderline gamer, Darla, and is being asked by an obviously powerful and demanding anonymous client to be shown several well known MMOs to better understand their genres.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chu is trying to uncover the identity of his client, and comes to believe that he is the North Korean dictator Kim Jong Un.
In the course of his research he learns the real identities of his employees, none of which are what he thought they were, and the real identity of Darla, who is way further past the borderline that he originally assumed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a fun read for me, because it relatively accurately portrays MMOs and online games.
At the same time Ruff&amp;rsquo;s writing very causally avoids Gamer Dudebro stereotypes and shows that people playing video games are way more diverse than their cliche.
If you ever have had your Internet spaceship refueled by a 60+ year old english granny and ex-schoolteacher you will understand exactly what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B07T6938D1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;88 Names&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Matt Ruff&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: A Kim Jong-Il Production</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-a-kim-jong-il-production.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 14:52:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-a-kim-jong-il-production.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Paul Fischer writes &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B00OMH54L2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;A Kim Jong-Il Production&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, a documentary the 1978 abduction of the famous South Korean actress Madam Choi, and her ex-husband, the filmmaker Shin Sang-Ok.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before becoming the leader of North Korea, Kim Jong-Il headed the Ministry for Propaganda.
Dissatisfied with the talent available, he had the famous actress Choi Eun-Hee kidnammed.
When her ex-husband started to investigate, he had him kidnapped in Hong Kong and transported to North Korea by ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together, they made &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abduction_of_Shin_Sang-ok_and_Choi_Eun-hee#Films&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;seven films&lt;/a&gt;

 for Kim Jong-Il, gaining his trust.
During a research trip in Vienna they fled to the US embassy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book uses &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abduction_of_Shin_Sang-ok_and_Choi_Eun-hee&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this true story&lt;/a&gt;

 to shed a light on life in North Korea, and to explain how it became the hermetically sealed country it is today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seventh film of Choi and Shin, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eCKSR0JArUQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pulgasari&lt;/a&gt;

, can be found on Youtube with english subtitles. It is a Godzilla-like monster tale, in which a rice toy of a blacksmiths daugther comes to life and turns into a giant metal-eating monster fighting for the rights of poor farmers in feudal Korea. When the monster eventually turns aganst the farmers, the blacksmiths daugther sacrifices herself killing the monster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goes well with &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-88-names.html&#34;&gt;88 Names&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Mara und der Feuerbringer</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-mara-und-der-feuerbringer.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 12:51:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-mara-und-der-feuerbringer.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tommmy Krappweis ist nicht nur der Schöpfer von &amp;ldquo;Bernd, das Brot&amp;rdquo;, sondern auch ein Musiker, Stuntman, Filmemacher und Autor diverser Bücher.
In der Trilogie um &amp;ldquo;Mara und der Feuerbringer&amp;rdquo; nimmt er uns mit in die Geschichten um die 14-jährige Münchnerin Mara Lorbeer in der Welt der nordischen Sagen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B07RHCGD95&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/08/mara1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B07RHCGD95&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mara und der Feuerbringer&lt;/a&gt;

, Band 1&amp;quot;, Tommy Krappweis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mara Lorbeer ist 14, Scheidungskind und lebt bei ihrer esoterisch angehauchten Mutter in München.
Während der Rückreise von einem Baum-Umwarmungs-Seminar, auf das sie ihre Mutter mitgeschleppt hat, wird sie von einem sprechenden Zweig angesprochen, der ihr mitteilt, daß sie eine germanische Seherin ist, die den Weltuntergang, Ragnarök, verhindern muß.
Im Fortgang der Geschichte freundet sich Mara mit verschiedenen Personen an: dem Professor für germanische Mythologie Reinhold Weissinger, seiner Ex-Frau Stefanie Warnatzsch-Abra, SIegfried dem Drachentöter, dem nordischen Gott.
Zusammen treten sie gegen Loge, den Feuerbringer, den mysteriösen Dr. Thurisaz, und den Drachen Nidhöggr.
Über drei Bände entfaltet sich um Mara der Kampf der Guten gegen die Bösen im Reich der nordischen Mythologie, während sich im Weltlichen die Beziehung von Mara zu ihrer Mutter klärt und Mara zugleich lernt, sich selbst besser zu definieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mara und der Feuerbringer&amp;rdquo; ist nicht nur eine Tour durch die nordische Mythologie und wie sie sich in unserer heutigen Welt wiederspiegelt, sondern auch eine Comig-of-Age Geschichte, bunt und leicht anarchisch erzählt, wie man es von Tommy Krappweis erwarten kann.
Nicht nur für Jugendliche eine wunderbare Erzählung.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B07RHCGD95&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mara und der Feuerbringer&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Tommy Krappweis, EUR 9.99 pro Band.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

