<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>book on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/book.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in book on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2022 21:45:14 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/book/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Crafting Interpreters</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/16/fertig-gelesen-crafting-interpreters.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/16/fertig-gelesen-crafting-interpreters.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Robert Nystrom is a language developer who works at Google on the Dart programming language.
In his book &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Robert-Nystrom-ebook/dp/B09YLQSGKL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Crafting Interpreters&lt;/a&gt;

 he explains lexing, parsing and executing a programming language in an accessible way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Robert-Nystrom-ebook/dp/B09YLQSGKL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/crafting-interpreters.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Robert-Nystrom-ebook/dp/B09YLQSGKL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Crafting Interpreters&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;quot;, Robert Nystrom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nystrom sets out with the (correct) observation that the matter of handling and executing code is a complex topic that is not made easier with all the theory that surrounds it.
In his book, he takes the reader on a journey to implement a toy language, Lox, two times.
First with a tree walker execution algorithm, not unlike PHP 3 or early Ruby.
Then, again, with a bytecode executor written in C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book starts out by defining an intentionally very basic, but complete programming language, and then chapter by chapter builds the infrastructure to scan, parse and execute the code.
All explanations are very practical and on the code, but a lot of boxes, asides and cross-references make the theory behind all this discoverable, while at the same time keeping it out of the way.
One of the nicest and most practical introductions to programming language interpretation and compilation that I have seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Robert-Nystrom-ebook/dp/B09YLQSGKL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Crafting Interpreters&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Robert Nystrom, EUR 25.84&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Fietsparkeren bij Stations</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/07/fertig-gelesen-fietsparkeren-bij-stations.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/07/fertig-gelesen-fietsparkeren-bij-stations.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Netherlands realized around 2000 that they have a problem with bike parking around train stations, and with parking around stations in general.
A program was set up to fix that, assuming things would be done with in ten years.
The program was a great success, and people taking the bike to use the train, and to use a bike after they arrived at their destination by train increased greatly.
This created more needs, and so the program is, changed, still active today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Folkert-Piersma/dp/9068688286&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fietsparkeren bij Stations&lt;/a&gt;

, Folkert Piersma and Wout Ritzema&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book talks, in one chapter each, about analyzing customer needs, the history of the program, guidelines and goals, the plannning process, typical bike parking facilities, architecture and design, investment costs, facility operations, technical resources, innovative solutions and finally an outlook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effect of all this can be seen around about any dutch train stations:
Not only is the sea of bikes around the train stations gone despite more people arriving by bike at the train than ever before,  also the quality of the area around the train stations improved.
The dark and seedy underpasses and the general feeling of insecurity around many train stations areas in other cities is not present here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book explains how all of this is not an accidental outcome, but the result of a process that has been run for two decades with clear goals, working evaluation and continous improvement.
A must read for anybody interested in infrastructure at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Folkert-Piersma/dp/9068688286&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fietsparkeren bij Stations&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Folkert Piersma and Wout Ritzema, EUR 29.40 Hardcover&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Pale Rider</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/06/fertig-gelesen-pale-rider.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/06/fertig-gelesen-pale-rider.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A book from 2017, about the Spanish Flu, which in the wake of the first world war turned into a global pandemic, killing between 50 and 100 million people on all continents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/pale-rider.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Laura-Spinney-ebook/dp/B01GH07CG6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pale Rider&lt;/a&gt;

, Laura Spinney&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spinney describes the situation in the world in 1918, and how the Spanish Flu came into the world, and was experienced by people in various parts of the world.
The flu returned in several waves, some of which behaved unlike normal flu seasons and also had weirdly shaped killing patterns in the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also describes reactions of the population to pandemic fighting measures &amp;ndash; and we know them all from personal experience by now.
There have been people protecting mask mandates, self-isolation and social distancing on purpose, &amp;ldquo;mah freedums&amp;rdquo; criers and so on, just like with Covid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In parts 5 and 6, she looks at the flu from a modern perspective:
We now know about viruses, and specific the influenza A virus and its variants.
We understand its genetics and which parts of the virus are relevant for infection of humans, and they mutate.
We catalogue them &amp;ndash; the spanish flu was H1N1.
Spinney then looks at SARS, MERS and bird flu, and other viruses, and how they ramp up for another pandemic, strangely prescient of the Covid pandemic of 2020.
Also addresses, again spot on, anti-science propaganda and ossified politics unable to integrate new findings into existing rule frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An enlightening and at the same time very frustrating read, written and published 3 years before Covid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Laura-Spinney-ebook/dp/B01GH07CG6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pale Rider&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Laura Spinney, EUR 9.49 on Kindle&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Kaiju Preservation Society</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/05/fertig-gelesen-the-kaiju-preservation-society.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/05/fertig-gelesen-the-kaiju-preservation-society.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On an alternate earth alternate biology produces beings that can grow up to 150 meters tall and that are powered by natural biological nuclear reactor: The Kaiju.
Whenever anything, humans or Kaiju, uses nuclear energy, the boundary between the alternate realities is weakened and things can cross over.
That happened the first time late in the second world war, and that is how the legend of Godzilla came into the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B09DD2DK5Z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/kps.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B09DD2DK5Z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Kaiju Preservation Society&lt;/a&gt;

, John Scalzi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s Covid times, it&amp;rsquo;s New York, and Jamie got fired from his management position of a delivery service and has to deliver things himself now.
Doing that, he meets an old acquaintance of him, which offers him a&amp;hellip; different job.
The job turns out to involve secrecy, a dimensional portal and working in an alternate world in which he meets things that usually live in SciFi novels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a fun read, from a fun Scalzi from earlier times woken up again.
Doubly so when contrasted with the rather exhausting Interdependency.
Action, Dad joke puns and an improbable premise delivered masterfully, with the parts clicking nicely into each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A strong recommendation, and time well spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B09DD2DK5Z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Kaiju Preservation Society&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, John Scalzi, EUR 8.99 on Kindle&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Sid Meier&#39;s Memoir!</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/04/fertig-gelesen-sid-meier-memoir.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/04/fertig-gelesen-sid-meier-memoir.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The subtitle of &amp;ldquo;Sid Meier&amp;rsquo;s Memoir!&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ldquo;A Life in Computer Games&amp;rdquo;.
And that is exactly what we get:
Sid Meier lists, chronologically and very systematically, all the games he has been working on during his lifetime.
And tells us what happened to him, the game and the game development process while he worked on it.
Somehow that becomes a Memoir, even if some things are only implied or appear out of order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/memoir.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Sid-Meier-ebook/dp/B085845CX9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sid Meier&amp;rsquo;s Memoir!&lt;/a&gt;

, Sid Meier&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Born in 1954, Sid Meier is a prolific writer of computer games.
Together with Bill Stealey, he funded Microprose in 1982, and write a number of flight simulators - among them Solo Flight and F-15 Strike Eagle.
Growing tired of flight sim, he eventually &amp;ldquo;invents&amp;rdquo; the turn based strategy category of games by writing Pirates and Civilization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaving MicroProse after it merged with Spectrum, he funded Firaxis, and was able to pick up the Civilization trademark and some co-developers dissatisfied with MicroProse.
They were able to continue Civilization and turn it into what is has become today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is, as promised, some kind of Memoir and a fun read.
It also gives some insight into Meiers thought processes and what is important to him in game development.
An interesting person, producing an interesting and insightful book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Sid-Meier-ebook/dp/B085845CX9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sid Meier&amp;rsquo;s Memoir!&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Sid Meier, EUR 8.49 on Kindle&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Pattern on the Stone</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/03/fertig-gelesen-the-pattern-on-the-stone.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/03/fertig-gelesen-the-pattern-on-the-stone.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is an old book, from 1998, and much of the technology referred to directly has evolved since then.
But, as this a book that deals with basics, in terms of metaphor and analogy, it is still valuable.
It explains how computers work, and how we make the tech that powers them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/pattern.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/W-Daniel-Hillis-ebook/dp/B06XC774TQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Pattern on the Stone&lt;/a&gt;

, W. Daniel Hillis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computers are really easy.
There is just Zero and One, and it does not get any more complicated than that.
The complexity in Computers and how they work comes instead from using simple rules, making them combinable, and then arranging them into more complicated structures by reusing previous building block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book makes that very clear.
It starts at Zeroes and Ones, and takes the reader on a tour, explaining how we get the things we have (or had, 25 years ago), and how they are made by reusing stuff we build previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/W-Daniel-Hillis-ebook/dp/B06XC774TQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Pattern on the Stone: The Simple Ideas that Make Computers Work&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, W. Daniel Hillis, EUR 9.99 on Kindle&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Undersea Network</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/02/fertig-gelesen-the-undersea-network.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/02/fertig-gelesen-the-undersea-network.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Where is the Internet coming from and how and when was it built?
It&amp;rsquo;s a network of tubes, or rather cables, and these days they are mostly fiber.
Much of it was built during the dotcom boom, but little has been written.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/network.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Nicole-Starosielski-ebook/dp/B00WO58MBI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Undersea Network&lt;/a&gt;

, Nicole Starosielski&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicole Starosielski is a professor at New York University Steinhardt, and specializes in Internet Infrastructure, specifically underwater sea cables.
In her book, she documents the history and development of the infrastructure that carries more than 99% of todays Internet data, the backbone that defines the global transport capacity of the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starosielski not only explores the technology, but also the topography and history of the cables, and of course the policts that follow inevitably if you plug a cable that connects to remote locations.
The book meanders between travel report, history book and sociotechnical politics brief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A companion to the book, the Website &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.surfacing.in/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Surfacing&lt;/a&gt;

 allows the reader to interactively follow and explore the structures the book explains.
Search terms at the beginning of each chapters imagery link the chapter in the book to the interactive display on the Surfacing website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Nicole-Starosielski-ebook/dp/B00WO58MBI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Undersea Network&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Nicole Starosielsky, EUR 19.61 on Kindle&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: AI Superpowers</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-ai-superpowers.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 16:19:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-ai-superpowers.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This 2018 book in some aspects is already outdated: Silicon Valley Techbro Kai-Fu Lee describes what AI is and what he thinks it will do to our future, the nature of work and the job market.
But since then, the worlds view on what AI can and cannot do, what the problems to solve really are and a lot of other things have changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/AI-Superpowers-Silicon-Valley-English-ebook/dp/B0795DNWCF&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/ai-superpowers.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/AI-Superpowers-Silicon-Valley-English-ebook/dp/B0795DNWCF&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;AI Superpowers:China, Silicon Valley, and the New World Order&lt;/a&gt;

, Kai-Fu Lee&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kai-Fu Lee is a Taiwanese born, American computer scientist, and worked at Apple, SGI, Microsoft and Google before becoming a venture capitalist in China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He coined the adage &amp;ldquo;If data is the new oil, then China is the new Saudi Arabia&amp;rdquo; and in the books proposes that China has several advantages over the US in an arms race over artificial intelligence:
Generally training deep learning models seems to be better suited to the Chinese approach of brute forcing a solution than to deep engineering;
China has few data protection regulations getting in the way of data collection;
Chinese startup culture is even more aggressive than the US one; and
the chinese government funds and steers the startup industry in China into the AI of AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lee believes that a number of jobs will be modified or eliminated by a potential AI revolution, including a number of white collar (office) jobs.
The examples he gives are jobs that consist mostly of - in his opinion - simple pattern recognition, such as rough translator, bank loan officer or customer care worker.
Similarly, the blue collar (worker) jobs at risk are truck driver, cashier or clothing factory worker.
In a way, three years later, his estimates look overly optimistic:
Self-driving cars are further away than they looked three years ago, and automated customer care with natural language recognition quickly transformed into the voice-mail hell as ten or twenty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is true is that AI can support human workers a lot in taking the boring parts of these jobs away, helping to provide rough estimates and marking clear cases as such.
Still, AI in 2021 seems to be successful where it augments human workers instead of completely replacing them.
In general, Lee&amp;rsquo;s view of the world is very mechanistic, and way too optimistic in what AI can actually completely solve without having a complete model of the world it acts in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Important input and still a good overview, but overtaken quickly by the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Old Man&#39;s War</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-old-mans-war.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 13:53:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-old-mans-war.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Old-Mans-English-John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B000SEIK2S&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Old Man&amp;rsquo;s War&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; is the first &amp;ldquo;large&amp;rdquo; works by John Scalzi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Old-Mans-English-John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B000SEIK2S&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/oldmanswar.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Old-Mans-English-John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B000SEIK2S&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Old Man&amp;rsquo;s War&lt;/a&gt;

, John Scalzi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plot premise is weird, but simple: Humanity has taken to the stars, but with private enterprise.
Basically all advanced space technology is controlled by the Colonial Union.
Life on earth on the other hand goes on almost as before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Perry enlists to serve in the Colonial Defense Force at the age of 75, to protect humanity, but mostly to have the CU fight the effects of him aging with some unspecified Scifi tech.
He leaves earth and during his induction to the CDF learns that he will be indeed rejuvenated, by transferring his consciousness into a new, young, genetically engineered body tailored for planetary combat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perry&amp;rsquo;s first tour of duty sees battles on a number of CU planets and fights against various interstellar races.
He soon learns that the CU is not actually involved much in galactic politics and has only limited knowledge about the background and motivation of the various space-faring intelligences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fight against the man-eating Rraey leaves him wounded and left for dead on the contested planet Coral.
He is found by a member of the Ghost Brigades,  Jane Sagan, that he thinks looks like a younger version of his deceased wife Kathy, and befriends her.
He learns that Ghost Brigades are synthetic humans created from the DNA scans of CDF volunteers that died before they could join the CDF, but without the memory and experience of their human predecessors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While technically Mil SciFi, and therefore a genre I despise, Scalzi manages to keep the focus the story on the characters and their interactions instead of troop movements and space battles.
He is playing with the themes of generic engineering, encounters with alien races and the discovery of their motivation, and with building a connection to an image of a loved one, but without the memory and the shared experiences.
An engaging book with characters I can relate to, and a story well told.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Old-Mans-English-John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B000SEIK2S&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Old Man&amp;rsquo;s War&lt;/a&gt;

 is continued in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Ghost-Brigades-Mans-Book-English-ebook/dp/B001QS9TSE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Ghost Brigades&lt;/a&gt;

 and in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B000YJ85BI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Last Colony&lt;/a&gt;

, finishing the John Perry&amp;rsquo;s viewpoint books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story of &amp;ldquo;The Last Colony&amp;rdquo; is being retold in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B002ENBLM2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zoe&amp;rsquo;s Tale&lt;/a&gt;

 from another character&amp;rsquo;s viewpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Human-Division-Mans-Book-English-ebook/dp/B00C2RSA9C&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Human Division&lt;/a&gt;

 then continues the original storyline, from another characters point of view, dealing with the aftermath of the revelation of the CU&amp;rsquo;s scheming with earth politics. Humanity finally joins the emerging galactic society and must find a place in one of the various alliances that the different intelligent species begin to form. The resulting diplomatic complications are further told in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B00SEPVPAW&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The End of All Things&lt;/a&gt;

 in a series of Novellas from different character viewpoints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all a series very worthwhile reading, exactly sufficient for one vacation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: These Savage Shores</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-these-savage-shores.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 15:12:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-these-savage-shores.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/therightram&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ram V&lt;/a&gt;

 is a writer, sometimes for comics.
Together with artist Sumit Kumar he wrote a simple story: English Vampires vs. Indian Rakshasa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/These-Savage-Shores-English-Ram-ebook/dp/B07YYNFP38&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/savage.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/These-Savage-Shores-English-Ram-ebook/dp/B07YYNFP38&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;These Savage Shores&lt;/a&gt;

, Ram V &amp;amp; Sumit Kumar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1760&amp;rsquo;ies.
An english vampire puts his peers at risk by not having his desires under control, and is exiled to Calicut, India.
He soon finds out that even older and fiercer beings rule the night: Rakshasa, the Vampire equivalent of Indian Myth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bishan, a Raskshasa, kills the vampire, drawing the english vampires out for revenge.
Before the background of a colonization war in India, Bishan and the vampire master Jurre Granno clash, first in India, then in England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fantastic illustrations, and a complex story well told, with rich metaphors, showing a clash of cultures and the infighting in pre-colonization India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a comic, the kindle edition does not read well on a Kindle, but works fine on Kindle for iPad or similar devices.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: This Is How You Lose The Time War</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 16:01:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Max Gladstone and Amal El-Mohtar co-authored &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/This-How-Lose-Time-English-ebook/dp/B07RTYNHRM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This Is How You Lose The Time-War&lt;/a&gt;

, not exactly a Science Fiction novel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/This-How-Lose-Time-English-ebook/dp/B07RTYNHRM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/time-war.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/This-How-Lose-Time-English-ebook/dp/B07RTYNHRM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This Is How You Lose The Time War&lt;/a&gt;

, Amal El-Mohtar and Max Gladstone&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red and Blue are representatives, spies and saboteurs of two nearly all-powerful, warring factions.
They travel through time to manipulate events at critical points in history in favor of their respective factions.
They are leaving each other messages, they taunt each other, and gradually earn mutual respect.
Eventually they grow close to each other, and love develops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red&amp;rsquo;s commanding officer learns of the interaction and forces Red to leave a message to Blue that kills her.
Red later fixes that &amp;ldquo;problem&amp;rdquo; by traveling into Blue&amp;rsquo;s childhood to give her immunity to the toxic message, and both escape the war by making off to elsewhere in time and space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an epistolary novel, written in the form of the letters Red and Blue exchange.
We only learn very gradually about the characters, their capabilities and their background, and it becomes clear that what we read is not actually the account of two humans, but rather godlike entities or avatars of forces of nature.
Red and Blue over time grow close, and solve an initially unbridgeable conflict between the cultures or forces they represent at a very personal level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a hard read, and if you were looking for an actual Science Fiction story, this isn&amp;rsquo;t one.
Telling a story in the form of letters and having characters that are only remotely human at best is not a good vehicle to create tension, of paint a clear picture of what goes on.
At multiple points the book reads more like some form of poetry as opposed a novel or regular prose.
The storytelling ultimately manages to pull off a somewhat satisfactory ending, though, even if it is visible from almost the very start of the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being so different and not fucking things up of course won the book a number of awards in 2019 and 2020, so there is that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Typeset in the Future</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-typeset-in-the-future.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 13:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-typeset-in-the-future.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dave Addey ran a Tumblr once, titled &amp;ldquo;Typeset in the Future&amp;rdquo;, in which he dissected the typography of Science Fiction films.
This has been turned into the eponymous book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Typeset-Future-Typography-Science-Fiction-ebook/dp/B07G7SGRZ2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/typeset.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Typeset-Future-Typography-Science-Fiction-ebook/dp/B07G7SGRZ2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Typeset in the Future&lt;/a&gt;

, Dave Addey&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2013, Addey nerded out over the fonts in a Science Fiction movie and discovered it was an Eurostile variant (&amp;ldquo;Eurostile Extended Bold&amp;rdquo;).
He started a Tumblr about this, and in great detail went through a number of movies, and about every sign, letter and font used in there.
The Tumblr became quite successful, and he turned the most important posts into a book, adding a lot of images with examples and a number of interviews and essays to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/typeset2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ebook is a joy to read on anything but a Kindle - I did on a 10&amp;quot; iPad, and it worked quite well.
The dead tree edition would make an excellent conversation piece.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: UNIX: A History and a Memoir</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-unix-a-history-and-a-memoir.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 15:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-unix-a-history-and-a-memoir.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The memoir of Brian Kernighan, and the story of how UNIX came to be and what working at Bell Labs was like at that time:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/UNIX-History-English-Brian-Kernighan-ebook/dp/B07ZQHX3R1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UNIX: A History and a Memoir&lt;/a&gt;

 is required reading for anyone who wants to know where Unix concepts came from and what ideas were behind its inception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/UNIX-History-English-Brian-Kernighan-ebook/dp/B07ZQHX3R1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/unix.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/UNIX-History-English-Brian-Kernighan-ebook/dp/B07ZQHX3R1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UNIX: A History and a Memoir&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;quot;, Brian Kernighan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kernighan takes us through the history and the setting of Bell Labs, why it existed and what it did.
He explains the hardware of the time, in terms of size, power and capabilities, and why Bell did get involved into writing an Operating System, and the failure of Multics.
Unix inception and its co-evolution with the C language was a kind of response to the Multics project, at the same time pioneering novel ideas and taking tested salvageable concepts from Multics, making something new and much more useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While he roughly follows the timeline of Unix releases, Kernighan takes short detours, including mini-biographies of his colleagues and the influence they had on the design of the system and the ideas embodied in it.
He finishes with the commercialization of Unix, Unix descendants - BSD, Minix, Linux and Plan 9, and with the closure of Bell Labs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you work with Linux, the C language or any Unix tools, you should read this book to understand where these things came from and what formed this environment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: 88 Names</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-88-names.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 14:18:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-88-names.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It began with a tweet by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/s_bergmann/status/1392518815897030661&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sebastian Bergmann&lt;/a&gt;

, which made me buy &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B07T6938D1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;88 names&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; by Matt Ruff.
The book is a tour of massive multiplayer online role playing games for people who do not play, and also a discussion of identity on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Chu has a small sherpa company, an outfit that helps causal players who have the coin to experience hard content in MMORPGs in an easy and successful way without investing too much time into the game.
Chu is coming out of a relationship with a borderline gamer, Darla, and is being asked by an obviously powerful and demanding anonymous client to be shown several well known MMOs to better understand their genres.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chu is trying to uncover the identity of his client, and comes to believe that he is the North Korean dictator Kim Jong Un.
In the course of his research he learns the real identities of his employees, none of which are what he thought they were, and the real identity of Darla, who is way further past the borderline that he originally assumed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a fun read for me, because it relatively accurately portrays MMOs and online games.
At the same time Ruff&amp;rsquo;s writing very causally avoids Gamer Dudebro stereotypes and shows that people playing video games are way more diverse than their cliche.
If you ever have had your Internet spaceship refueled by a 60+ year old english granny and ex-schoolteacher you will understand exactly what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B07T6938D1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;88 Names&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Matt Ruff&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: A Kim Jong-Il Production</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-a-kim-jong-il-production.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 14:52:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-a-kim-jong-il-production.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Paul Fischer writes &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B00OMH54L2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;A Kim Jong-Il Production&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, a documentary the 1978 abduction of the famous South Korean actress Madam Choi, and her ex-husband, the filmmaker Shin Sang-Ok.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before becoming the leader of North Korea, Kim Jong-Il headed the Ministry for Propaganda.
Dissatisfied with the talent available, he had the famous actress Choi Eun-Hee kidnammed.
When her ex-husband started to investigate, he had him kidnapped in Hong Kong and transported to North Korea by ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together, they made &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abduction_of_Shin_Sang-ok_and_Choi_Eun-hee#Films&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;seven films&lt;/a&gt;

 for Kim Jong-Il, gaining his trust.
During a research trip in Vienna they fled to the US embassy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book uses &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abduction_of_Shin_Sang-ok_and_Choi_Eun-hee&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this true story&lt;/a&gt;

 to shed a light on life in North Korea, and to explain how it became the hermetically sealed country it is today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seventh film of Choi and Shin, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eCKSR0JArUQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pulgasari&lt;/a&gt;

, can be found on Youtube with english subtitles. It is a Godzilla-like monster tale, in which a rice toy of a blacksmiths daugther comes to life and turns into a giant metal-eating monster fighting for the rights of poor farmers in feudal Korea. When the monster eventually turns aganst the farmers, the blacksmiths daugther sacrifices herself killing the monster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goes well with &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-88-names.html&#34;&gt;88 Names&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Mara und der Feuerbringer</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-mara-und-der-feuerbringer.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 12:51:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-mara-und-der-feuerbringer.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tommmy Krappweis ist nicht nur der Schöpfer von &amp;ldquo;Bernd, das Brot&amp;rdquo;, sondern auch ein Musiker, Stuntman, Filmemacher und Autor diverser Bücher.
In der Trilogie um &amp;ldquo;Mara und der Feuerbringer&amp;rdquo; nimmt er uns mit in die Geschichten um die 14-jährige Münchnerin Mara Lorbeer in der Welt der nordischen Sagen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B07RHCGD95&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/08/mara1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B07RHCGD95&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mara und der Feuerbringer&lt;/a&gt;

, Band 1&amp;quot;, Tommy Krappweis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mara Lorbeer ist 14, Scheidungskind und lebt bei ihrer esoterisch angehauchten Mutter in München.
Während der Rückreise von einem Baum-Umwarmungs-Seminar, auf das sie ihre Mutter mitgeschleppt hat, wird sie von einem sprechenden Zweig angesprochen, der ihr mitteilt, daß sie eine germanische Seherin ist, die den Weltuntergang, Ragnarök, verhindern muß.
Im Fortgang der Geschichte freundet sich Mara mit verschiedenen Personen an: dem Professor für germanische Mythologie Reinhold Weissinger, seiner Ex-Frau Stefanie Warnatzsch-Abra, SIegfried dem Drachentöter, dem nordischen Gott.
Zusammen treten sie gegen Loge, den Feuerbringer, den mysteriösen Dr. Thurisaz, und den Drachen Nidhöggr.
Über drei Bände entfaltet sich um Mara der Kampf der Guten gegen die Bösen im Reich der nordischen Mythologie, während sich im Weltlichen die Beziehung von Mara zu ihrer Mutter klärt und Mara zugleich lernt, sich selbst besser zu definieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mara und der Feuerbringer&amp;rdquo; ist nicht nur eine Tour durch die nordische Mythologie und wie sie sich in unserer heutigen Welt wiederspiegelt, sondern auch eine Comig-of-Age Geschichte, bunt und leicht anarchisch erzählt, wie man es von Tommy Krappweis erwarten kann.
Nicht nur für Jugendliche eine wunderbare Erzählung.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B07RHCGD95&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mara und der Feuerbringer&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Tommy Krappweis, EUR 9.99 pro Band.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Merchant Princes Omnibus</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/07/28/fertig-gelesen-the-merchant-princes-omnibus.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jul 2021 09:48:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/07/28/fertig-gelesen-the-merchant-princes-omnibus.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Charles Stross &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/kindle/series/B00WKNMLD4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Merchant Princes&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; series of six books is another &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sliders&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sliders&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; type of story, with the usual Stross-like twist.
The story follows Miriam Beckstein, a woman who thinks she is a tech journalist.
Miriam falls off a chair while looking at a strange pattern, and finds herself in a medival parallel earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/kindle/series/B00WKNMLD4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/07/merchant-princes.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/kindle/series/B00WKNMLD4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Merchant Princes Omnibus&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;quot;, Charles Stross&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the course of the story, Miriam learns that she is actually from this parallel earth, and really is the Countess Helge Thorold-Hjorth in the kingdom of Gruinmarkt, which sits in the place of her world lines Boston.
Her relatives and the other members of the six clans have the unique ability of walking between worlds, which they apparently abuse to work as uncatchable drug and money couriers in our world.
World walking involves looking at a specific pattern, which seems to activate a heritable genetic trait in their brains that make them shift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the course of the story we learn a lot about this ability:
The pattern seems to control the linked universes, the ability to walk between worlds seems to be bioengineered into the clans, but the how, who and when are unknown.
There seem to be more parallel worlds, which open up as the story unfolds, and also the mythical &amp;ldquo;lost clan&amp;rdquo; is found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things are becoming really complicated as the world of the lost clan, &amp;ldquo;New Britain&amp;rdquo;&amp;quot;, is discovered.
Miriam flees to this world, which is technologically somewhere in the 1920, and fuels a communist, anti-monarchist revolution by importing gold and ideas into this world.
Meanwhile, the clans activities on our world are becoming known to the US government, which desperately wants to get hold of worldwalkers to understand and duplicate their abilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fourth world is being discovered, in which a technologically advanced humanity died out for unknown reasons, and which currently is in the grips of an ice-age.
And in a bit of foreshadowing, a fifth world is being discovered, in which earth is gone, and something else is found instead that resembles a black hole surrounded by unidentified energetic flares.
While the clan struggles with an infight between the conservative and progressive factions, the US government finds a way to world-walk into Gruinmarkt and systematically nukes this world to secure access to the untapped oil reserves in this parallel universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story is continued in another trilogy, &amp;ldquo;Empire Games&amp;rdquo;, which is set 17 years later.
The conflicts started in the original series are being played out further, and the mysterious black hole from the fifth world is being activated by accident.
The final part of this trilogy will be published this year, End of September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Merchant Princes&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Empire Games&amp;rdquo; writing and storytelling is everything you would expect from Stross, so time and money well spent.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Outland</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/07/23/fertig-gelesen-outland.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jul 2021 09:00:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/07/23/fertig-gelesen-outland.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Outland-Dennis-Taylor-ebook/dp/B07TP6TKP1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Outland&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; is the first book by Dennis E. Taylor, preceding the Bobiverse and also &amp;ldquo;The Singularity Trap&amp;rdquo;.
It is a &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sliders&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sliders&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; storyline, much like &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2016/02/28/fertig-gelesen-the-long-earth.html&#34;&gt;Pratchett&amp;rsquo;s and Baxter&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Long Earth&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;

, in which our heroes discover a parallel dimension with a seemingly uninhabited earth, and then need to colonize it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Outland-Dennis-Taylor-ebook/dp/B07TP6TKP1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/07/outland.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Outland-Dennis-Taylor-ebook/dp/B07TP6TKP1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Outland&lt;/a&gt;

, Dennis E. Taylor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dennis E. Taylor is a computer programmer writing Scifi, and had problems finding a publisher for his debut novel, &amp;ldquo;Outland&amp;rdquo;, in 2015, so he self-published.
The story was intended as the introduction to a series of books, &amp;ldquo;World Lines&amp;rdquo;.
The original novel was withdrawn in 2018, extensively reworked, and re-publshed in 2019 as a standalone book, which is the version linked in this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story follows an ensemble cast of students that through a failed physics experiment manage to open a dimensional portal into a parallel earth, which differs from this earth mostly in that it is seemingly uninhabited.
While the students come up with schemes to get rich quick by mining gold in the parallel earth and somehow selling it locally, a global catastrophe strikes:
The Yellowstone Supervolcano activates, covering most of the United States in ashfall and changing climate globally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our students now use the portal to evacuate a number of people to start a colony in the wilderness of their parallel earth.
But bootstrapping human civilization from basically nothing with contemporary humans seems to be harder and more dangerous than anybody thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original book showcased early Dennis E. Taylor, but unpolished. The nerd humor and the the writing style were already somewhat there, but the characters were flat and a lot of things were still raw.
The rewrite fixes this, and also makes the book more standalone, while still letting the door open to optional sequels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Outland-Dennis-Taylor-ebook/dp/B07TP6TKP1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Outland&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; by Dennis E. Taylor, EUR 4.39, also on Kinde unlimited.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Montecrypto</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/06/05/fertig-gelesen-montecrypto.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 20:54:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/06/05/fertig-gelesen-montecrypto.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Wir hatten hier in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/#review&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;den Reviews&lt;/a&gt;


schon eine ganze Menge Tom Hillenbrand: &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2014/08/11/fertig-gelesen-drachenvater.html&#34;&gt;Drachenväter&lt;/a&gt;

, &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2014/08/17/fertig-gelesen-drohnenland.html&#34;&gt;Drohnenland&lt;/a&gt;

, und &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2015/11/29/fertig-gelesen-die-drohnen-des-monsieur-leclerq.html&#34;&gt;Die Drohnen des Monsieur Leclerq&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das aktuelle Buch von Tom Hillenbrand ist &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/dp/3462001574&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Montecrypto&lt;/a&gt;

, das sich mit dem Hype um Cryptocurrencies beschäftigt und eine Art &amp;ldquo;Der Graf von Monte Cristo&amp;rdquo;-Geschichte erzählt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/dp/3462001574&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/06/montecrypto.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/dp/3462001574&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Montecrypto&lt;/a&gt;

, von Tom Hillenbrand&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gregory Hollister, ein reicher Investor, ist verstorben. Angeblich hat er noch eine große Menge Geld, und dieses ist in Bitcoin angelegt und irgendwo versteckt. Wo genau, ist unklar, und so bekommt der Finanzdetektiv Ed Dante von Hollisters Schwester den Auftrag, den verschwundenen Schatz zu identifizieren und aufzuspüren. Dante setzt dabei aus Versehen ein auf dem Computer von Hollister installiertes Script in Gang, das eine weltweite Schatzsuche inszeniert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doch es stellt sich heraus, daß die Geschichte um das Ableben von Hollister weitaus komplizierter ist, denn Hollister hat auch noch eine andere, wesentlich kontrolliertere Cryptowährung ins Leben gerufen und am Ende ist alles ein Racheplot in einem Racheplot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gewohnt gute Kost von Hillenbrand. Schnell und spannend durchzulesen, flott inszeniert und aktuelle Themen aufgreifend. Ich habe mich gut unterhalten gefühlt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Montecrypto&amp;rdquo;, Tom Hillenbrand, Eur 12.99&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Black Count</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/06/05/fertig-gelesen-the-black-count.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 21:36:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/06/05/fertig-gelesen-the-black-count.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another Monte-Cristo-themed book, Tom Reiss&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/dp/B008QYTJZO&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Black Count&lt;/a&gt;

 nicely complements the german sci-fi novel &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/06/05/fertig-gelesen-montecrypto.html&#34;&gt;Montecrypto&lt;/a&gt;

 by Tom Hillenbrand. It is a biography of the father of the French write Alexandere Dumas, Thomas-Alexandre Dumas Davy de la Pailleterie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/dp/B008QYTJZO&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/06/black-count.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/dp/B008QYTJZO&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Black Count&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;quot;, by Tom Reiss.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alexandre Dumas, the author of &amp;ldquo;The Three Musketeers&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;The Count of Monte Cristo&amp;rdquo; and many other books, is one of the most read French authors. He had it easy coming up with stories, because his father had one of the most unusual and wildest lives imaginable. Dumas was, in a way, telling episodes from his fathers adventures, toned down to become more believable, in some of his stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas-Alexandre was born on the French colony island Saint-Domingue (now Hawaii). His father was the French Marquis Alexandre Antoine Davy de la Pailletterie. His mother Marie-Cessette Dumas, an enslaved woman of &amp;ldquo;Afro-Caribbean&amp;rdquo; ancestry,  which means that she or her ancestors were enslaved somewhere in Africa and forcibly brought to the Island. Not much is known about her actual origin or history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His father, very broke, returned to France, where Thomas-Alexandre was legally freed: in France, slavery was prohibited since 1315, in the colonies not so much. He was educated in a military school and then joined the army as a young man. He also started to use his mothers name after he fell out with his father.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dumas entered the military at the age of 24 as a private, but quickly rose in rank. This was not only due to his bodily fitness, his incredible fighting skills and his immense organisational talent, but also due to the wealth of opportunities that the upheaval of the French Revolution of 1789 offered, 3 years into his military career. He held the rank of a General-in-Chief over the 53.000 troops of the French Army in the Alps, at the age of 31. Among his soldiers, he was known for upholding the ideals of the French revolution, Liberty and Equality, and the ideals of Humanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He served under the orders of the commander-in-chief General Napoleon Bonaparte in Milan in 1796, clashing with him over plundering and expropriation policies. He also fought with Napoleon&amp;rsquo;s aide-de-camp over similar matters of fairness and courage in battle. Despite that, he joined Napoleon&amp;rsquo;s Egyptian expedition in 1798, and became the cavalry commander of the French Army of the Orient. The conditions of the march from Alexandria to Cairo were harsh, and Dumas discussed with other french generals if they would refuse to march past Cairo. Napoleon later learned of that meeting, accused Dumas of treason and forced him to return to France on an unsound vessel. The ship sank slowly during the trip, and was forced aground in a storm near Taranto in Naples. Naples Cardinal Fabrizio Ruffo imprisoned Dumas and his fellow travellers for two years. In jail, Dumas was permanently injured due to infection and malnourishment. He died in 1806, five years after his release, from stomach cancer, at which time his son Alexandre Dumas was 4 years old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Thomas-Alexandre Dumas story easily has sufficient material for several of the stories his son wrote, and his son in fact used parts of his fathers biography in several of his stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before Reiss&amp;rsquo; well researched book the life and exploits of this colorful hero of the French Revolution were almost forgotten. Reiss&amp;rsquo; storytelling brings us back the story of Dumas, who lived through one of the most exciting parts of French history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/dp/B008QYTJZO&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Black Count&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Tom Reiss, EUR 8.59&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

