<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Climate on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/climate.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Climate on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</managingEditor>

    
    <webMaster>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</webMaster>

    
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 12:29:47 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/climate/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Panasonic Comfort Cloud</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2025/04/03/panasonic-comfort-cloud.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 03:04:05 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2025/04/03/panasonic-comfort-cloud.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As discussed &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2025/03/10/going-fully-electric.html&#34;&gt;previously&lt;/a&gt;

,
we have replaced our home heating with Air-Air-Heatpumps,
that is, air-conditioning units that have a reverse-mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our case, the indoor units are Panasonic Etherea Z (CS-Z25ZKEW and CS-Z20ZKEW),
which are connected to a multi-split outdoor unit,
a 3x on the north side, and a 5x (one blind) on the south side, for a total of seven units.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;adding-cs-zxxzkew-units-to-panasonic-comfort-cloud&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#adding-cs-zxxzkew-units-to-panasonic-comfort-cloud&#34;&gt;
	Adding CS-ZxxZKEW units to Panasonic Comfort Cloud
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These units have integrated Wifi, and can be connected to the Panasonic comfort cloud.
This was problematic, because the manual and the labeling was unclear, and led into the wrong direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For each indoor unit there is a remote that came with a sticker.
The sticker has a QR-code, which leads to an install link for the Panasonic Comfort Cloud application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/04/comfort-01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;QR-code for the Panasonic Comfort Cloud installation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to make an account,
and then end up in a very empty screen with a single &amp;ldquo;+&amp;rdquo; sign that allows you to start the &amp;ldquo;add device&amp;rdquo; workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/04/comfort-02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Comfort Cloud start screen after making an account.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next steps seem are straight forward: Add an air-conditioner:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/04/comfort-03.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Select the kind with a wireless remote controller:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/04/comfort-04.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, choose what kind of device you have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/04/comfort-06.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at the device and decide what kind of device this is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/04/comfort-05.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if you think you have a device with &lt;strong&gt;ONE&lt;/strong&gt; front panel sticker, you&amp;rsquo;d be wrong, and things will not work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you choose that, the device will instruct you to turn on the WiFi on the wall unit (that is correct):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/04/comfort-07.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cellphone will then try to join the WiFi &lt;code&gt;Panasonic-CS-wirelessAP&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/04/comfort-08.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and that will not work, because the wall unit starts up the WiFi &lt;code&gt;Panasonic-CS-V2-eM00&lt;/code&gt;.
Wall unit and telephone are using different WiFi ESSIDs, and will not see each other, configuration will fail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a unit without a front panel sticker!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the following flow works:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start the App.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inside the App, lie to the app and say &amp;ldquo;No QR Code&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The App then says &amp;ldquo;Open the flap&amp;rdquo;, and you can say &amp;ldquo;Right, there is a QR code inside, thanks.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The App (not iOS) then wants to scan the very same QR Code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This then takes ages, but adds the unit using a secret config Bluetooth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is not the workflow described in the manual delivered with the unit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But it works.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/04/comfort-10.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add the units one after the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;home-assistant-integration-with-panasonic-comfort-cloud&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#home-assistant-integration-with-panasonic-comfort-cloud&#34;&gt;
	Home Assistant Integration with Panasonic Comfort Cloud
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install HACS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install Panasonic Comfort Cloud from HACS. &lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/04/comfort-12.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Settings -&amp;gt; Devices and Services -&amp;gt; Add Integration -&amp;gt; Panasonic Comfort Cloud &lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/04/comfort-13.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configure Panasonic Comfort Cloud Integration, device discovery runs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For each device,
we get 13 valid entities and several others
that are implemented but not valid for our device type. &lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/04/comfort-14.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The entity &lt;code&gt;climate.&amp;lt;device name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; yields a useful control panel. &lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/04/comfort-15.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dashboard the shit out of everything for profit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can now turn the air conditioners on and off using HASS.
I will be able to create air conditioner automations that keep the house in a sane temperature range automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Going fully electric</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2025/03/10/going-fully-electric.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 03:04:05 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2025/03/10/going-fully-electric.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;End of April 2022, we got &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/02/a-solar-roof.html&#34;&gt;our solar roof&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-03.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Using gas, we are heating this house using 1100-1300 m^3 gas per year.
That&amp;rsquo;s 11-13 MWh primary energy. At 156 qm, that is between 72 kWh/(qm * year) and
76 kWh/(qm * year).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Netherlands, this is good for an energielabel &amp;ldquo;A&amp;rdquo;,
in Germany 75 kWh/(qm * year) is the border between &amp;ldquo;B&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;C&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;getting-rid-of-natural-gas-heating-and-cooling-the-top-floor&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#getting-rid-of-natural-gas-heating-and-cooling-the-top-floor&#34;&gt;
	Getting rid of natural gas heating and cooling the top floor
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our objective for 2025 was to get rid of the gas heating,
and install electrical heating based on heat pumps.
Additionally, I needed cooling, because upstairs it can get rather warm in the summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/03/electric-1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In summer, the temperature upstairs won&amp;rsquo;t fall below 24ºC, even at night.
During these times, I can&amp;rsquo;t sleep upstairs anymore.
I would migrate to the first floor overnight, and suffer during the day.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After shopping around a bit, we decided to go for a set of Panasonic Multisplit Airconditioners (Air-Air Heatpumps):
Two multi-split outdoor units, and a total of seven indoor units.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 5x outdoor unit would be positioned at the south wall, driving 4 indoor units,
and the 3x outdoor unit would be sitting at the north wall, driving 3 indoor units.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warm water would be supplied by a heat pump boiler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/03/electric-2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Panasonic indoor unit, wall mounted under the roof of the room.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The indoor units get wall mounted on either the north or south wall of the house.
They require two insulated copper pipes for the refrigerant, a power cable and a plastic hose for condensate water
to the passed to the outside, through the wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For that, an 80 mm hole is being drilled into the wall to pass the connectors to the outside.
On the south side, we have been able to remove the wood paneling of the house,
and run these things over the outside insulation under the wood panels.
On the north side, the connections run to the wide of the house,
and are passed downstairs under the wood panels of the large windows.
They are then led to the outdoor unit on the ground.
Condensate is spilled directly to the ground (into the plants),
and power and refrigerant connections are led to the outdoor units.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/03/electric-3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is what the wall mount and the hole look like, under the indoor units.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running the plumbing and the wires under the wood hides all the ugly pipes quite well,
but required quite some effort with the house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/03/electric-4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The 5x outdoor unit, already in place. No plumbing is connected, so far,
but the wood panels are already removed, ready to take the pipes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;fixing-the-fuse-box&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#fixing-the-fuse-box&#34;&gt;
	Fixing the Fuse Box
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The air conditioners require single phase connections, and dedicated fuses, each.
Making this change would have overloaded our fuse box,
which was in a desolate state after 20 years of incremental changes anyway.
So an additional task of the installation process was a complete renewal of the fuse box,
including newly added differential breakers, more space and a general cleanup.
I also got some wall sockets in the fuse box, for the fiber connection and the fiber modem,
plus some spares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/03/electric-5.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The fuse box and electrical meter, after the cleanup.
There are still two additional Shelley meters that need to go in.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;warm-water&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#warm-water&#34;&gt;
	Warm Water
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The largest and most ugly part of the installation is the warm water boiler.
In the photo you see it before installation: a 200l tank with a heat pump on top.
For installation, it needs to be fixated, connected and requires two 160mm pipes to the roof
for air-in and air-out. These are not yet visible in the image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/03/electric-6.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, you would install it in the place where the old gas boiler was.
Since we are keeping the gas boiler around for at least another 1-2 years as a backup,
that was not (yet) possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This device is also the loudest of all parts.
When running, it creates a 43 dBa noise level,
39 dBa in 1.5m distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/03/electric-7.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We typically run it at 11:00 in the morning.
At that time, we have sufficient solar energy to drive the heat pump (500 W intake),
and the outside air is already warm, making it easier for the heat pump to do its work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warming up 200 kg of water from 15ºC to 50ºC takes around 8.13 kWh of energy,
and the heat pump is rated with a COP of slightly under 3 for 7ºC air-in temperature.
That means an initial &amp;ldquo;heat-pump only&amp;rdquo; run will take about 3 kWh of energy at 500 W power,
so warming up the entire thing will have an initial run-time of 6 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or you press the &amp;ldquo;Boost&amp;rdquo; button, which will enable an additional electrical heater inside,
adding another 1500 W of energy intake to speed things up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/03/electric-8.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A teenage boy has showered late in the evening. The heat pump brings the water reservoir up to spec again.
This used 1.1 kWh (around 30 cent).
You can see how the heat pump uses more power to warm up the water the warmer the water in storage gets.
The difference from 40ºC to 50ºC is almost 100 Watt.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a normal day, we have to replace the used water and warm it up,
that will take around 2 hours of time and circa 1.5 kWh of energy on a normal day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;redesigning-space-on-the-top-floor&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#redesigning-space-on-the-top-floor&#34;&gt;
	Redesigning Space on the Top Floor
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, an additional task in the installation process was to wall off the top floor from the staircase and the rest of the house.
We also wanted to make the airspace smaller above the staircase, and install some unheated storage space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will keep the cool air generated upstairs (where it is warmest in summer) upstairs,
and give us some much needed storage space for some things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/03/electric-9.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the staircase to the top floor, looking up. A wooden lattice is being constructed, strong enough to carry some weight.
Insulation will go into the lattice, Rigips is installed on the lower side, and will be painted over.
A wooden floor goes on top.
An retractable staircase will go into the larger rectangle.
The staircase will get walls from floor to top, with an aluminium frame and acrylic glass, and a door.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/03/electric-10.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Roof, retractable staircase, and a half-installed air-conditioner, top floor.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;did-it-all-work&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#did-it-all-work&#34;&gt;
	Did it all work?
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/03/electric-11.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ten days into March, we are at 0 m^3 gas usage.
So we are natural-gas free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are using as much electrical energy as we produce, which is normal for early March.
Currently, we are coming out at net 13 kWh consumed for the first ten days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electricity usage is definitively up. A lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/03/electric-12.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The first ten days of March, compared to the last 10 days of September, and air temperatures of early march.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can see that the house baselined at around or below 10 kWh/day in September,
with the spikes being days where the car was being charged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In March, the car was charged on March, 1st, for 15.34 kWh,
leading to a usage spike of 42.6 kWh and a grid draw of 32.9 kWh, for a total net draw of 23.63 kWh.
Doing the math leaves us with approximately 17 kWh electrical energy for heating,
at an assumed COP of 3 this yields 50-ish kWh of heat energy, or a gas equivalent of 5 m^3.
That is not too shabby for a day with freezing at night and around 8ºC during the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Energy used is roughly proportional to the outdoor temperature.
Especially the last three days have been warm and sunny,
so all indoor units but the one in the living room on the first floor have been off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the night of the 9th of March, things looked like this (compared to September):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/03/electric-13.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Baseline usage in September was around 300 Watt. We are now at around 700-750 Watt with a single unit running.
This keeps the temperature stable in the living room, and kitchen.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first floor is roughtly &amp;ldquo;J&amp;rdquo;-shaped:
The long side of the J is the living room, with a indoor unit at the top of the J, the south wall.
The bow of the J is the eating place, and the short side of the J is the kitchen.
The north wall, and the bow of the J, has a second indoor unit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this night, I kept the living room indoor unit running at 23ºC.
The north wall unit in the kitchen was kept off.
The kitchen door was left half-open to give the entree and guest bathroom a bit of warmth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently 23ºC measured at the indoor unit (almost under the roof of the room) are 21ºC measured at the Honeywell
wall thermostat used by the old has heating, and 20.0ºC at knee height in the living room.
We get 20.7ºC at 1.80m height in the kitchen.
The single active wall unit was set to &amp;ldquo;quiet&amp;rdquo; mode, which is exactly that:
there is air movement, it is almost hearable but can be felt,
and sometimes you can hear the mechanics in the indoor unit reposition the air-guides, quietly and carefully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learnings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At 8ºC dropping to 3ºC outdoor temperature at night, a single indoor unit in quiet mode can keep the ground floor stable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to set temperatures agressively, 23ºC at 2.20m room height are 21ºC at 1.60m and 20ºC at 70cm height,
there is clear thermal layering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;21ºC in the living room are 20.7ºC in the kitchen, which is way better than expected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original estimate was using 4 MWh/year electrical power for heating (around 1200 Euro/year), instead of 12 MWh gas
(around 1500 Euro/year at current pricing).
I do not expect to overshoot this,
but it may be that we actually end up with considerably less energy usage in the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all the solution works, and performs at least as well as projected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2025/03/electric-14.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;em&gt;NE-roof: Solar Array, the outside air-ducts for the warm water boiler, and the gas boiler is active.
It&amp;rsquo;s the final day of natural gas usage for heating.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Power (and Energy)</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2024/07/16/energy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2024 04:05:06 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2024/07/16/energy.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s talk about power and household items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Power is measured in Watt (W).
1000 Watt make a Kilowatt (kW).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work (Energy) is power expended for an amount of time.
1000 Watt (a Kilowatt) used for one hour is a Kilowatt-hour (kWh).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How much is a Watt?
In our graphics, a Watt is a single red pixel, right of the word cellphone
One Watt is what an iPhone uses when you are running Ice Cubes, scrolling social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/07/energy-01.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;em&gt;Zoom into this image to see the pixel. It symbolizes 1 W.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;media-appliances&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#media-appliances&#34;&gt;
	Media appliances
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are using 5 W your cellphone gets hot.
It is the approximate maximum a device can use without having active cooling, a spinning fan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A device with an active cooler such as a Mac mini uses 5 W when used normally, and up to 25 W under load.
It can use up to 50 W.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;25 W is also what a typical cheap Intel laptop uses when idle.
For example, the Lenovo Yoga I once had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;80 W is what a medium large TV uses in your living room. showing the news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;80 W is also what my gaming machine uses, with a Ryzen CPU, an Nvidia 4070 and 64 GB of memory,
when idle showing steam and the Windows desktop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;400 W is what my gaming machine uses when I play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/07/energy-02.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;em&gt;Typical household media consumption, Energy used. One pixel = one W.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;household-heat&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#household-heat&#34;&gt;
	Household heat
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s walk over from the living room to the kitchen.
A lot of these household devices produce heat, for washing, drying or cooking.
At 10 Ampere, you get around 2300 W from 230 V. At 16 Ampere, 3680 W.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of these heaters are very simple devices: They are fully on or completely off.
So we see a lot of devices that are using either full power or almost no power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/07/energy-09.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Wiesheu Minimat 43s, a professional baking oven of the kind that you find in gas stations or supermarkets.
It uses single phase normal power, 16A, so that still can fit into a normal household.
The device heats up, using 3000W, and then switches on and off to maintain temperature.
This pattern is typical for household appliances that produce process heat:
Ovens, cooking plates, washing machines, dryers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/07/energy-03.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;em&gt;Adding a 2000 W (10 A) and a 3000 W (16 A) household device.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;driving-and-charging-a-car&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#driving-and-charging-a-car&#34;&gt;
	Driving and charging a car
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people now drive electrical cars.
Those that have the space often use a local charge-point that uses three-phase power at 16 A per phase to charge.
Three phases at 16 A and 230 V deliver 3 * 16 A * 230 V = 11000 W.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/07/energy-04.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;em&gt;Adding the charge-point, 11000 W.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over one hour, this uses 11 kWh of Energy.
A battery of 60 kWh that was at 10% is typically charged to 80%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;scale&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;60&lt;/span&gt; * &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;0.8-0.1&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;42.0
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; ./11
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;3.8181
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Charging a car with a 60 kWh battery from 10% to 80% replaces 70% of the total battery capacity, 42 kWh.
At a charge rate of 11 kW, it takes 3.8 h to charge the car.
Since charging slows down as the battery fills up, it will take approximately 4 h to complete the charge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could get a 3 phase, 32 A connection, for a 22 kW charge-point.
But the electricity company will charge you a lot more for that,
and it is kind of pointless.
Already at 11kW, even a 100 kWh Tesla battery will charge from 10% to 80% in 6.5 h,
and you do not have to drive the battery to empty before you charge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, if you charge every evening, just because you can, you are going to replace what you used up this day.
For 100 km, that is typically 20 kWh or less, so the car will be back at 80% after one or two hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t get a 22 kW charge-point, it is pointless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people want charge-points that can do surplus charging,
using only as much power as the solar array on their roof can provide.
Most charge-points can go from 3 phases to 1 phase, and from 16 A down to 6 A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; * &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt; * &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;230&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;1380
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; * &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt; * &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;230&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;4140
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a single phase, you can go down as low as 1380 W at 6 A.
For three-phase, you can go down as low as 4140 W at 6 A.
That is good for 5.5 kWh or 16.5 kWh on a sunny afternoon (4 h of time at 1.4 kW or 4.1 kW).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a proper charge controller, you could charge your electric car from the solar array of the house slowly,
but for free.
Even on somewhat cloudy days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When driving, that car (in my case, a Renault Megane e-Tech 60 kWh) straight on a flat Netherlands Autobahn,
the car consumes 15,000 W.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/07/energy-05.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If your car shows &amp;ldquo;15 kWh being used&amp;rdquo;,
it means that if you continued to drive this way for an hour, it would use 15 kWh of the battery.
It is actually using 15 kW, 15,000 W, right now.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Motors in electrical cars are not like motors in combustion engine cars.
They can use an almost infinite amount of energy for a short amount of time.
The current the battery can provide limits their output
(which is a function of the battery&amp;rsquo;s internal resistance).
Also limiting are the thickness of the wires,
and ultimately the amount of cooling we provide for the motor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for a short time, the car can provide astronomical amounts of power.
The Renault Megane we used as an example further up can be
driven on the autobahn at 100 km/h with 15,000 W.
But it can consume 160,000 W (220 horsepower) for a short time to get away from the traffic light in a race.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/07/energy-06.png&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/07/energy-06.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hitting a Megane on the head will use 160 kW, 220 hp. &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/07/energy-06.png&#34;&gt;full size&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you drove using that much energy for an hour, you&amp;rsquo;d use 160 kWh.
At 42 kWh of useful battery content from a 60 kWh battery,
with a discharge rate of 160 kW the 42 kWh will be drained in 16 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; 42/160
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;0.2625
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;42 kWh battery content, 160 kW used, so we will have that used up in 0.2625 h.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;gp&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; 60*0.2625
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;go&#34;&gt;15.75
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sixty minutes to the hour, so 0.2625 of an hour are 15.75 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An electrical flow heater, dispensing water in a household, is using around 21 kW.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Tesla V4 fast charger will provide 250,000 W.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Porsche Taycan can provide 560 000 Watt (760 hp) for a short time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/07/energy-07.png&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/07/energy-07.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hitting a Porsche Taycan on the head will use 560 kW, 760 hp. &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/07/energy-07.png&#34;&gt;full size&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bonus-picture-being-dumb&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#bonus-picture-being-dumb&#34;&gt;
	Bonus picture: Being dumb
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/07/energy-08.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I am opening the deep freezer door to take out the chocolate ice cream, and I do not close the door properly.
The deep freezer goes into overdrive.
Since I am plotting the 1d average power, I can see how that affects the freezer:
Average goes up from 13 W to 19 W, peak from 35 W to 90 W.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-can-i-save-energy&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#how-can-i-save-energy&#34;&gt;
	How can I save energy?
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The numbers you see here are power, not energy.
They only become energy if you are using the power over longer amounts of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saving energy would mean to measure kWh, not kW, and then cut down on the kWh used.
Or even convert the household so that it generates kWh, i.e., by installing roof solar or balcony solar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, kW is often a good indicator:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Driving 100 km in an electric car at 100 km/h uses 15 kWh.
Doing the same at 130 km/h uses 22 kWh.
Doing the same in a combustion engine car at 130 km/h uses 6l of diesel, 60 kWh of raw energy content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Washing machines, dryers, and dishwashers tend to use a lot of energy, but often only for an hour or so.
A modern washer uses around 1.3 kWh to wash 7 kg of clothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Permanently running devices such as file-servers use a lot of energy because they are always on.
Multiply their power by 24 to get energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/07/energy-10.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Running the washing machine used 1.3 kWh at 13:00.
But over the whole day, my desk and all the computers on it are using the most energy,
because the file server is running 24/7 at 100 W.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that energy use is completely dwarfed by driving.
Here is a day
that shows what happens when we charge the Megane e-Tech at the charge-point and the Carver S+ using a normal wall-plug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/07/energy-11.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Charging the Megane for 20 kWh and the Carver for 7 kWh. The rest of households power consumption is much smaller.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is that bad?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2024/07/energy-12.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On that particular day, 2024-Jul-12, we produced 38.8 kWh of energy using the solar array on our roof.
We consumed 33.9 kWh.
Overall, we returned 4.92 kWh to the grid,
but we actually put 29.7 kWh into the grid and took 24.8 kWh out of the grid at other times.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a sunny day.
While we have been drawing almost 25 kWh from the grid (we use around 10 kWh on normal days),
we also fed almost 30 kWh into the grid, for a surplus of almost five kWh.
That is, despite the 2.5-fold higher power consumption than normal, we have provided a net power surplus to the grid.
We also pulled power from the grid around noon, when solar power is usually available in abundance,
and the hourly energy prices are lowest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;tldr&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#tldr&#34;&gt;
	TL;DR
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find a way to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/dp/B0054PSIDW&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;measure power and energy consumption&lt;/a&gt;


so that you know and do not have to guess.
Collect and visualize that data using
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.home-assistant.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Home Assistant&lt;/a&gt;


or similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Media power consumption is meaningless in the grander scheme of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Household heat matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get rid of gas, get a heat pump.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cook electrically, not using gas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure your household devices working with heat are state of the art:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a decent washing machine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not use a tumble dryer, dry on a clothes horse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a decent fridge/freezer combo. Make sure it is de-iced and efficient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Watch out for always-on devices, but be sure to relate their energy use to the rest of the household&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mobility matters even more than household heat: Driving uses way more energy than living in a place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work from home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When moving, do not use a car, use a bike. Or public transport.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When using a car, use a small car. Weight matters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When using a car, drive energy efficiently: Going 130 km/h instead of 100 km/h uses 50% more energy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have to use a car, get rid of a combustion engine car, drive an electric car.
It uses 1/3 the energy of a combustion engine car.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make energy.
Cover every surface in solar cells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Store energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a battery that can provide enough power for your household.
Power (Watt) is often a function of the cell count.
Cells also provide capacity, so larger batteries (more kWh) also provide more power (kW) up to a limit (11 kW).
When planning, check both numbers, kW and kWh.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To get a household to self-sufficiency, surprisingly small batteries are needed.
The minimum of either half the daily power consumption
and the production in a day in March or October should be enough.
You may want more, but that is because of power, not energy content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In any case, ~10 kWh LFP should be fine for most households.
Having more than you can fill on an early spring/late autumn day is useless, and you won&amp;rsquo;t fill it Nov – Feb anyway.
Having giant capacities in summer is useless, because you won&amp;rsquo;t empty the battery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good Energy News</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/08/15/good-energy-news.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2022 05:06:07 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/08/15/good-energy-news.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two good news in one day. First, my energy provider tells me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Levert u meer terug dan u van het net afneemt, dan betalen we u vanaf die datum 16.8 eurocent per kWh.
De oude vergoeding was 7 eurocent per kWh.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If you push energy into the grid, we now pay you 16.8 Eurocent per kWh. The old payment was 7.0 Eurocent per kWh.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other good news is that it is very likely that the existing &amp;ldquo;Salderingsregeling&amp;rdquo; may be continued until 2025.
At least that seems to be the plan, says &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.milieucentraal.nl/energie-besparen/zonnepanelen/salderingsregeling-voor-zonnepanelen/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;milieu centraal&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Salderingsregeling&amp;rdquo; says that for power that I feed back into the grid I can draw back without cost.
You can imagine that as using the grid as a battery with infinite capacity, or as the counter going backwards.
There are a few limits and regulations, but more on that below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original plan was to end the Salderingsregeling at the End of &amp;lsquo;22.
This was then extended to the End of &amp;lsquo;23, and it seems that it is now being discussed to extend it to the End of &amp;lsquo;24.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when I am consuming 5000 kWh from the grid and push 2000 kWh into the grid, I will have to pay only 3000 kWh.
It does not matter that I actually withdrew 4000 kWh from the grid, because some consumption was at night, or because I overshot the production of my panels at a certain point in time.
Only the net Saldo matters, the difference between production and consumption over the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also works the other way around:
If I am producing 5000 kWh and consume only 2000 kWh from the grid, my Saldo will be 3000 kWh in my favor.
For that I am supposed to get a &amp;ldquo;reasonable compensation&amp;rdquo;, says the law.
At the same time the goverment made noises that basically said that &amp;ldquo;80% of the purchase price seem to be reasonable&amp;rdquo;.
Apparently this prompts my energy provider to make the above change, offering 75% of the purchase price to preempt regulation.
You know what, I am actually somewhat okay with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the entire specific regulation seems to be not fixed, yet, and the actual handling and pricing is still subject to change.
We will see how this will actually play out, but right now the change has been entirely pro consumer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also clear that we will not keep the Salderingsregeling ad infinitum.
The original plan was to gradually switch it from 100% Saldering to 9% less each year.
That still seems to be the case, so we expect to see this table to be implemented:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;%Saldering&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;2022&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;100%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;100%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;2024&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;100%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;2025&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;64%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;2026&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;64%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;2027&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;55%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;2028&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;46%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;2029&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;37%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;2030&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;28%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;2031+&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of a gradual decline we see a big initial jump from 100% to 64%.
That&amp;rsquo;s because the original plan was to decrease by 9% starting 2022, and while the end deadline was kept, the initial full Saldering was kept alive for several years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time the government says it expects a reasonable compensation for the other power that is no longer part of the Salderingsregeling, and that&amp;rsquo;s the above 80% (or now 75% number).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a bit unclear how that now will work out:
Will there be two kinds of tariff for power pushed to the grid that is part of the Saldering, and a second tariff for the other power that is not part of the Saldering, or one tariff for everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will see how that works out soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energieverbrauch in Deutschland</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/07/03/energieverbrauch-in-deutschland.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 12:42:30 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/07/03/energieverbrauch-in-deutschland.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Der Wikipedia-Artikel zum Thema &lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Energieverbrauch#Energieverbrauch_in_Deutschland&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Energieverbrauch&lt;/a&gt;

 ist wirklich interessant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schaut man sich zum Beispiel diese Grafik (oder die Tabelle, auf der sie basiert) an, dann sieht man:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/07/germany-primary-energy.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Primärenergieverbrauch Deutschland 1990 bis jetzt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wie man sieht, ist der Primärenergieverbrauch von Deutschland seit 1990 fast konstant geblieben.
Wikipedia schreibt im Detail: &amp;ldquo;Zwischen 1990 und 2011 nahm das reale Bruttoinlandprodukt um 34 % zu, der Energieverbrauch nahm jedoch um 9 % ab.&amp;rdquo;
Rechnet man um, sind es bummelig 14000 Petajoule, was circa 4000 TWh entspricht.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Private Haushalte nutzen &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.umweltbundesamt.de/daten/private-haushalte-konsum/wohnen/energieverbrauch-privater-haushalte#hochster-anteil-am-energieverbrauch-zum-heizen&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;laut Umweltbundesamt&lt;/a&gt;

 circa 650 TWh, und davon sind etwa 450 TWh Heizenergie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Im Grunde genommen ergeben sich daraus sofort die folgenden Ideen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dächer voll machen:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10 KWp Limit weg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anmeldung und Steuer vereinfachen, und Eigenverbrauch nicht besteuern.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solarinstallation fördern (statt 9000 Euro bei E-Autos dann lieber hier).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Akkus als Ausgleich fördern:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hausakku fördern (s.o. Solaranlage)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rückspeisefähigkeit bei E-Autos und deren Ladepunkten vorschreiben.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wärmepumpen fördern und vorschreiben.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selbst, wenn man bei den Wärmepumpen nur einen Workfaktor von 3 annnimmt, bekommt man die 450 TWh zum Heizen gedrittelt, also einen Strom-Mehrverbrauch von maximal 150 TWh und eine Einsparung von 300 TWh (zum Vergleich: Atomkraft liefert derzeit noch ca. 230 TWh).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und: 15 kWh Hausakku entsprechen auch bei sehr großen Häusern 1-2 Tagen Autonomie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist wunderbar, denn Solar und Wind sind in Deutschland jahreszeitlich in etwa konstant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/07/germany-solar-und-wind.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Die Summe aus Solar und Wind ist in etwa konstant.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lokale Energiespeicher dienen also in erster Linie dazu, die passende Glättung zu erzeugen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The new energy bill</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/06/28/the-new-energy-bill.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 08:09:10 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/06/28/the-new-energy-bill.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We got our solar roof around 1st of April.
I am describing our setup &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/02/a-solar-roof.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;

.
Today we got the bill for Summer 2021 to Summer 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-i-measured&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#what-i-measured&#34;&gt;
	What I measured
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I installed a P1 interface on my electricity counter late in April, so my data does not cover all of the lifetime of the Solar Roof.
Starting the graph at 01-Apr-2022, I get this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/06/bill-in-and-out.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;At this resolution, not very helpful.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is visible is the fact that we do not have a battery, and therefore each day we produce energy, but also consume energy from the grid.
What is not visible is the relation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/06/bill-counter.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the absolute counter values is more helpful.
The total production is on the right hand side, the consumption on the left hand side, and the important number is the Range value below the graph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We produced 1.66 MWh during the range between 01-Apr and now. We consumed 279 kWh in that interval.
That leaves us with slightly under 1.5 MWh pushed to the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/06/bill-gas-meter.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heating consumed around 10 m^3 in one evening, otherwise we use gas for warm water. Not a lot.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We consumed 28.7 m^3 (around 287 kWh) of gas since the begin of metering.
This includes one day of runaway heating worth around 10 m^w, and the rest is warm water.
Warm water is not the cost driver, heating with gas is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let&amp;rsquo;s look at the financials:
We get back 561 Euro, because we paid 2297 Euro in 12 monthly installments, and used 1735 Euro worth of power and gas.
Mostly gas, but more on that further down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our monthly installment two years ago was 192 Euro, last year 202 Euro, and this year it will be 213 Euro.
Of these 213 Euro, 199 Euro will be for gas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So already, without knowing details, we have our mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;get-off-gas-now&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#get-off-gas-now&#34;&gt;
	Get off Gas, now!
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is our electricity intake for the last 5 years:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/06/bill-electricity.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Down to 2.052 MW/a from 4.850 MW/a.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Active since April 2022, the solar array has fed back sufficient electricity to compensate for more than half our consumption.
Do I believe in overprovisioning?
Well, yes, kind of.
The array has been built with future use-cases in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, in the last 12 months we used 3881 kWh, and pushed 1834 kWh back to the grid for the set consumption you see in the bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/06/bill-gas.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Down to 1251 m^3 of gas.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out gas consumption also fell, but that is mostly due to a mild winter and not heating much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;doing-the-math&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#doing-the-math&#34;&gt;
	Doing the math
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are paying around 22 ct per kWh of electricity, and while there is a bit of fixed cost, it hardly matters – 22.5 ct per kWh all in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gas costs around 108 ct per m^3, which is an energy equivalent of 10-12 kWh warmth depending on the type of gas.
Fixed cost here is substantial, and we end up at 132 ct per m^3 overall cost (1349.88 Euro for 1251 m^3, and 274.58 Euro of fixed cost).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heating&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;Electricity&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;Heat Pump&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;Gas&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Heat generated&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;10 kWh&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;10 kWh&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;10 kWh&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Energy used&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;10 kWh&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;2-3 kWh&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;1^3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Cost per unit&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;0.225 Euro&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;0.225 Euro&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;1.32 Euro&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Total cost&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;2.25 Euro&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;0.5-0.75 Euro&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt;1.32 Euro&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to create 10 kWh of warmth from a heat pump, you have to expend 2-3 kWh of electricity, coming in at 50 ct to 75 ct per m^3 gas-equivalent of heating.
That would be around 1.75 to 2.5 times cheaper than heating with gas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A heat exchanger can be a air-water-air system, so a heat exchanger that uses energy from outside air to heat water that is fed into the existing heating.
This will work to around -10 C to -20 C outside temperatur, but for temperatures below zero, it will become successively inefficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your area permits it, you can take energy not from outside air, but from the water or earth below the house.
This is virtually always frost-free and hence relatively efficient.
So if you have a houseboat or are allowed to install an earth circuit, this can be a completely painless solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Existing radiators driven by heat exchangers almost always need adjustment or exchange, because the water-in temperature of the system is substantially lower than a preexisting gas burner.
So somebody with actual clue will have to do the math and adjustment during installation, and some people will have to either change radiators, or install active venting (fans, basically) that push air through the radiators as a leisurely pace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need air condition anyway, because for example there is a roof room that needs active cooling in summer, you can make sure that you get an airco unit that can operate in reverse mode.
Most of the units that support it are as efficient as heat exchangers, and heat air directly.
Here the work factor is comparable to normal heat exchangers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either system will get you off gas, or (with the airco) work in parallel to an existing gas or oil heating – which is nice in case you do not trust the new system and need backup.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A solar roof</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/02/a-solar-roof.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 08:42:10 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/02/a-solar-roof.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I live in a house in a rural village somewhere in &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Randstad&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Randstad&lt;/a&gt;

.
We are paying around 70 Euro per month in electricity, and up to 380 Euro per month in gas.
We are using the latter for heating and warm water, but we are already cooking with electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The house has a decent energy rating and a heat exchanger in the forced ventilation system.
That is to keep the warmth in when getting fresh air in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Energy cost of 2021. Electricity remains largely unchanged in 2022, but gas cost rose a lot.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are using a lot of electricity for a 3-person household &amp;ndash; 5500 kWh, a lot of which can be attributed to &amp;ldquo;always on&amp;rdquo; electronics at home.
In particular, one file server consumes around 100W, which accumulates to not quite 1 MWh per year.
Outsourcing that to a cloud service would be too slow, and a lot more expensive, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-situation-and-the-configuration&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#the-situation-and-the-configuration&#34;&gt;
	The situation and the configuration
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The house has a rather steep roof.
One solar installation service, recommended to us via a colleague, declined to make an offer for installation because they were not equipped to handle the roof steepness.
In the end, we went with Zonneplan, who did not have any objections to the general situation at all, and were able to handle it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-03.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Roof steepness, as seen from the south.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roof itself is oriented at 155 deg, pointing the roof ridge line to south/southeast.
The west side is getting better light, but the first half of the day lights up the eastern roof as well.
According to &lt;a href=&#34;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/ephemeris-moon-and-sun-seeker/id1488277219&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;basic astronomy tooling&lt;/a&gt;

, the sun crosses the houses ridge line at 11:45 CEST, and solar noon (sun at 180 deg) is at 13:45.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-04.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ridge line of the house, and the solar panel configuration.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We opted for a solution that places 9 panels on the eastern roof, and 16 on the western side.
The east side of the house got a 3x3 configuration, the west side a 4x4.
The lower two rows on the western side can get shadow from the neighbor and from the house wings (see the shadow on the image above), so they need &amp;ldquo;optimizers&amp;rdquo; to handle shade.
This is what it looks like on the west side:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-05.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Panels on the west side of the roof.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The installed panel type has a size of 1.75m x 1.03m, and a Wp rating of 370W, so we get 200W/qm as expected from current tech.
This is good for 3330Wp on the eastern side and 5920Wp on the western side, for a theoretical total of 9250Wp.
In practice the configuration will never reach that level of output, because both sides of the roof cannot receive direct lighting at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-06.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The type sticker of one of the panels.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inverter is a three-phase Huawei SUN2000-10KTL.
It weighs 16kg and measures 52.5cm x 47.0cm x 16.6 cm, is rated IP65 and could in theory work from -25 to +60 degC.
It still likes to sit inside, dry and warm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-07.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Huawei SUN 2000 inverter.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The device makes no perceptible sound, even under load.
When producing 4500 Watt, it gets a bit warm, but not so much that it will feel painful to the touch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-08.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;FLIR image of the inverter while transforming 4500W from the roof.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Installing the solar panels on the roof catches energy that otherwise has been hitting the roof and reaching the rooms inside.
The rooms directly under the roof are now about 1.5C cooler, a great improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The panels themselves, even when in full sunlight, do not get particularly warm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-09.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;FLIR images of the solar panels while in full sunlight.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;production-and-consumption&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#production-and-consumption&#34;&gt;
	Production and consumption
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a spotless day in April, still on MET, and hardly any clouds.
We have sunrise at 6:40, around 7:00 we see a sharp rise of energy produced on the eastern panels.
This peaks around 9:00 at ~2300W, then falls off a bit until around 11:30 the western panels start to kick in.
From here on the production switches over from eastside to westside, for a peak of 5300W around 16:00.
Sunset is at 20:40, and indeed we get at least a bit of energy almost to the end, though the decline is rather steep starting at 19:40 or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total production is 44.5 kWh over the day.
Around 10 kWh can be attributed to the modules on the eastern side, and their power comes in early when we need it for breakfast.
They help a great deal to even out production over the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-10.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inverter has a GSM module and feeds into the systems of Zonneplan.
That also means I get no direct access to the Modbus in the Inverter without interfering with their warranty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can access the electricity counter of our house, though, through the Dutch P1 interface.
This is done, for example, with a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zuidwijk.com/product/p1-reader-ethernet/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;P1 reader ethernet&lt;/a&gt;

 by Marcel Zuidwijk, connecting the P1 interface from the counter to a free power on the DSL modem.
The data is put onto the &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/11/15/my-home-sensor-network.html&#34;&gt;house MQTT bus&lt;/a&gt;

, using &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Lalufu/p1-mqtt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;software&lt;/a&gt;

 written by a friend and colleague.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading the counters, I get a good overview of what happens during the day:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-11.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Red line: Power drawn from the grid. Green line: Power sent into the grid. You can see how between 6:00 and 20:00 we are sending power to the grid at almost all times. The &amp;ldquo;Range&amp;rdquo; data shows we have drawn 6.25 kWh from the grid over the day, and sent around 30.1 kWh into the grid over the day.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the image above, we can see that we sent 30.1 kWh into the grid yesterday.
The Zonneplan app gives me a total production of 39.42 kWh for that day.
We also took 6.25 kWh from the grid on top of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That gives us a usage of (6.25 kWh + 39.42 kWh - 30.1 kWh =) 15.57 kWh for the day.
Out of this, we covered (39.42 kWh - 30.1 kWh =) 9.32 kWh internally.
We pushed a net surplus of (30.1 kWh - 6.25kWh = ) 23.85 kWh into the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the current counters, I can get a more detailed graph over the day.
You can see a base load in the house of around 300W &amp;ndash; around 100W can be attributed to one server, the rest is various other electronics that is always on.
Great spikes show household appliances doing things: Dishwasher, washing machine, espresso maker, microwave, cooking plates and ovens all draw around 2kW to 3kW, mostly to heat up water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/solar-12.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Up: drawing power from grid. Down: Sending power into the grid. You can see how clouds and internal consumption take their bites of the &amp;ldquo;perfect&amp;rdquo; production curve.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the day-curve this way you can see that we would profit from a household battery.
On this day in April, we could maybe do with a battery of 5kWh or less, but in darker times a larger battery would be more effective.
We could achieve complete autonomy from Equinox to Equinox, and charge the missing energy from the grid during cheap times in the darker half of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The matching piece of equipment would be a Huawei LUNA2000-15-S0 battery pack.
It is a 15 kWh piece of equipment that is 137cm high, 67cm wide and 14cm deep, coming in at 164kg and around 7200 Euro plus shipping.
The pack is based on LFP technology, not on Li-Ion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;legal-and-financials&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#legal-and-financials&#34;&gt;
	Legal and financials
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We purchased the entire solution through Zonneplan at 10162 Euro, so around 1100 Euro per 1 kWp.
This could be a noticeably less, if we did not have shade on the west side &amp;ndash; these optimizers are expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zonneplan not only installed the whole thing, which took less than a day, but also took care of all the planning, and all the paperwork.
That was very comfortable, and they handled all the things professionally and competently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In April, we produced 871.1 kWh, and sent 718 kWh into the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Netherlands, power sent into the grid &amp;ldquo;turns the counter backwards&amp;rdquo;.
That is, you can treat the network like a battery, 1 kWh sent in is 1 kWh you can get back later for free.
This is called &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rijksoverheid.nl/onderwerpen/duurzame-energie/zonne-energie&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Salderingsregeling voor huishoudens en MKB&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Households and small businesses are allowed to feed self-generated electricity back into the grid until January 1, 2023. And offset it against their consumption at another time. This is called offsetting.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This rule was supposed to end at 1. January 2023, but will be prolonged at least one year more, says &lt;a href=&#34;https://solarmagazine.nl/nieuws-zonne-energie/i26235/startdatum-afbouw-salderingsregeling-zonnepanelen-niet-haalbaar-ambtenaren-adviseren-1-jaar-uitstel&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Solar Mag&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Startdatum afbouw salderingsregeling zonnepanelen niet haalbaar, ambtenaren adviseren 1 jaar uitstel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start date for phasing out solar panel feed-in scheme not feasible, officials advise 1 year postponement&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phasing out the salderingsregeling to Zero is supposed to be done in 9% steps, not all at once.
So in the first year, 91% of the power would be part of the salderingsregeling, the rest the electricity provider would pay for, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law says that the provider must pay &amp;ldquo;redelijke vergoeding&amp;rdquo; (a reasonable compensation).
At this point, a compensation of 80% of what you pay for electricity to them is considered reasonable by the lawmaker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That would mean, I get paid at least 18.0 ct/kWh when I am paying them 22.5 ct/kWh.
That&amp;rsquo;s workable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;outlook&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#outlook&#34;&gt;
	Outlook
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now we have solved our  electricity problem, and manage to have solid overproduction (at least in the brighter part of the year).
We are also getting a tiny electric car this year, which will eat into our budget.
That also means we are not getting a Huawei battery this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will have to eventually change the house heating from a central gas burner to a different system, likely air conditioners/heat exchangers that use electricity to warm up and cool air directly.
They work as heat pumps, and produce between 3 kWh and 5 kWh heat for each 1 kWh they consume.
This will considerably increase our consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warming up 1l of water by 1C takes around 1.16 Wh, and the cooking gas we use provides around 10 to 12 kWh per cubic metre (1000l).
So a shower that uses 240l (0.24 cubic metres) of gas consumes around 2.4kWh.
Similar math can be applied to dishwashers and washing machines (&amp;ldquo;uses 0.885kWh to heat up 15l of water by 50C&amp;rdquo;), and to cooking plates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be using a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; more electricity if we are going to eliminate cooking gas completely in this household.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A solar roof 2</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/02/a-solar-roof-2.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 09:42:00 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/02/a-solar-roof-2.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Zum vorhergehenden Artikel bekam ich einen Leserbrief als Github Issue, das ist hier inhaltlich unverändert veröffentliche,
weil ich glaube, daß es wichtige Informationen und Überlegungen enthält.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Von &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/typxxi&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@typxxi&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich schreibe einmal auf Deutsch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;akku-lebensdauer&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#akku-lebensdauer&#34;&gt;
	Akku Lebensdauer
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Großer Speicher heißt nicht immer gut, weil der LFP Akku dann eher über kalendarische Alterung stirbt,
und nicht in Folge der Zyklen.
Ein LFP-Akku schafft um die 3500 bis 6000 Zyklen.
Das hiesse bei Dir im Idealfall, Du schaffst so 200 Zyklen pro Jahr und damit 17 bis 30 Jahre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;200 ist schon viel, denn durch die Ost-West-Teilung und Verschattungen wird das im Winter recht schwierig,
weil nicht genug hineinkommen wird, da die PV zu klein ist und eine 15 kWh Batterie zu groß bei dem aktuellen Lastprofil von 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich bezweifele, dass Du überhaupt 200 Zyklen bei der 15 kWh voll kriegen wirst, weil Dein Nachtverbrauch im Sommer gering ausfällt -
wegen der Kürze der Nacht.
So bleiben dann nur noch die Übergangs-Jahreszeiten mit längeren Nächten und guten Sonnenerträgen,
wo Du bei 5500 kWh und damit grob 15 kWh / Tag landest, was für die Nacht ja aber kaum 50% = 7,5 kWh bedeuten wird.
Wahrscheinlich ist es so. daß das Haus in 6h auf Grundlast zurückfällt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;grundlast-und-strom-sparen&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#grundlast-und-strom-sparen&#34;&gt;
	Grundlast und Strom sparen
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grundlast ermittelt man am besten beim nächsten Familienurlaub durch Aufschreiben des Zählerstandes bei der Abreise und
Ablesen bei Rückkehr.
Der Verbrauch in der Zeit, den Stunden Eurer Abwesenheit ergibt Deine Grundlast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist elektrisch nicht ganz korrekt, weil zyklische Verbraucher wie Kühlgeräte mitgezählt werden,
die der Definition nach kein Teil der Grundlast sind.
In diesem Fall schon, weil wir die Zyklen für den Akku per Überschlag bestimmen wollen,
und wir auch versteckten Verbrauchern durch Messen und Rechnen auf die Spur kommen wollen.
Denn dort liegt das größte Potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Da reicht es nicht, den Server mit 100W zu schätzen, sondern zu messen und um jedes Watt zu
kämpfen (wobei in NL vielleicht nicht, solange jede PV kWh 91 % oder 82 % oder 73 % Wert behält).
Dann beginnt auch der Kampf um jeden einzelnen eurer Stromsauger, die 24/7 Verbraucher wie eine Fritz!Box
mit 11 W, oder deren Repeater, die gern einmal 10 W und mehr nehmen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daumenregel: 1 W Verbrauch im 24/7 Betrieb = 9 kWh p.a.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genauer: 1 Watt x 24 h / Tag x 365 Tage / 1000 = 8,76 kWh,
oder einfacher: 1 Jahr = 8760 Stunden und in kWh eben 8,8 kWh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Server kostet dann fix 880 kWh/a,
und da sollte eine Menge zu sparen sein durch eine passende Energiesparplattform,
denn gerade da kam ja auch der Erfolg des Raspi her.
Ein Raspi 4 liegt grob 4 W als unterem Ende, also 96 W Einsparung,
nur kann da ja auch ein Fileserver Rack dran hängen,
sodass andere Kaliber Sinn machen, nur ist das der 1. Punkt, Strom zu sparen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zum Raspi Verbrauch hier ein guter Beitrag , der die verschiedenen Lastsituation betrachtete:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://buyzero.de/blogs/news/was-kostet-mich-der-pi-4-an-strom-im-jahr-how-much-does-power-usage-cost-for-the-pi-4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Was kostet mich der Pi 4 an Strom im Jahr?&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, zuerst bei Verbrauch schauen und sparen, gibt lächerliche Dinge, aber sie bringen was.
Natürlich in Deutschland mehr als in NL, weil hier die kWh eingespeist mit 8 cent vergütet wird und aktuell so 35 Cent kostet,
wenn sie in der Nacht gebraucht wird.
Daher ist der Druck hier größer, Strom zu sparen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wer Alexa in Form von Echo Show &amp;amp; Co hat, der kann sich fragen, ob er 1. die Display-Helligkeit braucht,
mit der die läuft, oder es mit weniger auch geht.
3 Watt sind nirgendwo fixer gespart als da.
Und noch viel mehr, wenn man die Frage der Helligkeit richtig zu Ende denkt für sich: Display ist immer aus, außer es schallt &amp;ldquo;Alexa!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Einstellung gibt es tatsächlich, den Nachtmodus, den wir auf 12:00 bis 11:59 gesetzt haben,
sodass der Echo Show 1x pro Tag mittags erwacht und Lebenszeichen von sich gibt.
Schont das Display (unser 1. Show mit 5 Zoll hat ein leidendes Display) und spart so grob 6 Watt
, wenn ich mich recht entsinne: 54 kWh p.a. bzw. 18€&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und die Kids lernen das nur so, was wir selber in der Jugend nie lernten,
denn Wasser und Strom flossen ja immer gut und reichlich und nur die Eltern hatten 1x im Jahr Kopfschmerzen,
woher nur dieser Anstieg stammte.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;batteriebedarf-abschätzen&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#batteriebedarf-absch%c3%a4tzen&#34;&gt;
	Batteriebedarf abschätzen
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, zurück zur Batterie.
Ich gehe von sagen wir 220 W Grundlast aus, dann hast Du vereinfacht in 6 Monaten eine Dunkelphase mit 7 h Kernnacht und 3h Abendprogramm,
wo die Batterie liefern darf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wir nehmen an: 7h x 220 W + 3h x 750W&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist schon eher viel für TV schauen, 120 W bei 65&amp;quot; mit Sky Receiver &amp;amp; Licht an + 50&amp;quot; Monitor &amp;amp; Laptop an = 90W = 1540 + 2250 =3790 Wh
ergibt einen Bedarf von 4 kWh pro Nacht in den 6 Monaten.
Im Sommer aber auch weniger, weil die Sonne eher und länger Strom liefern kann, die Batteriephasen kürzer ausfallen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kontrollrechnung: die übrigen 14h x 750 W ergäben 10,5 kWh und damit Tagesverbrauch 15 kWh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, damit sollte klar sein, dass die 15 kWh Batterie zu groß sein dürfte, außer die Dinge ändern sich wie angedeutet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;batteriebedarf-mit-wärmepumpe-splitklima&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#batteriebedarf-mit-w%c3%a4rmepumpe-splitklima&#34;&gt;
	Batteriebedarf mit Wärmepumpe (Splitklima)
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fangen wir mal damit an, dass Du einen gleitenden Übergang bei der Heizung siehst,
dann gäbe es da als 1. Weg die Nachrüstung einer Split Klimaanlage als Heizung.
Für die großen Räume vor allem im EG, wofür Du selber nicht viel Geschick brauchst,
weil es nur 1 Kernbohrung braucht und danach nur noch Kabel verbinden und Maulschlüssel nutzen, ggf. mit Drehmomentschlüssel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Anlage kann dann heizen und im Sommer kühlen, was alle südeuropäischen Länder seit Jahren nutzen,
weil deren Heizlast geringer ist.
Der Wirkungsgrad ist sehr hoch, weil aus der Außenluft die Energie gezogen und direkt nebenan im Raum abgegeben wird
ohne 20 m Heizungsleitungen und Verluste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wir haben 5,4 kWh große Mitsubishi nachgerüstet - im Altbau der 70er, der aber schon damals mit über 10 cm Wand und Decke gedämmt war.
Die Kosten liegen incl. WLAN und aller Quick Connect Leitungen bei circa. 1100 € -
wenn Du hier jemanden beauftragst, dann sind es 3000 €, sodass Du siehst, wie sehr sich da das lohnt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nimm aber eine Marke.
In der Regel reicht aber das Basisgerät, denn Du kannst da viel Geld in Design investieren mit begrenztem Nutzen,
denn für 500 € mehr bekommst Du die gleiche Anlage, die aber per Fernbedienung den Luftstrom nicht nur vertikal,
sondern auch seitlich lenken kann.
Wer das braucht, bitte, aber 1600 € heben die Hemmschwelle, so etwas mal zu probieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und: große Räume eignen sich besser, weil 1. Wärme aufsteigt,
und die Anlagenkosten sich nicht linear verteilen, also kleinere 2,2 kW Anlage für 4 0% zu haben ist.
Sie kostet stattdessen dann 800 € statt 1100 €, macht also kaum Sinn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Von daher Split-Klimaanlagen immer größer auslegen als der Heizbedarf wäre, weil Du immer noch mit Tür auf das Haus als solches mit wärmen kannst,
besonders bei Euren wohl vielen Etagen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Na klar, für 500 € mehr bekommst Du auch noch einen kleinen Bonus bei der Effizienz,
denn statt COP 4,1 gibt es dann vielleicht 4,4 - also 1 kWh elektrisch bringt 4,1 oder 4,4 kWh Wärme.
Du brauchst aber lange, um mit der 10 % höheren Effizienz die 500 € reinzuholen,
da hast Du mehr von vielen kleinere Anlagen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bei Multisplit-Anlagen muss man wissen, dass Du da auch 2 oder 3 Innenräume heizen kannst,
wobei jeweils 2 oder 3 Innengeräte an 1 Außengerät angeschlossen werden.
Funktioniert gut, kostet aber auch und hat Schwächen, wenn ein Raum kalt und der andere auf Vollgas / Vollstrom laufen soll.
Mag sich bei benachbarten Räumen lohnen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bei Quickconnect musst Du wissen, dass sich das Kühlmittel im Außengerät befindet.
Mit der Quickconnect Leitung kannst Du die beiden Geräteteile selber verbinden und in Betrieb nehmen - außer Du lebst in Deutschland,
da brauchst Du den Klimaschein.
In Italien war das für uns nicht der Fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es muss Dank Quickconnect kein Vacuum erzeugt oder kontrolliert werden, solange Du mit 7 m Rohrlänge klar kommst.
denn für 7m packt Mitsubisih Kältemittel in das Außengerät.
Ansonsten muss der Klimatechniker kommen und nachfüllen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lange Vorgeschichte, um zu zeigen, dass man auch elektrisch zuheizen kann,
oder gar mit 3 Anlagen a 5,4 kW den alten Heizkessel an Heizleistung mit 16 kW erreichen kann.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An den sehr kalten Tagen, die Du an 2 Händen zählen kannst, wenn es unter 5° C geht,
verliert die WP ihren Wirkungsgrad und Arbeitsleistung, da sollte dann was helfen?
Gas heizen und mit elektrischem Heizlüfter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das alles nur, um zu sagen, dass diese Heizung sinnvoll sein kann,
und dann auch teils von Batteriestrom profitieren kann.
Das ist vor allen Dingen in der Übergangszeit sinnvoll,
wenn morgens die Sonne noch weg ist oder abends schon wieder.
Jedoch braucht eine 5,4 kW Heizung mit COP 4 maximal Strom von 1,6 kW -
wenn Du bei 12 ° heim kommst und das Ding auf 28° drehst und mit voller Drehzahl Wärme brauchst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die 1,6 kW machen es Dir auch leicht, dieses Gerät nachträglich an eine normale Unterputzdose in den Stromkreis einzubinden.
Damit will ich sagen, dass hier eine 5,4 kW Anlage im Winter einen Wohnraum konstant auf 23° C hielt.
Der Verbrauch lag dabei bei 4 kWh am Tag, in der Übergangszeit weniger: 2 bis 3 kWh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Für die Rechnung ist das wichtig, ja der Akku auch morgens noch voll sein sollte, wenn man die Nachtzeit von Batterie versorgen will.
Von den 2 bis 3 kWh entfallen dann vielleicht 40 % auf die Nacht oder weniger, wenn man Nachtabsenkung der Temperatur in Kauf nimmt.
Nimm einfach mal 1,3 kWh für die Nacht je Gerät und schwups bist Du bei 3 Geräten bei 4 kWh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mit den 4 kWh Alltagsverbrauch und mit 4 kWh fürs Heizen per Split Klima in 3 Räumen und mehr landest Du bei 8 kWh Bedarf,
und irgendwie ist der 15 kWh Akku immer noch verdammt groß, liegen also 3600 € Kapital brach herum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daher der Rat, das ganze mal mit 10 kWh zu denken, die Dir vielleicht 2400 € sparen, die reichen, um dafür Splitklima zu kaufen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wasserbereitung&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#wasserbereitung&#34;&gt;
	Wasserbereitung
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jetzt mag noch die Frage kommen, wie es mit dem warmen Wasser wäre.
Genau, das ist dann auch so eine noch einfachere Sache.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es gibt vor allen in Südeuropa Monoblockanlagen, die meist in einem wärmeren Raum aufgestellt werden.
In Frage kommen Heizungskeller oder ähnlich.
Die Anlage zieht dort aus der Umluft die Wärme ziehen, und heizt einen 100 Liter Wasserbehälter auf.
Diese werden an nur 2 Rohren in den bestehen Warmwasserkreislauf eingebunden, was Du auch selber machen kannst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keine weitere Veränderung erforderlich, alles beim Alten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein solches Gerät hat Abmessungen von etwa 50 x 50 cm x 120 cm Höhe, und wird meist an die Wand gehängt, in Südeuropa auch gern in die Küche.
Entsprechend gestalten die Anbieter aus Südeuropa das auch gern mal wie ein Interieur Möbel,
schönere Oberfläche und Bedienung als die typischen Heizungen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Preis liegt um die 900-1100 € von Ariston, in der einfachsten Variante.
Ich rate Dir aber sofort, da genau zu schauen, denn die kommen ohne WLAN und SMART,
haben mitunter aber eine Steuerleitung, sodass Du bei PV Überschuss eben auch das Wasser warm machen kannst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lohnt sich alles für NL heute nicht so sehr , aber mit jedem Jahr weiter un 9% weniger Wert der eingespeisten kWh um so eher und mehr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Für die Rechnung nimmst Du einfach an:
Du hast da 100 Liter, die mit 15° C reinkommen und auf 55°C erwärmt werden müssen. 40° C x 1,1 Wh/ °C und 100 Liter
enden bei Wärmebedarf von 4400 Wh, wobei so eine Ariston Nuos Primo mit COP 3 als Wirkungsgrad kommt.
Das bedeutet, Du brauchst 1,5 kWh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ist die Frage aber, wie viel kWh Du morgens brauchst, bevor die Sonne aufgeht, um den Behälter aufzuheizen.
Da sind die 40° C ja selten fällig, weil nicht immer abends noch geduscht worden ist und 100 Liter 15° Wasser nachgefüllt worden sind,
sondern Du mit 100 Liter 40° C warmen Wasser aus der Nacht kommst und dann nur noch 1/3 der Heizlast hättest, eben 15° C erwärmen
statt 40 °C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Strombedarf sinkt dann auf 0,600 kWh wären.
Und damit ist 3/4 des Jahres, wenn im Akku auch Strom sein wird, der Akku mit 9 kWh ausgelastet.
Im Sommer noch weniger, im Spätherbst und frühen Frühling mehr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;auto&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#auto&#34;&gt;
	Auto
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ach ja, der Elektroflitzer soll ja auch eher tagsüber geladen werden als mit Verlusten aus der Batterie in die Batterie,
sodass man dessen Bedarf als Ausnahmen vergessen kann.
Er ist im Übrigen die viel billigere Batterie, stell Dir mal einen 50 kWh PKW vor,
der aus den HUAWEI 15 kWh Speichern gebaut würde, denn dann wären das schon 25000 €,
also ist der günstigste Speicher Dein Auto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selbst in Deutschland wird Vehicle 2 Load als Rückspeisen ins Haus bzw. als Vehicle 2 Grid ins Netz kommen.
Zuerst VW, die sich gegen die Stromlobby durchsetzten.
Von daher baue den Akku nicht zu groß, wenn in 1 Jahr VW und dann andere Vehicle 2 Load Fahrzeuge liefern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein Ford F150 Lightning Truck kann ein ganzes Haus versorgen, weil bis zu 9 kW aus dem Fahrzeug gehen können, wobei klares Negativbeispiel.
Ein MG4 in Golf Größe kommt in der Basis mit einer 51 kWh LFP battery und einer 2,3 kW Leistung Vehicle 2 Load (kein 2 Grid).
Der MG4 Akku mit 3500 Zyklen und mehr kann dann die Hausbatterie ersetzen.
Noch ein Grund mehr, eine NICHT ZU GROSSE HAUSBATTERIE zu kaufen.
(Nebenrechnung: 300 km WLTP hieße bei 3500 Zyklen aber eine Akkulebensdauer von 1.250.000 km,
die das AUto nie fahren wird.
Der Akku hält also länger als das Auto mechanisch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;überschüsse-handhaben&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#%c3%bcbersch%c3%bcsse-handhaben&#34;&gt;
	Überschüsse handhaben
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nun der Punkt, der ebenso wichtig ist: Wenn Überschuss, dann bestimmte Verbraucher mit Überschuss Strom betreiben&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das nennt sich bei Auto und Wallbox Überschussladen.
Die Softwarelösung heißt wohl EVCC, wenn Du nicht eine teure, an den Wechselrichterhersteller gebundene Lösung kaufst.
Nur läuft die dann meist nur mit einer Huawei Wallbox, so es die gibt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der nächste Verbraucher wäre ein Problem, von daher schau Dir EVCC an, die einen Raspi braucht oder einen SonOff ihost,
der ein lokales Smarthome ohne China Cloud für aktuell noch heute 55 € bietet.
Also eine grob Pi 3 / Pi 4 vergleichbare Leistung mit einer Docker Einbindung und Zigbee, WLAN und BT an Bord,
sowie anderem Zeug.
Heute noch im Release Angebot, was seit März gelaufen ist.
Ansonsten wohl etwas teurer, aber günstiger als Pi 4 neu von ebay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EVCC erlaubt Dir das Laden von einem oder mehreren Fahrzeugen bzw. Verbrauchern mit Regeln
&amp;ldquo;Wie lade nur das, was an Überschussstrom sonst ins Netz ginge (die Fahrzeuge können meist erst ab 6A)&amp;rdquo;
und das auch intelligent.
Denn neben dem reinen grünen Überschuss gibt es noch andere Ladeprogramme, um das Fahrzeug schnell zu laden
auch mit Strom vom Netz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und Deine Splitklima, ggf. aber auf alle Fälle die Warmwasser-Wärmepumpe sind ein Super Überschussverbraucher&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dieser Energymaster ist die Zentrale, denn nur diese Überschussverbraucher lassen sich wirklich gut mit Überschuss betreiben.
Eine Spülmaschine oder Waschmaschine nur und erst dann ein zuschalten, wenn der Strom reicht,
ist im Alltag eher ein Alptraum in der Steuerung und muss man bzw. alle in der Familie wollen.
Abends nach Haus und die Maschine ist nicht gelaufen, da kippt die Stimmung dann fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Von daher schau mal EVCC an, ist Open Source und bestimmte Funktionen brauchen einen Sponsor,
was der Wallbox Hersteller übernommen haben kann, sodass alle Produkte des Herstellers das gratis können -
oder kostet Dich maximal $2 p.a. und ist Open Source made in Germany mit sehr lebendiger Community.
Du findest die Site auf &lt;a href=&#34;evcc.io&#34;&gt;evcc.io&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;steuerung-und-modellierung&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#steuerung-und-modellierung&#34;&gt;
	Steuerung und Modellierung
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;War es das ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All das ist die alte, händische Art so was anzudenken und zu durchplanen.
Es hätte Dir vor 1 Jahr vielleicht auch mehr geholfen, das so zu finden, aber sei es drum.
Da auf dem Blog nichts Neues stand, sah es erst einmal nach dem Stand der Dinge aus,
wo sich ein Akku kaum rentiert, wenn man von 1 kWh eingespeist morgen oder im Dezember noch 0,91 kWh zurück bekommt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Von daher mag das jetzt Sinn machen und Dich auch schon länger fragen lassen,
was noch geht und wie in welcher Reihenfolge.
Nur der Rat, dass Du lieber einen eng bemessenen Hausakku kaufst,
und im Hinterkopf hast, dass die PKW das künftig von Haus mitbringen werden,
und zwar vor 2030, denn VW ist ein Big Player wie ein F150 Lightning in den USA bei Trucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All das hier ist die alte, einfache Art, weil jeder der Dein Blog dazu liest, dem auch folgen kann.
Willst Du mehr und genauer, also auch PV Anlage planen und vergleichen können,
dann kannst Du sozusagen Dein Haus an Deinem Ort einfach in 3 D planen.
Deine Anlage, wie sie ist, nachbauen und passend dazu Deine Verbrauchsprofile hinterlegen,
wann welcher Verbraucher am Tag oder in der Woche läuft und was an Strom braucht,
oder aber Du nimmst die 5500 kWh und lässt die für einen 3 Personenhaushalt mit 1 auf Achse und der Rest zu Haus runterbrechen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diese Software errechnet dann auf Basis der Einstrahlungsdaten an Deinem Ort die Erträge je Minute aus der PV,
und stellt dem ggü. die Verbräuche , sodass das System für jede Minute eine Bilanz erstellt und das ganze zu einem Jahresergebnis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Da kannst Du dann alternative Module simulieren, alternativ Belegungen und Wechselrichter, ebenso Batteriegrößen,
DIY Akkus und die Wärmepumpe bzw. Dein Auto elektrisch fahren lassen mit wöchentlich 500 km und Ladeprofilen und Zeiten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das findest Du auf bei Valentin Software in Berlin - gratis als 30 Tage Demo,
wobei Du die Kundenprofil-Auswertungen halt nicht drucken kannst, aber mit Screenshot kriegst Du alles auch so.
Alle Versionen gibt es dort zum Download und laufen prima.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Anbieter hat auch alle Daten der Module und Wechselrichter hinterlegt.
Du sparst Dir das fehlerträchtige Abtippen der Specs, die das System braucht, um zu simulieren.
Du mussst nur Modul Daten etc. auswählen, und dann sollte das System signalisieren,
dass alle Komponenten passen oder woran es scheitert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das Ergebnis der Simulation ist super, die Daten sind realistisch, also die Planung zuverlässig,
die Modul, Batterie, Wechselrichterdaten werden teils von den Herstellern eingepflegt und laufend aktualisiert,
weshalb alles von deren Servern zur Laufzeit kommt.
Ist dann Dein Wechselrichter dabei mit neuen Specs oder verbesserter Version,
dann wirst Du gefragt, mit welchem Modell Du weiter arbeiten willst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Planung selber ist da schon was anderes.
Man braucht, um sich da einzufinden, aber am Ende geht es oder Du kennst Leute und kannst fragen.
Von daher halt der Hinweis, dass Du PV SOL in der PREMIUM Version.
Nimm nicht die kleineren, sondern gleich das Profi-Tool,
das Du sehr gut nutzen kannst, um Dein System von heute zukunftssicher zu gestalten durch u.a. Simulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;wechselrichter-brauchen-strom&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#wechselrichter-brauchen-strom&#34;&gt;
	Wechselrichter brauchen Strom
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lange Geschichte, aber ich denke, dass Du was daraus machen wirst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dazu hast Du noch bedingte Reserveflächen, die auf den Garagen / Carport etc.
Je weniger die eingespeiste kWh wert sein wird, je eher wirst Du mehr Leistung auf dem Dach haben wollen.
Und von daher hast Du jetzt Zeit, die Zukunft so zu planen, dass Du Dir ad hoc auch nix verbaust wie mit einem teuren, zu großen Speicher, denn:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;im Winter wirst Du den ausschalten,
weil ein Hybrid Wechselrichter dann auch fix 70 oder über 120 Watt in der Nacht jede Stunde aus der Batterie ziehen kann,
um nur bereit zu sein, Strom zu erzeugen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jetzt passiert nix dergleichen, denn die PV Module liefern keinen Strom und Dein Wechselrichter legt sich schlafen.
Kommt die Batterie, dann will der aber 24/7 seinen Anteil zum Betrieb und der kann hoch sein:
höher als Dir lieb ist, weshalb dann viele gerade mit so einer eingeschränkten Ost -Westleistung wie bei Dir eben die Kiste im Winter aussschalten,
weil der Überschuss zum Laden zu gering sein wird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daran denken die wenigsten und fallen nachher aus allen Wolken,
wenn die Monatsauswertungen plötzlich hohe Verluste zeigen wie 200 kWh für den Betrieb des Akkus im Monat,
weil ja der Verbrauch des Wechselrichters nur durch den Akku provoziert wird.
Ohne Akku wären die nicht da.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;schluß&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#schlu%c3%9f&#34;&gt;
	Schluß
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gutes Studium und Gelingen - ich schaue mal bei Gelegenheit vorbei und wenn Fragen sind,
dann kann ich vielleicht mit Antworten helfen oder sagen, wo Du die Antworten findest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Klar, das macht alles heute noch nicht wirklich Sinn in NL,
weil eben 91 % oder 82 % jeder eingespeisten kWh gratis zurückkommen,
wann immer Du die im Jahr brauchen könntest.
Aber mit jedem Jahr weiter kommst Du deutschen Verhältnissen näher, wo eben die kWh vom Netz das 4,x fache dessen kostet,
was Deine eben eingespeiste kWh bringt, von daher endet das in derselben Richtung früher oder später.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rechenzentren und ihren Stromverbrauch regulieren</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/11/01/rechenzentren-und-ihren-stromverbrauch-regulieren.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 13:04:46 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/11/01/rechenzentren-und-ihren-stromverbrauch-regulieren.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Es gibt ein Interview mit Stefan Ramesohl vom Umweltministerium (des Bundes) in Netzpolitik.org: &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://netzpolitik.org/2020/interview-zur-umweltpolitischen-digitalagenda-warum-niemand-weiss-wie-viele-rechenzentren-es-in-europa-gibt/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Warum niemand weiß, wie viele Rechenzentren es in Europa gibt&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;. Im Wesentlichen hat das Umweltministerium angesagt, daß es auf europäischer Ebene Rechenzentren erfassen und katalogisieren will, um in einem zweiten Schritt den Energieverbrauch von Rechenzentren zu regulieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist sehr spannend, denn derzeit gibt es keine Übersicht über Rechenzentren in Europa, und tatsächlich sind einige Rechenzentrumsbetreiber sehr paranoid, was den genauen Standort ihrer Hardware angeht und wieviel und welche Hardware darin ist oder was diese tut. Das ist zwar lächerlich - es ist sehr schwierig eine Energiesenke wie ein Rechenzentrum und ihre Abwärme zu verstecken - aber auch ein sehr sensitives Thema.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;eine-leseliste&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#eine-leseliste&#34;&gt;
	Eine Leseliste
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In dem Interview gibt es ein paar Dinge, die Anmerkungen verdienen, aber bevor es los geht noch die anderen Artikel in diesem Blog als Links:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/07/19/threads-vs-watts.html&#34;&gt;Threads vs. Watts&lt;/a&gt;

: Ich habe einen Dell R630 mit zwei Xeon 6132 CPUs getestet, und deren Energieverbrauch unter Last gemessen. Die Resultate sind repräsentativ für die ganze Klasse von Rechnern, die eine Art Arbeitspferd im modernen Rechenzentrum sind. Der Hauptpunkt: 50% der maximalen Energieaufnahme werden bereits bei 20% Auslastung aufgenommen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2018/02/21/a-journey-to-open-compute.html&#34;&gt;A Journey to Open Compute&lt;/a&gt;

: Mit Open Compute hat Facebook die Energieaufnahme eines Rechners in Idle auf 50% eines herkömmlichen Rechners senken können, und unter Volllast auf 80%. Das wird ermöglicht, indem man Rechner, Rack und Raum nach einer gemeinsamen Spezifikation baut und optimiert. Der Open Compute Standard ist jetzt eine offene Spezifikation, aber wegen der Abhängigkeiten zwischen Raum, Rack und Rechner lohnt sich das alles nur, wenn man ein &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Tech#GAFAM_or_FAAMG&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GAFAM&lt;/a&gt;

-type Hyperscaler ist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/11/07/power-budgets-for-computing-resources-portable-and-stationary.html&#34;&gt;Power budgets for computing resources - portable and stationary&lt;/a&gt;

 listet generell die Zusammenhänge zwischen Rechnen, Batterieverbrauch und Abwärme auf.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/10/05/data-centers-and-energy.html&#34;&gt;Data Centers and Energy&lt;/a&gt;

: Wenn man Netflix schaut, wird Energie verbraucht. Wo und wieviel? Wir reden über Endgeräte (die nur wenige Watt brauchen), über Open Compute in Rechenzentren und über Energieverbrauch im Netzwerk, speziell auf der letzten Meile. Letzterer variiert enorm: 5G braucht sehr viel Energie, (V)DSL ist ebenfalls sehr aufwendig, und Glasfaser nicht - sie ist leicht eine Zehnerpotenz günstiger.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/12/28/streaming-and-energy.html&#34;&gt;Streaming and Energy&lt;/a&gt;

 und &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/03/19/netflix-does-not-bring-down-the-internet.html&#34;&gt;Netflix does not bring down the Internet&lt;/a&gt;

: Speziell Videostreaming funktioniert schon sehr optimiert: Videos werden in Edge Data Centers gespeichert und nicht neu codiert, sie werden in der niedrigsten sinnvollen Auflösung geliefert und die Decodierung erfolgt mit spezieller Hardware, damit die Batterie im Endgerät länger hält. All das braucht weniger Energie als angenommen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/06/08/cloud-and-energy.html&#34;&gt;Cloud and Energy&lt;/a&gt;

: Das Uptime Institut sagt: &amp;ldquo;Data center energy efficiency gains have flattened out&amp;rdquo; (und sieht einen durchschnittlichen PUE von 1.58). Uptime sagt im selben Text aber auch, daß neuere und größere Facilities mit Open Compute &lt;em&gt;signifikant&lt;/em&gt; bessere PUE haben. Der einfachste Weg zur Verbesserung von PUE für die meisten Firmen ist, ihre Workloads in die Cloud zu verlagern (und dynamisch zu skalieren). Das hat bei korrekter Durchführung neben Energieffizienz auch noch jede Menge andere Vorteile, die sich aus einem gelungenen Outsourcing ergeben.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hyperscaler-rechenzentren-sind-viel-energieeffizienter&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#hyperscaler-rechenzentren-sind-viel-energieeffizienter&#34;&gt;
	Hyperscaler-Rechenzentren sind viel energieeffizienter
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Auf Twitter ging ich auf &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/isotopp/status/1322857383929012224&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;das Interview ein&lt;/a&gt;

:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Netzpolitik.org:&lt;/em&gt; Diese großen Player können ja kein Interesse an staatlicher Regulierung haben, sondern werden versuchen, eine branchenweite Selbstverpflichtung herbeizuführen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eher nicht. Als &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Tech#GAFAM_or_FAAMG&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GAFAM&lt;/a&gt;

 wäre man sinnvollerweise für mehr Regulierung, denn das käme effektiv einem Cloud-Zwang gleich.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wie oben bereits dargestellt, hat GAFAM bereits Rechenzentren, die sehr viel effizienter mit der Energie umgehen als normale Rechenzentren es tun. Das ist so, weil diese Rechenzentren Raum, Rack und Rechner als ein System designed haben und weil die Betreiber als Hyperscaler es sich leisten können, solche Rechenzentren nach Maß zu designen, bauen zu lassen und zu optimieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Während also ein traditionelles Rechenzentrum Rechner für eine Million Watt betreibt und dafür um die 600.000W an Kühlung und anderer Sekundärenergie aufbringen muß (Power Utilization Efficiency, PUE 1.6), können die am Besten optimierten Google-Rechenzentren eine Million Watt an Rechnern mit 60.000W Sekundärenergie betreiben (PUE 1.06).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein effektiver PUE von &amp;lt;1.2 ist par für die Hyperscaler-Cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein kleinerer Rechenzentrums-Nutzer füllt nicht ein ganzes RZ mit Rechnern, läßt also nicht nach Maß bauen, sondern mietet existierenden RZ-Space, der prinzipbedingt nicht gut geeignet ist für Open Compute (OCP). Existierende RZ-Space ist generisch, er muß jede Art von IT-Equiment aufnehmen können und ist daher oft Überkühlt, der Airflow ist nicht optimiert und hat auf diese Weise mindestens dreimal mehr Overhead als RZ-Space, den Hyperscaler nach Maß bauen (PUE &amp;lt;1.2 vs. PUE ~ 1.6). Noch kleinere Benutzer füllen nur einzelne Räume oder haben Raumabschnitte (&amp;ldquo;Cages&amp;rdquo;), teilen also die Kühlung mit anderen Nutzern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hyperscaler bauen nicht nur ein RZ, sondern tun das in Serie, und iterieren dabei das Design. Sie lassen auch Rechner und Rechnerkonzepte wie OCP entwickeln, und stimmen dabei das Design des RZ auf das Design von Rack und Rechner ab - daher kommt die energetische Überlegenheit von OCP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dazu kommt, wie oben auch dargestellt, daß ein ausgelasteter Rechner energieeffizienter ist als einer, der teilweise vor sich hin idled. Ein Dell R630 verbraucht bereits 50% seiner maximalen Energie bei 20% Auslastung.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maschinen auszulasten und Workloads dynamisch zu skalieren ist etwas, für das &amp;ldquo;die Cloud&amp;rdquo;, also die API-gesteuerten Rechenzentren der Hyperscaler, gebaut worden sind. Hyperscale Clouds haben &amp;ldquo;sellable cores per provisioned cores&amp;rdquo; als eine zentrale Optimierungsmetrik, sie wollen ausgelastete Rechner, weil das die Einnahmen definiert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/07/watt-thread.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Watts per Thread (Dell R630, Dual Xeon 6132)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wie dem auch sei: Aus energetischer Sicht ist Auslastung wichtig, weil die Watts zur Aktivierung des n-ten Rechenkerns asymptotisch günstiger sind. Das ist so, weil die Idle-Energieaufnahme der Maschine und des ganzen Rechenzentrums drumherum sich so amortisiert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Außerdem: Wenn man es sich leisten kann, Hyperthreading zu aktivieren (Wegen der diversen Intel-Caching-Bugs der letzten Jahre ist das oft ein Sicherheitsrisiko), dann sind die Hyperthreads energetisch betrachtet nahezu kostenfrei. Integer- und Stringprocessing-Workloads können Hypterthreads als nahezu vollwertige zweite CPU betrachten, Fließkomma-intensive Workloads nicht.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Webshops sind, wenn sie richtig gebaut worden sind, String- und Integer-Anwendungen und sehr wenig Fließkomma-intensiv, könnten also von Hyperthreading voll profitieren. Die Anzahl der nutzbaren Cores verdoppelt sich rechnerisch und ist bei Webshop fast vollständig realisierbar - ein Webshop mit einer fast reinen Integer/String Workload kann von den 56 rechnerischen Kernen einer Dual-6132 eine Load von deutlich über 40 stabil verarbeiten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;kosten-und-energie&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#kosten-und-energie&#34;&gt;
	Kosten und Energie
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Über eine Nutzungsdauer von fünf Jahren gerechnet machen Energiekosten in etwa die Hälfte der Gesamtkosten eines Rechners aus - für einen Hyperscaler ist das ein so intensiver Kostenfaktor, daß sie aus wirtschaftlichen Gründen seit mehr als 15 Jahren intensiv die Energieaufnahme ihrer Rechenzentren in allen Punkten optimieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist der primäre Grund für das Open Compute Projekt (OCP) und die Bauweise der Hyperscaler-Rechenzentren. Für Hyperscaler lohnt dies, weil das der Kernbereich ihres wirtschaftlichen Handelns ist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dazu kommt, wie in der Leseliste dargestellt, daß alle Hyperscaler (bis auf Amazon) bereits 100% graugrün sind, also zu großen Teilen bereits auf tatsächlich regenerativer Energie laufen und den Rest mit Zertifikaten kompensieren, und obendrein sehr nah in der Zukunft liegende Ziele haben, was komplett grünen Betrieb &lt;em&gt;und&lt;/em&gt; Überkompensation angeht. Speziell Google ist ein sehr großer Investor in Wind- und Solarkraftanlagen, Netflix überkompensiert bereits jetzt, ist also Carbon-Negative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Für ein Firma, für die der Betrieb und die Skalierung von Rechenzentren und ihrer Hardware nicht der Kern ihres wirtschaftlichen Handelns ist, ist es ausgeschlossen hier mitzuhalten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oder wie Ramesohl es formuliert:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es ist einfach so, dass eine gewisse Skalierung zu großen Vorteilen führt, die dann wiederum über eine Wettbewerbsfähigkeit im Markt die Marktposition stärkt und damit den Marktanteil erhöht. Das ist ein selbstverstärkender Effekt. Hinzu kommt, dass diese Akteure in der Lage waren, zu investieren und sich damit ein technologisches Know-how aufzubauen, was wiederum im Umkehrschluss ihre Marktposition stärkt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist richtig, dass gerade bei den großen Playern entsprechende selbstdefinierte Nachhaltigkeitsziele vorliegen. Das sind teilweise sehr ambitionierte Pläne, die versuchen, die Emissionen, die im Laufe der Unternehmensgeschichte bisher aufgelaufen sind, rückwirkend zu kompensieren.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bandbreite-und-energie&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#bandbreite-und-energie&#34;&gt;
	Bandbreite und Energie
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ramesohl sagt auch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Da geht es um die Frage, ob jede Internetwerbung eine Autoplay-Funktion braucht, also abspielt, wenn ich nur über die Seite scrolle. Das erzeugt nämlich ein enormes Datenvolumen. Oder die Frage, ob alles standardmäßig in höchster Auflösung gestreamt werden muss, wenn es auf einem kleinen Bildschirm angeschaut wird.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dahinter steht die Fehlmeinung, daß eine Netzwerkinfrastruktur mehr Energie benötigt, wenn Daten übertragen werden. Das ist nicht der Fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So wie eine Festplatte oder RAM nicht schwerer werden oder mehr Energie verbrauchen, wenn Daten darin gespeichert werden, so braucht ein kabelgebundenener Netzwerklink nicht (wesentlich) mehr Energie, wenn Daten übertragen werden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RAM und Festplatten brauchen (mehr) Energie, wenn Daten &lt;em&gt;geändert&lt;/em&gt; werden, also Bits gekippt werden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und kabelgebundenene Netzwerkinfrastruktur überträgt immer Daten (Trägersignale), auf die die Nutzlast dann aufmoduliert wird. Das wiederum braucht im Vergleich zur Grundlast des Netzes (das Senden des Trägers) kaum Energie. Anders sieht es bei Funkverbindungen, also Datenübertragung via Mobilfunknetz aus, dort wird der Sender komplett abgeschaltet, wenn er nicht gebraucht wird, um das Spektrum frei zu halten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speziell bei Glasfaser ist es so, daß man die Bandbreite zudem mit nur wenig mehr Energieaufwand um Größenordnungen hochdrehen kann, wenn man will - durch den Austausch der Laser kann dasselbe Medium in der Kapazität verzehnfacht oder verhundertfacht werden ohne signifikat mehr Energie zu verbrauchen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;was-tun-wir-mit-all-dem-compute&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#was-tun-wir-mit-all-dem-compute&#34;&gt;
	Was tun wir mit all dem Compute
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am Ende ist es eventuell eine gute Idee, nicht nur genauer hin zu schauen, wo Rechenzentren stehen und wie sie designed sind, sondern was mit den Megawatts gemacht wird, die dort verwendet werden. Auf diese Weise bekommen wir eventuell Bitcoin weg gebombt. Das wäre schon einmal sehr wichtig, denn hier wird Energie in der Größenordnung ganzer Staaten in sinnlosen Berechnungen (&amp;ldquo;Proof of Work&amp;rdquo;) verheizt. Und nein, das kann man nicht ändern, PoW kann nicht sinnvolles berechnen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cloud and Energy</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/06/08/cloud-and-energy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 11:15:48 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2020/06/08/cloud-and-energy.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/10/05/data-centers-and-energy.html&#34;&gt;Data Centers and Energy&lt;/a&gt;

 I wrote about Hyperscaler Data Centers and Open Compute, and how they bring down the PUE of data centers, making them more efficient, and in &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/12/28/streaming-and-energy.html&#34;&gt;Streaming and Energy&lt;/a&gt;

 I followed up on this, explaining how Netflix energy usage fits into this. Now the Uptime Institute has released &lt;a href=&#34;https://journal.uptimeinstitute.com/data-center-pues-flat-since-2013/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a study&lt;/a&gt;

 that claims &amp;ldquo;Data center energy efficiency gains have flattened out&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is summarized as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average power usage effectiveness (PUE) ratio for a data center in 2020 is 1.58, only marginally better than 7 years ago, according to the latest annual Uptime Institute survey (findings to be published shortly).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But with a lot of caveats:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As ever, the data does not tell a complete story. This data is based on the average PUE per site, regardless of size or age. Newer data centers, usually built by hyperscale or colocation companies, tend to be much more efficient, and larger. A growing amount of work is therefore done in larger, more efficient data centers (Uptime Institute data in 2019 shows data centers above 20 MW to have lower PUEs). Data released by Google shows almost exactly the same curve shape — but at much lower values.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which basically says the opposite: actually newer, larger hyperscaler cloud datacenters are way more energy efficient, and continued to do so after 2013. But a lot of IT is stagnating in old build, and is not being upgraded nor moved anywhere, so the numbers seem to stagnate when they are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It suggests the best way to improve the PUE of your data center is to move to get cloud and get rid of it, but Uptime being Uptime they cannot phrase it that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(via &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SpeicherStief/status/1269906522122960896&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@speicherstief&lt;/a&gt;

)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Streaming and Energy</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/12/28/streaming-and-energy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2019 19:42:16 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/12/28/streaming-and-energy.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A bunch of boomers in Germany is running a distraction campaign on the energy use of data centers and streaming. Example articles in german language can be found in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zeit.de/2020/01/digitalpolitik-digitalisierung-klimaschutz-co2-stromverbrauch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zeit&lt;/a&gt;


and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bento.de/politik/klickscham-wie-viel-co2-streaming-und-googlen-verursacht-und-welche-loesungen-es-gibt-a-c6e5ff54-71e9-46da-80cf-6ee1547d8b3a&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bento&lt;/a&gt;

,
but there is a larger series of articles acrooss multiple newspapers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A better structured reasoning can be found in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.srf.ch/news/panorama/energieverbrauch-im-internet-warum-streaming-viel-strom-braucht&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SRF&lt;/a&gt;

 (German), and it highlights how arbitrary and wrong the energy numbers in the former articles are. But even this article ignores the facts that the energy consumption in a typical cloud data center is most likely carbon neutral, because the power used is likely to be completely green. How green exactly is depending on the cloud operator and the location of the data center - I have written a &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/10/05/data-centers-and-energy.html&#34;&gt;much more detailed overview&lt;/a&gt;

 elsewhere in this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some reason, the majority of these articles focus on video streaming, ignoring outright waste of energy at a much larger scale, for example blockchain use. Furthermore, most of the calculations on the energy use of specifically video streaming are making flawed assumptions. They are designed to create vastly oversized energy footprints, and even more oversized carbon footprints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some things to remember:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A video is not being encoded for every view.&lt;/strong&gt; A raw video is encoded or transcoded once for each target format, of which there is a small integer number. So 4K raw source material is being transcoded into 1080p, 720p, 480p and maybe a few even smaller formats. Some streamers support specific classes of end user devices with a limited, non-extensible set of legacy codecs, such as gaming consoles or similar. They typically add one or two more formats to the set, but in the end the storage cost (and energy) dominates the transcoding cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The encoded file is stored and played on demand for each viewer. In effect this turns watching a video on a streaming service basically into a normal file download with a &amp;ldquo;fancy&amp;rdquo; download protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2019/12/google-chunked.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;via &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netmanias.com/en/post/blog/5923/google-http-adaptive-streaming-iptv-video-streaming-youtube/youtube-changing-the-way-of-delivering-videos-chunking-and-adaptive-streaming-are-in-progressive-download-is-out&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Netmanias: Youtube Chunking, 2013&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Define &amp;ldquo;fancy&amp;rdquo;: The file is being chopped into chunks of around a few seconds playback time, and a number of chunks ahead of the current playback position is being downloaded in advance and buffered on the end user device. How many of these chunks are preloaded depends on a lot of parameters, such as device type, internet connection speed and user behavior (&amp;ldquo;are they jumping around a lot?&amp;rdquo;). Using chunked downloads allows for switching video resolution depending on changes in line speed or display window size, and for jumping around in the video without downloading unnecessary parts of the video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A video is not shipped across the Atlantic Ocean for each viewer.&lt;/strong&gt; Most likely (and especially for popular videos), an edge cache is holding a copy of the file locally and serving it to the customer. Google documents this in &lt;a href=&#34;https://peering.google.com/#/infrastructure&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;their peering and caching documentation&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2019/12/google-edge.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google provides a map of their Google Global Cache nodes. There is at least one in every metropolitan area. These nodes also cache popular Youtube videos. The cache is quite effective, an older 2012 paper (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.net.in.tum.de/fileadmin/bibtex/publications/papers/braun_noms2012_youtube_caching.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;

) discusses that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Netflix does similar things with their own infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This turns watching a video on a streaming service into downloading a file with a fancy download protocol from a pretty local server, with local being defined as &amp;ldquo;very close to your location in terms of network, not physical topology&amp;rdquo;. Where network topology matches physical topology, this may be &amp;ldquo;in your city&amp;rdquo;, in any case it is the minimum number of network hops, the copy &amp;ldquo;closest to you&amp;rdquo; that is being served.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A video is not being decoded in software on a regular CPU&lt;/strong&gt; The effect of a software vs. hardware video encoder is being shown in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2YpOZV8elqA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this 2014 Youtube Video&lt;/a&gt;

, in which a Samsung S4 cellphone is being used to encode a live video stream from a specific brand of surveillance camera. Software encoding produces 8 fps, hardware encoding with the special hardware in the cellphone produces line rate at 25 fps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately we do not get to see the changed energy profile, but purpose built video encoding and decoding hardware as is present on any average graphics hardware in 2019, down to the cellphone level, does things not only faster, but also with a fraction of the energy need. Such hardware is used for streaming video encoding in data centers, and for playback on end user devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is especially important on battery powered devices, where less energy usage translates into longer device runtime directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For encoding, the approaches differ. Netflix is running on AWS, and used to use &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/netflix-techblog/high-quality-video-encoding-at-scale-d159db052746&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;software encoding on regular EC2 instances&lt;/a&gt;

. A relatively recent Netflix talk about their &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JouA10QJiNc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;encoding pipeline&lt;/a&gt;

 has all the details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google offers their own dedicated &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloud.google.com/solutions/media-entertainment/use-cases/video-encoding-transcoding/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;video encoding cloud service&lt;/a&gt;

, but does not document what they are using. It is likely that a hybrid of software and hardware encoding is being used: Google is known to have &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quora.com/What-does-YouTube-use-for-encoding-video/answer/Ciro-Santilli&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;fuzzed ffmpeg&lt;/a&gt;

 a lot and to use it extensively. Also, ffmpeg can &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tal.org/tutorials/ffmpeg_nvidia_encode&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;make use of GPU hardware for encoding&lt;/a&gt;

, when such hardware is available, and GCP has such hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Running a cloud service uses energy, but it is way less energy than anybody else would use for the same job. Also, if you choose your cloud provider wisely, you may use energy, but won&amp;rsquo;t produce CO2&lt;/strong&gt; I have explained that in &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/10/05/data-centers-and-energy.html&#34;&gt;much more detail&lt;/a&gt;

 elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TL;DR is: Cloud providers run data centers on renewable energy, Google is one of the worlds largest investors into solar and wind farms. So even if energy is being used, no CO2 is being produced to run the data center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloud providers use purpose built data centers that match their purpose built computers, &amp;ldquo;Open Compute Technology&amp;rdquo;. These machines use less than half the power of normal servers when idle, and around 33% less energy when fully loaded. They also run in data centers that do not require compression cooling, but can consume ambient air temperatures, greatly reducing the cooling energy spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloud technology can size applications on demand, allowing way better utilisation of servers. While a typical enterprise data center has around 5%-10% utilisation, cloud data centers are 3x to 7x better utilised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT:&lt;/strong&gt; Netflix specifically is overcompensating. In
&lt;a href=&#34;https://media.netflix.com/en/company-blog/a-renewable-energy-update-from-us&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;A renewable energy update from us&lt;/a&gt;


they explain how much energy they use, primary and secondary, and how they
compensate for this. This is assuming that their cloud provider, Amazon, was
running on 100% coal, which they aren&amp;rsquo;t, and that means they are actually
carbon negative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT:&lt;/strong&gt; The BBC has an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/sounds/play/p0819sc4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;

 on this, and they come to the same conclusions (via &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/elizab0t/status/1223570360555188224&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;

).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate change happened 30 years ago</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/10/15/climate-change-happened-30-years-ago.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 15:58:31 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/10/15/climate-change-happened-30-years-ago.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Water is a very weird substance. Melting ice at 0C to water at
0C takes a fantastic amount of energy: Water has a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latent_heat&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;latent
heat&lt;/a&gt;

 of 384J/gram.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.engineeringtoolbox.com/latent-heat-melting-solids-d_96.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Compared to other materials&lt;/a&gt;


that is pretty much at the upper end of the spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warming up 1g of liquid water by 1C is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.britannica.com/science/calorie&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;original
definition&lt;/a&gt;

 of 1
Calorie, or 4.184 Joules in todays units.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The water on our planet is a buffer that can store energy if
there is more energy incoming that the earth can dissipate, or
release energy if the bilancing is negative. Since some time
around 1990 the energy bilancing of our planet is positive and
the oceans are capturing energy at an alarming rate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/climate-ocean.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(via &lt;a href=&#34;//twitter.com/Lijing_Cheng/status/1183429014033092609&#34;&gt;Lijing Cheng&lt;/a&gt;

)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This acts as a buffer, keeping the air cooler than it should be given the
energy surplus we experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the yearly cycle of the sea ice in terms of area and
thickness can be plotted, and is shown to go around a mostly stable center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/climate-ice1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(via &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/simongerman600/status/1183474084694429696&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Simon Küstenmacher&lt;/a&gt;

)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, this changes in the 1990ies, in a very alarming way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/climate-ice2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both, the sea ice and the water mass of the ocean, are buffers that keep the
earths climate on point and prevent it from changing quickly. But for the
last 30 years, since approximately 1990, we are putting more energy into the
system than it can dissipate, loading the buffers up more and more until we
exhaust them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once that happens, there will be a no mitigation any more and the atmosphere
will be warming up very rapidly and in a non-linear fashion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem here is that even carbon neutrality at the current level will
not be enough: The earth will not become more retaining for infrared than it
already is, but the current level of CO2 is high enough to be
energy-positive and it continues to load the buffers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOAA keeps lists of CO2 over time at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.co2.earth/monthly-co2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;monthly CO2.earth&lt;/a&gt;

.
The current level of CO2 in our atmosphere is 408ppm in September 2019. In
September 1990, when this process started, it was 351 ppm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So basically we have been adding not quite 2ppm/year, and we need to get
back to 1990s levels in order to stabilize our home planet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Climate change started already, 30 years ago, and currently we are living
off our safety buffers, the sea ice and the water masses of earth taking the
surplus and keeping us alive.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Centers and Energy</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/10/05/data-centers-and-energy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2019 11:44:55 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/10/05/data-centers-and-energy.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Deutsche Welle is shocked:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dw.com/de/co2-aussto%C3%9F-von-online-video-streaming-als-klima-killer/a-49469109?maca=de-Twitter-sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Generation Greta is watching Netflix&lt;/a&gt;


(Article in German Language), Netflix runs on computers, and apparently
computers are using power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s have a look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT:&lt;/strong&gt; Second part &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2019/12/28/streaming-and-energy.html&#34;&gt;Streaming and Energy&lt;/a&gt;

 now available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;end-user-device&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#end-user-device&#34;&gt;
	End-User Device.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s 2019. End user devices are using Wi-Fi, and are running on
Batteries. They are Cellphones, Tablets or Laptops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devices that are not connected to grid are more usable if they
are trying to save energy, and so all modern devices are full of
special purpose hardware that allows them to fulfill their main
functions more energy efficient. In particular for the use-case
of watching video modern hardware, even cellphones, have special
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Application-specific_integrated_circuit&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ASICs&lt;/a&gt;


that can do video and audio decompression and compression on the
fly faster and with much less energy usage than a CPU could do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, devices without a fan are limited to a sustained power
usage of 5W or less, because that is typically the heat that a
device can dissipate without a fan and without looking strange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this is an enormous improvement: An old-style desktop
computer has a TDP (Thermal Design Power) of 150W and actually
uses a large two digit number of Watts to run, and an old-school
17&amp;quot; monitor instead of a modern LCD uses as much energy. A
modern tablet or cellphone does both, loading an email and
displaying it, within a power budget of 1.5W to 5.0W, so easily
20-40x more energy efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article mentions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Eine geringere Video-Auflösung spart immer Daten und damit
Strom. Ein Smartphone etwa kann eine HD-Auflösung gar nicht
darstellen.&amp;rdquo; Außerdem gelte: je größer der Bildschirm, etwa
bei einem Smart-TV im Wohnzimmer, desto höher der
Stromverbrauch. Fazit: HD-Filme auf dem Smartphone über das
mobile Netz zu schauen, ist am stromintensivsten und damit am
klimaschädlichsten.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;»&amp;ldquo;A smaller resolution saves data and power. A smartphone for
example cannot show HD resolution&amp;rdquo;. Also, the larger the screen,
the more power use. In total: Watching HD movies on a smartphone
is the most energy intense and most climate endangering use.«&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s an amazing mix of truth and nonsense:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The smartphone will still use less than 5W, because it can&amp;rsquo;t
fry itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And doing this at home via Wi-Fi will not use mobile
infrastructure but whatever access point is in the house, so
relatively low power (10W total for AP and phone?).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The smartphone can indeed show Full HD, because modern smartphone
screens are in fact 1920x1280 or larger in resolution,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but you won&amp;rsquo;t be able to notice that, because the pixels at 450dpi or
higher are too small for human eyes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And all this is so obvious that Netflix knows this and won&amp;rsquo;t
actually give you full HD for a smartphone endpoint. Unless of
course you are streaming from the smartphone to a TV, in which
case it does. You can prove this by downloading, and observing
that a full episode of an 1h show comes down to &amp;lt;250 MB of
total storage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#data-center&#34;&gt;
	Data Center
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern Cloud Data Centers are containing Megawatts and Megawatts
of compute capacity
(What&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/search?q=1000000&amp;#43;Watt&amp;#43;in&amp;#43;Horse&amp;#43;Power&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Megawatt?&lt;/a&gt;

),
with a single facility now touching the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifelinedatacenters.com/data-center/gigamom-the-era-of-the-100-mw-data-center/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;100 MW barrier&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google specifically is using 100% renewable energy for their
data centers,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sustainability.google/projects/announcement-100/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;since 2017&lt;/a&gt;

,
for a total of 2600 Megawatt. They are doing this by financing
solar and wind facilities directly, and not through greenwashing
certificates (&lt;a href=&#34;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-environment.appspot.com/pdf/renewable-energy.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;

).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Azure claims to have reached CO2 neutrality in 2014, and also
talks about Power Usage Effectiveness (We&amp;rsquo;ll be touching that
subject in more depth below). In their
&lt;a href=&#34;https://azure.microsoft.com/nl-nl/global-infrastructure/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dutch page&lt;/a&gt;


they claim&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hebben in 2014 CO2-neutraliteit bereikt en voldoen aan onze
doelstelling om een gemiddelde PUE (Power Usage Effectiveness)
van 1,125 voor elk nieuw datacenter te realiseren. Hiermee
zitten we 30 procent boven het industriegemiddelde.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;We have reached CO2 neutrality in 2014 and reached our targets
for power usage effectiveness of 1.125 for all new data centers.
With this, we are 30% better than industry average.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazons energy page is &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/about-aws/sustainability/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;AWS &amp;amp;
Sustainability&lt;/a&gt;


and they claim more than 50% power from renewables, and commit
to a 100% renewable goal for their global infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like all the other cloud providers, they also highlight the way
lower PUE and much higher utilitzation of their servers compared
to on-premises IT (65% vs. 15% average utilization, and 29%
better power effectiveness, adding up to a 84% better overall
power bilancing in their math).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also list their ongoing solar and wind farm builds. For the
amount of power usage they can&amp;rsquo;t yet cover from direct renewable
sources, the page states &amp;lsquo;AWS purchases and retires
environmental attributes, like Renewable Energy Credits and
Guarantees of Origin, to cover the non-renewable energy we use
in these regions&amp;rsquo;, making them overall CO2 neutral.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, computer power usage is not linear: Power management on
a data center CPU turns cores on and off as needed, and thus, a
CPU uses already circa 50% power at 10% utilisation. From a cost
and from an environmental perspective it is best to utilise any
CPU to the fullest. Some older &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/07/19/threads-vs-watts.html&#34;&gt;measurements of mine&lt;/a&gt;

 on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;networking&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#networking&#34;&gt;
	Networking
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article from Deutsche Welle states correctly that the Last
Mile is what counts. That is, because everything before the Last
Mile is already fiber, and fiber lines allow extremely fast
networking at relatively low energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Germany, specifically, is wasting a lot of energy on the last
mile, because in order to make Germanys aging copper
infrastructure capable of handling modern data rates, a stunning
amount of signal processing is required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/data-centers-and-energy/outdoor_dslam.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Siemens DSL DSLAM (not VDSL) as can be found in typical outdoor
cabinets all over the city. VDSL requires even more compute to
send Megabits/s over what is hardly better than a wet cow wire
(Image via
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_subscriber_line_access_multiplexer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;

)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nokia.com/blog/vdsl2-and-gpon-study-finds-sweet-spots/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nokia&lt;/a&gt;


lists Fiber as 45% more cost efficient and way more energy
efficient than VDSL2:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copper infrastructure maintenance is typically the most costly
of all network types. By comparison, GPON is significantly
cheaper — upwards of 45% less to operate than VDSL2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s why replacing aging copper plant with fiber has
significant operational benefits. New fiber is more reliable
than old copper while, at the same time, consumes much less
energy. Also, with GPON operational costs are further reduced
with the elimination of the digital subscriber line access
multiplexer (DSLAM) from the access architecture.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.seeclearfield.com/assets/documents/data-sheets/clfd-odc-100-outdoor-cabinet.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Clearfield&lt;/a&gt;


specifices the total installable power in their typical grey
&amp;lsquo;outdoor VDSL cabinets&amp;rsquo; as up to 3000W, but most cabinets will
not be fully powered to the max. German Telekom
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Outdoor_DSLAM.JPG&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;DSLAMs&lt;/a&gt;


are being fed 48V/25A, around 1000W for the street level devices
with four cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving this to fiber will dramatically save energy, and in fact,
everywhere in the world outside of Germany this is happening
right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mobile data networks are indeed
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lightreading.com/mobile/5g/power-consumption-5g-basestations-are-hungry-hungry-hippos/d/d-id/749979&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;great power sinks&lt;/a&gt;

.
If you can use cabled networking, do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;modern-data-centers-and-power&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#modern-data-centers-and-power&#34;&gt;
	Modern Data Centers and Power
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rumperedis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;John Laban&lt;/a&gt;

 is an ambassador
for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.opencompute.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Open Compute Project&lt;/a&gt;

.
Funded originally by Facebook, OCP is a project that tries to
build more power efficient cloud data centers. In his
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/JohnLaban/ocp-copenhagen-presentation-sept-2017&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;presentations&lt;/a&gt;

,
John explains how OCP achieves this by getting rid of old
technology in the data center and making the room and the rack a
system:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/data-centers-and-energy/traditional-data-center.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional Data Centers: Dark Green - Payload. Everything else - Payload Support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/data-centers-and-energy/ocp-data-center.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OCP Data Centers: Dark Green - Payload. Still around: Generator, Airco is now adiabatic instead of CRAC. Everything else: gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OCP data centers redesign the air flow in the data center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally data centers have a raised floor, which transports
cold air to the racks, goes through the racks and is then cooled
again. Air-in temperatures are often as low as 17-25C, and
humidity is tightly controlled. OCP data centers allow
non-condensing air of up to 35-45C to go into the servers, which
does basically away with heat pumps and air condition and allows
ambient temperature air to go into the DC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional servers have often a relatively low height (&amp;ldquo;1U&amp;rdquo;,
one rack unit), which forces the designers to use relatively
small fans, small heat sinks (== higher air flow speed necessary
for cooling) and produces a lot of friction for the air in the
devices. In a 350W server, the worst case I have personally
observed is 50W for air movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OCP uses higher rack units (&amp;ldquo;OU&amp;rdquo;, Open Compute Units) and
usually makes devices no flatter than 2 OU. Instead, horizontal
partitions are used (3 devices in 2 OU) for a more square device
front, minimising friction and allowing larger heat sinks. It
also allows larger fans, with in turn allows moving the same
volume of air with less RPM and a lot less power. Best cases I
have personally observed were as low as 5-10W for a 350W server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/data-centers-and-energy/ocp-server.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OCP Server: 2 OU high, 1/3 Rack wide, less friction, larger
coolers, no panels impeding airflow, larger fans = slower RPM =
less energy for air movement. Can take up to 45C air-in
(&amp;lsquo;ambient air intake&amp;rsquo;, no heat pump required for cooling).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OCP also improves power consumption by centralising power
supplies in a rack (larger power supplies are usually more
efficient), reducing the number of power conversions in the
total power flow, and making uninterruptible power supplies more
efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total OCP power savings vary by use-case and climate zone, but
are usually 20-50%. South Korean Telekom tested OCP servers in a
climate chamber with various settings
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BBcFXAXXqRE#t=11m33s&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Testbed&lt;/a&gt;

,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BBcFXAXXqRE#t=14m30s&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Findings&lt;/a&gt;

)
and what really shows is how the OCP power consumption stays the
same at all possible air-in temperatures while legacy equipment
consumes a lot more power because it has to turn up the fans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pue-power-usage-efficiency&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#pue-power-usage-efficiency&#34;&gt;
	PUE, Power Usage Efficiency
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Power Usage Efficiency, PUE, is the ratio of total power
consumption of a data center compared to power intake of the
compute equipment. The overhead typically contains cooling, air
movement, and power transformation losses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data center built by web.de in Amalienbadstraße, Durlach
(Karlsruhe), had a PUE of 2.0 - for each Megawatt used for
compute, another Megawatt was required for cooling and air
movement. The reasons for that are manifold: The building
itself, an old factory building built by Pfaff, had low ceilings
forcing warm air back into the machines and forcing bad
airflows. The hardware used had a lot of loss due to badly
designed airflows. And the location of the data center, down in
the valley of the river rhine instead of high up in the Black
Forest, combined high ambient air temperatures with high air
humidity, making evaporative or adiabatic cooling an
inefficient option - compressive cooling with heat pumps
was necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More modern data traditional centers can achieve a design PUE as
low as 1.2 and an effective operational PUE of 1.6. Rigidly
optimized OCP data centers can go below 1.1 effective PUE (sic!)
in good conditions. Google published their numbers in their
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/about/datacenters/efficiency/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PUE dashboard&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All current cloud vendors deploy OCP equipment or (in the case
of Microsoft) self-developed equipment that is
comparable in efficiency. They also add additional special
purpose hardware to their cloud offerings that allows offloading
of common functionality from the sellable cores of their
machines, in order to maximise sellable inventory, save power
and, of course, increase utilisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All aspects of improved efficiency and utilisation included,
cloud hardware often is 3x (or more) efficient than a traditional data center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT:&lt;/strong&gt; A longer article by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jessfraz/status/1232847716964716544&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jessie Frazelle&lt;/a&gt;

 on Data Center Energy use: &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.jessfraz.com/post/power-to-the-people/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Power to the People&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT:&lt;/strong&gt; A study by Masanet, Koomey et al, &lt;a href=&#34;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/367/6481/984&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Recalibrating global data center energy-use estimates&lt;/a&gt;

. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jgkoomey/status/1233113568934907904&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;TL;DR is&lt;/a&gt;

: »We find that computing output from data centers went up six fold from 2010 to 2018 but electricity use only went up 6%.« Masanet, Koomey et al have a second article, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/nclimate1786&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Characteristics of low-carbon data centres&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;https://sci-hub.se/https://www.nature.com/articles/nclimate1786&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT:&lt;/strong&gt; I have been sent a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.se.com/ww/en/work/campaign/data-center-design-overview/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;link to a writeup on data center planning considerations&lt;/a&gt;

. While this was part of a SEO effort, the source (Schneider Electric) is competent - Scheider specializes in Data Center Design and Planning and Energy Systems - and the writeup is actually useful. The text gives a bit of insight into the process and the factors that go into site planning and choices. A lot depends on intended purpose, local climate, available space and power and ultimately also site size and building increments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#summary&#34;&gt;
	Summary
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to technology from 10 years ago, in the data center we
are now using a lot less energy and with cloud technology also
have dramatically improved utilisation (ie use less hardware to
achieve the same outcome). Also,
all of this is green energy, mostly from actual green production
and not grey-green with certificates. Cloud operators are some
of the largest investors in Wind and Solar all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At home, savings are even larger, because we went from Desktop
machines with abysmal power profiles to modern low power
hardware which uses single digit wattages to produce results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Networking, especially the last mile, especially mobile
networking, especially 5G, is a power hog. The amount of signal
processing that goes into 5G and VDSL is amazing. If you want
low power networking, use fiber, maybe bridge the last 5 meters
with Wi-Fi.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Renewables: Energy is free, guarantees cost money</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/07/26/renewables-energy-is-free-guarantees-cost-money.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2017 11:40:36 +0000</pubDate><author>kris-blog@koehntopp.de (Kristian Köhntopp)</author>

      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/07/26/renewables-energy-is-free-guarantees-cost-money.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Digging through my bookmarks and open tabs was interesting. The picture of
the future that emerges: With costs for energy approaching the 1 cent range
per kWh, electrical energy is going to be close to free. Money can and will
be charged for guarantees, because batteries or other forms of storage still
cost money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guardian: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2017/jun/06/spectacular-drop-in-renewable-energy-costs-leads-to-record-global-boost&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Spectacular&amp;rsquo; drop in renewable energy costs leads to record global boost&lt;/a&gt;


»The new renewable energy capacity installed worldwide in 2016 was 161GW,
a 10% rise on 2015 […] The new record capacity cost $242bn, a 23%
reduction in investment compared to 2015, and renewables investment
remained larger than for all fossil fuels. Subsidies for green energy,
however, are still much lower than those for coal, oil and gas.«&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SolAmerica: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.solamericaenergy.com/news/carter-farms/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SolAmerica Energy Launches 1.3 MW Solar Project on President Carter&amp;rsquo;s Farm in Plains, Georgia&lt;/a&gt;

 »Former
President Jimmy Carter leased a 10-acre (40.000 sqm) site in his hometown
to SolAmerica for development of the 1.3 MW solar project, which will
provide over 50% of the power needs of the City of Plains.«&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bloomberg: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2017-06-29/german-tenants-win-right-to-generate-solar-power-on-rented-roofs&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;German Tenants Win Right to Generate Solar Power on Rented Roofs&lt;/a&gt;


»Lawmakers are set to pass legislation dubbed “Tenant Power” on
Thursday in Berlin. The bill promises owners of tenant blocks a subsidy of
as much as 3.8 cents (4.3 U.S. cents) a kilowatt-hour for generating solar
power on rooftops or from basement combined heat and power units.«&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bloomberg: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2017-06-15/solar-power-will-kill-coal-sooner-than-you-think&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Solar Power Will Kill Coal Faster Than You Think&lt;/a&gt;


The tipping point will be 2021 for China, Germany is already past
it.
&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/07/china-tipping-point.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Forbes: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forbes.com/sites/uhenergy/2017/01/24/the-cost-of-wind-and-solar-intermittency/amp/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Cost Of Wind And Solar Intermittency&lt;/a&gt;


»What is the integration threshold? There is no threshold, per se. The
cost of managing intermittency is nonlinear and depends upon the mix and
location of dispatchable and non-dispatchable sources, the match of local
demand patterns with variable source pattern, and various other factors.
Based on model studies of Germany and Indiana, Falko Ueckerdt found
integration costs began to become significant at 20% [intermittent energy
sources].«&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Christopher Schwarzer: &lt;a href=&#34;http://christophschwarzer.com/?p=1066&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;DIE DEUTSCHLAND-BATTERIE, TerraE baut Zellfabrik in der Bundesrepublik&lt;/a&gt;

 (Article in German) »Die Gründungsgesellschafter der TerraE Holding GmbH sind Holger
Gritzka, bisher Head of Battery Technologies bei ThyssenKrupp, Dr. Ulrich
Ehmes, zuvor CEO der Schweizer Batteriefirma Leclanché sowie die BMZ
Holding GmbH.« TerraE wird spätestens Ende 2019 eine deutsche
Batteriefabrik am Start haben. BMZ hat die Batterien für die
Streetscooter geliefert.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PV Magazine: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pv-magazine.de/2017/07/24/terrae-bildet-konsortium-fuer-gigawattfertigung-fuer-lithium-batteriezellen/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;TerraE bildet Konsortium für Gigawattfertigung füLithium-Batteriezellen&lt;/a&gt;


(Article in German) »17 Unternehmen und Forschungsinstitut haben sich mit
TerraE zu einem Konsortium zusammengeschlossen. Ziel ist der Aufbau einer
Großserienfertigung von Lithium-Ionen-Zellen an zwei Standorten in
Deutschland.«&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PV Magazine: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pv-magazine.com/2017/06/29/energy-storage-already-cost-competitive-in-commercial-sector-finds-study/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Energy storage already cost-competitive in commercial sector, finds study&lt;/a&gt;


»Cheaper battery prices sees storage playing a broader role in energy
markets, particularly for commercial customers seeking to reduce peak
consumption, research from McKinsey shows.«&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Energiespeicher Blog: &lt;a href=&#34;http://energiespeicher.blogspot.nl/2017/06/unterirdische-pumpspeicher.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Unterirdische Pumpspeicher&lt;/a&gt;


(Article in German) »Wie bereits mehrfach erwähnt, sind Pumpspeicher die
verbreitetste Methode elektrische Energie in großer Menge abzuspeichern.
[&amp;hellip;] Unterirdische Speicherkraftwerke sind von den Kosten nicht in einer
anderen Welt als Batterien oder obertägige Pumpspeicher. Allerdings gibt
es je nach Technologie erhebliche unterschiedliche technische Probleme und
spezifische Kosten.«&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Singularity Hub: &lt;a href=&#34;https://singularityhub.com/2017/07/01/canada-is-building-a-7-megawatt-hour-compressed-air-energy-storage-plant/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Canada Is Building a 7 Megawatt-Hour Compressed Air Energy Storage Plant&lt;/a&gt;


»Compressing air in porous caves can serve as a backup form of power that
can be tapped when the demand for power is high.«&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New Shift: &lt;a href=&#34;https://shift.newco.co/this-is-how-big-oil-will-die-38b843bd4fe0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This is how Big Oil will die&lt;/a&gt;


»And here is what is disruptive for Big Oil: Self-driving vehicles get to
combine the capital savings from the improved lifetime of EVs, with the
savings from eliminating the driver. The costs of electric self-driving
cars will be so low, it will be cheaper to hail a ride than to drive the
car you already own.« Using the math in the article, this will even be
the case if the car is a traditional Taxi with driver, as long as it is
electric and has the lifetime assumed in the article.The second half of
the article discusses the US coal crash, which happened between 2011 and
2016 (the four largest US coal companies were worth about 45 bn USD
together in 2011, and all bancrupt in 2016).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark Bently:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/msbentley/status/882905622714478592&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;

 »I
recently made this simply plot showing the solar flux at various
longitudes on Mercury&amp;rsquo;s equator. The blue line shows the value at
Earth.
&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/07/mercury-solar.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bloomberg: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2017-05-17/gulf-of-suez-wind-farm-seeks-to-save-pelicans-storks-with-radar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bird Radar May Help Reduce Wind Turbine Deaths&lt;/a&gt;


Shared for this
graph:
&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2017/07/bird-death.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
