<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>media on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/media.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in media on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 18:53:53 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/media/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Starter Villain</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/10/01/fertig-gelesen-starter-villain.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 01:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/10/01/fertig-gelesen-starter-villain.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mastodon.social/@scalzi&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;John Scalzi&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;

 latest book is currently
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Starter-Villain-turbo-charged-supervillains-minions-ebook/dp/B0BJDXRGX8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Starter Villain&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2023/10/starter-villain.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The premise is simple: Charlie&amp;rsquo;s estranged Uncle Jake died.
Charlie and his uncle are estranged because Charlie&amp;rsquo;s father and Jake had a fallout at the funeral of Charlie&amp;rsquo;s mom,
and Charlie has not had much contact at all with Jake ever since.
Now, with Jake also dead, it turns out that Charlie somehow is his only heir.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then Charlie is holding watch at Jake&amp;rsquo;s funeral, and the entire story turns quickly into a James Bond novel,
with strange brutes trying to stab the corpse of Jake, ensuring he&amp;rsquo;s really dead,
and a collection of very weirdly imprinted flower bouquets &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;See you in hell&amp;rdquo; being one of the nicer ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charlie quickly learns that his uncle was a Villain, complete with a lair on a volcano island,
laser weapons to destroy satellites, and a collection of very nice and special cats (and Dolphins, but they are special and not nice).
He also learns that &amp;ldquo;Villain&amp;rdquo; does not exactly mean what he thinks that it means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scalzi spent his pages playing nicely with the clichés and expectations around James-Bond-like supervillains,
and turning them into a fun story with a number of expected and unexpected twists.
He wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be Scalzi if there is no stuff to think about lurking in the background.
In this case, fairly obviously the relationship between 1950&amp;rsquo;s supervillains and present day billionaires, oligarchs
and our survival as a species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A nice two-afternoon read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Starter-Villain-turbo-charged-supervillains-minions-ebook/dp/B0BJDXRGX8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Starter Villain&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;,
John Scalzi, EUR 9,99.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: A Life with Footnotes</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/30/fertig-gelesen-a-life-with-footnotes.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2023 01:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/30/fertig-gelesen-a-life-with-footnotes.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Rob Wilkins was the assistant and a good friend of Terry Pratchett.
He wrote a posthumous biography, titled
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B09R2B8J17&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;A Life With Footnotes&lt;/a&gt;

.
Wilkins is now the manager of the Pratchett literary estate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2023/09/pratchett.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book does what a biography is supposed to do:
It traces the life of Terry Pratchett,
illuminating his origins and the experiences that shaped his worldview.
Filled with anecdotes and tales from his readings, from conventions, and other encounters with fans,
it sketches a portrait of a lovable, quirky personality who crafted stories in his mind and then simply penned them down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rob Wilkins then takes on the challenging segment of the biography and guides us through the tragic phase of Terry Pratchett:
his Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s diagnosis, the mental and physical decline, the ever-increasing loss of control, and the interplay of good and bad days,
leading up to the emotional farewell that occurred long before his physical passing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B09R2B8J17&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Terry Pratchett: A Life With Footnotes&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Rob Wilkins, EUR 9,49.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Combat Ready Kitchen</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/29/fertig-gelesen-combat-ready-kitchen.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2023 01:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/29/fertig-gelesen-combat-ready-kitchen.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B00TY3ZOQE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Combat Ready Kitchen&lt;/a&gt;

,
Anastacia Marx de Salcedo traces the history of food preservation from an american point of view,
and demonstrates the co-development of combat rations and modern U.S. supermarket food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2023/09/combat-ready.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book takes us through the history of U.S. combat rations, from before the invention of the tin can, through canned,
better preserved, but incredibly heavy food to what soldiers have today.
It shows how these military innovations have been seeded, purposefully, into the civilian food industry,
in order to enable the military to source food from civilian companies for their purposes, in formats that suit them.
This also had influence on how the industry preserves food for civilian consumption and enabled a multitude of convenience foods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the development of food preservation for military and civilian needs was somewhat systematic,
the book is not.
It goes through the history not chronologically, but anecdotally, roughly ordered by kind of food,
but with plenty of sidelines, side stories and other distractions.
It still is an entertaining read, but it makes it hard to put down the book and take stock of what you just learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I took away is that food preservation as we understand it today is much more recent than most people think.
It is a thing humanity only learned in the late 80ies and early 90ies, and even today fundamental progress is being made.
Also, a lot of the stuff we do is not actually bad for the food, the nutrients or the taste,
it is in fact perfectly fine.
Still, other things amount to basically breaking down the food to constituent parts, and then reassembling something
from the parts, and that&amp;rsquo;s maybe less good, given how little we actually understand what makes a meal nourishing or healthy,
even today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entertaining and interesting, but structured in a way that makes it harder than necessary for me to pull value out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;%28https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B00TY3ZOQE%29&#34;&gt;Combat Ready Kitchen: How the U.S. Military Shapes The Way You Eat&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;,
Anastacia Marx de Salcedo, EUR 5.25.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Blue Machine</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/26/fertig-gelesen-blue-machine.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 01:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2023/09/26/fertig-gelesen-blue-machine.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://fediscience.org/@helenczerski&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Helen Czerski&lt;/a&gt;

 wrote a book.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Blue-Machine-Ocean-Shapes-English-ebook/dp/B0BCTPP3DH&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Blue Machine: How the ocean shapes our world&lt;/a&gt;


occupies the weird space between memoir, travel blog and science outreach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the middle of this she manages to explain the biggest machine on our planet:
The collection of oceans in which the continents are embedded.
But also the deep love of science, the desire to understand how our world functions,
and the connection between all people than live on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is the story of a person who literally travelled the world, from the poles to the equator,
and from the surface of the oceans to their dark cold depths.
It also is the story of a physicist with knowledge about bubbles and how they work,
and how that line of research led her around the world, and into the oceans.
It also is a gentle introduction into climate science,
showing us how the ocean can be seen as a machine that manages the thermals of the planet,
capturing and transporting heat, feeding the weather machine in the atmosphere with energy and water vapor,
and also capturing and releasing carbon dioxide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following her travels and experiences, we learn about the vertical layering structure of the oceans,
about the ability of water to capture fantastic amounts of energy,
about currents and how they transport water, energy, nutrients and life around the world,
and how humans have been living off all this on the surface of something much greater, deeper and larger than we ever imagined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an amazing and entertaining book that shares a unique and personal perspective of our world,
and at the same time manages to convey how something this vast and enormous can be at the same time fragile and in need our or care and understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strongly recommended read, well worth the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Blue-Machine-Ocean-Shapes-English-ebook/dp/B0BCTPP3DH&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Blue Machine&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Helen Czerski, EUR 15.62&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Crafting Interpreters</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/16/fertig-gelesen-crafting-interpreters.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/16/fertig-gelesen-crafting-interpreters.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Robert Nystrom is a language developer who works at Google on the Dart programming language.
In his book &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Robert-Nystrom-ebook/dp/B09YLQSGKL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Crafting Interpreters&lt;/a&gt;

 he explains lexing, parsing and executing a programming language in an accessible way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Robert-Nystrom-ebook/dp/B09YLQSGKL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/crafting-interpreters.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Robert-Nystrom-ebook/dp/B09YLQSGKL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Crafting Interpreters&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;quot;, Robert Nystrom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nystrom sets out with the (correct) observation that the matter of handling and executing code is a complex topic that is not made easier with all the theory that surrounds it.
In his book, he takes the reader on a journey to implement a toy language, Lox, two times.
First with a tree walker execution algorithm, not unlike PHP 3 or early Ruby.
Then, again, with a bytecode executor written in C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book starts out by defining an intentionally very basic, but complete programming language, and then chapter by chapter builds the infrastructure to scan, parse and execute the code.
All explanations are very practical and on the code, but a lot of boxes, asides and cross-references make the theory behind all this discoverable, while at the same time keeping it out of the way.
One of the nicest and most practical introductions to programming language interpretation and compilation that I have seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Robert-Nystrom-ebook/dp/B09YLQSGKL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Crafting Interpreters&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Robert Nystrom, EUR 25.84&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Fietsparkeren bij Stations</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/07/fertig-gelesen-fietsparkeren-bij-stations.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/07/fertig-gelesen-fietsparkeren-bij-stations.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Netherlands realized around 2000 that they have a problem with bike parking around train stations, and with parking around stations in general.
A program was set up to fix that, assuming things would be done with in ten years.
The program was a great success, and people taking the bike to use the train, and to use a bike after they arrived at their destination by train increased greatly.
This created more needs, and so the program is, changed, still active today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Folkert-Piersma/dp/9068688286&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fietsparkeren bij Stations&lt;/a&gt;

, Folkert Piersma and Wout Ritzema&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Title Page&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book talks, in one chapter each, about analyzing customer needs, the history of the program, guidelines and goals, the plannning process, typical bike parking facilities, architecture and design, investment costs, facility operations, technical resources, innovative solutions and finally an outlook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;em&gt;Table of Content&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What matters to cycling train travellers?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Historic review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Policy for the development and construction of bicycle parking facilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Types of bicycle parking facilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Architecture and design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investment costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Operation, maintenance and enforcement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technical resources and innovations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Innovative types of parking facilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Challenges and opportunities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overview of bicycle parking facilities at railway stations, numbers of bicycle parking spaces per station to storage type&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-03.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Bike/Train combination is special.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bike/train combination is special in many ways.
First, as a mode of transport, they have more in common than you would think.
Both have a low impact on air quality, and they are also propelled in a natural manner:
The electric trains of the Dutch Railways run on 100% wind energy,
while bikes are propelled by muscle power, at times supported with a bit of electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both cyclists and train travelers like speed and convenience;
cyclists want to get to their train as fast as possible without encountering any obstacles,
while train travelers move fast while they read a newspaper, prepare for work or take a nap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Dutch Railways, nearly 50% of all train travelers (in 2019, about 1.5 million journeys were made each day)
get to the station by bike and in some places, that figure is 70%.
Approximately 16% of those travelers use the bike to get from the station to their final destination.
Twenty years ago, those figures were 30 % and 10 % respectively.
Because of the growing popularity of the bike and growing consideration for health and sustainability,
we expect these percentages in the bike/train combination to rise further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This combination already means that the car has fierce competition,
especially for city-to-city connections.
A study by the University of Amsterdam shows that the travel time from,
for example, the centre of Arnhem to the Rijksmuseum in Amsterdam (approximately 100 km)
is virtually the same for both the bike/train combination and the car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-04.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Load diagrams and station plan with the bike parking in relation to the platforms.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-05.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Groot, licht, dichtbij. Dit is ideaal!&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; Christien&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protected and unprotected bike parking.
People coming to the station can park their bike protected or unprotected.
Protected bike parking can be with personnel or without.
An example of protected bike parking without personnel would be bike boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-06.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ik kom hier graag. Er is gewoon altijd plek!&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; Xiaohe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planability and reliable availability of bike slots are important to customers and commuters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-07.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bike parking in the 1970s.
Fietsenstalling bij station Koudum Molkwerum (boven) en fietsenstalling bi station Dronrip (jaren zeventig van de vorige euw).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Times and usage-patterns change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand where the Netherlands are today, we have to look at the past.
These photos from the 1970s show the situation in typical stations from that time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-08.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Station Kampen, 1982.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Dutch word for a bike park is &amp;ldquo;stalling&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;stable&amp;rdquo;), and in this case it is meant quite literally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-09.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Replanning and rebuilding bike parking at station Deventer.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Situation shown in 2002, and in 2012 after renovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-10.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Programma fietsparkeren bij Stations&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The change is not accidental, but the consequence of the program &amp;ldquo;Bike Parking at Stations&amp;rdquo;,
which started off around 2000.
It has changed the nature of bike parking at stations in the Netherlands fundamentally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it also had different, further reaching aspects,
and that is why it is still ongoing after 20 years:
Not only is the sea of bikes around the train stations gone
despite more people arriving by bike at the train than ever before,
also the quality of the area around the train stations improved.
The dark and seedy underpasses and the general feeling of insecurity around many train stations areas in other cities is no longer present here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-11.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What works and what doesn&amp;rsquo;t?
After gaining experience with the initial construction program and being pleasantly surprised by its success,
the program was expanded to a broader basis, and the learnings were implemented.
Financially, the group also improved its position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It quickly became clear that not all conditions included in the &amp;ldquo;Taking Your Bike to the Train&amp;rdquo; directive were functioning well or efficiently.
In Chapter 3, we already discussed the aisle widths in the bicycle storage facilities,
which were found to be able to be narrower, allowing for a more efficient layout of the storage area.
Another important adjustment was the positioning of the monitored and unmonitored storage facilities
in relation to the station entrance and the prescribed covered walking route from the monitored storage to the station.
It also turned out to be necessary to equip the indoor monitored storage with tiered racks,
which was already the case in virtually all existing monitored storage facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-12.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Planning and exploration phases for a bicycle parking facility are presented and explained&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-13.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Target audience and their needs.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Highlighting some important research&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding the Target Audience&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bicycle parking facilities at stations have a very specific target audience with distinct needs,
as also mentioned in Chapter 1.
We know that train travelers are &amp;ldquo;time travelers&amp;rdquo;
and we assume that cyclists heading to the station are almost always in a hurry
because the train won&amp;rsquo;t wait.
It starts with the route from home to the station:
Cyclists prefer the shortest and fastest route from home to the station.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, cyclists want to get on the train as quickly as possible
and spend as little time as possible parking their bikes.
Therefore, we place the bicycle parking facility as close as possible to the station entrance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-14.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Capacity planning using the example of the fictional station Amperveen.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Case STATION AMPERVEEN: Local Customization for Projections&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fictional station Amperveen and its surroundings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the current observed usage, this station requires 3630 spots.
With the currently available 3000 spots, there is already a shortage of 630 spots.
It would not be surprising if the long-term projection ends up at 5750 spots
(20 % increase in travelers, 20 % increase in bicycle usage, and 10 % latent demand).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-15.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Real Simulations: Amsterdam Centraal Station. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EqwasBTzZS8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ZW1A with a capacity of 7000 parking spaces has just been completed&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-16.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Case Station Amperveen: Distance to the Station&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the analysis of parking locations, the distance to the station is also important.
We try to create parking facilities as close as possible to the station entrance,
but sometimes it is not possible to meet the full demand.
Offering &amp;lsquo;first 24 hours free&amp;rsquo; parking is also considered a form of unpaid parking.
If a station has a significant number of weekend parkers, which is often the case in student cities,
it may be considered to provide a free unguarded parking facility at a slightly greater distance,
up to a maximum of 400 meters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-17.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Types, by Prevalence and Price:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ground-Level Parking (as seen in the 1970s photos)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bicycle Flat (Multi-story Bicycle Parking)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indoor Parking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Underground Parking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mega Parking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-18.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pedestrian Flow Analysis for the bike-parking &amp;ldquo;Stationsplein Eindhoven Central (south side)&amp;rdquo;.
Variations in the Layout of bike lots.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-19.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what did we learn in the last 20 years?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Typical 90&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Trend 2020&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not all ground level parking has a roof&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;All ground level parking has a roof&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Concrete stairs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Natural stone finished stairs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No technical aids to bridge height differences&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Technical aids to bridge height differences, such as brush ramps, moving walkways, or escalators (if required and funded by the municipality)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Unfinished concrete ceiling&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Finished with a system ceiling or a smooth finished ceiling&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Concrete tiles on the floor&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Smooth concrete floor&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Unfinished retaining walls visible&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Retaining walls coated or finished with a cladding&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cables and pipes visible&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cables and pipes concealed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Unfinished interior walls&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(Light) Art on the interior walls&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Partition wall made of aerated concrete blocks or system wall&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Partition wall made of glass in an aluminum frame&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Windows in a portion of the wall&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Floor-to-ceiling windows&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Turnstile at pedestrian exit with low steel revolving gate&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Full-height glass turnstile&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/fietspark-20.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And this is what it looks like.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Folkert-Piersma/dp/9068688286&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fietsparkeren bij Stations&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Folkert Piersma and Wout Ritzema, EUR 29.40 Hardcover&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Pale Rider</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/06/fertig-gelesen-pale-rider.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/06/fertig-gelesen-pale-rider.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A book from 2017, about the Spanish Flu, which in the wake of the first world war turned into a global pandemic, killing between 50 and 100 million people on all continents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/pale-rider.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Laura-Spinney-ebook/dp/B01GH07CG6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pale Rider&lt;/a&gt;

, Laura Spinney&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spinney describes the situation in the world in 1918, and how the Spanish Flu came into the world, and was experienced by people in various parts of the world.
The flu returned in several waves, some of which behaved unlike normal flu seasons and also had weirdly shaped killing patterns in the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also describes reactions of the population to pandemic fighting measures &amp;ndash; and we know them all from personal experience by now.
There have been people protecting mask mandates, self-isolation and social distancing on purpose, &amp;ldquo;mah freedums&amp;rdquo; criers and so on, just like with Covid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In parts 5 and 6, she looks at the flu from a modern perspective:
We now know about viruses, and specific the influenza A virus and its variants.
We understand its genetics and which parts of the virus are relevant for infection of humans, and they mutate.
We catalogue them &amp;ndash; the spanish flu was H1N1.
Spinney then looks at SARS, MERS and bird flu, and other viruses, and how they ramp up for another pandemic, strangely prescient of the Covid pandemic of 2020.
Also addresses, again spot on, anti-science propaganda and ossified politics unable to integrate new findings into existing rule frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An enlightening and at the same time very frustrating read, written and published 3 years before Covid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Laura-Spinney-ebook/dp/B01GH07CG6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pale Rider&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Laura Spinney, EUR 9.49 on Kindle&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Kaiju Preservation Society</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/05/fertig-gelesen-the-kaiju-preservation-society.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/05/fertig-gelesen-the-kaiju-preservation-society.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On an alternate earth alternate biology produces beings that can grow up to 150 meters tall and that are powered by natural biological nuclear reactor: The Kaiju.
Whenever anything, humans or Kaiju, uses nuclear energy, the boundary between the alternate realities is weakened and things can cross over.
That happened the first time late in the second world war, and that is how the legend of Godzilla came into the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B09DD2DK5Z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/kps.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B09DD2DK5Z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Kaiju Preservation Society&lt;/a&gt;

, John Scalzi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s Covid times, it&amp;rsquo;s New York, and Jamie got fired from his management position of a delivery service and has to deliver things himself now.
Doing that, he meets an old acquaintance of him, which offers him a&amp;hellip; different job.
The job turns out to involve secrecy, a dimensional portal and working in an alternate world in which he meets things that usually live in SciFi novels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a fun read, from a fun Scalzi from earlier times woken up again.
Doubly so when contrasted with the rather exhausting Interdependency.
Action, Dad joke puns and an improbable premise delivered masterfully, with the parts clicking nicely into each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A strong recommendation, and time well spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B09DD2DK5Z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Kaiju Preservation Society&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, John Scalzi, EUR 8.99 on Kindle&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Sid Meier&#39;s Memoir!</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/04/fertig-gelesen-sid-meier-memoir.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/04/fertig-gelesen-sid-meier-memoir.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The subtitle of &amp;ldquo;Sid Meier&amp;rsquo;s Memoir!&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ldquo;A Life in Computer Games&amp;rdquo;.
And that is exactly what we get:
Sid Meier lists, chronologically and very systematically, all the games he has been working on during his lifetime.
And tells us what happened to him, the game and the game development process while he worked on it.
Somehow that becomes a Memoir, even if some things are only implied or appear out of order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/memoir.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Sid-Meier-ebook/dp/B085845CX9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sid Meier&amp;rsquo;s Memoir!&lt;/a&gt;

, Sid Meier&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Born in 1954, Sid Meier is a prolific writer of computer games.
Together with Bill Stealey, he funded Microprose in 1982, and write a number of flight simulators - among them Solo Flight and F-15 Strike Eagle.
Growing tired of flight sim, he eventually &amp;ldquo;invents&amp;rdquo; the turn based strategy category of games by writing Pirates and Civilization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaving MicroProse after it merged with Spectrum, he funded Firaxis, and was able to pick up the Civilization trademark and some co-developers dissatisfied with MicroProse.
They were able to continue Civilization and turn it into what is has become today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is, as promised, some kind of Memoir and a fun read.
It also gives some insight into Meiers thought processes and what is important to him in game development.
An interesting person, producing an interesting and insightful book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Sid-Meier-ebook/dp/B085845CX9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sid Meier&amp;rsquo;s Memoir!&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Sid Meier, EUR 8.49 on Kindle&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Pattern on the Stone</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/03/fertig-gelesen-the-pattern-on-the-stone.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/03/fertig-gelesen-the-pattern-on-the-stone.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is an old book, from 1998, and much of the technology referred to directly has evolved since then.
But, as this a book that deals with basics, in terms of metaphor and analogy, it is still valuable.
It explains how computers work, and how we make the tech that powers them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/pattern.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/W-Daniel-Hillis-ebook/dp/B06XC774TQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Pattern on the Stone&lt;/a&gt;

, W. Daniel Hillis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computers are really easy.
There is just Zero and One, and it does not get any more complicated than that.
The complexity in Computers and how they work comes instead from using simple rules, making them combinable, and then arranging them into more complicated structures by reusing previous building block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book makes that very clear.
It starts at Zeroes and Ones, and takes the reader on a tour, explaining how we get the things we have (or had, 25 years ago), and how they are made by reusing stuff we build previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/W-Daniel-Hillis-ebook/dp/B06XC774TQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Pattern on the Stone: The Simple Ideas that Make Computers Work&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, W. Daniel Hillis, EUR 9.99 on Kindle&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: The Undersea Network</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/02/fertig-gelesen-the-undersea-network.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 07:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2022/05/02/fertig-gelesen-the-undersea-network.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Where is the Internet coming from and how and when was it built?
It&amp;rsquo;s a network of tubes, or rather cables, and these days they are mostly fiber.
Much of it was built during the dotcom boom, but little has been written.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2022/05/network.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Nicole-Starosielski-ebook/dp/B00WO58MBI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Undersea Network&lt;/a&gt;

, Nicole Starosielski&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicole Starosielski is a professor at New York University Steinhardt, and specializes in Internet Infrastructure, specifically underwater sea cables.
In her book, she documents the history and development of the infrastructure that carries more than 99% of todays Internet data, the backbone that defines the global transport capacity of the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starosielski not only explores the technology, but also the topography and history of the cables, and of course the policts that follow inevitably if you plug a cable that connects to remote locations.
The book meanders between travel report, history book and sociotechnical politics brief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A companion to the book, the Website &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.surfacing.in/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Surfacing&lt;/a&gt;

 allows the reader to interactively follow and explore the structures the book explains.
Search terms at the beginning of each chapters imagery link the chapter in the book to the interactive display on the Surfacing website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/-/en/Nicole-Starosielski-ebook/dp/B00WO58MBI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Undersea Network&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Nicole Starosielsky, EUR 19.61 on Kindle&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metaverse (en)</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/10/27/metaverse-en.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2021 17:10:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/10/27/metaverse-en.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/isotopp/status/1450739310546886657&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;wrote on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;

 something about the term &amp;ldquo;Metaverse&amp;rdquo;.
That led to a contact with &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/michacarl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Michael Carl&lt;/a&gt;

, who wanted to make an episode for his &lt;a href=&#34;https://carls-zukunft.de/folge-58-how-to-build-a-metaversum-in-three-simple-steps/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Podcast&lt;/a&gt;

 with me.
My &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1_OIl_bcrjVczLQrMrVnt5IoYbitp1504mb2GbQK0EM4/edit#heading=h.wbe6wnc7fg59&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;german notes and talk prep&lt;/a&gt;

 are now also available here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;metaverse&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#metaverse&#34;&gt;
	Metaverse
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term &amp;ldquo;Metaverse&amp;rdquo; was initially coined by Neal Stephenson in 1992, but in the context of the current discussion it was defined as in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.matthewball.vc/all/themetaverse&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Metaverse: What It Is, Where to Find it, Who Will Build It, and Fortnite&lt;/a&gt;

 by Matthew Ball. Ball later &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.matthewball.vc/the-metaverse&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;wrote a lot more about the same&lt;/a&gt;

, and that led to the current Valley Hype around it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are starting with games, who no longer are what they started out as, but somehow transcended:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fortnite by Epic Games, which now also hosts non-Fortnite events,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roblox, a platform to make and host low-end games, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minecraft in the Java and Bedrock editions, to show how both fail differently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fortnite&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#fortnite&#34;&gt;
	Fortnite
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortnite originally was a Battle Royale game, but is now also a platform that can host events. You can also buy skins for your characters or items, often in a partnership with other IP, for example Marvel/DC super heroes.
People gave concerts in there, or hosting other events.
Epic likes to do this, openly, because it establishes Fortnite with people who are not originally interested in Battle Royale or part of gaming culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Epic Games also makes the Unreal Engine, and the associated pipelines for creating and editing in-game assets, hosts a market to sell these things, and is building a living infrastructure to produce games, and market them.
They are in a way the invisible back-cover of many games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;roblox&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#roblox&#34;&gt;
	Roblox
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, but way more casual, Roblox operates a platform to create, host and market low-end games, &amp;ldquo;making games as a game&amp;rdquo;, and matching this, they also have assets, and an asset and game marketing outlet.
Roblox is mostly a thing with young and very young people, and vastly underrated with older people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;minecraft-in-two-flavors&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#minecraft-in-two-flavors&#34;&gt;
	Minecraft in two flavors
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minecraft is a classic: The original game is written in Java, and meanwhile completely replaceable with third party components. There are alternative clients, alternative servers, and alternative assets.
The game is bad: It is a sandbox without much story, an ill-defined goal and primitive graphics, the original servers are slow and buggy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the graphics are simple enough that even old potato computers can render it.
It is written in Java, which can be easily reversed and extended without cooperation from the vendor.
And thus there is an extremely rich community of modders, server and client plugins, and many other extensions.
As such, Minecraft is a gateway drug into Java programming with young people, because it has unlimited potential for self-motivation and initiates undirected and unprompted learning in many people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of that leads to monetization that the current owner, Microsoft, can hook on.
As an IP asset, Minecraft Java is an utter failure, because after the initial purchase Microsoft is no longer part of the value chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is why there is &amp;ldquo;Minecraft Bedrock Edition&amp;rdquo;, more performant, better designed and from the ground up with an asset marketplace.
You can buy Bedrock extensions in that marketplace, and only there.
As a maker of extensions, you will have to license IP from Microsoft, and pay percentages, as a customer anyway.
With gamers, it is not very popular, sterile, and without its own subculture.
Compared to the Java Edition, an even bigger failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bedrock model is comparable to the Apple Developer mode, but smaller in scope:
You can&amp;rsquo;t seriously develop for Apple machines without having an Apple-ID, a developer license, support for Apple Cloud for handover, and without leaving percentages to the Apple Store.
Bedrock copies that model, but not as a Computer-Tablet ecosystem, only as a game, and that did not take off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;metaverse-a-first-definition&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#metaverse-a-first-definition&#34;&gt;
	Metaverse: A first definition.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The definition of &amp;ldquo;Metaverse&amp;rdquo; is hence less 3D goggles, and more &amp;ldquo;Integration of the gaming industry with the value chain of the entertainment industry for an open digital asset market&amp;rdquo;.
Or more open: siphoning off percentages along the gaming value chain during production, marketing and usage, and improving the value of gaming assets by partnering with entertainment properties and using their IP in gaming contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objective is to get more lifetime consumer budget out of a person, without bothering them too much by investing actual time.
We want to extend the scope of &amp;ldquo;sellable media&amp;rdquo; in the widest sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;attention-and-time-budgets&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#attention-and-time-budgets&#34;&gt;
	Attention and time budgets
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People have monetary limits, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disposable_and_discretionary_income&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the consumption part of disposable income&lt;/a&gt;

.
They also have time limits, an attention budget.
Both are convertible, but that is media dependent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming a useful lifetime of 60 years for media consumption, during that time I could read for example one book per week, for a total of 40 books per year.
In a total lifetime, that are 2400 books, at - say - 30 Euro each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With AAA games, one can do around 4-6 of them per year, 240-300 in a lifetime, at a value of around 60 Euro each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s a total lifetime value of around 70k Euro in books, or 20k Euro in games per person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can see that games are too cheap compared to their production cost, but a higher price than 60 Euro is unrealistic even for AAA titles.
That is one reason why each and every game has additional ways of spending money after purchase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general with both media types, there is a lot of my lifetime attention span bound for comparatively little money:
We need to up the burn rate.
Books, movies and especially AAA games are much too valuable per time and their consume binds too much attention for the business to scale up.
We need a different way to extract money that does not bind as many minutes of person-lifetime and attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is critically important, because there is also a lot of free content which competes for attention with our paid for assets, and which often is &amp;ldquo;good enough&amp;rdquo; to bind time which we then cannot monetize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-sidebar-death-and-inheritances&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#a-sidebar-death-and-inheritances&#34;&gt;
	A sidebar: death and inheritances
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With an aging population there is the sidebar &amp;ldquo;boomers die, their children inherit&amp;rdquo;.
For example, right now I have around 600 Steam titles, and around 1000 Kindle books.
When I die this represents multiple 10k Euro of value.
How can my son inherit this?
Politics has no answers, and the vendors say &amp;ldquo;he won&amp;rsquo;t&amp;rdquo;.
I can only leave my Steam login to my son, and crack the DRM of my Kindle titles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economically, Kindle and Steam inheritances are largely irrelevant, or would be even be positive, and it is unclear why vendors are blocking this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I am inheriting a villa at the lake, I can go in, open the veranda, walk down through the park to the shore and enjoy the asset within minutes.
It does not take much time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inheriting my Kindle and Steam library, my son will need to invest a lot of time to enjoy that:
With 1200 books that will bind 30 years of lifetime,  and with an inheritance of 1000 games there will be titles from 2002 that look like drawn with crayons today.
I am inheriting &amp;ldquo;Skyrim&amp;rdquo;, but I will have to purchase the &amp;ldquo;VR&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Remastered&amp;rdquo; editions of that myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can see immediately that this will hardly lead to a loss in revenue for vendors, in some cases it is more like a kind of advertisement, actually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;assets-high-budget-little-time&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#assets-high-budget-little-time&#34;&gt;
	Assets: high budget, little time
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even today, games offer loot boxes, pay-to-win and pay-to-skip purchases, and they sell cosmetics. Unlike the first three, the last one is hardly controversial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pay-to-Win: to finish the game successfully you have to buy equipment with real money. Ideally this becomes apparent only of tou already are invested in the game emotionally and with lifetime.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pay-to-Skip: gameplay is often interrupted with annoying delays in which you can&amp;rsquo;t play, except you purchase immediate continuations with real money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lootboxes: The game sells containers with &amp;ldquo;random&amp;rdquo; in-game assets to you, some of which are very important in the context of the game. The actual game is just a wrapper for an addictive (and usually rigged) game of chance. The practice is already illegal as unregulated gambling in several EU countries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrary to this, cosmetics are widely accepted: These are assets that change the way the character or their equipment looks like, without affecting gameplay. Also, virtual houses and house furnishings that have no effect on gameplay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in &amp;ldquo;Elder Scrolls Online&amp;rdquo; as a player you can get easily and early in-game houses which are spectacularly located, and have a lot of empty space for decorations.
Furnishings to decorate the house can be gotten as trophies in-game, but every day things can only be gotten by using real money and purchase from the shop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has many desirable properties for the vendor:
The player can spend a lot of money (without limits!) in-game, and hardly has to invest time or attention to make use of these assets.
We are no longer revenue-bound by the players&amp;rsquo; attention budget.
This is a much better thing to sell than books, films or the games themselves.
The game only provides context and reason for the cosmetics to exist, and defines their visuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;epic-games&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#epic-games&#34;&gt;
	Epic Games
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is precisely the operating model of Epic Games:
With the Unreal Engine the company owns a platform for the fast and efficient design and rendering of really good-looking games.
This also includes the tooling for making in-game assets, but also a market to sell these to other game developers.
With the Epic Launcher and the integrated shop this is also a platform for game sales, and to collect meta and usage data for Epic, which again (for money) are sold back to the developer as analytics.
Epic operates a payment system, which pipes money from the customer to the developer, not only for games, but also for extensions, DLC and in-game purchases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Fortnite, Epic has their own game, which at the same time can also sell 3D assets to players as equipment, cosmetics and other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortnite is a special kind of game - player vs. player, battle royal - players play against each other and last man standing wins the round.
This kind of game is not interesting for all target demographics, but the engine of Fortnite is flexible and can be repurposed.
This enables other use-cases, among them also as a &amp;ldquo;virtual event platform&amp;rdquo;, which also keeps the interest up through media tie-ins and licensed IP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interpretation of &amp;ldquo;The Metaverse&amp;rdquo; as a value chain for digital assets, specifically 3D assets, is too short-sighted:
As an ecosystem with a controlled number of large market operators and a very large numbers of content creators and customers the foundations will look better and have better longevity.
It is entirely possible to allow third parties to operate in this &amp;ldquo;virtual world&amp;rdquo;, trade with each other, especially if the market operators at all times get a tiny share from each transaction.
This is the idea of the &amp;ldquo;Microsoft tax&amp;rdquo;, revitalized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;players-in-this-market&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#players-in-this-market&#34;&gt;
	Players in this market
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different parties have different starting positions and strengths:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Epic Games/Fortnite - weak in IP, but some original IP, even if niche. Unreal Engine and other things on the &amp;ldquo;games invisible back-cover&amp;rdquo; as a big strength.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roblox - original IP, very young customers, grooms them into future customers, wait 10 years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Microsoft - Minecraft, MS Store et al., too enterprise for success? But Halo, MSFS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple (sic!) - no IP, but platform/chain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disney (sic!) - only IP, but weak marketing outside of films/merchandise. Knows the game very well in the real world: Imagine Disneyland principles applied to a Metaverse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook - wants in at all costs, &amp;ldquo;pivot our enterprise&amp;rdquo;: If &amp;ldquo;social&amp;rdquo; of the future is &amp;ldquo;here&amp;rdquo;, we need to be &amp;ldquo;here&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google - all of this is a reason why Stadia still exists, despite being a flop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amazon - this is where the gaming strategy of Amazon is anchored. Amazon would like to be the AWS of the gaming world, instead of Epic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tech-maturity-cycle-and-standards&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#tech-maturity-cycle-and-standards&#34;&gt;
	Tech Maturity Cycle and standards
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cynefin_framework&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cynefin&lt;/a&gt;

 as a Market Maturity Model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are in the chaotic phase of market maturity:
Nobody has a business model for this.
It is unclear what the market will look like, what the standards are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the landgrab phase, building market share in a new and emerging market.
Interop is secondary, because the future standards are not yet visible.
Player try to differentiate themselves with features, also to find out which features matter.
All players grow in a growing market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as a business model and stable feature lists exists and there is a system for money extraction the market can consolidate.
As always, 3-5 companies will dominate the market, which is dropping out of hypergrowth.
The dominating companies acknowledge their respective existence and roles, and compete semi-cooperatively:
It is more important to erect barriers to entry for disruptors than to destroy the existing competition, and hence there will be complex, hard to implement standards with expensive compliance tests.
This will then, against all wishes, lead to interoperability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;metaverse-revised-definition&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#metaverse-revised-definition&#34;&gt;
	Metaverse, revised definition
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we get:
The Metaverse is an integration of the gaming industry with the entertainment industry, and the merging of their value chains, optionally extracting a transactional tax at any point of the value chain.
The objective is to monetize the lifetime intellectual consumption budget of any person, and extending the market of products relevant to that person, decoupling spend from attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A main result is that books, films and games bind too much time to consume and limit spend.
3D assets are a better sale binding for less time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also the backdrop to read &amp;ldquo;Epic vs. Apple and Google&amp;rdquo; properly:
This is about opening the monopolistic markets these companies have for their hardware products, and allow other companies to monetize their walled gardens with their own offerings directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The german outlook is dreary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lacking highspeed, low latency infrastructure for gaming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lacking a German company with identity platforms (&amp;ldquo;Login with x&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lacking resources and companies with 3D asset tooling, production, marketplaces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lacking German film/tv/literature IP that can be integrated with any of this, especially on a global scale.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;German companies and culture looks inward, into the own country, not towards a global cultural base.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare with Korea: Korean production chains in K-Pop; Korean &amp;ldquo;cultural technology&amp;rdquo; that integrated other cultures styles and art and integrates it into K-Pop; production and grooming pipelines for stars and starlets; emerging similar chains for IP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In comparison, Germany counts as unarmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;toxic-dystopic-interpretation&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#toxic-dystopic-interpretation&#34;&gt;
	Toxic-dystopic interpretation
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Property&amp;rdquo; in a simulated reality looks like property, but is virtual and can be duplicated easily.
Virtualization removes resource constraints in production, but &amp;ldquo;value&amp;rdquo; is only created by uniqueness in consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The platform operators and &amp;ldquo;tax&amp;rdquo; authorities have full market transparency and can meter the time spent and consumption habits of everybody.
They know what you look at and listen to, what you are using, which styles you like and can sell this data for money to creators. They will also sell access to you to creators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HHOS: in the future at birth of child, you will first have to decide which corporate tribe it joins and then find a name compliant with that tribes rules. Switching between tribes is as complicated as an emigration to or from North Korea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A central building block is also DRM, here under the marketing name of &amp;ldquo;NFT&amp;rdquo;. NFT is the blockchain word for DRM, only with added destruction of the planet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unique things are only possible with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;locking the machine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TPM,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in-game only licensed assets and mods usable, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NFT Laser Eyes crypto bullshit that burns the planet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this context also the current engagement of Epic in the NFT bull.
Proper standards will be important, and &amp;ldquo;identity&amp;rdquo; is central for &amp;ldquo;property&amp;rdquo;.
This does not need blockchain, and will work better without - the platforms are central anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friend, commenting further:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to bind these people into this universe (&amp;ldquo;Hyperinclusion&amp;rdquo;).
They buy in the metaverses store, date their partners in metaverse locations, watch ads for products only available in the metaverse, and can hardly formulate metaverse critical thinking.
There is no public space anymore, everything is part of the gated community (cf loss of the almende).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There may be competition between a small number of metaverses, but within one metaverse there is only managed competition.
That is, the metaverse monopolizes a life in its totality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is a lot like mining towns in the US in the late 19th century.
The shop was owned by the mine, the priest was employed by the mine, and the sheriff and mayor were mine employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effectively the FB strategy is to make their social media monopoly permanent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads us to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;currency&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#currency&#34;&gt;
	Currency
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cryptocurrencies have demonstrated to large players that money creation is now &amp;ldquo;up for grabs&amp;rdquo;.
A metaverse is a very good environment to realize that &amp;ldquo;en passant&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, watch the Epic engagement in crypto for details.
This is problematic:
Metaverse and production in it takes resources from the real world, but does not produce value for the real world.
The real world is getting poorer, but that is where we live.
What does that mean long term for the creation of value and money?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;material&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#material&#34;&gt;
	Material
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;URL collection&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;golem-auf-der-suche-nach-dem-wal&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#golem-auf-der-suche-nach-dem-wal&#34;&gt;
	Golem &amp;ldquo;Auf der Suche nach dem Wal&amp;rdquo;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.golem.de/news/geschaeftsethik-bei-videospielen-auf-der-suche-nach-dem-wal-2110-160163.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Auf der Suche nach dem Wal&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, a video game growth manager (German article).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;colorado-law-review-dark-patterns&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#colorado-law-review-dark-patterns&#34;&gt;
	Colorado Law Review Dark Patterns
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link from the above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://lawreview.colorado.edu/printed/when-the-cats-away-techlash-loot-boxes-and-regulating-dark-patterns-in-the-video-game-industrys-monetization-strategies/%23IV_Broad_Guidance_for_Crafting_Effective_Dark_Pattern_Regulation_in_the_Video_Game_Industry&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=docs&amp;amp;ust=1635284752797000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw30IDuuhFqtcvDbNj32joER&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;When the Cat’s Away: Techlash, Loot Boxes, and Regulating “Dark Patterns” in the Video Game Industry’s Monetization Strategies&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;,
Sektion &amp;ldquo;IV. Broad Guidance for Crafting Effective Dark Pattern Regulation in the Video Game Industry&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;matthew-ballhttpstwittercomballmatthew&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#matthew-ballhttpstwittercomballmatthew&#34;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ballmatthew&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Matthew Ball&lt;/a&gt;


    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.matthewball.vc/all/themetaverse&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Metaverse: What It Is, Where to Find it, Who Will Build It, and Fortnite&lt;/a&gt;

: Original Metaverse Article&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Media side:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time Netflix launched its streaming service, much of Hollywood knew that the future of television was online (IP TV had been deployed in the late 1999s). The challenge was timing and how to package such a service (it took another 10 years for Hollywood to accept all of their channels, genres and content needs to be collapsed into a single app/brand).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ball writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Metaverse, we think, will be &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Persistent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Synchronous and live.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be without any cap to concurrent users, while also providing each user with an individual sense of “presence”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be a fully functioning economy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be an experience that spans both the digital and physical worlds, private and public networks/experiences, and open and closed platforms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offer unprecedented interoperability of data, digital items/assets, content, and so on across each of these experiences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be populated by “content” and “experiences” created and operated by an incredibly wide range of contributors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Metaverse is not…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A “virtual world”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A “virtual space”  (2nd life)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Virtual reality”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A “digital and virtual economy”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &amp;ldquo;game&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A “virtual theme park or Disneyland”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A “new app store”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A “new UGC platform”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is, of course, nonsense, it will be all of these things, &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt;.
This is Valley Hype to make the Next Internet sellable, and to have a common tale to tell.
But in the end this is all about the things it is supposedly NOT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.matthewball.vc/the-metaverse-primer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nine newer longer articles&lt;/a&gt;

 on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fortnite-loyalty-programhttpstwittercomduddyalan233status1391884040547049473&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#fortnite-loyalty-programhttpstwittercomduddyalan233status1391884040547049473&#34;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DuddyAlan233/status/1391884040547049473&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fortnite Loyalty Program&lt;/a&gt;


    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep up engagement and interest.
A problem for any MMO:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People don&amp;rsquo;t live in the metaverse, the live here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Primary consumption is casual, not high-end gamer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That is the weakness of the concept, esp Facebook.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can only become a Metaverse if it becomes a permanent place.
That&amp;rsquo;s still a long road to travel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My VR goggles are sitting around, idle (sold the Oculus because mandatory FB account).
That is, because &amp;ldquo;entering VR&amp;rdquo; is an act (set things up, calibrate), and the goggles isolate (when I put them on, I am &amp;ldquo;gone&amp;rdquo;), and because it is used only by very few games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;epic-and-facebook-the-race-called-metaversehttpstwittercomthegamespodcaststatus1450468392952115233&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#epic-and-facebook-the-race-called-metaversehttpstwittercomthegamespodcaststatus1450468392952115233&#34;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/thegamespodcast/status/1450468392952115233&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Epic and Facebook: The Race called Metaverse&lt;/a&gt;


    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pastry-eth-threadhttpstwittercompastryethstatus1423803492314009606&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#pastry-eth-threadhttpstwittercompastryethstatus1423803492314009606&#34;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/PastryEth/status/1423803492314009606&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pastry Eth Thread&lt;/a&gt;


    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crypto bullshit with a few good ideas, but also illusions/lies about what will happen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;1/5 of FB now working on AR&amp;rdquo;, FB looks at Metaverse as &amp;ldquo;Oculus&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;VR&amp;rdquo;. That&amp;rsquo;s dangerous tunnel vision.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The &amp;ldquo;Metaverse&amp;rdquo; is a virtual space created by the convergence of virtually enhanced physical reality, AR &amp;amp; the Internet: Our current 2D search based version of the Internet is giving way to a fully 3D immersive reality&amp;rdquo;: bullshit, unless consumption becomes casual. 3D Assets in Pancake Games are easier to sell &amp;ldquo;Cosmetics&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Metaverse is always “on” &amp;amp; is beyond the control of any individual. It exists in real time, can host any size audience, has a functioning economy, spans across platforms, provides interoperability for digital assets, &amp;amp; consists of the content and experiences its users create.&amp;rdquo; That is 2nd 2nd life as a concept, and  &amp;ldquo;3D Shoppingmalls&amp;rdquo; of the early 90ies revived. As a concept not wrong, and at the same time completely wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;In the Metaverse, the earning power for young creators won’t be limited to the top 1%. There will be an entire new era of young entrepreneurs making a living in virtual worlds, earning real value and steady income quicker than ever imagined.&amp;rdquo; LOL. Mainly this is about a microsoft tax, that will siphon off money from creators along the way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Creators who were once limited in their ability by technological constraints, lack of capital, time, or creativity, now have everything that is needed. What happens when physical objects are dematerialized? All formerly scarce materials become abundant.&amp;rdquo; LOL. DRM all the way is a requirement to make this work. Also, the permanent promise of creators paradise, when this is really about monopolization of the value chain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afterwards: Thread degrades into Laser Eyes Nonsense&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;digital-twinshttpswwwdezeencom20210723digital-twins-metaverse-david-weir-mccall-epic-games&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#digital-twinshttpswwwdezeencom20210723digital-twins-metaverse-david-weir-mccall-epic-games&#34;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dezeen.com/2021/07/23/digital-twins-metaverse-david-weir-mccall-epic-games/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Digital Twins&lt;/a&gt;


    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital twins will act as &amp;ldquo;foundations of the metaverse&amp;rdquo; and allow people to move between real and virtual spaces&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again &amp;ldquo;2nd 2nd Life&amp;rdquo;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skeuomorph&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Skeumorphism&lt;/a&gt;

 is what we do with new tech that does not yet have its own design language. The first cars looked like coaches, and the first Apple applications mimicked Rolodexes and Moleskines. &amp;ldquo;Digital Twins&amp;rdquo; is the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Core idea:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In April 2020, music artist Travis Scott staged a virtual concert inside the game that was attended live by 12.3 million people. It was a global phenomenon that sent the American rapper to the top of all music charts and earned him a reported $20 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read: &amp;ldquo;OMG, somebody has used a children&amp;rsquo;s battle royale to earn money without shooting players, but with traditional media work.&amp;rdquo;, and we are back to &amp;ldquo;all the ideas of 2nd life we know are problematic may still be valid again&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If the metaverse is an equivalent reality that coexists next to the physical reality, there needs to be a connection,&amp;rdquo; said Weir-McCall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does not need that at all. If, then more likely as AR than as 3D models, because connections to the real world is what you lose with 3D VR goggles. Casual is king.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;facebook-glasshttpswwwreuterscomtechnologyfacebook-unveils-its-first-smart-glasses-2021-09-09-and-acceptance&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#facebook-glasshttpswwwreuterscomtechnologyfacebook-unveils-its-first-smart-glasses-2021-09-09-and-acceptance&#34;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/technology/facebook-unveils-its-first-smart-glasses-2021-09-09/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Facebook Glass&lt;/a&gt;

 and acceptance
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Goggle were identifiable and their users vilified as glassholes.
Facebook is using Ray Bay to cover that.
There is no technical relationship between Oculus and AR.
This is about hiding the tech in the goggles to make it acceptable, and prevent a Facebook glasshole effect.
Also, AR is more casual than VR.
Fashion also allows easier re-sales of the same item, see also Apple Watch accessories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;laser-eyeshttpstwittercomcryptomarsmoonstatus1448249433573904384&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#laser-eyeshttpstwittercomcryptomarsmoonstatus1448249433573904384&#34;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Cryptomarsmoon/status/1448249433573904384&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Laser Eyes&lt;/a&gt;


    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s gonna be epic to bring the squid game to the metaverse. Salute to your team! I am a big fan of the TV series. I am super excited to have a chance to participate in this game! LFG!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More Laser Eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metaverse</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/10/26/metaverse.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 20:55:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/10/26/metaverse.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ich &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/isotopp/status/1450739310546886657&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;schrieb auf Twitter&lt;/a&gt;

 was zum aktuellen Begriff &amp;ldquo;Metaverse&amp;rdquo;.
Das hat zu einem Kontakt mit &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/michacarl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Michael Carl&lt;/a&gt;

 geführt, der mich in seinem &lt;a href=&#34;https://carls-zukunft.de/folge-58-how-to-build-a-metaversum-in-three-simple-steps/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Podcast&lt;/a&gt;

 haben wollte.
Meine &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1_OIl_bcrjVczLQrMrVnt5IoYbitp1504mb2GbQK0EM4/edit#heading=h.wbe6wnc7fg59&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gesprächsnotizen und Vorbereitung&lt;/a&gt;

 habe ich nun auch hier:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;metaverse&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#metaverse&#34;&gt;
	Metaverse
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Begriff &amp;ldquo;Metaverse&amp;rdquo; stammt ursprünglich von Neal Stephenson, aus dem Jahre 1992, aber er ist im aktuellen Kontext von Matthew Ball in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.matthewball.vc/all/themetaverse&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Metaverse: What It Is, Where to Find it, Who Will Build It, and Fortnite&lt;/a&gt;

 mit Sinn gefüllt worden. Ball hat dann später &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.matthewball.vc/the-metaverse&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;mehr zum Thema&lt;/a&gt;

 geschrieben, und so den aktuellen Silicon Valley Hype erzeugt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Überlegung beginnt mit Spielen, die nicht mehr sind, was sie mal waren, sondern irgendwie mehr geworden sind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fortnite von Epic Games, in der nun auch Nicht-Fortnite-Aktivitäten stattfinden,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roblox, eine Plattform zur spielerischen Generierung von Computerspielen, und&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minecraft in der Java- und der Bedrock-Edition, um zu zeigen, wie beides auf seine Weise unternehmerische Fehlschläge sind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fortnite&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#fortnite&#34;&gt;
	Fortnite
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortnite war mal Battle Royale, aber ist inzwischen auch eine &amp;ldquo;Veranstaltungsplattform&amp;rdquo;, man kann dort Skins kaufen, Partnerschaften mit anderem IP, zum Beispiel Marvel/DC Super Heroes.
Leute haben dort Konzerte gegeben oder andere Veranstaltungen durchgeführt.
Epic unterstützt das, recht offen, weil es Fortnite so auch bei Leuten bekannt macht, die an Battle Royal und Gamer-Kultur nicht primär interessiert sind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Epic Games macht auch die Unreal Engine, und die dazu gehörenden Pipelines zum Erstellen und Editieren von digitalen Game-Assets, betreibt einen Markt für diese Dinge und baut auch sonst eine lebendige Infrastruktur zur Spielerzeugung und zur Vermarktung auf.
Gewissermaßen ist dies die unsichtbare &amp;ldquo;Rückseite&amp;rdquo; von Spielen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;roblox&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#roblox&#34;&gt;
	Roblox
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ganz ähnlich, aber viel mehr casual betreibt Roblox sowieso eine Plattform zur Erzeugung von Spielen, und macht so Assets, aber auch einen Markt für Assets.
Roblox ist vor allen Dingen bei jungen und sehr jungen Menschen populär, und wird bei älteren Menschen weit unterschätzt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;minecraft-in-zwei-geschmacksrichtungen&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#minecraft-in-zwei-geschmacksrichtungen&#34;&gt;
	Minecraft in zwei Geschmacksrichtungen
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minecraft ist ein Klassiker: Das originale Minecraft ist in Java geschrieben und inzwischen komplett durch Komponenten von Drittherstellern ersetzbar. Es gibt alternative Clients, alternative Server, alternative Assets.
Das Spiel ist schlecht: Es ist eine Sandbox ohne viel Story und ohne Spielziel mit primitiver Grafik, die originalen Server sind langsam und fehlerhaft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aber die Grafik ist simpel, sodass das Spiel auch auf abgelegten Kartoffelcomputern funktioniert.
Es ist alles in Java geschrieben, das sich leicht reversen und dann unkooperativ erweitern lässt, und so gibt es eine reichhaltige Community mit Moddern, Server- und Client-Plugins, und vielen anderen Erweiterungen.
Das macht das Spiel populär und zu einer &amp;ldquo;Einstiegsdroge&amp;rdquo; in die Java-Programmierung bei jungen Menschen, weil es ein unglaubliches Potenzial für Selbstmotivation bietet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nichts davon ist durch den derzeitigen Eigentümer Microsoft monetarisierbar.
Als IP ist Minecraft für Microsoft gescheitert, weil Microsoft nach dem Kauf des Spiels nicht mehr Teil der Verwertungskette ist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daher gibt es von Microsoft &amp;ldquo;Minecraft Bedrock Edition&amp;rdquo;, performanter und besser designt, und von Grund auf mit einem Asset-Markt integriert.
Erweiterungen für Bedrock sind im Laden kaufbar, und nur dort.
Man muss als Anbieter IP von Microsoft lizenzieren und dann Prozente zahlen, als Kunde sowieso.
Bei den Spielern ist es deswegen kaum populär, steril und ohne eigene Kultur.
Im Vergleich zu Java Edition noch ein größerer Fehlschlag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das Bedrock-Modell ist vergleichbar mit dem Apple Entwicklermodell, aber kleiner im Scope:
Man kann nicht ernsthaft für Apple entwickeln ohne Apple-ID, Entwickler-Lizenz, Cloud-Nutzung für Handover und Storage und ohne Prozente im Apple Store zu bezahlen.
Bedrock ist danach modelliert, aber halt kein Computer-Tablet-ökosystem, sondern nur ein Spiel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;metaverse-eine-erste-definition&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#metaverse-eine-erste-definition&#34;&gt;
	Metaverse: Eine erste Definition
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die tatsächliche Definition von &amp;ldquo;Metaverse&amp;rdquo; sind also nicht 3D-Brillen, sondern &amp;ldquo;die Integration der Computerspieleindustrie mit der Wertschöpfungskette der Unterhaltungsindustrie für einen offenen, digitalen Assetmarkt&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oder offener: Das Anzapfen der Spieleverwertungskette an jeder Stelle im Produktionsfluß, und das Aufwerten der Spieleverwertungskette durch Integration mit Intellectual Property aus Filmen und Büchern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es geht also darum, aus dem Lebenszeit-Konsum-Budget einer Person mehr Geld herauszuziehen, ohne zu viel Lebenszeit bei dieser Person zu verbrauchen, also um eine Aufweitung von Ausgaben für &amp;ldquo;Medien&amp;rdquo; im aller weitesten Sinne.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;budgets-für-aufmerksamkeit-und-geld&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#budgets-f%c3%bcr-aufmerksamkeit-und-geld&#34;&gt;
	Budgets für Aufmerksamkeit und Geld
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Menschen haben Geldlimits für ihre Freizeit, der &lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Verf%C3%BCgbares_Einkommen&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Konsumanteil des verfügbaren Einkommens&lt;/a&gt;

.
Sie haben auch Zeitlimits für ihre Freizeit, ein Budget für Aufmerksamkeit.
Beides ist konvertibel, aber das hängt am Medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nimmt man eine nützliche Lebenszeit, in der ich &amp;ldquo;Lesen&amp;rdquo; kann von 60 Jahren an, und unterstellt man einem fleißigen Leser 40 Bücher (eines pro Woche) im Jahr, dann wird diese Person in ihrem Leben 2400 Bücher lesen, im Wert von sagen wir ~30 Euro pro Stück.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arbeitet man mit Computerspielen der AAA-Klasse, dann schafft man eventuell 4-6 Spiele im Jahr sinnvoll durchzuspielen, also im Leben 240-300 Titel, im Wert von ~60 Euro pro Stück.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das setzt eine Größenordnung von Lebensumsatz pro Person für diese Dinge, also ~70k Euro in Büchern oder 20k Euro in Spielen pro Personenleben.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wir sehen insbesondere, daß Spiele im Vergleich zu ihrem Produktionsaufwand viel zu billig sind, aber ein höherer Preis als 60 Euro ist auch für einen AAA-Titel nicht durchsetzbar.
Das ist einer der Gründe, warum in jedem einzelnen dieser Spiele weitere Möglichkeiten zum Geldausgeben enthalten sind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generell ist es aber bei beiden Medien so, daß das Geldausgeben im Vergleich zu der aufgewendeten Zeit zu langsam ist:
Die Burnrate muss hoch.
Bücher, aber auch Filme und insbesondere AAA-Titel von Computerspielen sind viel zu werthaltig, und ihr Konsum ist zu aufwendig.
Wir suchen was anderes, bei dem nicht so viele Minuten Lebenszeit pro ausgegebenem Euro aufgewendet werden müsse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist kritisch, weil es ja auch noch viele freie Inhalte gibt, die auch um Aufmerksamkeit buhlen und &amp;ldquo;gut genug&amp;rdquo; sind, um bezahlte Inhalte zu verdrängen.
Sie kosten Minuten Aufmerksamkeit, ohne Geld zu verdienen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;nebenschauplatz-sterben-und-erben&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#nebenschauplatz-sterben-und-erben&#34;&gt;
	Nebenschauplatz: Sterben und Erben
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Angesichts der alternden Bevölkerung gibt es auch noch den Nebenschauplatz &amp;ldquo;Boomer sterben, Kinder erben&amp;rdquo;.
Ich habe zum Beispiel genau jetzt ca. 600 Steam Titel und 1000 Kindle Books.
Wenn ich sterbe, sind das einige 10k Euro Wert.
Wie vererbe ich die meinem Sohn?
Die Politik hat keine Antworten, und die Hersteller lassen das nicht zu.
Ich kann meinem Kind also nur mein Steam Login vermachen und von meinen Kindle-Büchern das DRM knacken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wirtschaftlich sind Kindle und Steam-Erbschaften für die Hersteller weitgehend irrelevant, oder wären sogar positiv, und es ist unklar, wieso man sich so sträubt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenn ein Haus am See erbe, kann ich da hereingehen, die Veranda aufschließen, in den Park gehen und so das Asset genießen.
Das kostet mich nicht viel Zeit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erbe ich dagegen eine Kindle- oder Steam-Library, kostet mich das viel Zeit in der Erschließung:
Wenn ich 1200 Bücher erbe, sind das 30 Jahre Lebenszeit, die ich investieren muss, um das Erbe zu verarbeiten.
Wenn ich 1000 Spiele erbe, sind da Titel von 2002 bei, die heute wie Dreck aussehen.
Ich erbe &amp;ldquo;Skyrim&amp;rdquo;, muss aber &amp;ldquo;Skyrim VR&amp;rdquo; und &amp;ldquo;Skyrim Remastered&amp;rdquo; selbst kaufen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wir sehen sofort: Erben ist für den Hersteller kein relevanter Umsatzverlust, sondern eher noch ein Mittel zur Verkaufsförderung.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;assets-hoher-geldaufwand-geringer-zeitaufwand&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#assets-hoher-geldaufwand-geringer-zeitaufwand&#34;&gt;
	Assets: hoher Geldaufwand, geringer Zeitaufwand
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bereits heute ist in Spielen neben Lootboxen und Pay-to-Win und Pay-to-Skip Modellen der Verkauf von Cosmetics eine der größten Einnahmequellen, und im Gegensatz zu den anderen Geldquellen weitgehend unumstritten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pay-to-Win: Das Spiel ist nicht erfolgreich zu beenden, außer man kauft Ausrüstungsgegenstände für Echtgeld dazu. Idealerweise wird das erst sichtbar, wenn man bereits eine Menge Zeit und Emotion in das Spiel investiert hat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pay-to-Skip: Das Spiel wird immer wieder durch ärgerliche Wartepausen unterbrochen, in denen man nicht weiterspielen kann, außer man kauft die Pause durch Echtgeld weg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lootboxen: Das Spiel verkauft einem Container einem zufälligen Inhalt an Spielgegenständen, bei denen selten wertvolle Dinge enthalten sind. Das eigentliche Spiel ist also eine Verpackung für ein Glücksspiel im Inneren. Diese Praxis ist mittlerweile in einigen EU-Ländern verboten.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Im Gegensatz dazu sind Cosmetics weitgehend unumstritten: Das sind Gegenstände, die der Spielfigur und ihrer Ausrüstung ein anderes Aussehen geben, ein virtuelles Haus und seine Einrichtung, die auf das Spiel keine wesentliche Auswirkung haben und ähnliches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Im Spiel &amp;ldquo;Elder Scrolls Online&amp;rdquo; zum Beispiel bekommt man als Spieler leicht und zu geringen Kosten virtuelle Wohnhäuser in der Spielwelt, die sehr spektakulär liegen und aussehen und viel leeren Platz bieten.
Gegenstände zum Einrichten kann man sich als Trophäen erspielen, aber wesentliche Alltagsgegenstände zur Einrichtung sind nur via Echtgeld-Einsatz im Shop zu kaufen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das für den Hersteller wunderbare dabei:
Der Spieler kann in den Kauf von Cosmetics beliebig viel Geld reinpumpen und wird dabei kaum Lebenszeit oder Aufmerksamkeit aufbringen müssen.
Limitierend kann also nur die Geldbörse des Kunden wirken, nicht aber sein Zeitbudget.
Das macht so etwas zu einem viel besseren Geschäftsfeld als Bücher, Filme oder die Spiele selbst.
Das Spiel liefert nur den Kontext und Anlass für die Cosmetics zu existieren und bestimmt ihr Aussehen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;epic-games&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#epic-games&#34;&gt;
	Epic Games
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dies ist genau die Geschäftsgrundlage von Epic Games:
Mit der Unreal Engine bietet die Firma eine Plattform zum schnellen und effizienten Design von sehr gut aussehenden Videospielen.
Dazu gehören auch Werkzeuge zum Erzeugen der Ingame-Assets, aber auch der Betrieb einer Verkaufsplattform für solche Assets an Spielhersteller.
Mit dem Epic Launcher und dem darin integrierten Shop auch eine Plattform zum Verkauf von Spielen, und zum Erfassen von Meta- und Nutzungsdaten an Epic, die dann wiederum (gegen Geld) dem Spielhersteller als Analytics angeboten werden.
Das von Epic betriebene Payment-System ist die Pipeline, über die Geld vom Kunden zum Spielhersteller fließen kann, und über die nicht nur die Spiele, sondern auch Erweiterungen, In-Game Käufe und andere Geldausgaben abgewickelt werden können.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mit Fortnite hat man aber auch ein eigenes Spiel am Start, das zugleich auch 3D Assets an Endkunden als Ausrüstungsgegenstände, Cosmetics oder sonst wie verkaufen kann.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortnite ist eine bestimmte Sorte Spiel - Player vs. Player, im Battle Royal Modus, Spieler treten gegeneinander an und der letzte Überlebende gewinnt.
Diese Sorte Spiel ist nicht für alle Zielgruppen interessant, aber die Engine von Fortnite lässt sich auch anderweitig nutzen.
Entsprechend weckt man Interesse durch Nutzung von Fortnite als &amp;ldquo;virtuelle Veranstaltungsplattform&amp;rdquo; und hält das Interesse durch Media Tie-Ins und Licensed IP aufrecht.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Interpretation von Metaverse als Verwertungskette von digitalen Assets, speziell 3D Assets, als &amp;ldquo;Online-Merchandise&amp;rdquo; greift jedoch zu kurz:
Als Ökosystem mit einer kontrollierten Anzahl von großen Marktbetreibern und einer großen Anzahl von Kunden und Kreativen steht man viel besser und vor allen Dingen dauerhafter da.
Man kann Dritten auf diese Weise erlauben, untereinander Handel zu treiben, aber dabei laufend einen geringen Anteil an allen Transaktionen abgreifen.
Gewissermaßen will man die Idee der &amp;ldquo;Microsoft-Tax&amp;rdquo; in einem anderen Kontext wieder aufleben lassen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;spieler-am-markt&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#spieler-am-markt&#34;&gt;
	Spieler am Markt
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unterschiedliche Ausgangspositionen bei&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Epic Games/Fortnite - schwach bei IP, aber original IP, wenn auch Nische, Unreal Engine und die anderen Dinge auf der &amp;ldquo;Rückseite&amp;rdquo; der Spiele als große Stärke.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roblox - original IP, sehr junge Kundschaft, erzieht sich gerade Kinder, 10 Jahre warten, groß unterschätzt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Microsoft - Minecraft, MS Store et al, zu Enterprise um erfolgreich zu sein? Aber Halo, MSFS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple (sic!) - kein IP, aber Plattform/Kette.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disney (sic!) - nur IP, aber schwach in Verwertung außerhalb von Filmen/offline Merchandise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook - will da unbedingt rein, &amp;ldquo;Enterprise Pivot&amp;rdquo;: wenn Social in Zukunft &amp;ldquo;hier&amp;rdquo; stattfindet, dann muss Facebook &amp;ldquo;hier&amp;rdquo; sein.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google - insbesondere der Grund, wieso Google Stadia nicht wirklich einstellen kann, selbst wenn es ein Flop wird/ist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amazon - hier ist auch die Spiele Strategie von Amazon mit einordnen. Amazon wäre gerne das AWS der Spielewelt anstelle von Epic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tech-maturity-cycle-und-standards&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#tech-maturity-cycle-und-standards&#34;&gt;
	Tech Maturity Cycle und Standards
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cynefin_framework&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cynefin&lt;/a&gt;

 als Market Maturity Model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wir sind derzeit in einer chaotischen Phase der Marktentwicklung:
Niemand hat ein Geschäftsmodell in diesem Markt, es ist unklar, wie dieser überhaupt aussehen wird.
Standards existieren noch nicht.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es geht um Landgrab, also um den Aufbau von Marktanteilen in einem entstehenden und wachsenden Markt.
Interop ist sekundär, weil noch keine Idee vorhanden ist, wie die Standards aussehen werden.
Man versucht sich vom Mitbewerb durch Features zu differenzieren, und dabei auch herauszufinden, was wichtig ist.
Alle Spieler wachsen in einem wachsenden, entstehenden Markt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sobald es ein Geschäftsmodell, stabile Featurelisten und ein System zur Geldextraktion gibt, wird sich der Markt konsolidieren.
Dann beherrschen 3-5 Firmen den Markt, der auch aus dem Hyperwachstum heraus geht.
Die marktbeherrschenden Firmen erkennen einander an und konkurrieren semi-kooperativ miteinander:
Es ist wichtiger, den Marktzugang von Disruptoren zu erschweren, und es wird komplexe, schwierig zu implementierende Standards geben, mit Compliance Prüfungen und anderen Kostenfaktoren.
Das wird dann aber auch - zähneknirschend - zu Interoperabilität führen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;metaverse-überarbeitete-definition&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#metaverse-%c3%bcberarbeitete-definition&#34;&gt;
	Metaverse, überarbeitete Definition
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das führt uns zur überarbeiteten Definition von Metaverse:
Die Integration der Spieleindustrie mit der Unterhaltungsindustrie und die Integration der Wertschöpfungsketten, mit der Möglichkeit die Verwertungskette an jeder Stelle im Produktionsfluß mit einer Art Steuer zu belegen.
Ein systematisches Anzapfen des Lifetime Intellectual Property-Konsumbudgets einer Person, und die Aufweitung des Marktes, der für einen Konsumenten relevant ist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Erkenntnis, daß Buch, Filme und Spiele zu zeitaufwendig zu erstellen und zu konsumieren sind.
3D Assets ist viel größere Verkaufsgelegenheit, ohne daß der Kunde so viel Lebenszeit investieren muss, um tatsächlich den Kauf zu konsumieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vor diesem Hintergrund ist auch die laufende Auseinandersetzung von Epic vs. Apple und Google vor Gericht zu lesen: Es geht darum, das Anzapf-Monopol von Apple und den von Apple dominierten Markt für andere zu Öffnen zu unterminieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besondere deutsche Probleme dabei:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keine Infrastruktur für Highspeed, Low Latency wie man das für Spiele braucht.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keine deutsche Firma mit nennenswerter Identity Plattform (web.de? T-Online? &amp;ldquo;Login mit x&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keine deutschen Ressourcen im 3D-Asset Tooling, Produktion, &amp;hellip; Markt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keine deutsche Film/Fernseh/Lit Industrie zur Produktion von IP, Stories, die weltweit wiedererkennbare Kultur prägen, die man verkaufen kann.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deutscher Blick geht nach innen, ins eigene Land, nicht auf einen Weltmarkt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vergleiche dabei Korea: koreanische Produktionsketten in K-Pop; die &amp;ldquo;cultural technology&amp;rdquo; die andere Stile und Kunstrichtungen aufgreift und in K-Pop integriert; Produktionspipelines für Stars und Sternchen, aber auch für IP (beginnend).
Im Vergleich ist Deutschland essenziell wehrlos und angehängt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;toxisch-dystopische-interpretation&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#toxisch-dystopische-interpretation&#34;&gt;
	Toxisch-dystopische Interpretation
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das &amp;ldquo;Eigentum&amp;rdquo; in einer simulierten Realität sieht aus wie Eigentum, ist aber virtuell und kopierbar.
Es kommt im virtuellen zur einer Entfernung von Ressourcenknappheit bei der Produktion, aber &amp;ldquo;Wert&amp;rdquo; entsteht nur, wenn die Ware künstlich verknappt wird beim Konsum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Zollhaus-Stellen, Plattformbetreiber haben volle Markttransparenz, und können das Freizeit-Konsumverhalten jeder Person genau ausmessen.
Sie wissen, was Du siehst und hörst, was Du benutzt, welche Stile Dir zusagen und können diese Information gegen Geld an Kreative verkaufen, und verkaufen den Kreativen auch gegen Geld den Zugang zu Dir.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein Freund von mir:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nur ein halber Witz: man muss in Zukunft bei Geburt eines Kindes als Erstes entscheiden muss, ob es Apple-, Google- oder Facebook-Angehöriger wird und der Name erst danach entsprechend den Regeln des Dienstes festgelegt wird. Wechsel zwischen den Services ist dann komplex wie eine Emigration nach Nordkorea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zentraler Bestandteil bezüglich der Verknappung auch DRM, hier unter dem Modenamen &amp;ldquo;NFT&amp;rdquo; - &amp;ldquo;NFT&amp;rdquo; ist das Blockchain Wort für DRM, nur zusätzlich mit Umweltvergiftung durch Energieverschwendung.
Unikate gibt es nur mit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rechner zunageln,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TPM,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in-game nur lizenzierte Assets und Mods verwendbar, und&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NFT Laser Eyes Kryptoscheisse, die den Planeten verbrennt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In diesem Kontext ist auch das aktuelle Engagement von Epic im NFT Misthaufen zu lesen sehen.
Daher: korrekte Standards sind wichtig, und Identität ist die Grundlage für &amp;ldquo;Eigentum&amp;rdquo;.
Das braucht nicht nur keine Blockchain, es funktioniert auch besser ohne - die Plattformen sind eh zentral.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der Freund kommentiert wieder:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es geht darum, dass die Leute aus dem Universum nicht rauskommen können (Stichwort: Hyperinklusion).
Sie kaufen in Metaverse-Shops, daten ihre Partner in Metaverse-Locations, sehen nur noch Werbung für im Metaverse verfügbare Waren, können Metaverse-kritische Gedanken kaum noch formulieren.
Es gibt keinen Public-Space mehr im Leben, alles ist Teil der gated community (Vgl. Verlust der Almende).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Du hast vielleicht noch einen Wettbewerb zwischen x Metaversen, aber innerhalb eines Metaversums gibt es dann einen oder nur noch einen gesteuerten Wettbewerb.
D.h. das Metaversum monopolisiert den Menschen in seiner Gesamtheit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist ein bisschen wie die Minenstädte in den USA Ende des 19. Jhd.
Der Shop gehörte der Mine, der Pfarrer arbeitete für die Mine, die Mine stellte Sheriff und Bürgermeister.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effektiv will FB durch das Metaversum ihr gegenwärtiges Social-Media-Monopol verewigen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das führt thematisch zur Geldtheorie:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;currency&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#currency&#34;&gt;
	Currency
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Durch die CryptoCurrencies ist für die großen jetzt klar, dass die Geldschöpfung &amp;ldquo;up for the grabs&amp;rdquo; ist. Ein Metaversum wäre der perfekte Ansatz das &amp;ldquo;en passant&amp;rdquo; zu realisieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An dieser Stelle kommt dann gleich wieder das Epic Engagement bei &amp;ldquo;Cryptocurrentcies&amp;rdquo; zum Tragen.
Das ist sehr problematisch:
Metaversum und Produktion dort nimmt nur Ressourcen aus der realen Welt, produziert dort aber nicht.
Am Ende wird die reale Welt ärmer, dort leben wir aber.
Was heißt das langfristig für Wertschöpfung und Geld?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;material&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#material&#34;&gt;
	Material
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;URL-Sammlung&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unsortierte-seitenlinien&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#unsortierte-seitenlinien&#34;&gt;
	Unsortierte Seitenlinien
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Immature Market, Geschäftsmodell existiert noch nicht als erprobter Business Plan (Cynefin Chaotic)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Einzelne Firmen weiter (Liste oben), Cynefin Complex&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alle Firmen unvollständig aufgestellt. Akquise schwierig, wen kaufen? Und die zu kaufenden Firmen sind selbst noch nicht fertig: Integration auch schwierig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;golem-auf-der-suche-nach-dem-wal&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#golem-auf-der-suche-nach-dem-wal&#34;&gt;
	Golem &amp;ldquo;Auf der Suche nach dem Wal&amp;rdquo;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.golem.de/news/geschaeftsethik-bei-videospielen-auf-der-suche-nach-dem-wal-2110-160163.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Auf der Suche nach dem Wal&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Videospiele Growth Manager, ein Bericht. Richtige Richtung, zu kurz, erklärt aber die Kette.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Im Gegensatz zu einem typischen Videospiel, bei dem man versucht, so viele Leute wie möglich dazu zu bringen, einmalig 60 Dollar für ein Spiel auszugeben, will ein Free-to-Play Spiel so viele Leute wie möglich zum Spielen zu animieren. Sobald sie spielen, bemüht sich das Unternehmen, so viele digitale Güter wie möglich an sie zu verkaufen. Es gibt zwar eine Obergrenze dafür, wie viel man für ein Spiel verlangen kann, aber es gibt keine Obergrenze für die Zahl an sinnlosen digitalen Tokens, die man verhökern kann.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Metaverse: Industrialisiere diesen Prozess und mainstreame ihn. Aspekte: Spielen nach Termin, Pay to Skip, Pay to Win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;colorado-law-review-dark-patterns&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#colorado-law-review-dark-patterns&#34;&gt;
	Colorado Law Review Dark Patterns
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link aus dem oa Golem Artikel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://lawreview.colorado.edu/printed/when-the-cats-away-techlash-loot-boxes-and-regulating-dark-patterns-in-the-video-game-industrys-monetization-strategies/%23IV_Broad_Guidance_for_Crafting_Effective_Dark_Pattern_Regulation_in_the_Video_Game_Industry&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=docs&amp;amp;ust=1635284752797000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw30IDuuhFqtcvDbNj32joER&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;When the Cat’s Away: Techlash, Loot Boxes, and Regulating “Dark Patterns” in the Video Game Industry’s Monetization Strategies&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;,
Sektion &amp;ldquo;IV. Broad Guidance for Crafting Effective Dark Pattern Regulation in the Video Game Industry&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es gibt eine Feedbackschleife zwischen den Spieldesignern und dem Wal (der Person, die sinnlos investiert):
Ungesund für beide Seiten, macht das Spiel schnell zu einem Spiel für wenige Vielzahler, und damit langfristig global schlecht; besondere Herausforderung beim Produktmanagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;matthew-ballhttpstwittercomballmatthew&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#matthew-ballhttpstwittercomballmatthew&#34;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ballmatthew&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Matthew Ball&lt;/a&gt;


    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.matthewball.vc/all/themetaverse&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Metaverse: What It Is, Where to Find it, Who Will Build It, and Fortnite&lt;/a&gt;

: Original Metaverse Article&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medienseite:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time Netflix launched its streaming service, much of Hollywood knew that the future of television was online (IP TV had been deployed in the late 1999s). The challenge was timing and how to package such a service (it took another 10 years for Hollywood to accept all of their channels, genres and content needs to be collapsed into a single app/brand).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ball schreibt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Metaverse, we think, will be &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Persistent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Synchronous and live.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be without any cap to concurrent users, while also providing each user with an individual sense of “presence”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be a fully functioning economy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be an experience that spans both the digital and physical worlds, private and public networks/experiences, and open and closed platforms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offer unprecedented interoperability of data, digital items/assets, content, and so on across each of these experiences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be populated by “content” and “experiences” created and operated by an incredibly wide range of contributors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Metaverse is not…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A “virtual world”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A “virtual space”  (2nd life)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Virtual reality”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A “digital and virtual economy”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &amp;ldquo;game&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A “virtual theme park or Disneyland”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A “new app store”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A “new UGC platform”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist natürlich Unsinn, es wird alle diese Dinge &lt;em&gt;auch&lt;/em&gt; sein.
Das ist alles Valley Hype, um The Next Internet als Begriff zu etablieren und eine gemeinsame Erzählung zu haben.
Aber am Ende ist geht es genau um diese 8 Dinge die es angeblich NICHT sein soll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.matthewball.vc/the-metaverse-primer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Neuere Artikel Serie, 9 Artikel lang&lt;/a&gt;

 dazu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fortnite-loyalty-programhttpstwittercomduddyalan233status1391884040547049473&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#fortnite-loyalty-programhttpstwittercomduddyalan233status1391884040547049473&#34;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DuddyAlan233/status/1391884040547049473&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fortnite Loyalty Program&lt;/a&gt;


    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es geht darum, User Engagement zu erhalten.
Das Problem muss jedes MMO lösen, denn&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Die Leute leben nicht im Metaverse, die leben hier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Primärer Konsum ist Casual, nicht High End Gamer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Das ist die Schwachstelle des Konzeptes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erst wenn das Ding zu einem ständigen Ort wird, kann es ein Metaversum werden.
Das ist noch ein langer Weg:
Meine VR-Brille steht hier ungenutzt rum (Oculus verkauft, wegen FB Zwang).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist so, weil &amp;ldquo;in VR zu gehen&amp;rdquo; ein Akt ist (aufbauen, kalibrieren), und die Brille isoliert (ich bin dann weg), und weil es nicht viele Spiele gibt, die das sinnvoll nutzen (Elite Dangerous, MSFS-2020, Moss, selten auch Space Pirate Trainer).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;epic-and-facebook-the-race-called-metaversehttpstwittercomthegamespodcaststatus1450468392952115233&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#epic-and-facebook-the-race-called-metaversehttpstwittercomthegamespodcaststatus1450468392952115233&#34;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/thegamespodcast/status/1450468392952115233&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Epic and Facebook: The Race called Metaverse&lt;/a&gt;


    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pastry-eth-threadhttpstwittercompastryethstatus1423803492314009606&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#pastry-eth-threadhttpstwittercompastryethstatus1423803492314009606&#34;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/PastryEth/status/1423803492314009606&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pastry Eth Thread&lt;/a&gt;


    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crypto Dummlall mit einigen guten Ideen, aber Illusionen über wie es laufen wird&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;1/5 of Facebook now working on AR&amp;rdquo;, für FB ist das Metaverse zur Zeit &amp;ldquo;Oculus&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;VR&amp;rdquo;. Das ist ein gefährlicher Tunnelblick (siehe oben &amp;ldquo;casual&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The &amp;ldquo;Metaverse&amp;rdquo; is a virtual space created by the convergence of virtually enhanced physical reality, AR &amp;amp; the internet: Our current 2D search based version of the internet is giving way to a fully 3D immersive reality&amp;rdquo;: Das ist Quatsch, solange 3D nicht komplett Casual konsumierbar wird, und eine 3D Brille ist derzeit isolierend, schwer und verkabelt. 3D Assets in Pancake Games sind leichter und direkt zu verkaufen, jetzt. &amp;ldquo;Cosmetics&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Metaverse is always “on” &amp;amp; is beyond the control of any individual. It exists in real time, can host any size audience, has a functioning economy, spans across platforms, provides interoperability for digital assets, &amp;amp; consists of the content and experiences its users create.&amp;rdquo; Das Konzept 2nd 2nd Life, und die &amp;ldquo;3D Shoppingmalls&amp;rdquo; der frühen 90er feiern fröhliche Urständ, als Konzept nicht falsch und gleichzeitig total falsch. 3D Events, die Presence ersetzen sind interessant, aber super hart.
Auch hier Korean Cultural Technology, K-POP Konsum während COVID-19 (Pancake, large Audiences, Gemeinschaftserlebnisse, &amp;ldquo;VR&amp;rdquo; Nebensache)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;In the Metaverse, the earning power for young creators won’t be limited to the top 1%. There will be an entire new era of young entrepreneurs making a living in virtual worlds, earning real value and steady income quicker than ever imagined.&amp;rdquo; LOL. In erster Linie geht es um Zollhäuschen entlang der Verwertungskette, mit dem durch Creators erschaffenen Mehrwert als Motor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Creators who were once limited in their ability by technological constraints, lack of capital, time, or creativity, now have everything that is needed. What happens when physical objects are dematerialized? All formerly scarce materials become abundant.&amp;rdquo; LOL. DRM all the way ist notwendig, damit das funktioniert. Außerdem das Dauerversprechen vom Creators Paradise, wenn es tatsächlich um Monopolisierung der Wertschöpfungskette geht.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danach: Thread degrades in Laser Eyes Nonsense&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;digital-twinshttpswwwdezeencom20210723digital-twins-metaverse-david-weir-mccall-epic-games&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#digital-twinshttpswwwdezeencom20210723digital-twins-metaverse-david-weir-mccall-epic-games&#34;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dezeen.com/2021/07/23/digital-twins-metaverse-david-weir-mccall-epic-games/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Digital Twins&lt;/a&gt;


    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital twins will act as &amp;ldquo;foundations of the metaverse&amp;rdquo; and allow people to move between real and virtual spaces&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist &amp;ldquo;2nd 2nd Life&amp;rdquo; &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skeuomorph&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Skeumorphism&lt;/a&gt;

 ist, was wir machen, wenn wir noch nicht wissen, was die Design Language für eine neue Welt ist. Die ersten Autos sagen aus wie Kutschen, die ersten Apple Anwendungen haben Rolodexe und Moleskine imitiert. &amp;ldquo;Digital Twins&amp;rdquo; sind dasselbe Konzept, aber für ein Metaversum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und die Kernidee:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In April 2020, music artist Travis Scott staged a virtual concert inside the game that was attended live by 12.3 million people. It was a global phenomenon that sent the American rapper to the top of all music charts and earned him a reported $20 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lies: &amp;ldquo;OMG, jemand hat in einem Kinder-Battle Royale Spiel Geld verdient ohne zu metzeln, sondern mit traditioneller Medienarbeit&amp;rdquo; führt sofort zu &amp;ldquo;Alle Ideen von 2nd Life, von denen wir schon wissen, dass sie problematisch sind, feiern Wiederauferstehung.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If the metaverse is an equivalent reality that coexists next to the physical reality, there needs to be a connection,&amp;rdquo; said Weir-McCall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ist es nicht, muss es nicht. Wenn es dann doch muss, eventuell eher AR als 3D-Modelle, denn Connection zur realen Welt hat man mit einer vollen VR-Brille eben nicht. Was ich oben über Casual Konsum sage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mein Freund merkt an:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital Twins / Digital Shadows sind übrigens auch Begriffe um den die Datenspur von Leuten zu bezeichnen.
Der Gesundheitsbereich versucht das ebenso zu etablieren, um anhand dieser Zwillinge Diagnostik betreiben zu können.
Das wird auch noch einmal spannend, wie das mit dem Metaverse verbunden wird.
Gerade aus Facebooks Sicht - welche Daten kann das Metaversum aus Deinem Avatar auslesen?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;facebook-glasshttpswwwreuterscomtechnologyfacebook-unveils-its-first-smart-glasses-2021-09-09-und-akzeptanz&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#facebook-glasshttpswwwreuterscomtechnologyfacebook-unveils-its-first-smart-glasses-2021-09-09-und-akzeptanz&#34;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/technology/facebook-unveils-its-first-smart-glasses-2021-09-09/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Facebook Glass&lt;/a&gt;

 und Akzeptanz
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bei Google Brille waren die Träger erkennbar, der Begriff Glassholes entstand.
Mit Ray Ban ist das besser zu tarnen.
Ray Ban hat keinen technischen Beitrag zu Oculus und AR, es geht nur darum, den Markennamen und das Design als Tarnung für Oculus zu nehmen, um den Google Glass Effect zu vermeiden.
Außerdem ist AR mehr Casual als VR.
Mode erlaubt auch einfacheren Neuverkauf, siehe auch Apple Watch Zubehör.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;laser-eyeshttpstwittercomcryptomarsmoonstatus1448249433573904384&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#laser-eyeshttpstwittercomcryptomarsmoonstatus1448249433573904384&#34;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Cryptomarsmoon/status/1448249433573904384&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Laser Eyes&lt;/a&gt;


    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s gonna be epic to bring the squid game to the metaverse. Salute to your team! I am a big fan of the TV series. I am super excited to have a chance to participate in this game! LFG!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noch mehr Laser Eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: AI Superpowers</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-ai-superpowers.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 16:19:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-ai-superpowers.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This 2018 book in some aspects is already outdated: Silicon Valley Techbro Kai-Fu Lee describes what AI is and what he thinks it will do to our future, the nature of work and the job market.
But since then, the worlds view on what AI can and cannot do, what the problems to solve really are and a lot of other things have changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/AI-Superpowers-Silicon-Valley-English-ebook/dp/B0795DNWCF&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/ai-superpowers.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/AI-Superpowers-Silicon-Valley-English-ebook/dp/B0795DNWCF&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;AI Superpowers:China, Silicon Valley, and the New World Order&lt;/a&gt;

, Kai-Fu Lee&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kai-Fu Lee is a Taiwanese born, American computer scientist, and worked at Apple, SGI, Microsoft and Google before becoming a venture capitalist in China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He coined the adage &amp;ldquo;If data is the new oil, then China is the new Saudi Arabia&amp;rdquo; and in the books proposes that China has several advantages over the US in an arms race over artificial intelligence:
Generally training deep learning models seems to be better suited to the Chinese approach of brute forcing a solution than to deep engineering;
China has few data protection regulations getting in the way of data collection;
Chinese startup culture is even more aggressive than the US one; and
the chinese government funds and steers the startup industry in China into the AI of AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lee believes that a number of jobs will be modified or eliminated by a potential AI revolution, including a number of white collar (office) jobs.
The examples he gives are jobs that consist mostly of - in his opinion - simple pattern recognition, such as rough translator, bank loan officer or customer care worker.
Similarly, the blue collar (worker) jobs at risk are truck driver, cashier or clothing factory worker.
In a way, three years later, his estimates look overly optimistic:
Self-driving cars are further away than they looked three years ago, and automated customer care with natural language recognition quickly transformed into the voice-mail hell as ten or twenty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is true is that AI can support human workers a lot in taking the boring parts of these jobs away, helping to provide rough estimates and marking clear cases as such.
Still, AI in 2021 seems to be successful where it augments human workers instead of completely replacing them.
In general, Lee&amp;rsquo;s view of the world is very mechanistic, and way too optimistic in what AI can actually completely solve without having a complete model of the world it acts in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Important input and still a good overview, but overtaken quickly by the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Old Man&#39;s War</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-old-mans-war.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 13:53:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-old-mans-war.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Old-Mans-English-John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B000SEIK2S&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Old Man&amp;rsquo;s War&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; is the first &amp;ldquo;large&amp;rdquo; works by John Scalzi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Old-Mans-English-John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B000SEIK2S&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/oldmanswar.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Old-Mans-English-John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B000SEIK2S&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Old Man&amp;rsquo;s War&lt;/a&gt;

, John Scalzi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plot premise is weird, but simple: Humanity has taken to the stars, but with private enterprise.
Basically all advanced space technology is controlled by the Colonial Union.
Life on earth on the other hand goes on almost as before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Perry enlists to serve in the Colonial Defense Force at the age of 75, to protect humanity, but mostly to have the CU fight the effects of him aging with some unspecified Scifi tech.
He leaves earth and during his induction to the CDF learns that he will be indeed rejuvenated, by transferring his consciousness into a new, young, genetically engineered body tailored for planetary combat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perry&amp;rsquo;s first tour of duty sees battles on a number of CU planets and fights against various interstellar races.
He soon learns that the CU is not actually involved much in galactic politics and has only limited knowledge about the background and motivation of the various space-faring intelligences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fight against the man-eating Rraey leaves him wounded and left for dead on the contested planet Coral.
He is found by a member of the Ghost Brigades,  Jane Sagan, that he thinks looks like a younger version of his deceased wife Kathy, and befriends her.
He learns that Ghost Brigades are synthetic humans created from the DNA scans of CDF volunteers that died before they could join the CDF, but without the memory and experience of their human predecessors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While technically Mil SciFi, and therefore a genre I despise, Scalzi manages to keep the focus the story on the characters and their interactions instead of troop movements and space battles.
He is playing with the themes of generic engineering, encounters with alien races and the discovery of their motivation, and with building a connection to an image of a loved one, but without the memory and the shared experiences.
An engaging book with characters I can relate to, and a story well told.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Old-Mans-English-John-Scalzi-ebook/dp/B000SEIK2S&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Old Man&amp;rsquo;s War&lt;/a&gt;

 is continued in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Ghost-Brigades-Mans-Book-English-ebook/dp/B001QS9TSE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Ghost Brigades&lt;/a&gt;

 and in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B000YJ85BI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Last Colony&lt;/a&gt;

, finishing the John Perry&amp;rsquo;s viewpoint books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story of &amp;ldquo;The Last Colony&amp;rdquo; is being retold in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B002ENBLM2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zoe&amp;rsquo;s Tale&lt;/a&gt;

 from another character&amp;rsquo;s viewpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Human-Division-Mans-Book-English-ebook/dp/B00C2RSA9C&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Human Division&lt;/a&gt;

 then continues the original storyline, from another characters point of view, dealing with the aftermath of the revelation of the CU&amp;rsquo;s scheming with earth politics. Humanity finally joins the emerging galactic society and must find a place in one of the various alliances that the different intelligent species begin to form. The resulting diplomatic complications are further told in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B00SEPVPAW&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The End of All Things&lt;/a&gt;

 in a series of Novellas from different character viewpoints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all a series very worthwhile reading, exactly sufficient for one vacation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: These Savage Shores</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-these-savage-shores.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 15:12:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-these-savage-shores.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/therightram&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ram V&lt;/a&gt;

 is a writer, sometimes for comics.
Together with artist Sumit Kumar he wrote a simple story: English Vampires vs. Indian Rakshasa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/These-Savage-Shores-English-Ram-ebook/dp/B07YYNFP38&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/savage.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/These-Savage-Shores-English-Ram-ebook/dp/B07YYNFP38&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;These Savage Shores&lt;/a&gt;

, Ram V &amp;amp; Sumit Kumar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1760&amp;rsquo;ies.
An english vampire puts his peers at risk by not having his desires under control, and is exiled to Calicut, India.
He soon finds out that even older and fiercer beings rule the night: Rakshasa, the Vampire equivalent of Indian Myth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bishan, a Raskshasa, kills the vampire, drawing the english vampires out for revenge.
Before the background of a colonization war in India, Bishan and the vampire master Jurre Granno clash, first in India, then in England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fantastic illustrations, and a complex story well told, with rich metaphors, showing a clash of cultures and the infighting in pre-colonization India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a comic, the kindle edition does not read well on a Kindle, but works fine on Kindle for iPad or similar devices.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: This Is How You Lose The Time War</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 16:01:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Max Gladstone and Amal El-Mohtar co-authored &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/This-How-Lose-Time-English-ebook/dp/B07RTYNHRM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This Is How You Lose The Time-War&lt;/a&gt;

, not exactly a Science Fiction novel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/This-How-Lose-Time-English-ebook/dp/B07RTYNHRM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/time-war.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/This-How-Lose-Time-English-ebook/dp/B07RTYNHRM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This Is How You Lose The Time War&lt;/a&gt;

, Amal El-Mohtar and Max Gladstone&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red and Blue are representatives, spies and saboteurs of two nearly all-powerful, warring factions.
They travel through time to manipulate events at critical points in history in favor of their respective factions.
They are leaving each other messages, they taunt each other, and gradually earn mutual respect.
Eventually they grow close to each other, and love develops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red&amp;rsquo;s commanding officer learns of the interaction and forces Red to leave a message to Blue that kills her.
Red later fixes that &amp;ldquo;problem&amp;rdquo; by traveling into Blue&amp;rsquo;s childhood to give her immunity to the toxic message, and both escape the war by making off to elsewhere in time and space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an epistolary novel, written in the form of the letters Red and Blue exchange.
We only learn very gradually about the characters, their capabilities and their background, and it becomes clear that what we read is not actually the account of two humans, but rather godlike entities or avatars of forces of nature.
Red and Blue over time grow close, and solve an initially unbridgeable conflict between the cultures or forces they represent at a very personal level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a hard read, and if you were looking for an actual Science Fiction story, this isn&amp;rsquo;t one.
Telling a story in the form of letters and having characters that are only remotely human at best is not a good vehicle to create tension, of paint a clear picture of what goes on.
At multiple points the book reads more like some form of poetry as opposed a novel or regular prose.
The storytelling ultimately manages to pull off a somewhat satisfactory ending, though, even if it is visible from almost the very start of the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being so different and not fucking things up of course won the book a number of awards in 2019 and 2020, so there is that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: Typeset in the Future</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-typeset-in-the-future.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 13:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-typeset-in-the-future.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dave Addey ran a Tumblr once, titled &amp;ldquo;Typeset in the Future&amp;rdquo;, in which he dissected the typography of Science Fiction films.
This has been turned into the eponymous book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Typeset-Future-Typography-Science-Fiction-ebook/dp/B07G7SGRZ2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/typeset.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Typeset-Future-Typography-Science-Fiction-ebook/dp/B07G7SGRZ2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Typeset in the Future&lt;/a&gt;

, Dave Addey&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2013, Addey nerded out over the fonts in a Science Fiction movie and discovered it was an Eurostile variant (&amp;ldquo;Eurostile Extended Bold&amp;rdquo;).
He started a Tumblr about this, and in great detail went through a number of movies, and about every sign, letter and font used in there.
The Tumblr became quite successful, and he turned the most important posts into a book, adding a lot of images with examples and a number of interviews and essays to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/typeset2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ebook is a joy to read on anything but a Kindle - I did on a 10&amp;quot; iPad, and it worked quite well.
The dead tree edition would make an excellent conversation piece.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: UNIX: A History and a Memoir</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-unix-a-history-and-a-memoir.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 15:47:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/09/05/fertig-gelesen-unix-a-history-and-a-memoir.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The memoir of Brian Kernighan, and the story of how UNIX came to be and what working at Bell Labs was like at that time:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/UNIX-History-English-Brian-Kernighan-ebook/dp/B07ZQHX3R1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UNIX: A History and a Memoir&lt;/a&gt;

 is required reading for anyone who wants to know where Unix concepts came from and what ideas were behind its inception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/UNIX-History-English-Brian-Kernighan-ebook/dp/B07ZQHX3R1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;md__image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.koehntopp.info/uploads/2021/09/unix.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/UNIX-History-English-Brian-Kernighan-ebook/dp/B07ZQHX3R1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UNIX: A History and a Memoir&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;quot;, Brian Kernighan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kernighan takes us through the history and the setting of Bell Labs, why it existed and what it did.
He explains the hardware of the time, in terms of size, power and capabilities, and why Bell did get involved into writing an Operating System, and the failure of Multics.
Unix inception and its co-evolution with the C language was a kind of response to the Multics project, at the same time pioneering novel ideas and taking tested salvageable concepts from Multics, making something new and much more useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While he roughly follows the timeline of Unix releases, Kernighan takes short detours, including mini-biographies of his colleagues and the influence they had on the design of the system and the ideas embodied in it.
He finishes with the commercialization of Unix, Unix descendants - BSD, Minix, Linux and Plan 9, and with the closure of Bell Labs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you work with Linux, the C language or any Unix tools, you should read this book to understand where these things came from and what formed this environment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fertig gelesen: 88 Names</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-88-names.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 14:18:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2021/08/03/fertig-gelesen-88-names.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It began with a tweet by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/s_bergmann/status/1392518815897030661&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sebastian Bergmann&lt;/a&gt;

, which made me buy &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B07T6938D1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;88 names&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; by Matt Ruff.
The book is a tour of massive multiplayer online role playing games for people who do not play, and also a discussion of identity on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Chu has a small sherpa company, an outfit that helps causal players who have the coin to experience hard content in MMORPGs in an easy and successful way without investing too much time into the game.
Chu is coming out of a relationship with a borderline gamer, Darla, and is being asked by an obviously powerful and demanding anonymous client to be shown several well known MMOs to better understand their genres.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chu is trying to uncover the identity of his client, and comes to believe that he is the North Korean dictator Kim Jong Un.
In the course of his research he learns the real identities of his employees, none of which are what he thought they were, and the real identity of Darla, who is way further past the borderline that he originally assumed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a fun read for me, because it relatively accurately portrays MMOs and online games.
At the same time Ruff&amp;rsquo;s writing very causally avoids Gamer Dudebro stereotypes and shows that people playing video games are way more diverse than their cliche.
If you ever have had your Internet spaceship refueled by a 60+ year old english granny and ex-schoolteacher you will understand exactly what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/gp/product/B07T6938D1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;88 Names&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo;, Matt Ruff&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

