<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>energy on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>/tags/energy.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in energy on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/energy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Rechenzentren und ihren Stromverbrauch regulieren</title>
      <link>/2020/11/01/rechenzentren-und-ihren-stromverbrauch-regulieren.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/11/01/rechenzentren-und-ihren-stromverbrauch-regulieren.html</guid>
      <description>Es gibt ein Interview mit Stefan Ramesohl vom Umweltministerium (des Bundes) in Netzpolitik.org: &amp;ldquo;Warum niemand weiß, wie viele Rechenzentren es in Europa gibt &amp;rdquo;. Im Wesentlichen hat das Umweltministerium angesagt, daß es auf europäischer Ebene Rechenzentren erfassen und katalogisieren will, um in einem zweiten Schritt den Energieverbrauch von Rechenzentren zu regulieren.
Das ist sehr spannend, denn derzeit gibt es keine Übersicht über Rechenzentren in Europa, und tatsächlich sind einige Rechenzentrumsbetreiber sehr paranoid, was den genauen Standort ihrer Hardware angeht und wieviel und welche Hardware darin ist oder was diese tut.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cloud and Energy</title>
      <link>/2020/06/08/cloud-and-energy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/08/cloud-and-energy.html</guid>
      <description>In [Data Centers and Energy]({% link _posts/2019-10-05-data-centers-and-energy.md %}) I wrote about Hyperscaler Data Centers and Open Compute, and how they bring down the PUE of data centers, making them more efficient, and in [Streaming and Energy]({% link _posts/2019-12-28-streaming-and-energy.md %}) I followed up on this, explaining how Netflix energy usage fits into this. Now the Uptime Institute has released a study that claims &amp;ldquo;Data center energy efficiency gains have flattened out&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Streaming and Energy</title>
      <link>/2019/12/28/streaming-and-energy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/28/streaming-and-energy.html</guid>
      <description>A bunch of boomers in Germany is running a distraction campaign on the energy use of data centers and streaming. Example articles in german language can be found in Zeit and Bento , but there is a larger series of articles acrooss multiple newspapers.
A better structured reasoning can be found in SRF (German), and it highlights how arbitrary and wrong the energy numbers in the former articles are. But even this article ignores the facts that the energy consumption in a typical cloud data center is most likely carbon neutral, because the power used is likely to be completely green.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Centers and Energy</title>
      <link>/2019/10/05/data-centers-and-energy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/10/05/data-centers-and-energy.html</guid>
      <description>Deutsche Welle is shocked: Generation Greta is watching Netflix (Article in German Language), Netflix runs on computers, and apparently computers are using power.
Let&amp;rsquo;s have a look.
EDIT: Second part [Streaming and Energy]({% link _posts/2019-12-28-streaming-and-energy.md %}) now available.
End-User Device.   It&amp;rsquo;s 2019. End user devices are using Wifi, and are running on Batteries. They are Cellphones, Tablets or Laptops.
Devices that are not connected to grid are more usable if they are trying to save energy, and so all modern devices are full of special purpose hardware that allows them to fulfill their main functions more energy efficient.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Journey to Open Compute</title>
      <link>/2018/02/21/a-journey-to-open-compute.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/02/21/a-journey-to-open-compute.html</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, Booking.com hosted the Open Compute Meetup in Amsterdam. My talk is on Slideshare and a recording is on Youtube.
 Slideshare: A journey to OCP  Youtube: A journey to OCP   A cleaned up and more coherent transcript of the talk is here: Booking.com started out as a small online travel agency in Amsterdam, but is now financially about 15% of Google. We have about 200 offices in 70 countries, support 46 languages and reach about any touristically interesting spot on this planet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Renewables: Energy is free, guarantees cost money</title>
      <link>/2017/07/26/renewables-energy-is-free-guarantees-cost-money.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/26/renewables-energy-is-free-guarantees-cost-money.html</guid>
      <description>Digging through my bookmarks and open tabs was interesting. The picture of the future that emerges: With costs for energy approaching the 1 cent range per kWh, electrical energy is going to be close to free. Money can and will be charged for guarantees, because batteries or other forms of storage still cost money.
 Guardian: &amp;lsquo;Spectacular&amp;rsquo; drop in renewable energy costs leads to record global boost »The new renewable energy capacity installed worldwide in 2016 was 161GW, a 10% rise on 2015 […] The new record capacity cost $242bn, a 23% reduction in investment compared to 2015, and renewables investment remained larger than for all fossil fuels.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
