<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>neuland on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/neuland.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in neuland on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Nov 2021 19:45:06 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/neuland/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>25 years &#34;Individual Network e.V.&#34;</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/06/20/25-years-individual-network-e-v.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 09:47:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/06/20/25-years-individual-network-e-v.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Heiko Schlichting reminds us that
&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/101393200017787888697/posts/RD5VLcaQDaA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;25 years ago, on the 20./21. of June 1992, the Individual Network e.V. was created&lt;/a&gt;


(Text in German). Individual Network e.V. was a NGO of NGOs, a construct
where local citizen network NGOs could be members. Individual Network would
then make contracts with the German Science Network DFN and other providers
and buy traffic rights in bulk, in order to allow its members to use this
traffic for non-commercial, private use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to allow local NGOs to connect to the German Science Network DFN
locally using the local university lines, Individual Network had to have
some connection to DFN in order to be a member and customer. In the end it
was decided that Individual Network would finance two X.25 lines into DFN at
50% each, with the local NGO taking the endpoint financing the other half.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is how the NGO I represented, Toppoint Mailbox e.V., ended up with a
9600 bps X.25 line on 1.10.1992. This ended the era of long-distance dialup
at Toppoint Kiel (well, not quite) and introduced a permanent link to the
Internet. That was well before the first web servers, so SMTP, NNTP and FTP
were the order to the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People connected to Toppoint using dial-up modems, ISDN dial-ups or
semi-permanent (pre-conncted) ISDN dialups. Speeds were up to 128 kbps,
using channel bundling. I had a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Provider-independent_address_space&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PI&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;a href=&#34;https://networkengineering.stackexchange.com/questions/3697/the-slash-after-an-ip-address-cidr-notation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;/24&lt;/a&gt;


those days, for home use, costing me 50 DM, one time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, people reminded me of &lt;code&gt;...!mcshh!tpki!kriski!kris&lt;/code&gt;. Yes, we did not
use DNS back then, but had to name all hosts in the path of a mail. And
hostnames are globally unique (yep, that scales even less than IP V4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See also: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-VkLbiDAouM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Neuland&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Google took over the classroom</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/06/13/how-google-took-over-the-classroom.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2017 09:07:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/06/13/how-google-took-over-the-classroom.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Using electronic devices in the classroom seems to be a topic older than
time, and the implementation often involved a lot of tedium. The problems
and possible solutions are well understood in Germany
(&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linux-magazin.de/Ausgaben/2004/09/Einer-fuer-alle&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt;


about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ltsp.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LTSP&lt;/a&gt;

 among other things), but the
(purposefully) fragmented market for education in Germany is getting in the
way here. Biggest problem usually is keeping the machines clean and orderly,
and keeping the data available across device loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Children and teachers seem to be installing a lot of questionable software
and extensions, and getting rid of these by setting up the machine seems to
be the only way to be sure. So any school installation usually focuses on
automatic fast imaging of the machines, and on server-side data storage for
everything to make sure nothing is lost when a machine is lost or re-imaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the US, 2013 saw the introduction of a lot of iPads,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wired.com/2015/05/los-angeles-edtech/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;for example in LA&lt;/a&gt;

.
That did not work so well: Apple is a company that until very recently
focused very much on data storage on the device itself with an optional
cloud sync - for them, it&amp;rsquo;s a sales tool for more storage. Also, expensive
devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/05/13/technology/google-education-chromebooks-schools.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Chromebooks&lt;/a&gt;


seem to be taking US education by storm, and it makes a lot of sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chromebooks are cheap devices and while they cache data locally, all data is
agressively stored upstream in a cloud. That makes devices actually
interchangeable - the important part is the login, not on which device you
are. They can be easily restored to a default state with the aptly named
&amp;ldquo;Powerwash&amp;rdquo; option, and they are mostly based on open technology - HTML5 for
content and a powerful browser all the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For pupils and teachers, using a device with a proper keyboard is a big plus
over a thing such as an iPad, as well. Plus, the device is not really
important. As long as you can run Chrome and login to Google, the device in
fact does not matter at all. It can be a Chromebook, or any PC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For publishers of educational material, it&amp;rsquo;s also a nice thing. Materials
are made in a well defined open format with good tooling (HTML5, again), and
it is usually bound to an account and not permanently stored on a device.
That makes licensing easy, updates a breeze and the tooling question is a
solved issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Communication between teachers, pupils, and parents is also easily done, and
integrated into everything. Admin tools for classes, accounts, and
everything else exists, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, #neuland is not looking at this at all, because fragmented
market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, Datenkranke! Kugelschreiber!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strong weak ties</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/04/05/strong-weak-ties.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2017 11:42:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/04/05/strong-weak-ties.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A long time ago, I wrote a text on the German Blog and on Carta:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carta.info/41830/wieso-wir-uns-veroffentlichen/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wieso wir uns veröffentlichen&lt;/a&gt;


(Why we publish ourselves).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the middle of a discussion about privacy I was explaining why people
publish themselves, why they publicly reveal (sometimes intimate) facts
about themselves. They are doing this, I wrote, to find other like-minded
people, to become searchable and to become approachable, to build trust.
Trust is a wonderful thing. It is the powerful assumption that most people
most of the time want to help you and that falsely trying out to trust
people is a recoverable mistake. Having trust and being in a trustworthy
environment keeps transactional costs low and makes cooperation possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s rewarding and awesome. How does this work in practice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So tomorrow there is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.messefrankfurt.com/frankfurt/en/besucher/welcome/messeveranstaltungen/messen/entertainment-media-creation/prolight_sound2017.html?nc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pro Light and Sound in Frankfurt&lt;/a&gt;

.
Sammy wants to go there, and gets the combination ticket. That&amp;rsquo;s admission
to the trade show, plus a ticket for German rail. That ticket is being
delivered as a Bahn Tix code, which you can
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ypxepZLxff8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;punch into any German ticket machine&lt;/a&gt;


and get a printout. We are in the Netherlands. The next ticket machine is in
Venlo. The route she&amp;rsquo;s going to use does not pass Venlo. There is
&lt;a href=&#34;http://praxistipps.chip.de/bahntix-online-ausdrucken-geht-das_44999&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;no way to get Bahn Tix online&lt;/a&gt;

.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am asking on Google plus for help, and because I know at least one person
following me is a Train Driver I mention them into the thread. Sammy, me and
that person get into a Hangout. Ticket is being picked up and given the
train driver of ICE 220 FFM -&amp;gt; Amsterdam Centraal. Shift change at the
border, ticket travels on to Amsterdam, +30 platform change 7b -&amp;gt; 2.
Printed Ticket is being successfully delivered from the engine to Sammy at
11:58.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a direct application of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interpersonal_ties&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Interpersonal Ties&lt;/a&gt;


theory (pointing to article by
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sociology.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/publications/the_strength_of_weak_ties_and_exch_w-gans.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Granovetter&lt;/a&gt;


(1973) and in a way to the works of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Ultrasociety-Years-Humans-Greatest-Cooperators/dp/0996139516&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Peter Turchin&lt;/a&gt;

.
High trust societies are societies where people have
&lt;a href=&#34;http://changingminds.org/explanations/theories/weak_ties.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;many weak ties&lt;/a&gt;

,
that can be strengthened as demand arises. It&amp;rsquo;s these strong weak ties that
enable (inter-) action and where cooperation wins between people are
highest. In order to have strong weak ties, a society needs to have a
relatively low and controlled wealth difference
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gini_coefficient&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gini coefficient&lt;/a&gt;

) and a
working judicial system and low corruption. This creates social cohesion,
and enables &amp;ldquo;random&amp;rdquo; cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, you win friends. Looking forward to a visit, soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

