<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>neuland on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</title>
    <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/neuland.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in neuland on Die wunderbare Welt von Isotopp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/tags/neuland/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>25 years &#34;Individual Network e.V.&#34;</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/06/20/25-years-individual-network-e-v.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/06/20/25-years-individual-network-e-v.html</guid>
      <description>Heiko Schlichting reminds us that 25 years ago, on the 20./21. of June 1992, the Individual Network e.V. was created (Text in German). Individual Network e.V. was a NGO of NGOs, a construct where local citizen network NGOs could be members. Individual Network would then make contracts with the German Science Network DFN and other providers and buy traffic rights in bulk, in order to allow its members to use this traffic for non-commercial, private use.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Google took over the classroom</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/06/13/how-google-took-over-the-classroom.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/06/13/how-google-took-over-the-classroom.html</guid>
      <description>Using electronic devices in the classroom seems to be a topic older than time, and the implementation often involved a lot of tedium. The problems and possible solutions are well understood in Germany (report about LTSP among other things), but the (purposefully) fragmented market for education in Germany is getting in the way here. Biggest problem usually is keeping the machines clean and orderly, and keeping the data available across device loss.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strong weak ties</title>
      <link>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/04/05/strong-weak-ties.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.koehntopp.info/2017/04/05/strong-weak-ties.html</guid>
      <description>A long time ago, I wrote a text on the German Blog and on Carta: Wieso wir uns veröffentlichen (Why we publish ourselves).
In the middle of a discussion about privacy I was explaining why people publish themselves, why they publicly reveal (sometimes intimate) facts about themselves. They are doing this, I wrote, to find other like-minded people, to become searchable and to become approachable, to build trust. Trust is a wonderful thing.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
